<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Growth Economics Blog</title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description>Dietrich Vollrath Economic Growth Blog</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 12:22:37 -0500</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evidence on Violence and Ethnic Groups in Africa</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Ethnic/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Ethnic/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At the rate I’m going this summer, I will soon be down to one blog post a year, and it will be about a paper that came out in 2008. I swear to my coauthors that this is because I’m working &lt;em&gt;so damn hard&lt;/em&gt; on [fill in name of joint project here], and will soon have those [tables/drafts] prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few things have recently caused me to come up for air, and one was a little back and forth that took place on Twitter over a paper by Stelios Michalopoulos and Elias Papaioannou (MP) on “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/aer.20131311&quot;&gt;The Long-run Effects of the Scramble for Africa&lt;/a&gt;”. Bill Easterly linked to a brief &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/zbQ75Ri41J&quot;&gt;write-up&lt;/a&gt; of the paper from the AER, where it was just published. This led to several responses from others critical of several aspects of the MP paper. I had a brief back and forth with some people myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a disclaimer. I am friendly with both Stelios and Elias. I see them at conferences, I ask about their kids, they ask about mine. I can spell their names without checking online. Stelios and I overlapped at grad school for four years. I believe I’m going to give you a fair assessment of their paper and the mini-controversy about it. But you have full information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One point that was made about the paper was that the use of the term “homeland” is problematic, particularly in Africa. Economists, and I know I do this, tend to get exapserated by people picking over the semantics. Who cares what they call them? MP define exactly what they mean by “homeland” in the paper. But there are connotations to words, and no matter how precisely you define something in a paper, those connotations exist. “Homeland” was a term used by the South African apartheid government for the areas where black Africans were allowed to live. Referring to “homelands” in Africa can make it sound like there are places where certain groups are supposed to live, forever and always. It was a poor choice by MP to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly, the issue with “homelands” bleeds into criticism of the idea that it is possible to fix boundaries on an ethnicity at all. I don’t have the knowledge or time to work through the history of thought on this, but suffice it to say that today if you asked scholars working on Africa (I did e-mail with a few) about ethnic homelands, they’d all say - paraphrasing - “that’s not a thing”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet MP find what they find. Poor language choices don’t invalidate the data. Empirically, it helps to separate MP’s work into two pieces. First, split ethnicities have predictive power for incidents of violence. Second, we can interpret this as a &lt;em&gt;causal&lt;/em&gt; impact of splitting an ethnicity. Asserting the first does not imply the second. And denying the second does not invalidate the first. But it will be worth thinking more about what exactly they mean when they say a split ethnicity. More on that as we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On predictive power, their succession of regressions is hard to ignore. MP look at 1,212 ethnic/country observations. There is one observation for the Lobi in the Ivory Coast, and a separate observation for the Lobi in Burkina Faso, for example. The mapping of ethnic groups to countrys comes from a map done by Murdock (1957), and that has been used extensively by these authors and others in studying African development. An ethnic group that is fully contained within a country would have one observation only. Then MP use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acleddata.com&quot;&gt;ACLED&lt;/a&gt; database, which has information on political violence in Africa from 1997 to 2013. Importantly, it contains location information, and MP use that to assign acts of political violence to the ethnic areas defined by Murdock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each ethnic/country observation gets a variable called SPLIT, which is 1 for both partitioned groups. So the Lobi/Ivory Coast observation would have a 1, and so would the Lobi/Burkina Faso. A group wholly contained in a country would get a zero. Then MP run a series of regressions of different measures of political violence against this SPLIT variable, controlling for lots of other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MP are not looking only at incidents of violence that occur in partitioned groups, they are comparing the amount of violence in partitioned groups to non-partitioned groups. It’s helpful here to remember that “running a regression” essentially means “compare the average outcome for two sets of observations”. The average level of political violence in partitioned groups/countries (SPLIT = 1) is higher than the level of political violence in non-partitioned groups/countries (SPLIT = 0). “Controlling for lots of other things” means that the average level of political violence is still higher in partitioned groups even if you only look at group/countries that all share a common set of characteristics (other than being partitioned). An important control here are the country fixed effects, which means their results show that there is more political violence in partitioned groups in a country compared to other non-partitioned groups in that same country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those measures of political violence are things like: the count of violent incidents, the number of deadly incidents, the total casualties from political violence, the amount of civil violence, or the number of more formal battles (but not necesseraily riots). In each case, partitioned groups had higher levels of violence in this time period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would be nice to see is the predictive power of just the SPLIT variable. MP’s full regressions have adjusted R-squares of about 45%, of they explain about half of the variation in political violence - but that is the explanatory power of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the variables. How important is SPLIT by itself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of that answer, it’s crucial to remember that saying there is a statistically significant effect of partitioning, or saying that MP can explain 45% of the variation in violence, does not mean &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; partitioned groups are &lt;em&gt;by definition&lt;/em&gt; more violent. The Twitter dicussion was thick with examples of partioned groups that did not tend to have violence occur. Okay, great. MP aren’t saying that partitioning forces you to have violence, they are saying that partitioned places are more likely to exhibit violence. It’s a probability statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to criticize MP’s work on the predictive power of ethnic partitioning, then I think the main issue would be with Murdock’s underlying map. We don’t exactly know what Murdock used to define these borders, and if you look at his map, they can seem as arbitrarily drawn as any political boundary. Maybe he got these wrong, and what MP take to be “ethnic homelands” are not indicative of actual ethnic groupings now (or in 1957 for that matter). This reaches back to the point from the beginning - maybe Murdock’s boundaries don’t indicate anything real about ethnic groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that change the interpretation of MP? Sure. Their regressions show that areas defined by George Murdock that are divided by political boundaries are prone to violence. Does that necessarily mean that this is due to ethnic-based conflict? Perhaps Murdock drew his groups based on some observed characteristic of violence in 1957, and so those places were bound to be violent anyway? MP can offer some evidence on this, as when they use alternative data on ethnic-based conflicts (from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epr.ucla.edu&quot;&gt;EPR&lt;/a&gt; database) it shows that partitioned Murdock-groups do indeed have more ethnic-based conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And nothing about MP’s results is contingent on the ethnic population of Murdock’s groups being tied to that specific geographic location over time. The violence within one of Murdock’s partitioned group could be from an entirely different group moving in over time, and no one from the original group even lives there any more. Ethnic groups can be fluidly moving across borders, within countries, and all over the place. But there is something about partitioned areas from Murdock’s map that tends to have more violence than other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, let’s say that MP have established the predictive power of partitioning for future conflict. Does their work imply that the partitioning was &lt;em&gt;causal&lt;/em&gt;. That is, was it the partitioning itself that created the violence. You might imagine that partitioning would make a border &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; violent, as the people on either side are closely related. So it isn’t obvious how the causality would go here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MP argue that their results do show a causal impact of partitioning, based on the arguemnt that the partitioning was done quasi-randomly by European colonists starting with the Berlin Conference in 1884-85. The money quote for them is from Robert Cecil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have been engaged in drawing lines upon maps where no white man’s feet have ever trod; we have been giving away mountains and rivers and lakes to each other, only hindered by the small impediment that we never knew exactly where the mountains and rivers and lakes were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, for MP the partitioning of one of Murdock’s ethnic groups was done blindly by Europeans without any knowledge of the location of those groups to begin with. From the perspective of the groups, this was done randomly. Hence the characteristics of partitioned and non-partitioned ethnicities do not vary systematically - which MP verify on several geographic and historical dimensions - and hence the estimated effect of partitioning is in fact causal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take this seriously, then finding that this is causal is another strong piece of evidence in the “history matters” or “path dependence” literature that finds persistent effects of historical choices on current development. Which is a polite way of saying that colonization - the historical choice made by colonizers to exploit certain areas of the globe and not others - created lasting damage to colonies. That damage may be in terms of depressed investment in human/physical capital, or may be in institutions and political structures that are built for corruption rather than development. In this MP case, the damage was from arbitrarily dividing some ethnic groups, creating frictions across borders, leading to violence that disrupts development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to stay skeptical of the MP causality claim, then again I think your target is Murdock. While the Berlin Conference made decisions blindly, Murdock knew those boundaries to a large extent, and may have drawn his lines specifically with them in mind. Perhaps he retrofitted the ethnic mapping to the boundaries, and he presumed that violent areas must be partitioned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that’s a stretch, but even if you want to dismiss the causality claims, that doesn’t negate the predictive power of the MP regressions. If you want to tell me that a more contextual study of these conflicts will indicate that they are not ethnicity-based at all, but due to fights over limited resources, or instigation from outside sources, or just randomly bad luck, fine. But you still have to explain why these things tend to occur (but not always) in areas where Murdock’s groups were partitioned. The data indicates that there is only about a 5-10% chance that this is just a coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the context of the individual conflicts is vastly more important than MP’s paper, if what you are trying to do is solve a specific conflict. You wouldn’t call them to negotiate a cease-fire between militants and the government in, well, any country anywhere. But understanding that partitioning of the Murdock groups is associated with violence is informative - without invalidating any of the contextual information.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Early Transformation of Britain&#39;s Economy</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Britain-Shares/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Britain-Shares/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a nice working paper out by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lse.ac.uk/economicHistory/workingPapers/2016/WP240.pdf&quot;&gt;Patrick Wallis, Justin Colson, and David Chilosi&lt;/a&gt; called “Puncturing the Malthus Delusion: Structural Change in the British Economy before the Industrial Revolution, 1500-1800”. The big project they undertake here is to mine the probate inventories (along with several other sources) from Britain in this period to build up a picture of the rough allocation of workers across sectors. They do a very nice job of walking through their data sources, and the limitations, in the paper, so let me leave those details aside. In short, they use the reported occupations in wills to back out a picture of the sectoral structure, finding it consistent with other sources based on apprentice records, as well as prior estimates from specific years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get to the good stuff. Here is their Figure 7,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/WCC_fig7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sector Shares over time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dots refer to prior point estimates from other sources. The lines show their inferred sectoral distribution over time if they force the pattern of structural change to hit the point estimates from other established sources. For those interested, what this establishes is that alternative point estimates (labels with C or M) are basically consistent with the main points estimates (labels with ST or B), based on the authors time pattern of change. That is both a neat way of evaluating your data, with the benefit of not pissing off any potential referee’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that aside, there are a few things about this figure that are very informative:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Britain was already incredibly non-agricultural in 1550. Only about 60% of workers in Britain in the late 16th century worked on farms in some capacity. For comparison, in 2010 India had a employment share in agriculture of about 54%, Nigeria 61%, and Malawi 65%. Ethiopia was still at 75% in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Britain experienced a substantial structural shift &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; of agriculture between 1550 and 1750. From about 60% agricultural to about 40% agricultural. 40% puts Britain in 1750 at about the 2010 level of Thailand (38%), Indonesia (38%), or Ghana (42%). Thus Britain in 1750 is about 260 years ahead of those three countries in terms of the structural transformation out of agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Britain’s structural shift was &lt;em&gt;really slow&lt;/em&gt; compared to contemporary developing countries. It took Britain 200 years to drop 20 percentage points from its agricultural labor share. In comparison, Ghana dropped 20 percentage points in the 50 years from 1960 to 2010, Tanzania had a similar drop. South Africa, Peru, Mexico, Egypt, Columbia, and Brazil all saw drops of more than 30 percentage points in those same 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meaning-what&quot;&gt;Meaning What?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WCC paper is very nice because it builds up a strong base of support for the spotty point estimates that were out there before. Which means we can be a little less hesitant in drawing conclusions, or at least forming hypotheses. Then again, now that Brad DeLong has said some &lt;a href=&quot;http://equitablegrowth.org/equitablog/must-read-dietrich-vollrath-2/&quot;&gt;nice things&lt;/a&gt; about me, maybe I can just start spouting off and you’ll all believe me anyway. I’ll let you figure out what is what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Bayesian prior on “the probability the Great Divergence had its origins prior to the Industrial Revolution” should get updated to a higher number. Brad’s link from above was about a post I did on the persistence of technological change. &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/&quot;&gt;That post’s&lt;/a&gt; point was that a lot of evidence points to 1500 &lt;em&gt;or earlier&lt;/em&gt; as a time frame for when we can start to predict which countries will end up rich, and which poor. The fact that Britain in 1550 is already as un-agricultural as India is in 2010 says that something in 1550 was already “going right” in Britain. Again, we should be digging backwards for explanations. (By the way, digging backward for explanations does not mean digging backwards for policy recommendations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These numbers are bad news if you have “Glorious Revolution” in the “monocausal origins of economic growth” office pool. The data reinforce the argument that the Glorious Revolution was as much a &lt;em&gt;response&lt;/em&gt; to economic change, as it was a &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; of economic change. WCC provide a rough estimate of output per worker based on their labor allocations and estimates of output from others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/WCC_fig11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Output per worker&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that there is a distinct surge upwards in all three sectors starting early in the 1600’s, well before the Glorious Revolution (1688-89) and the supposed origin of growth-friendly institutions. Britain seemed to be figuring out its economic game well before they imported a Dutch king willing to share power with merchants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;malthusian-structural-change&quot;&gt;Malthusian Structural Change&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is in the title, the authors spend very little time talking about how their data “punctures the Malthusian Delusion”. In fact, the terms “Malthus” or “Maltusian” is not used in the main text of the paper a single time. I’m guessing they take as a given that structural change out of agriculture constitutes non-Malthusian economic activity. Hence the puncturing referred to in the title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is nothing about structural change that implies Malthusian forces have been banished, overcome, or left behind. Yes, (too) many papers talking about Malthus give the impression that output in these economies is homogenously made up of subsistence goods like food. But that is just a modeling simplification used to elide the discussion of how labor gets allocated across different activities. An economy operating under Malthusian conditions - a positive relationship of population growth and living standards, and those living standards depending negatively on population size - need not be 100% agricultural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could have an economy that had 95% of labor in industry and services, and yet was Malthusian because output was tied to some fixed natural resources (say agricultural land to grow cotton and supplies of coal to heat up the thingies that make the cotton into underpants and tablecloths). You could even get Malthusian forces arising &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of urbanization. Your standard urban economics model will imply that stable city sizes occur when the costs of congestion outweight the benefits of agglomeration, meaning that adding more people to a city lowers living standards. Remi Jedwab and I have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/jv2016_megacity.pdf&quot;&gt;working paper&lt;/a&gt; using this concept to think about the origin of poor mega-cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point (aside from self-citation) is that Malthusian economies can have rich structural characteristics and dynamics. “Stagnation in living standards over many centuries” does not mean “Everyone living on a farm barely scraping by at the biological minimum requirements for life”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain experiencing a structural change from 1550 to 1750 does not mean it was already experiencing sustained growth. The growth experienced in that period may well have been snuffed out by Malthusian forces of population growth in time. But perhaps that structural change helped bring on the changes in demographic behavior that allowed sustained growth to occur? This structural shift bleeds directly into the Industrial Revolution, which bleeds directly into the demographic shifts involved with sustained growth. Whether this implies a chain of causality is too much to make of this evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is productivity the victim of it&#39;s own success?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Baumol/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Baumol/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn’t really intend to take such a long break from blogging, but I kind of looked up and realized it had been a month or so. There was (at least from my standpoint) a flurry of posts regarding productivity, the slowdown in productivity, reasons for the slowdown in productivity, and responses to the slowdown in productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ezra Klein does an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vox.com/a/new-economy-future/technology-productivity&quot;&gt;overview&lt;/a&gt; of a lot of these topics, so if you need to dive into the concept of the productivity slowdown, this is a good place to start. Klein gets into the question of mis-measurement of productivity - perhaps we are underestimating it. Edward Luce &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/315f8b88-2364-11e6-9d4d-c11776a5124d.html?siteedition=intl&amp;amp;ftcamp=published_links%2Frss%2Fcomment%2Ffeed%2F%2Fproduct#axzz4BUveXHlE&quot;&gt;picks up&lt;/a&gt; goes the other way, wondering if we are overestimating productivity by mismeasuring labor inputs to gig work. Chad Syverson has recently issued a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nber.org/papers/w21974?utm_campaign=ntw&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_source=ntw&quot;&gt;working paper&lt;/a&gt; that tries to work through the “mismeasurement” question, and comes to the conclusion that this really can’t account for much, if any, of the slowdown in productivity growth over the last few decades. Timothy B. Lee &lt;a href=&quot;http://timothyblee.com/2016/05/07/some-thoughts-on-the-end-of-economic-growth/&quot;&gt;lists&lt;/a&gt; some thoughts on the future of innovation in general, coming out somewhat pessimistic about it. There was a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brookings.edu/about/projects/bpea/papers/2016/byrne-et-al-productivity-measurement&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Byrne, Fernald, and Reinsdorf in March that covers some of the same ground. Gavyn Davies &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ft.com/gavyndavies/2016/06/12/why-hasnt-the-productivity-crisis-caused-a-bear-market-yet/&quot;&gt;asks&lt;/a&gt; why the slowdown hasn’t shown up in asset prices (yet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of threads running through these posts and others. So some of what I’m writing here is just me trying to get a simple mental framework in place to think about things. If I’m lucky, it will also serve as a useful way of explaining these threads to others. But I promise nothing, as this is definitely me thinking out loud. Here goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goods-and-services&quot;&gt;Goods and Services&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s think of the economy as producing two kinds of things: services and goods. Services are provided purely as time. Think of hours of lawyering from a lawyer, or hours of teaching from a teacher, or hours of training from a personal trainer. To a large extent, you buy chucks of time from other people with services. Goods are provided as physical things: TV’s, apples, or cars. Obviously lots of products are mixes of the two - restaurant meals combine physical goods with someones time - but that’s okay. I’m not trying to say that all things are uniquely services or goods, just that these are the two types of things we produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to assume that services and goods are enjoyed as perfect complements to each other. That is, we like bundles of goods and services, and are completely unwilling to substitute one for the other. It’s like saying that I’d refuse to go to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://saltlickbbq.com&quot;&gt;Salt Lick&lt;/a&gt; if I had to actually walk up and get a second order of brisket myself. Which is ridiculous, but then again it can be physically impossible to walk after the first order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In math, let’s say that utility is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;U = min(\alpha_S S, \alpha_G G)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where S are the hours of services I get, and G are the number of goods I get. The &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt; terms are weights on how much I like the two things, and thus also serve as a way of measuring quality. Higher &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt; means that it gives me more utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say that services are produced with time &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt;. I’m also going to say that goods are produced using &lt;em&gt;NO&lt;/em&gt; time. They may need capital and resources, but no time. If you like, they’re put together by robots. Which makes my little struture here a useful way of thinking about any possible Skynet/HAL future of robot AI manufacturing. There are a total of H units of time available in the economy. Think of these as working hours. Given my assumption, S = H.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, I’m interested in measuring productivity, so I really want to measure U/H, or utility per hour. So I’m going to divide through the utility function by H. Here it is worth stopping to note a few things. First, I am completely eliminating any discrepancy between measured economic output (GDP) and utility (U). I’m assuming I can measure the utility function directly. Or if you like, I’m assuming that GDP has a one-to-one mapping to utility. I’m not doing this because I think GDP is perfect, but I want to make points about how productivity changes even if we were to measure it perfectly. Second, I’m measuring U/H here, which “labor productivity”, but if I wanted “total factor productivity” I could divide by some bundle of inputs involving H as well as capital. But that is going to be beside the point here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives me&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Prod = \frac{U}{H} = min \left(\alpha_S, \alpha_G G/H \right)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;as my measure of productivity. And with this I can start thinking about productivity issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with services:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Services only contribute to productivity through their quality. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_S\inline&quot;/&gt; is the only thing that shows up in the measure of productivity. Which is related to …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is no extensive margin in services. Because we are trying to measure utility &lt;em&gt;per hour&lt;/em&gt;, and services are provided using &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt;, we can’t raise productivity by getting “more” services per hour. I can’t work 65 minutes per hour. Which implies that …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New services cannibalize time from old services. If I come up with a new way to use worker’s time, by necessity it must subtract from the time they spend doing something else. Perhaps there is some margin along which workers would enter or exit the labor force that would allow for getting more services, but in practical terms that is probably very small.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare this to goods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The quality of goods contributes to productivity. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_G\inline&quot;/&gt; is &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; way for goods to add to productivity, but ….&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is an extensive margin in goods. That is, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?G\inline&quot;/&gt; can go up over time. Holding constant quality, we can produce more of those goods. Unlike hours, there is no finite number of goods we can produce. Which implies …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New goods need not cannibalize old goods. If someone invents a new good, this doesn’t necessarily mean that we buy fewer of the old goods (there’s a GoT joke in here somewhere about the “old goods and the new”).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No, it doesn’t matter that it is G/H in there, even though I assumed goods don’t require time. We’re measuring productivity &lt;em&gt;per hour&lt;/em&gt;, so what matters is how many goods we produce per hour, whether or not hours matter for production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baumol-and-the-slowdown&quot;&gt;Baumol and the slowdown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This setup means we can talk about one theory for the productivity slowdown. Because goods and services are perfect complements, eventually productivity (and productivity growth) will be determined solely by the &lt;em&gt;slowest&lt;/em&gt;-growing sector. Productivity is a minimum of the two sectors, and hence the faster growing sector will eventually always surpass the slower growing sector, and we’re stuck at the minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This captures the essence of what William Baumol suggested decades ago. “Strong Baumolism” would be the case where services are assumed to have &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt; quality growth, and hence productivity growth will go to zero eventually. “Weak Baumolism” would just be that services have a lower rate of quality growth than the growth of the combined goods term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason for services to grow so slow is related to the points I made above. Services only grow through quality improvements, because they depend on time. Goods, in contrast, can grow in both quality and quantity, so this gives them more possibilities for growth. The productivity slowdown we are witnessing is thus just us reaching the point where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_S &amp;lt; \alpha_G G/H\inline&quot;/&gt;, and now productivity only grows as fast as &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_S\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that one implication of this is that the productivity growth rate of &lt;em&gt;goods&lt;/em&gt; is likely to fall as well. Why? Because there is no longer any marginal value to new goods when &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_S &amp;lt; \alpha_G G/H\inline&quot;/&gt;. We have “too many” goods, in this setup, and so the marginal value of a new good is zero. Hence the profits you could expect to earn from new goods, or better goods, is relatively small. And hence little effort is put into innovating in goods production. With some kind of endogenous innovation concept, you’d expect that the growth rate of goods productivity - the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_G G\inline&quot;/&gt; term - would fall. Perhaps even lower than the growth rate of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_S\inline&quot;/&gt;, for so long as &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_S &amp;lt; \alpha_G G/H\inline&quot;/&gt; there is no incentive to innovate in goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly this is really stark, but that’s the value of the simple model. It suggests not only why we might have hit a productivity slowdown (services), but why that could drag down innovation rates in goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also suggests why all sorts of super-cool innovations that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; get made in goods production don’t seem to show up in the productivity statistics. With perfect complements, those new goods have essentially no value on the margin, and hence add little or nothing to productivity. This is why I said that productivity may be a victim of its own success. Massive improvements in goods-producing technology have pushed us into the Baumol situation, where further goods-producing technologies have little (zero in my model) value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-case-for-services&quot;&gt;The case for services?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wouldn’t be economics if there weren’t a different way of interpreting the same situation. What if in fact services are growing in quality very rapidly? So fast, in fact, that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_S &amp;gt; \alpha_G G/H\inline&quot;/&gt;? Then productivity growth is limited by growth in the goods-producing sector. Any new innovations in service quality would have exactly zero impact on measured productivity &lt;em&gt;even if we measure productivity perfectly&lt;/em&gt;. It’s not that we haven’t captured the value of Facebook or Uber in our statistics, it’s that they really do have zero marginal value because they are so frickin awesome already. Given the perfect complements assumption, we’re always held back by our slower-growing sector, and in this case it is goods. So yes innovations are occurring rapidly in services, but it is irrelevant to measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could squeeze Bob Gordon’s book into this scenario. Take his argument that we kind of exhausted these scale-intensive opportunities for productivity growth in manufacturing and infrastructure. That would explain why the productivity growth coming from goods is slower now. But it would also jive with his contention about the relatively small measured productivity contribution of innovations in services in the last few decades. It isn’t that services are not getting better, it is that this improvement doesn’t add to productivity because services are operating ahead of goods at this point, with &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_S &amp;gt; \alpha_G G/H\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eliminating-possibilities&quot;&gt;Eliminating possibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Productivity is mis-measured” is probably wrong, even though people have lots of evidence of technological innovations. Most likely what is happening is that those innovations are happening in a sector that is already more productive than others. Because sectors are complements, innovation in the high-productivity sector is going to &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; contribute little to measured productivity growth. It doesn’t matter if you think that high-productivity sector is services or goods here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the “we’ve run out of cool things to invent” argument is probably wrong, too. But maybe we’ve run out of &lt;em&gt;incentives&lt;/em&gt; to actually invent things, particularly in the goods sector. In the Baumol setting, with services being the limiting factor on productivity growth, the goods sector has little incentive to innovate. Why bother? So the fact that goods-sector productivity growth is slow doesn’t mean we used up all the good ideas, it just means there isn’t a big rush to bring those ideas to the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Baumol story - as opposed to my re-interpretation of Gordon - is probably the right null hypothesis to have in your head. Services have a built-in limit on their productivity growth, because we cannot innovate and get “more time” in the way we can innovate and get “more stuff” with goods. With services and goods being complements, this means overall productivity growth is restricted to the pace of service quality growth, and hence is slowing down. This would be true even if we measured productivity perfectly; if we could actually measure utility per hour. The measured productivity slowdown can be “real” and yet that does not mean we cannot or have not innovated. The complementary nature of the preferences matter here in a material way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Roman History Reading List II</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Rome-Reading-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Rome-Reading-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick follow-up to last December’s original &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/roman-history-reading/&quot;&gt;Roman History Reading List&lt;/a&gt;, which turned out to be pretty popular. As before, this is “hobby reading” for me, and I make no claims about these lists being definitive. But if you are interested in dipping into this area, the lists will be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Theodor Mommsen’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1ORh3Rr&quot;&gt;The History of Rome&lt;/a&gt; is one of the all-time classics. I found his writing riveting, and as a general overview of the events leading up to the end of the Republic it is a fantastic place to start. Some of Mommsen’s conclusions have not held up to scrutiny, but that is a small price to pay here. The link is to a translation that abridges Mommsen to the era of the end of the Republic (133BC to roughly 31BC), and abridges further when the translators feel the details are not necessary. Not having read Mommsen before, I didn’t mind. One day I want to go for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1W8JxIE&quot;&gt;“full Mommsen”&lt;/a&gt;, but that might have to wait a few years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Erich Gruen’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1Tr0qbQ&quot;&gt;The Last Generation of the Roman Republic&lt;/a&gt; is another excellent book. More narrowly focused than others, it concentrates on the supposed “inevitability” of the end of the Roman Republic. He comes to the conclusion that it was more a horrific mistake like the onset of WWI than the result of a creeping internal rot. While you can easily skim a few of the middle chapters, the blow by blow account of the political wrangling going on in the months leading up to Caesar crossing the Rubicon is unmatched. I was physically tense reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adrian Goldsworthy’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1NDYQq4&quot;&gt;Caesar: Life of a Colossus&lt;/a&gt; obviously digs into Caesar’s individual story more deeply. The one very redeeming quality of this book is the consistent reminder that no one knew Caesar was going to be, well, Caesar. He studiously avoids looking for “signs” in Caesar’s youth that foreshadow his inevitable rise. On the down side, this is very much the work of a military historian, so for me the narrative drags as he dissects the tactics of various Gallic battles.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sallust’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1NDZns0&quot;&gt;The Catiline Conspiracy&lt;/a&gt; is one of the more accessible ancient texts (or at least this translation is). You do have to keep reminding yourself that Sallust has an agenda. I’m not even sure I know what it is, but he is writing to try and establish a narrative about what actually happened leading up to the fall of the Republic.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Robert Harris’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/25fc7xb&quot;&gt;Imperium&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1NDZBiT&quot;&gt;Conspirata&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1YMhsEY&quot;&gt;Dictator&lt;/a&gt; are historical fiction that presumes to tell Cicero’s story from the perspective of his main servant, Tiro. One of the big advantages of reading history this way is that it cements the characters in your head more solidly. I have much better recall of secondary players in this era thanks to Harris. And the books are fun, given that they don’t feel compelled to be exhaustive. But they do contribute to the overall inflation of Cicero’s importance. Cicero is more George Will than George Washington in the grand scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dan Carlin did an epic series of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dancarlin.com/product/hardcore-history-death-throes-of-the-republic-series/&quot;&gt;podcasts&lt;/a&gt; telling the story of the fall of the Roman Republic. Carlin is a &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; story-teller, and given that this runs probably 10 hours in total, it is fantastic for a long trip. This isn’t original history, this is Carlin consolidating lots of the secondary analyses I’ve linked to. Much of the podcast is like an extended reading of Tom Holland’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/25fd5cZ&quot;&gt;Rubicon&lt;/a&gt;, but that is no crime as the book is excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has become nearly impossible to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; draw analogies between this period of Roman history and the current political climate in the U.S. I won’t pretend to have some kind of grand insight given the reading I’ve done. But if you are looking to finish the sentence “Trump is just like….”, then the answer you are looking for is not Caesar, Pompey, Brutus, or other big names in the story. You’re looking for Clodius Pulcher. Read the Gruen book for an excellent discussion of the underlying motivations of Clodius’ supporters and his ability to use that support to his advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Can we get rich by &quot;Doing Business&quot; better?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Business-Indicators/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Business-Indicators/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;John Cochrane wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/ending-americas-slow-growth-tailspin-1462230818&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; for the Wall Street Journal’s &lt;s&gt;Confirmation Bias&lt;/s&gt; Opinion page. It used the World Bank’s Doing Business index to suggest that the US could achieve massive gains in economic growth by adopting policies that pushed up our Doing Business score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bradford-delong.com/2016/05/this-is-extraordinarily-unprofessional.html&quot;&gt;Brad DeLong&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://evansoltas.com/2016/05/07/pro-business-reform-pro-growth/&quot;&gt;Evan Soltas&lt;/a&gt; had at the post. DeLong saying that Cochrane’s attempt to forecast out of sample the relationship of the DB index and GDP per capita was flawed. Soltas took a look at distinct shocks to the DB index in a attempt to alleviate the obvious “correlation is not causation” problem inherent in Cochrane’s piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t planning on saying anything else about this, but Cochrane posted &lt;a href=&quot;http://johnhcochrane.blogspot.com/2016/05/regulations-and-growth.html&quot;&gt;another&lt;/a&gt; piece on his blog that included a figure pulled from my book with Chad Jones. Which got me looking more closely at his original piece. Which frustrated me. So here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;growth-economics-with-nigel-tufnel&quot;&gt;Growth Economics with Nigel Tufnel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I’m going to get to the gory details of why the Doing Business (DB) indicators generally suck as a measure of anything useful. But let me start with this note. The DB index Cochrane uses is a “distance to the frontier” index. Meaning you get a number that tells you how close to best practices in business conditions a country gets. If you are at the best practices in all categories, you’d get a 100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cochrane says, and I quote, “If America could improve on the best seen in other countries by 10%, a 110 score would generate $400,000 income per capita…”. Stew on that for a moment. Think about how that DB &lt;em&gt;frontier index&lt;/em&gt; is constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cochrane went there. He said it could go to 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KOO5S4vxi0o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;apples-and-oranges&quot;&gt;Apples and Oranges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is a more basic problem, one which DeLong and Soltas implicitly concede to Cochrane. And that is in believing the DB distance to the frontier is a meaningful way of measuring …. doing business, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distance to the frontier number is attempting to aggregate imcomparable quantities. Channeling my inner Nick Rowe, let’s use fruit to make a point. Alice has 10 apples and 5 oranges. Bob has 3 apples and 4 oranges. How would the World Bank calculate the “Doing Fruit” distance to the frontier index? First, we have to establish both the best and worst performance by fruit. For apples, this is easy. The frontier amount of apples is 10, the worst amount of apples is 3. But we can’t do that for oranges, because the WB has arbitrarily set up standards that imply that the frontier amount of oranges is 7, while the lower bound is zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the WB &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doingbusiness.org/~/media/GIAWB/Doing%20Business/Documents/Annual-Reports/English/DB16-Chapters/DB16-DTF-and-DBRanking.pdf&quot;&gt;procedures&lt;/a&gt;, Alice’s distance to the frontier in apples is (3 - 10)/(3 - 10) = 1. That is, Alice is at the frontier. Alice’s distance to the frontier in oranges is (0 - 5)/(0 - 7) = 0.714. She’s 71% of the way to the (arbitrary) frontier. For Bob, his apple distance is (3 - 3)/(3 - 3) = 0, and his orange distance is (0 - 4)/(0 - 7) = 0.571.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the overall distance to the frontier just averages the two distance measures for each person. So Alice’s overall distance to the frontier is (1 + 0.714)/2 = 0.857. Bob’s distance is (0 + .571)/2 = 0.286. Let’s say we plot their GDP per capita against the “Doing Fruit” index and find a positive relationship. We could publish this as an op-ed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://fruitgrowersnews.com&quot;&gt;Fruit Growers News&lt;/a&gt;, and argue for policy changes in the number of apples and oranges to boost living standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does that relationship actually mean anything? Not really. What happens to the “Doing Fruit” index, and presumably to GDP per capita, if the following happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bob raises his apple count to 9.&lt;/strong&gt; Nothing happens. You can go figure it out if you want, but so long as Bob has fewer apples than Alice, his number defines the lower bound, and hence he is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; at the lower bound, which means he always gets a zero in apples. Bob had a reform but didn’t change his “Doing Fruit” distance to the frontier. Does this mean Bob’s reform wouldn’t raise GDP per capita?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alice lowers her apple count to 9.&lt;/strong&gt; Nothing happens. Similar reasoning as above. She defines the top end, so lowering her apple total doesn’t change her distance to the frontier. She is the frontier. Does this mean that Alice could lower her apple total without affecting GDP per capita?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The WB raises the lower bound on oranges to 2.&lt;/strong&gt; Alice’s index drops to 0.8, Bob’s drops to 0.2. So according to the WB, they both just got farther from the frontier, even though all we changed was the arbitrary lower limit to oranges. Do they both get poorer?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduce a new person.&lt;/strong&gt; If Charlie, with only 2 apples but 7 oranges, joins the party, then Bob’s “Doing Fruit” index rises to 0.473, because he’s now above the lower limit in apples. Nice job, Bob! Does Bob’s GDP per capita go up in response, even though nothing changed in Bob’s fruit totals?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 3-body Problem.&lt;/strong&gt; With Charlie involved, Alice has an 0.857, Bob an 0.473, and Charlie an 0.500. If Alice’s number of apples falls to 8, then we get Alice with an 0.857 (again), Bob with a 0.535, and Charlie with a 0.500. So by changing Alice’s frontier total of apples we just made Bob look better. So good, in fact, that he has now passed Charlie. The decline in Alice’s apple total leaves her &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; GDP per capita unaffected, but makes Bob richer than Charlie?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marginal fruit changes.&lt;/strong&gt; With Charlie involved, what happens if Bob raises his apple total by 1? His DF index goes up by 0.062, and presumably he gets richer because of this reform. If he raises his orange total by 1, his DF goes up by 0.071, and thus increasing oranges is better for GDP per capita than increasing apples. Oh, unless Charlie happens to have 4 apples, in which case it totally is better to increase apples than oranges on the margin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on, but I think I’ve made the point. Adding up across indicators like apples and oranges results in indices that have no meaning. With sufficient time, I could come up with my own abitrary reweighting of the individual components of the Doing Business indicators and make the relationship between the index and GDP per capita go to zero, or go to infinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the means of valuing the different business indicators against each other, we end up having no idea how to assess institutional changes. For example, within the “Dealing with Construction Permits” section of the DB indicators, there is both a measure of the time (days) to get a construction permit and a “Building quality control index” which is an arbitrary classification that runs from 0-15 (in whole numbers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going up one category in quality control (e.g, from 9 to 10) increases your overall “Dealing with Construction Permits” score by 0.067 (i.e. 1/15th). By construction, this has an identical effect on your overall score as lowering the number of days to register a permit by 23 days (actually, 23.13 days). From the perspective of a business owner, do we think that dropping the days to permit a building by 23 is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; equivalent to raising the quality control index by 1? Should I believe they would have identical effects on GDP per capita?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is this quality control index anyway? It’s the sum of a bunch of roughly binary indicators. So going from 9 to 10 could represent having a licensed engineer be required to review the plans (yes, that makes doing business easier in this index). Or it could be because construction companies become legally liable for structural flaws. Or it could be because construction supervisors are now required to have university degrees. These (and a host of other things) all contribute &lt;em&gt;identically&lt;/em&gt; to the “Building quality control index”. But are they all equally worthwhile to doing business? Are they even good for doing business? Should I believe they all contribute similarly to raising GDP per capita - if they even do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that all the curve-fitting in the world won’t change the fact that the Doing Business index contains effectively no information. The individual indicators themselves can be useful, but as an aggregate it doesn’t make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-gets-worse&quot;&gt;It Gets Worse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the follow up &lt;a href=&quot;http://johnhcochrane.blogspot.com/2016/05/regulations-and-growth.html&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, Cochrane appeals to a graph from my textbook with Chad Jones. An updated version using data from 2008 shows the relationship of an index of “social infrastructure” and TFP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/figure_7_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;TFP and SI&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This index of “social infrastructure” is even more useless than the DB index. How do I know? Because I calculated it, graphed it, and stuck it on the slide that Cochrane linked to. I simply scaled and averaged the 6 different components of the World Bank’s governance indicators, much like the DB index. It has all the issues I described above, except worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This figure tells us very little. Which is why in the book we immediately say that you cannot infer anything causal from it, and then go on to talk about some of the better studies done looking at specific institutions and their effects on economic outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;short-run-growth-versus-long-run-growth&quot;&gt;Short-Run Growth versus Long-Run Growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s concede the issues - barring the “go to 11” one - to Cochrane; there really is a causal relationship between the DB index and GDP per capita, and his original fitted curve is the right one. Does it follow that we could get 6% growth, as Cochrane suggests here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A score of 100—labeled Frontier—is certainly possible… [and] generates $163,000 of income per capita, 209% better than the U.S., or 6% additional annual growth for 20 years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Why? We’ve been through this before on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/you-cant-reform-your-way-to-rapid-growth/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll let you jump to that post to see the exact math. Assume a baseline growth rate of GDP per capita of 1.0% per year, a convergence speed of 2% (meaning 2% of any gap between current and potential GDP is closed each period), and that potential GDP per capita really does go up by 209%. This would result in growth of 5.2% in 2017. That’s pretty good, but below Cochrane’s 6%. And the growth rate would decline in every year after 2017 until it reached 1% again. Technically that would take until infinity; practically you wouldn’t be able to tell the difference after about 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is like the dark side of compounding. It only takes small changes in percentage growth rates to generate really big changes in levels of GDP over a sufficiently long time. Convergence is slow. Even a massive shock to potential GDP doesn’t boost growth that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do I assert that it takes so long to reach potential GDP (i.e. why is the convergence speed 2%)? First, that’s what we estimate from the data. Second, the adjustment costs to a significant change in the rules and regulations underlying the DB indicators mean that it could take a long time to reach the new potential GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that boosting our DB index to 100 really is a fundamental reduction in regulatory red tape. This is like a productivity increase &lt;em&gt;in compliance and government&lt;/em&gt;. We can generate the same “output” of regulation with far fewer people. So all those private employees who do compliance work are not necessary, nor are the public employees who check their work. This work may be bullshit, unnecessary, and fundamentally useless - but those people make a living doing it. They are like redundant assembly line workers after the introduction of a robot. They won’t seamlessly melt back into the workforce. What’s a 50-year old safety professional specializing in OSHA compliance for a construction company supposed to do when he gets let go? As we’ve seen before as industries get destroyed, it can take a long time for ex-workers to adapt, if they ever do. That adaptation of the human capital stock is part of the slow convergence speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And recall that many of the characteristics that would boost your DB index score - like the requirements on construction inspections and the education requirements for those inspectors - in fact involve &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; regulation and time spent on compliance, not less. So should I even believe that these changes are positive for potential GDP at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;does-it-matter&quot;&gt;Does it matter?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that, be careful not to draw the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; conclusion, which is that business regulations do not matter at all. That’s not what I’m saying, and not what the criticisms of Cochrane imply. The point is that we cannot infer how much they matter from the DB index, or a cross-sectional plot of that against GDP per capita. And forecasting the effect of improving the DB index - seriously, 11? - is a lost cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a country like the US, the marginal effect of regulatory changes are almost certainly mild. Not zero. Not negative. But probably small. We have no good evidence of effects large enough to really move the GDP growth needle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t even clear we are really behind the frontier in business regulation. Singapore is held out as an example of a place with a great business environment, and is one of the data points suggesting that having a high DB index is associated with high GDP per captia. But Singapore has high GDP per capita in large part because it is just a single city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you compare single US cities to Singapore, they look just fine, if not better. Brookings did a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brookings.edu/research/reports2/2015/01/22-global-metro-monitor&quot;&gt;ranking&lt;/a&gt; of cities by 2014 GDP per capita. Singapore is 14th, with a (PPP-adjusted) GDP per capita of 66,684. But Hartford is at 83K, San Jose at 82K, Boston at 76K, Houston at 74K, Bridgeport at 73K, Washington at 73K, Seattle at 73K, San Francisco at 72K, and New York at 69K. There isn’t some kind of low-regulation Utopia out there that we are missing out on.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>More on Decomposing US Productivity Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/More-Decomp/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/More-Decomp/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Tables, tables, tables. There are going to be lots of tables today. My last &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Decomposition/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; was about the decomposition of aggregate productivity growth into different components. “Within” growth occurs because labor productivity within sectors is growing. “Across” growth occurs because workers move from one sector to another. For the US recently, this “across” growth has been negative, meaning that people are shifting from high to low productivity sectors. Finally, there is “covariance” growth, which captures whether workers are moving into (or out of) sectors that have high productivity &lt;em&gt;growth&lt;/em&gt;. This tends to be negative, meaning that workers are tending to move to sectors with low productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did that decomposition using data at the 10-sector level, meaning it is very high level (Agriculture, Manufacturing, Construction, etc..). To dig a little deeper, in this post I’ve pulled down BEA data on industry-level output and full time equivalents (FTE) that is at a finer level of disaggregation. I end up with 70 industries, but I can only cover the time period of 1998 to 2014. For the geeks out there, this means I’m using this sort of bastardized NAICS 2 and 3 digit classification to match up with what the BEA reports. (Because &lt;strong&gt;GOD FORBID&lt;/strong&gt; that the BEA uses precisely the same classification scheme for both output and FTE). Anyway, the data files I’m using, and a script to recreate what you see in this post, are linked at the bottom of this post. So feel free to play around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the data means that I can calculate labor productivity at the industry level for those 70 industries. I’ll call this “productivity” from now own to save myself some typing. But productivity here is just output divided by FTE. So for each industry I know their productivity level and their share of total FTE’s in the economy. That gives me all the information I need to do the within/across/covariance decomposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll get to the overall decomposition below, but before that I think it’s interesting to pick through the individual sectors themselves to see which ones are contributing positively and negatively to those different components of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m ultimately going to look at the growth of aggregate productivity for the 4 years 2010-2014. So to be consistent with the calculations, to start with we can look at the level of productivity and FTE shares in 2010. Here are the top 10 industries in terms of productivity in 2010, where productivity is measured in millions of 2009 dollars per FTE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Prod Level&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Funds, trusts, and other fina..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5.72&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Real estate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.3753&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Oil and gas extraction&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.0038&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Petroleum and coal products&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.9037&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Utilities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5026&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pipeline transportation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.4325&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chemical products&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.4263&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Motion picture and sound record..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3476&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mining, except oil and gas&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3470&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Rental and leasing services a..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3342&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know exactly what “Funds, trusts, and other..” is, but it is hard to get the image of Scrooge McDuck swimming in his money out of my head. Anyway, the level of productivity here is off the charts compared to other industries. Which is great, but will end up being irrelevant for us because it effectively employs zero people. The other industries here are perhaps not surprsing: utilities, oil and gas, chemicals, mining. I guess I’m surprsed that “Real Estate” (think your broker, not your general contractor) is so high in productivity. But that’s what you get earning 6% on every home transaction that takes place, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the bottom 10 industries in productivity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Prod Level&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Administrative and support se..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0614&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Apparel and leather and allie..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0603&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food and beverage stores&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0587&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other services, except government&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0581&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amusements, gambling, and rec..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0577&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Educational services&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0575&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General merchandise stores&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0471&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nursing and residential care ..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0430&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Social assistance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0390&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food services and drinking pl..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0388&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food services is, just for scale purposes, roughly 10 times less productive per FTE than “Chemical products” or “Motion picture and sound recording”. [&lt;em&gt;Also down here is educational services, and perhaps the inter-tubes can help me here. I can’t find definitely where public-school teachers get reported. Are they here, or are they in “State/local government”?&lt;/em&gt;] These are generally all service industries, which perhaps not surprsing. It’s also not an indictment of services, by the way. These industries don’t produce anything, but do provide their time, and hence you can’t raise productivity by lowering the time input (like in manufacturing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, here are the top 10 industries in 2010 in terms of their share of FTEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;FTE Share&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General State/Local&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.1242&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food services and drinking pl..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0608&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Administrative and support se..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0538&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other retail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0504&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other services, except government&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0463&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Construction&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0450&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ambulatory health care services&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0445&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wholesale trade&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0438&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Miscellaneous professional, s..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0390&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hospitals&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0365&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest users of FTE are again generally service industries. You can’t get too jazzed up about that, because one of the reasons this looks this way is that the BEA sub-divides manufacturing down to very small levels, but leaves “General State/local government” as one giant category. If we broke down that category into “Police”, “Fire”, “DMV”, etc. then this wouldn’t show up as 12%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that gives you some idea of what the static distribution of FTE and productivity across industries looks like. But we’re really interested in productivity &lt;em&gt;growth&lt;/em&gt;, and so what will matter for that are the &lt;em&gt;changes&lt;/em&gt; in productivity and FTE shares from 2010 to 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, here are the 10 industries with the highest total growth in productivity for that 4-year period. There are not percentages, these are absolute changes in productivity. Again Scrooge McDuck has an outsized number here, and again it is going to be irrelevant for us ultimately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Prod Change&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Funds, trusts, and other..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.18&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Oil and gas extraction&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.2692&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Water transportation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0904&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pipeline transportation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0725&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Broadcasting and telecommu..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0706&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mining, except oil and gas&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0579&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Computer and electronic ..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0389&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Petroleum and coal produ..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0253&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Rental and leasing servi..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0249&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Data processing, internet ..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0238&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Computer and Electronic products” is the manufacturing of those goods. The rest are relatively self-explanatory. Remember that these represent the change over four years. So “Pipeline transportation” raised productivity by approximately 72,500 dollars per FTE between 2010-2014, or about 18,125 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those sectors were doing well in terms of productivity. At the other end of the scale are the following 10 industries, which had the lowest productivity growth in the same period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Prod Change&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food and beverage stores&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0134&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Miscellaneous manufacturing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0142&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Utilities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0149&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food and beverage and tobacco..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0160&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Legal services&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0176&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Securities, commodity contrac..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0180&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Real estate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0189&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Waste management and remediat..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0282&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Motion picture and sound record..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0399&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chemical products&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0585&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chemical products had it bad in this period, and apparently so did movie studios. Maybe a surprise that securities and legal services had such poor productivity growth? I’m not going to start speculating on underlying causes for any of these numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big point of the prior post was that while these numbers on raw productivity growth are interesting, they are not the whole story. We have to consider these alongside the allocation of workers across those sectors. Like I said above, the fact that “Funds, trusts, and other” is so productive will be essentially meaningless, but the decline in productivity in “Legal services” will be meaningful, because it employs a lot of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s look at the raw change in the share of FTE’s employed by industry in the same 4-year period. Here are the 10 industries that had the biggest change in their FTE share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Chg. FTE Share&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other retail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0044&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Administrative and support se..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0038&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Social assistance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0037&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food services and drinking pl..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0035&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Construction&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0027&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food and beverage stores&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0022&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Motor vehicle and parts dealers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0022&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General merchandise stores&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0019&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Computer systems design and r..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0016&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ambulatory health care services&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0013&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this tells us is that “Other Retail”’s share of total FTE in the economy rose by 4.4-tenths of one percentage point. The other thing that shows up here is that none of these industries with rapidly growing shares of FTE also show up on the table of top productivity growth. In fact, “Food and beverage stores” is growing in the share of FTE, but it was in the &lt;em&gt;bottom&lt;/em&gt; ten of productivity growth in the prior table. This is an example of an industry with a negative covariance contribution - it is growing in FTE, but shrinking in productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the other end of the rankings are the 10 industries that lost FTE’s the fastest. Here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Chg. FTE Share&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;State/Local Gov Enterprise&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Federal Gov Enterprise&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other services, except government&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0010&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Computer and electronic produ..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0010&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Federal Reserve banks, credit..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0014&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Broadcasting and telecommunicat..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0016&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;National defense&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0018&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Federal Civilian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0020&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hospitals&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0021&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General State/Local&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0109&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting here is that the list is dominated by public employees. “State/Local gov enterprises”, “Federal gov enterprises”, “National defense”, “Federal civilian”, and “General state/local” are all industries under the general “Government” heading. The big drop in state and local employment here is obvious. One other quick note is that “Federal Reserve banks, ..” refers to the banking sector in general (those banks supervised by the Fed), and not specifically to the Federal Reserve banks themselves. One last interesting note is that “Broadcasting and telecommunications” shows up as another industry with a negative covariance contribution - it has growing productivity, but is shrinking in FTE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are still awake, then this still doesn’t help us out much, because the changes in FTE themselves could be good or bad for aggregate productivity depending on whether they are high or low productivity industries to begin with. So let me show you some more tables that list the top/bottom 10 indutries in terms of their actual “within” or “across” contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remind you, the decomposition of aggregate productivity looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta y_t = \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} s_{j0} + \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta s_{jt} y_{j0} + \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} \Delta s_{jt}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first summation is the “within” term, with &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_{jt}\inline&quot;/&gt; being productivity in sector &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?j\inline&quot;/&gt;, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{j0}\inline&quot;/&gt; their share of FTE in 2010. The second summation is the “across” term, and the final summation is the “covariance” term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with the within terms. Here are the top 10 industries in “within” contribution over the last 4 years. Each of the numbers in the table is an individual &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\Delta y_{jt} s_{j0}\inline&quot;/&gt; in the first summation above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Within&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Broadcasting and telecommunicat..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0007&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Oil and gas extraction&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0004&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Computer and electronic produ..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Management of companies and ent..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wholesale trade&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Motor vehicles, bodies and tr..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Publishing industries, except i..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Computer systems design and r..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Rental and leasing services a..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Insurance carriers and relate..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the rankings are not identical to the first table, which was just about productivity growth. This table is productivity growth &lt;em&gt;times&lt;/em&gt; the industry’s share of total FTE. You can see that “Funds, trusts, …” have disappeared, as I mentioned, because they employ so few people. “Wholesale trade” appears here not because it has ridiculously high productivity growth, but because it employs a relatively big share of FTE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are the bottom 10,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Within&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Social assistance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Securities, commodity contrac..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Legal services&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General merchandise stores&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Real estate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food and beverage and tobacco..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other retail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food and beverage stores&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Construction&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chemical products&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0004&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list looks similar to the one based purely on productivity, because these 10 industries all employ pretty big shares of FTE in the US. When the “Construction” industry experiences negative productivity growth, for example, this has a relatively big aggregate effect because it employs a lot of people. That’s the “within” term at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, look at the top/bottom 10 industries in terms of their “across” contribution. This is the change in their share of FTE &lt;em&gt;times&lt;/em&gt; their initial level of productivity, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\Delta s_{jt} y_{j0}\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Across&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other retail&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Construction&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Administrative and support se..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Motor vehicle and parts dealers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Computer systems design and r..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Motor vehicles, bodies and tr..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Social assistance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food services and drinking pl..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Food and beverage stores&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ambulatory health care services&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that these are positive means only that people are moving &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; these sectors. The terms could be large either because lots of people are moving in but an industry is low productivity (“Other Retail”) or because a few people are moving in and the industry is high productivity (“Motor vehicles, bodies..”). Regardless, this table gives you an idea of which industries are expanding their contribution to aggregate productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the other end, the bottom ten in “across” contribution are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;BEA Industry&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Across&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Legal services&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chemical products&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hospitals&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Utilities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Federal Reserve banks, credit..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Federal Civilian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Computer and electronic produ..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;National defense&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0004&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Broadcasting and telecommunicat..&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0005&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General State/Local&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-.0009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These industries are losing FTE for sure. Banks, utilities, broadcasting, and government employment are shrinking. Yet because they also happen to be relatively high productivity, so this subtracts a lot from aggregate growth. As you can start to sniff out from these tables, the negatives in the bottom 10 outweight the positives in the top 10 of “across” terms. And this is where that aggregate negative for “across” contribution comes from. FTE is leaving sectors that are relatively high productivity, and flowing into sectors with relatively low productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last component of productivity is the covariance term. These are all so close to zero that they are not terribly interesting. And since there are already a ridiculous number of tables, let’s just stop there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this all lead to? We can add up the 70 individual within terms, the 70 individual across terms, and the 70 individual covariance terms to arrive at aggregate growth in productivity (remember, output per FTE). I did this for the 4-year period from 2010-2014, but also for all 4-year periods up to 2014. And that is what is in the following figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_bea_decomp_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;US 4-year Decomposition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the last post, you can see that the combined “across” terms are negative recently. This drags down aggregate growth. The shift of workers out of government, legal services, hospitals, etc.. and into construction, admin, and retail pulls down aggregate growth. What we also see is that recently the “within” components are declining appreciably. While there are sectors that have growing productivity, this is largely offset by sectors where productivity growth is negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that a sign of a permanent change? There is nothing here to tell us that. Some of this is a function of looking at a relatively short 4-year time frame. If I did 10-year calculations, then there is nothing particularly funny-looking about 2014, it is just part of a general decline in “within” industry growth since about 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other thing to keep in mind when staring at the dip in “within” growth in 2014 and pondering whether this means we are inevitably doomed to be replaced by robots is that alot of this is driven by a surge in FTE in 2010-2014. This is easiest to see in a figure. Here’s the 4-year rolling growth rates of value-added (output) separate from the 4-year rolling growth rate of FTE’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_bea_growth_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;US FTE and VA&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you can see is that part of the slowdown in growth in productivity (value-added per FTE) is due to the striking growth in FTE reported by the BEA between 2010-2014. The economy is adding workers, or hours, or both very rapidly, while output growth is not growing any more rapidly than normal. This makes productivity fall. If you look at individual industries (I’ll spare you any more tables) you get a similar story. Many industries - including ones with high productivity to start with - have FTE growth that far outweighs their value-added growth, which makes their “within” productivity term negative. Why are industries adding FTE if they are not getting more out of them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this just a prelude to a burst of growth in value-added as these workers get up to speed? Or is this an example of the economy pulling back in relatively low-productivity &lt;em&gt;workers&lt;/em&gt;. We’re now beyond anything I can do with the data I have here. Check back in a few years, and we can see whether this was just a temporary blip, or a real slowdown in “within” industry productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, here are the promised data files and Stata script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/bea_ip_data.dta&quot;&gt;BEA Value-added&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/bea_fte_data.dta&quot;&gt;BEA FTE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/2016-05-10-BEA-Setup.do&quot;&gt;Stata do-file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technology versus the Distribution of Workers in Aggregate Productivity</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Decomposition/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Decomposition/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There was a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://artir.wordpress.com/2016/04/25/no-great-technological-stagnation/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by an engineer rebutting Robert Gordon’s (and others) thesis that technological change was slowing down. The evidence cited is a series of plots and figures showing how specific technologies (battery storage, energy efficiency, computer speed, etc..) are advancing just as fast as they have for decades, if not faster. And there were a number of responses along the lines of “See, Gordon is wrong!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mistake here is that this doesn’t constitute evidence that Gordon is wrong. But the mistake is partly forgivable because Gordon himself indulges in these kinds of anecdotal arguments to advance his thesis, and so it seems as if you could refute his conclusions by offereing alternative anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the important part of Gordon’s argument is not that specific technologies are or are not advancing. It is that &lt;em&gt;aggregate productivity growth&lt;/em&gt; is slowing down. And aggregate productivity growth depends not only on individual technologies, but crucially on the distribution of workers using those technologies. Arguing about only those individual technologies is like using an increase in the price of milk to argue that inflation must be high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggregate productivity growth depends on what we can call “within-sector” growth, which is going to be tied closely to those individual technologies. But it also depends on “across-sector” growth, which is tied to the movement of workers from one sector (or job) to another. If workers are shifting from high- to low-productivity sectors or jobs, then aggregate productivity growth may fall even though nothing happened to actual technological change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll make this more clear below, but here’s a quick summary of what I’ll try to establish. Gordon’s critics could well be right about their individual technologies, and yet wrong about this having anything to do with aggregate growth, because those sectors may not employ many people. And Gordon can be right about aggregate growth, but wrong about individual technologies stagnating, because the movement of workers to low-productivity sectors may be dragging down growth. In short, you cannot talk about aggregate productivity growth without talking about both technology &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the distribution of workers across sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gruesome-detail&quot;&gt;Gruesome Detail&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, there is math. Gordon’s argument is about the growth rate of total factor productivity (TFP). But sector and industry level data on TFP isn’t available for the time frames I want, so I’m going to look instead at value-added per hour, a measure of labor productivity. TFP and value-added per hour are going to be highly correlated, but not perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value-added per hour, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y\inline&quot;/&gt;, is the summation across all &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?J\inline&quot;/&gt; sectors of the economy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;y = \sum_{j=1}^J s_j y_j&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_j\inline&quot;/&gt; is the share of total hours worked in sector &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?j\inline&quot;/&gt;, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_j\inline&quot;/&gt; is the value-added per hour in sector &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?j\inline&quot;/&gt;. With that definition, the &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; in value-added per hour from time 0 to time &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt; can be written as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta y_t = \sum_{j=1}^J s_{jt} y_{jt} - \sum_{j=1}^J s_{j0} y_{j0}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t very informative by itself, but by rearranging the terms in those two summations, adding and subtracting some other common terms, and a little algebra, we can get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta y_t = \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} s_{j0} + \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta s_{jt} y_{j0} + \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} \Delta s_{jt}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of notes on this equation. First, this is the absolute change in value-added per hour. This isn’t the growth rate. You could divide by sides by &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_0\inline&quot;/&gt; to get a growth rate, but as written the equation looks simpler. Second, I’ve made precisely zero assumptions about behavior to get this. This is pure accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three separate summations on the right-hand side can be nicely interpreted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Within-sector growth&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} s_{j0}\inline&quot;/&gt; holds constant the allocation of hours seen at time zero. This is the growth we’d get if all that happened was that each sector got more productive, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\Delta y_{jt}\inline&quot;/&gt;, but we did not allow anyone to change jobs. The idea is to measure just improvements in labor productivity within sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Across-sector growth&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_{j=1}^J \Delta s_{jt} y_{j0}\inline&quot;/&gt; holds constant the value-added per hour seen at time zero. This is the growth we’d get if all that happened was that workers (and their hours of work) moved between jobs. Note that this will be positive if people move from low- to high-productivity jobs, or negative if they move from high- to low-.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Covariance&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} \Delta s_{jt}\inline&quot;/&gt; captures the fact that not only do sectors vary in their time-zero level of productivity, but differ in their productivity growth. This term captures whether or not people are moving into sectors where productivity is &lt;em&gt;growing&lt;/em&gt;, which would show up as a positive value. A negative means that workers are moving to sectors where productivity is shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the role of these three effects, I pulled down sector-level data from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rug.nl/research/ggdc/data/10-sector-database&quot;&gt;Groningen 10-sector database&lt;/a&gt; for the U.S., from 1950-2010. The 10 sectors are broad - agriculture, manufacturing, construction, etc. - but have the advantage of spanning a long time frame. I can pull data from the BLS at a much finer industry level at the cost of only going back to 1987. From what I found, the BLS data confirm the story I’ll tell with the Groningen data, so let’s stick with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each year, I calculated the three terms in the above equation, looking backward 10 years each time. So I have the rolling 10-year growth in value-added per hour (VAPH), as well as how it breaks down into within, across, and covariance terms. What I’ve plotted below is the total growth rate, not an annualized rate, so that everything still adds up exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_us_decomp_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;US Decomposition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is pretty clear is that within-sector growth is the dominant force in VAPH. And you can see the early high reported rates of growth of within-sector growth in the 1960’s (which capture growth from the 50’s into the 60’s). There is a clear slowdown in within sector growth from about 1975 to 1990, consistent with all the other evidence, and then things recover not quite back to the 1960’s level. The dip in 2009 and 2010 indicates that growth in VAPH from about 1999/2000 to 2009/2010 has been relatively slow, again consistent with our priors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now look at the contributions of across-sector growth and the covariance term. Across-sector growth is consistently positive throughout most of this period, but starts declining significantly around 1990, so that over the last ten years across-sector growth is &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; for overall growth in VAPH. That means between 2000 and 2010 workers were moving out of sectors with high productivity (in 2000), and into sectors with low productivity (in 2000). Without any slowdown in actual productivity growth, &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; aggregate productivity growth is going to be lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negative contribution of the covariance term tells a similar story of negative effects, although this appears to be a consistent issue. Workers are not only moving into low productivity sectors to begin with, but into sectors with low productivity &lt;em&gt;growth&lt;/em&gt;. This also drags down measured aggregate productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10-year growth rate, starting in the 1990’s (which means the effects started in the early 80’s), no longer lies &lt;em&gt;above&lt;/em&gt; the within-sector growth rate. In other words, starting in the 80’s, we see the across-sector and covariance effects of structural change producing a negligible or even negative effect on VAPH growth. This is most apparent in those final few years of the graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Gordon’s critics, they can be right that individual technologies are still growing quickly, but what they do not account for is that labor may be moving &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; of those sectors and hence aggregrate growth could still be low. If we could get finer and finer levels of industry data, it is quite possible that what looks like a decline in within-sector growth in 2009/2010 is really just negative across-industry growth at those finer levels of industry. Gordon being wrong about whether specific technologies are improving does not make him wrong about aggregate growth declining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the fact that aggregate growth was high in the 40’s and 50’s doesn’t necessarily mean that individual technologies were improving faster than they are today.I don’t have the data, but I’d be fascinated to know what this figure looks like going backwards in the 1950’s and 1940’s, during Gordon’s golden age of productivity growth. Were those decades really a time of amazing “true” technological growth - which might be proxied by the within-sector effect - or did they benefit as much from strong across-sector and covariance terms?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One plausible reason for strong across-sector and covariance terms is the hump-shaped nature of demand for manufactured goods. In the 40’s and 50’s and 60’s, there was within-sector productivity growth in durable goods - refrigerators, TVs, cars - for sure. But this also generated large movements of people &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; those sectors, which would have produced big positive across-sector and covariance terms. Why? Because Americans didn’t own lots of refrigerators, cars, and TVs. Higher within-sector productivity would have lowered prices, and a high elasticity of demand would have meant those sectors pulled labor into those sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But by the 70’s and later, higher within-sector productivity growth in durables and other manufatures may not have generated the same across-sector and covariance effects. Why? Because there are limits to durable good demand. Once everyone has a refrigerator, they tend to want to buy other things, and not &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; refrigerator. I know that’s not totally true; I have a 2nd fridge in my garage that serves as a strategic beer reserve. But in general, demand for durable goods becomes less elastic as we get richer. Which means that within-sector productivity gains don’t pull workers into manufacturing employment, it actively pushes them &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt;. And because the sectors that labor is moving into are relatively low productivity, and have low productivity growth, we get negative across-sector and covariance terms. By the way, there is nothing here that William Baumol couldn’t have told you thirty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A comparison with South Korea is interesting, because they are several decades behind the US in this transformation. In the figure below I plotted the same rolling 10-year growth rates as for the US. It shows the big across-sector contribution to growth in South Korea in the 80’s and 90’s, as they were industrializing heavily and the elasticity of demand for those kinds of durable goods was still large. Compare the figures, and you’ll see that while the US may have had 8% total growth in VAPH due to across-sector effects at the maximum, in South Korea this maximum is closer to 40%. As South Korea got richer, this across-sector contribution has been falling, but is still adding about 6% to total growth in VAPH. The example of South Korea is why I think that part of the explanation for the rapid productivity growth in the US during the 40’s and 50’s could be across-sector effects, and not just a higher rate of innovation or technological change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_kor_decomp_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;SK Decomposition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has now gotten so long that I need to wrap it up. Let me try to do that by essentially repeating my summary from above. You cannot talk about aggregate productivity growth without talking about both technology &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the distribution of workers across sectors. Anecdotes - positive or negative - about individual technologies are not informative about the aggregate level of productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Concentration and Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Comp-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Comp-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A whole raft of posts and articles (&lt;a href=&quot;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2612047&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://promarket.org/are-we-all-rent-seeking-investors/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://equitablegrowth.org/what-are-the-factors-behind-high-economic-rents/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2015/12/17/robert-reich-challenging-oligarchy/#fnr-5&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) has shown up recently regarding “rent-seeking”. This is kind of a catch-all for increased concentration within industries, more lenient anti-trust enforcement, and the increasing share of corporate profits in output. This is then tied to the slowdown in wages over the last few decades, increasing inequality, and even to slower aggregate growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments made by those &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; the concentrating and profit-making is that they are promoting efficiency, productivity, and hence growth. Do we know whether concentration or rent-seeking would be good or bad?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to draw a lot on one of my professors in grad school, Peter Howitt, who along with Philippe Aghion is really one of the godfathers of studying competition and growth. They have a really nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nber.org/papers/w18824.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; with Ufuk Akcigit regarding their “Schumpeterian theory” and how it connects to the data. Schumpeterian theory, for the uninitiated, is growth theory that explicitly deals with firms replacing each other by innovating. This “creative destruction” is what gives the theory its moniker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/aah1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Competition and innovation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AAH paper provides a few sets of empirical results culled from various work done by the authors. One of the most interesting is in the figure posted above, using British industry data, which plots patent activity by firms against the level of competition in their industry. Competition is measured by the ratio of marginal costs to price; the inverse of the markup a firm can charge. A higher ratio means MC and P are very close together in the industry, and hence it is very competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you can see is that patent activity, a proxy for innovation, has this inverted U-shape with respect to competition. That is, increasing competition doesn’t necessary mean more innovation. Why? Because at some point it isn’t worth it to the firms. If you have little market power, what incentive do you have to innovate? In contrast, if you have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of market*, then you also are less inclined to innovate, because why bother? You already control market share, and R&amp;amp;D is just a cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “neck-and-neck” industries are just those in which the leading firms are very close in productivity level. They have an additional incentive to innovate (which shows up as their curve being shifted up) because these firms want to try and shed their main competitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, what this figure implies for concentration and growth is that it depends. Concentration and consolidation mean that industries are moving to the &lt;em&gt;left&lt;/em&gt; along the x-axis, with less competition. Now, if that industry were already very competitive (close to 1, say), the consolidation may actually increase innovation. But if the industry is already consolidated to some degree, then decreasing competition is going to lower innovation and growth. I have in my head the difference between Marriott consolidating hotel chains around the country in the 70s and 80s, reaping some economies of scale, and investing in improved hotel quality, and Marriott in 2016, buying Starwood. Marriott will probably want to argue that they will still innovate more, but the worry is that they are on the “wrong side of the curve” in AAH’s diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/aah2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Entry and Growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second result AAH focus on deals with frontier versus backward firms. Here, they again look at British firms, but along the x-axis is the degree of competition measured by the entry of foreign firms into their industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For “frontier” firms, meaning those who have productivity levels close to the maximum in the industry, increased competition leads to &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; productivity growth. These firms respond to the foreign competition by getting better. But for “non-frontier” firms, the increased entry means they innovate &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt;. Their productivity growth rate actually falls. They don’t try as hard to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question with this result is what it implies for concentration. If concentration means less competition (going left on the x-axis) then this implies frontier firms will innovate &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt;, while non-frontier firms will innovate &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;. But of course concentration implies that firms are buying up one another (or forcing one another out of business). It seems likely that it is the frontier firms pushing the non-frontier firms out of business with concentration. Hence the lower competition would lower the growth rate of productivity in the frontier, and now larger, firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very nice, specific, example of the effect of competition on productivity is in one of my favorite &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.stanford.edu/~klenow/Schmitz.pdf&quot;&gt;papers&lt;/a&gt;, by James Schmitz. He studies the reaction of the US and Canadian iron ore industries to competition from Brazilian suppliers. They responded by massively upgrading productivity relative to its level in the prior decades. His figure shows the jump in labor productivity in the US industry around the early 1980’s, when Brazil came online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/schmitz.png&quot; alt=&quot;Iron Ore Productivity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting about this paper is that Schmitz documents how nearly all of the improvement in productivity came through work practices. There was not any massive technical innovation at play here. The competition changed behavior at the producers of iron ore, and essentially got capital utilization rates (i.e. hours of use per day of machines) way up over prior levels. Productivity improvements are not necessarily a function of R&amp;amp;D, these firms could have made those improvements for decades before Brazil entered. But they had a dominant market position, and didn’t need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, yes, the increasing concentration of industry and rent-seeking, may well be having a demonstrable drag on productivity growth. If this concentration has reduced the need to innovate to stay ahead, because no one can compete with you any more, then this is a negative for growth. Industries, like the iron ore industry prior to the 80’s, that have concentrated market structures with little competition, may not implement even obvious productivity improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there has been a long-run increase in concentration, decline in entry, and consolidation of market power, then this could be part of the productivity slow-down of the late 20th century/early 21st. Ryan Decker, John Haltiwanger, Javier Miranda, and Ron Jarmin, have been banging on the subject of declining “dynamism” for a while. Ryan’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rdecker.net/research&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; is probably the easiest place to find this research all centralized. While I expressed &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/economic-dynamism-and-productivity-growth/&quot;&gt;caution&lt;/a&gt; that declining new business formation is, by itself, necessarily a sign of slower innovation, the whole body of evidence they have about slower gross flows of workers between firms and firms into/out of existence suggests something is quite different over the last few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, and this is my impression, not some kind of established fact, concentration likely lowers innovative activity. Put it this way, the null hypothesis should probably be that concentration lowers innovation. An individual industry needs to provide evidence they are on the “right side of the curve” in the first AAH figure to believe concentration would be good for productivity growth in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Productivity versus Technology in American Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-TFP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-TFP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I just &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-Review/&quot;&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; Bob Gordon’s book on the rise and fall of American growth. A quick recap of Gordon’s thesis is that we experienced an anomalous burst of technological progress during the 1930’s and 1940’s, bleeding a little into the 1950’s and 60’s. Prior to that period, and since that period, technological progress was relatively slow, and Gordon expects that slow technological progress to be the norm for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thesis is based in large part on evidence of differences in TFP growth decade-by-decade. Gordon’s Figure 16-5 is probably the key graph in his book, as it shows TFP growth of 3.5% per year during the 1940’s, well above the norm for other decades. Even without the 1940’s, TFP growth around 1.5% per year in the 30’s, 50’s, and 60’s. In contrast, TFP growth was below 1% per year in the 1900’s, 10’s, and 20’s, as well as the 1980’s, 90’s, and 2000’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But TFP growth is measured as a residual, and is not necessarily equal to a measure of technology. I’ve made this point &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/labors-share-profits-and-the-productivity-slowdown/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; on this blog, but it is worth revisiting in light of Gordon’s book. In short, do Gordon’s TFP growth rates really indicate significant differences in &lt;em&gt;technological&lt;/em&gt; growth by decade?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;residuals-and-technology&quot;&gt;Residuals and Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, we have to establish how TFP and technology are related. The residual measure of TFP that Gordon uses is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R = \frac{Y}{K^{1-s_L}L^{s_L}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is a completely standard way of doing this. The &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L\inline&quot;/&gt; is labor’s share of revenues (GDP). As is typical, Gordon assumes there are constant returns to scale so that capital’s share is mechanically &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-s_L\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Output is actually defined by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = A K^{\alpha} L^{\beta},&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where I’ve left open the possibility that the elasticities on capital and labor add up to something other than one. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha+\beta&amp;gt;1\inline&quot;/&gt;, then you have increasing returns to scale. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha+\beta=1\inline&quot;/&gt;, you have constant returns. The term &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?A\inline&quot;/&gt; is the actual measure of technology. The residual measure Gordon uses is thus capturing the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R = A \frac{K^{\alpha - s_K}}{L^{\beta - s_L}}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is pretty clear that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?R\inline&quot;/&gt; need not necessarily be equal to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?A\inline&quot;/&gt;. In terms of growth rates, which is what Gordon is focused on, we can write this as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{R}}{R} = \frac{\dot{A}}{A} + (\alpha - 1 + s_L)\frac{\dot{K}}{K} + (\beta-s_L) \frac{\dot{L}}{L},&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the growth rate of the residual is not necessarily equal to the growth rate of technology. It all depends on whether the revenue shares, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-s_L\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L\inline&quot;/&gt;, are in fact equal to the elasticities, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get some structure to understand why they might differ, we can make the minimal assumption that firms are cost-minimizers. In that case it will be true that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\alpha + \beta = \mu(1-s_{\pi}).&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation says that the returns to scale, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha + \beta\inline&quot;/&gt;, are equal to the markup of prices over marginal cost, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu \geq 1\inline&quot;/&gt;, times the share of revenues that are paid to factors of production. That share is one minus the share of revenues paid out as profits, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi}\inline&quot;/&gt;. Note that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi} &amp;gt; 0\inline&quot;/&gt; means that the shares of output paid to capital and labor need not add up to one - but in Gordon’s calculation they have to add up to one. Gordon’s assumption is very typical, but it is one way of the things that will generate a possible divergence between the measure of productivity and the measure of technology. If you’re interested at all in how to derive all this, the ideas come from &lt;a href=&quot;#hall1988&quot;&gt;(Hall 1988; Hall 1989; Basu &amp;amp; Fernald 2002)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings us back to the residual measure. If you plug in the scale, markup, profit relationship into the growth rate of the residual, and rearrange, you can come up with the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{R}}{R} = \frac{\dot{A}}{A} + (\mu(1-s_{\pi}) -1)\frac{\dot{K}}{K} + s_L(\mu-1)\left[\frac{\dot{L}}{L} - \frac{\dot{K}}{K}\right].&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the only way to write this, as you can manipulate the equation into different forms. But I think this is a useful way to look at things. This says that there is a difference between the growth rate of TFP, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{R}/R\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the growth rate of technology, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{A}/A\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of this difference is the term involving &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi}\inline&quot;/&gt;, and this is picking up any effects of increasing returns to scale. If there are IRS, then this term will be non-zero. The increase in scale associated with a larger capital stock generates higher measured productivity growth, even if technology isn’t growing any faster than normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part of this difference is the last term involving &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L(\mu-1)\inline&quot;/&gt;. This captures the fact that assuming capital’s share in output is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-s_L\inline&quot;/&gt; may be wrong. If it is wrong, which would show up as &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu&amp;gt;1\inline&quot;/&gt; in some way, then the growth rate of TFP isn’t going to be equal to the growth rate of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-these-adjustments-matter&quot;&gt;Do these adjustments matter?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Gordon is relying on is that the residual TFP measure is in fact a good gauge of technological growth. In other words, that the two adjustments I outlined above are close to zero. That will be true if we have constant returns to scale, so &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha+\beta = 1\inline&quot;/&gt;, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; firms have no market power so that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu=1\inline&quot;/&gt;. These assumptions are commonly made, so it isn’t like Gordon is doing anything sneaky. Even if he is wrong about those precise values, if firms had a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; market power, so that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu=1.02\inline&quot;/&gt;, or there were mild IRS, so &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha+\beta=1.01\inline&quot;/&gt;, then the adjustments would be insignificant. Gordon’s measures of TFP growth are good measures of technological growth if we think that production is constant returns and markups are sufficiently close to one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if they are not, though? The period of time that has the biggest spike in TFP growth is the 1940’s, which seems to have a number of odd features that make me wary of the assumption about markups and returns being close to one. First, there were guaranteed markups given to firms producing defense goods (which Gordon mentions himself on page 553). Second, there were clearly some massive economies of scale in production during this decade. The U.S. didn’t build B-24 bombers at a bunch of mom-and-pop bomber assembly shops. They were built in a single location, Willow Run, at a peak rate of 432 &lt;em&gt;per month&lt;/em&gt; in 1944. It seems hard to believe that there weren’t economies of scale at work in the economy of the 1940’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does that have a meaningful quantitative impact on the measurement of technology growth? I’m eyeballing numbers here from Gordon’s graphs, so this is fuzzy, but I think it can give an idea of what was going on. First, we need a measure of capital growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{K}/K\inline&quot;/&gt;, and labor growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{L}/L\inline&quot;/&gt;. For capital growth, I used Gordon’s table A-2, which shows his adjusted capital stock data for several select years, including 1941 and 1950. Using those, it looks like capital grew at 1.7% per year in the 1940’s. That feels low, given the war, but isn’t really any different than the growth rate reported by the BEA. I have no real reasons to question the rate. For labor, I did go back to an NBER publication by &lt;a href=&quot;http://papers.nber.org/books/kend61-1&quot;&gt;Kendrick&lt;/a&gt; that Gordon uses, and tried to dig up the growth in hours he uses. Combining that with the adjustment for labor quality growth that Gordon pulled from &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/zanran_storage/www.hup.harvard.edu/ContentPages/50365105.pdf&quot;&gt;Goldin and Katz&lt;/a&gt;, Table 1.3, I get a total growth rate of labor of 1.8% per year for the 1940’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With those, I need a markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu\inline&quot;/&gt;. For the moment, let’s try to see how big of an effect I can have, and choose &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu=1.5\inline&quot;/&gt;. That’s big, with 50% markups over marginal cost. But if there really were massive economies of scale, then this kind of markup may not be that implausible. The last things to plug in are the share of revenues for labor, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L\inline&quot;/&gt;, and profits, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi}\inline&quot;/&gt;. For &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L\inline&quot;/&gt;, I use Gordon’s number, 0.7. For profits? I don’t know. It is quite plausible that firms in the 40’s charged markups, but that those were to cover fixed costs. So perhaps true economic profits are zero? Again, I’m trying to see how big of an effect these adjustments might have, so let’s set &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi} =0\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, from Gordon’s figure 16-5 we know that measured TFP growth in the 1940’s was about 3.3% per year. So put this all together and we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;0.033 = \frac{\dot{A}}{A} + (1.5(1-0)-1)0.017 + 0.7(1.5-1)(0.018-0.017) = \frac{\dot{A}}{A} + 0.00885.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the residual growth rate &lt;em&gt;overstates&lt;/em&gt; technological growth by about 0.85 percentage points per year. Technological growth was 0.033 - 0.00885 = 0.02415, or 2.42% per year, not 3.3% per year. That is a pretty sizable adjustment. But it is still very high compared to all other decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we’d have to make this adjustment to all those other decades as well. Would that lower their implied technology growth as well? That depends on (a) the growth rate of inputs in those decades, and (b) what you assume about the markup in those years. I think you could make the case that the adjustment would be much smaller in other decades. First, the growth rate of inputs is slower. The labor measure Gordon uses combines hours worked with an adjustment for growth in quality of labor. Labor quality (i.e. schooling) is growing more slowly now, and labor hours are not rising as fast due to both demographics and shorter work weeks. So it could easily be that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{K}/K &amp;gt; \dot{L}/L\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the growth rate of TFP &lt;em&gt;understates&lt;/em&gt; technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, maybe IRS was something unique to the 40’s (or other mid-century decades), which would eliminate the first adjustment due to scale. The transition towards services would certainly be one reason to believe that we do not have as much possibility of IRS in aggregate production. The 40’s may have been unique in having a large fraction of output produced by IRS industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played around with several other decades, with the idea of seeing if any adjustments are even &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; that could eliminate the gap in technological growth from the 1940’s. But there is no plausible way I see to make adjustments to their productivity growth that deliver “real” technological growth close to 2.42% per year. The adjustments are not big enough to change Gordon’s main thesis. The 1940’s appear to be an outlier(s) in terms of technology growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, some of the observed productivity growth in the 1940’s is probably not technology growth, per se, but rather reaping the benefits of increasing returns to scale. One way of interpreting Gordon’s thesis is that the WWII era was special because it incorporated IRS production into the economy, and that really was a one-time thing. But now that we’ve added those industries - and because there is ultimately limited demand for their output - we no longer reap the benefits of those IRS. If you pushed this far enough, then I think you would be worried less about Gordon’s “headwinds”. It isn’t that we are somehow failing to match the technological growth of an earlier period, it’s that we simply outgrew the stage at which IRS boosted measured productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;basufernald&quot;&gt;Basu, S. &amp;amp; Fernald, J., 2002. Aggregate Productivity and Aggregate Technology. &lt;i&gt;European Economic Review&lt;/i&gt;, 46, pp.963–991.&lt;/span&gt;  

&lt;div id=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style: none;&quot;&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;Abstract&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Aggregate productivity and aggregate technology are meaningful but distinct concepts. We show that a slightly-modified Solow productivity residual measures changes in economic welfare, even when productivity and technology differ because of distortions such as imperfect competition. We then present a general accounting framework that identifies several new non-technological gaps between productivity and technology, gaps reflecting imperfections and frictions in output and factor markets. Empirically, we find that these gaps are important, even though we abstract from variations in factor utilization and estimate only small average sectoral markups. Compared with productivity growth, our measured technology shocks are significantly less correlated with output, and are essentially uncorrelated with inputs. Our results imply that calibrating dynamic general equilibrium models as if Solow residuals were technology shocks confuses impulses and propagation mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;BibTeX&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;pre&gt;@article{basufernald,
  author = {Basu, Susanto and Fernald, John},
  date-added = {2013-04-20 00:29:41 +0000},
  date-modified = {2016-04-06 20:40:58 +0000},
  journal = {European Economic Review},
  keywords = {alloc},
  pages = {963-991},
  title = {Aggregate Productivity and Aggregate Technology},
  volume = {46},
  year = {2002}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hall1988&quot;&gt;Hall, R.E., 1988. The Relation between Price and Marginal Cost in U.S. Industry. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Political Economy&lt;/i&gt;, 96(5), pp.921–47. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/ucp/jpolec/v96y1988i5p921-47.html&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;  

&lt;div id=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style: none;&quot;&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;Abstract&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;p&gt; An examination of data on output and labor input reveals that some U.S. industries have marginal cost well below price. The conclusion rests on the finding that cyclical variations in labor input are small compared with variations in output. In booms, firms produce substantially more output and sell it for a price that exceeds the costs of the added inputs. This paper documents the disparity between price and marginal cost, where marginal cost is estimated from annual variations in cost. It considers a variety of explanations of the findings that are consistent with competition, but none is found to be completely plausible. Copyright 1988 by University of Chicago Press.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;BibTeX&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;pre&gt;@article{hall1988,
  author = {Hall, Robert E},
  date-added = {2016-04-06 20:43:33 +0000},
  date-modified = {2016-04-06 20:45:58 +0000},
  journal = {Journal of Political Economy},
  keywords = {account,alloc},
  month = oct,
  number = {5},
  pages = {921-47},
  title = {{The Relation between Price and Marginal Cost in U.S. Industry}},
  url = {https://ideas.repec.org/a/ucp/jpolec/v96y1988i5p921-47.html},
  volume = {96},
  year = {1988},
  bdsk-url-1 = {https://ideas.repec.org/a/ucp/jpolec/v96y1988i5p921-47.html}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hall1989&quot;&gt;Hall, R.E., 1989. &lt;i&gt;Invariance Properties of Solow’s Productivity Residual&lt;/i&gt;, National Bureau of Economic Research. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nber.org/papers/w3034&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;  

&lt;div id=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style: none;&quot;&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;Abstract&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;In 1957, Robert Solow published a paper that provided the theoretical foundation for almost all subsequent work on productivity measurement. Although most applications of Solow’s method have measured trends over fairly long time periods, the method also has important uses at higher frequencies. Under constant returns to scale and competition, the Solow residual measures the pure shift of the production function. Shifts in product demand and factor supplies should have no effect on the residual. Tests of this invariance property show that it fails in a great many industries. Though other explanations may deserve some weight, it appears that the leading cause of the failure of invariance is increasing returns and market power. The empirical findings give some support to the theory of monopolistic competition.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;BibTeX&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;pre&gt;@techreport{hall1989,
  author = {Hall, Robert E.},
  date-added = {2016-04-06 20:45:30 +0000},
  date-modified = {2016-04-06 20:47:29 +0000},
  doi = {10.3386/w3034},
  institution = {National Bureau of Economic Research},
  keywords = {alloc, account},
  month = jul,
  number = {3034},
  series = {Working Paper Series},
  title = {Invariance Properties of Solow&#39;s Productivity Residual},
  type = {Working Paper},
  url = {http://www.nber.org/papers/w3034},
  year = {1989},
  bdsk-url-1 = {http://www.nber.org/papers/w3034},
  bdsk-url-2 = {http://dx.doi.org/10.3386/w3034}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savings, Savings, and More Savings</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings-Redux/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings-Redux/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is about savings. It is also a plea with Nick Rowe to slow the &lt;em&gt;)#&lt;/em&gt;#@ down in posting things that get stuck in my head. I’m still working on this savings thing, and now he’s got a &lt;a href=&quot;http://worthwhile.typepad.com/worthwhile_canadian_initi/2014/05/mrscc1r1mpkmrtcidmrtcidt.html&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; up about capital that I’m chewing over too. I have a life, Nick, for God’s sake - pump the brakes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, this is just a wrap-up of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about “What happens to GDP if I save 100 dollars”? And the point there was that this is an ill-formed question. Or at least it is ill-formed because we economists have screwed up by using the word “savings” for lots of different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of an individual, they earn income in dollars. That income in dollars is divided across several different uses, several of which could be called “savings”. So let’s be a little more exact. Write &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Inc_t = C_{t,now} + C_{t,later} + I_t + Bank_t&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This says that income can be spent in four ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C_{t,now}\inline&quot;/&gt; is spending on consumption goods (or services) that are consumed in period &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;. For example, I bought a Diet Coke this afternoon, and just drank it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C_{t,later}\inline&quot;/&gt; is spending on consumption goods that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; consumed in period &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;. For example, I bought a case of Diet Coke today, and it is sitting in my office. I will not consume all of those Diet Cokes before the close of 2016Q1. The purchase, though, gets added to 2016Q1 GDP, even though I don’t consume all of them that quarter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I_t\inline&quot;/&gt; is spending on investment goods. Which, to be clear, is simply an arbitrary definition based on an assumption about what the goods will be used for. An example here would be if I bought a bulldozer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Bank_t\inline&quot;/&gt; is the net change in my bank account in period &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;. This could be positive (I saved!) or negative (I borrowed!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In plain English, numbers (2)-(4) all could conceivably be called “savings”. For the purposes of thinking about macroeconomics, though, the distinction between (4) and (1)-(3) is crucial. (1)-(3), whatever you call them, all involve actually &lt;em&gt;spending&lt;/em&gt; money. Whether you spend that money on goods that you then put in the pantry, or store underground, or use to produce more goods next period is irrelevant. You spent the money. “What happens to GDP if I save 100 dollars?” is, I’m sure, a question about what happens if I increase (4) by 100 dollars and decrease (1)-(3) in combination by 100 dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I said in the last post was that this &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have an effect on GDP. It certainly lowers the velocity of money, so nominal GDP would fall. If prices are sticky, then real GDP would fall as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have in mind a different concept of “save 100 dollars” then the effect on GDP could be different. If you mean that you raise (2) or (3) by 100 dollars while lowering (4) by 100 dollars, then this could &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; GDP. You are now spending 100 dollars that you otherwise would not have. You have raised velocity, so nominal GDP goes up, and if prices are sticky, real GDP goes up too. Even though you are “saving” 100 dollars of goods by buying a bulldozer or putting your Diet Coke cans in the garage fridge for later, you still spent 100 dollars on goods - and that is all GDP cares about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, perhaps by “save 100 dollars” you mean that you lowered (1) or (2) by 100 and raised (3) by 100. That is, you “saved” by switching from buying consumption goods to buying investment goods. What effect does that have on GDP in period &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;? None (okay, maybe a 2nd order effect if investment good producers have a different propensity to spend their income than you do). You still spent the 100 dollars. In the future, this may effect GDP because the bulldozer may let you produce more output. In growth models, like the Solow model, “savings” mean spending money on (3). And the more you save, the higher will be GDP in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the original question is best phrased as “What happens to GDP in this period if I put 100 dollars of my money in the bank this period rather than spending it on any kind of good or service?” And that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; lower GDP today. If you mean a different kind of “savings”, then you have to be specific. Or, as economists we have to teach you to be more specific. Or, as economists we have to push back and force you to be more specific. Because the answers are different depending on what you mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beware-what-follows&quot;&gt;Beware what follows&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last bit is all wild-ass speculation. If each person has an budget constraint of the form I gave above, we could add up across all individuals like this
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum_i Inc_t = \sum_i C_{t,now} + \sum_i C_{t,later} + \sum_i I_t + \sum_i Bank_t.&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say that total spending on goods and services (the two C terms plus the I term) are equal to some multiple, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?c\inline&quot;/&gt;, of income. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?c\inline&quot;/&gt; could be greater than one (so people are net borrowing) or less than (people are net saving). Then I have
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1-c) \sum_i Inc_t = \sum_i Bank_t.&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sum of income flowing to individuals has to add up to nominal GDP by the national income product accounts, so call &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_i Inc_t = PY\inline&quot;/&gt;. Then plugging this in and rearranging I have
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;PY = \frac{\sum_i Bank_t}{1-c}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(1-c)&amp;gt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, then this means people do not spend all their income, so it makes sense that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_i Bank_t &amp;gt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;. In other words, savings are accumulating in aggregate. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(1-c)&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, then it makes sense that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_i Bank_t&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, or savings are de-cumulating in aggregate. Either way, the ratio on the right is positive, and equal to nominal GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this some kind of bastard quantity theory? I ask because I honestly don’t know. I don’t even know what to make of this, or if I made some kind of dumb mistake in here somewhere. Should I take this seriously? Could I think of the terms in the ratio becoming unlinked? That is, could we think that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?c\inline&quot;/&gt; stays constant, but &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_i Bank_t\inline&quot;/&gt; goes up in absolute value, so nominal GDP goes up? What would it mean for the total flow of money into banks to go up, but for people’s propensity to consume from their income to stay the same?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reviewing the Rise and Fall of American Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-Review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-Review/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I finished reading Robert Gordon’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1Sb860J&quot;&gt;The Rise and Fall of American Growth&lt;/a&gt; a while ago, but finally found the time to write down an extended review. I’m way behind the curve. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foreignaffairs.com/reviews/review-essay/2016-02-15/innovation-over&quot;&gt;Tyler Cowen&lt;/a&gt; has an excellent review, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/UpdatedPriors&quot;&gt;Ryan Decker&lt;/a&gt; sort of live-tweeted his way through the book recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin, a comparison. A few months ago I praised Garrett Jones for the sleek nature of &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1UQCXV6&quot;&gt;Hive Mind&lt;/a&gt;. The Rise and Fall of American Growth is, um .. not sleek. It starts out with a 531-page description of the diffusion of major innovations within the U.S. over the last 140 years, then transitions to a 104-page presentation of Gordon’s thesis about what generated differences in productivity growth in that period, and finishes with a 12-page postscript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on what you’re after, this is either a bug or a feature. As a statement of Gordon’s thesis regarding productivity growth, it’s a bug. You can read Gordon’s thesis in two (free) working papers (&lt;a href=&quot;http://economics.weinberg.northwestern.edu/robert-gordon/Is%20US%20Economic%20Growth%20Over.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://economics.weinberg.northwestern.edu/robert-gordon/NBER%20P383F%20Sequel_140126.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The 531 pages of anecdotes about technology diffusion are ancillary to making this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the 531 pages are a feature if you want to understand just how amazing the transition in living standards has been over the last 140 years. For that purpose, the unending onslaught of facts, stories, and comparisons is necessary to make the case. Gordon takes the reader through the transition from the disconnected, unhealthy, underfed, dark lifestyle facing workers in 1880 to a world of lights, abundant food, communication, travel, and health. And that’s just by 1940. The core networks of modern life - electricity, sewers, roads, broadcasting - were in place by the end of the Great Depression. Despite these massive changes in welfare, what Gordon documents is that measured productivity growth up through the 1930’s was actually quite low. Growth in GDP per capita systematically understates growth in welfare; this is not something that has arisen recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1950’s, and spilling into the 60’s and early 1970’s, productivity growth jumped appreciably. For Gordon, this is partly a feature of those core networks being extended out into the whole country. Diffusion, more than innovation, is what fundamentally explains the spike in measured productivity growth in the immediate post-war period. Since the 1970’s, productivity growth has retreated back to pre-WWII levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I don’t understand about the book is the insistence that the &lt;em&gt;welfare&lt;/em&gt; gains of growth after the mid-century are necessarily smaller. Maybe they are, maybe they aren’t. Fundamentally it is a book about economic growth, not welfare growth. Yet all I kept hearing in my head while reading the second half of the 531-page narrative was “you darn kids and your Facebook”. This may just be a problem of tone, but it also pushes Gordon close to a real problem. He veers close to using the assumption that the welfare gains of current innovation are small to conclude that the rate of economic growth in the future must be small as well. That does not follow. It is quite possible that productivity growth could spike to 3.5% per year again in the 2020’s, and yet the welfare gains of this could be trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But will growth spike to 3.5% again? Gordon says no. For him, the innovations in the early 20th century were unique. In networking everyone together, they had a one-time boost to productivity that the computing/internet revolution of the last twenty years cannot match, and more importantly &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; not match. The productivity growth facts are what they are, productivity has grown much slower 1995-2015 than 1950-1970. But that doesn’t mean productivity growth will stay low. We just don’t know. Tyler Cowen’s review does a great job of laying out the fundamental problem; future technology is unforecastable. And while Gordon makes a passing effort at claiming it is, his anecdotal example of a &lt;em&gt;Ladies Home Journal&lt;/em&gt; from 1900 predicting air conditioning does not constitute evidence. We just don’t know what new innovations will bring, or what effect they will have on economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, there is a very powerful idea running along underneath Gordon’s book, and I don’t know that he draws enough attention to it. Gordon’s narrative shares a feature of Piketty’s &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt;; it questions aspects of the Kaldor Facts that have formed the basis for most work on economic growth. Those facts were based on observations made in the 1950’s-70’s. Piketty showed that the idea of a constant labor share is not a universal feature of growth, but an anomaly of immediate post-war period. Gordon shows that rapid, sustained productivity growth was &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; an anomaly of the immediate post-war period (see his Figure 16-5). Together, these two authors tell us that the stylized facts that generations of growth models have tried to match are probably wrong. So whatever the other merits of Gordon’s book, it is valuable for making this point vividly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve built generations of growth models on the idea that they have to deliver “balanced growth paths” because those match up to the Kaldor Facts. But if those facts do not hold, then this opens up a much wider set of possible growth models. Growth could run out of steam, growth could accelerate, growth could follow a random walk, etc. etc.. In that sense, Gordon’s book is worth reading, in that it forces you to reconsider - or at least defend - the assumptions underlying our explanations for economic growth. You could probably have gotten there in under 647 pages, but nevertheless it is a good point.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You Saved What?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nick Rowe just had a &lt;a href=&quot;http://worthwhile.typepad.com/worthwhile_canadian_initi/2016/02/does-saving-count-towards-gdp.html#more&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about the effect of savings on GDP. I’m paraphrasing, but a student asks him whether “saving an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100” raises GDP (or not), because the national income product accounts can be written as\inline&quot;/&gt;Y = C + S + T&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?. I think Nick nails the issue, which is that you &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; specify “instead of what?” when you say you “save an extra\inline&quot;/&gt;100”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve run into the same question before, and I’ve gone back and forth on how best to explain the answer (which, strictly speaking, is “it depends”). This also gives me a chance to rant a little about my pet peeve of measuring GDP in dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem we have is that “save an extra $100” means “keep 100 slips of green paper in my wallet rather than spending them” to any normal human being. This is a statement about how you use the medium of exchange. It’s a statement inherently related to the turnover of that medium of exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the word “savings” and the symbol “S” are also used as a concept in national income product accounts to stand for “the value of goods and services that are neither consumed nor handed over to the government as taxes”. Because you typically measure the value of good and services using dollars, this creates confusion. But “&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 of S” is a statement that uses dollars as a unit of account, and has nothing to do with\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of the medium of exchange. “&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 of S” means that you purchased\inline&quot;/&gt;100 worth of goods and services, &lt;em&gt;and then saved those goods and services&lt;/em&gt;. It does not mean you kept 100 slips of green paper in your wallet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question from Nick’s student isn’t easy to answer, and it should be easier. He wants to know the effect on GDP if he “saves an extra $100”, and right now the answer gets confusing because of this confusion in medium of exchange and unit of account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be clearer if we didn’t insist on measuring GDP (and its components like S) in units of dollars. Yes, we tell everyone they are “2005 dollars” or something like that, but we all hear “dollars!” in our head and think of little slips of green paper. I really think a better way to do this would be to just measure GDP as physical units of output. You can do this in a crude (but effective) way by just measuring GDP as the equivalent number of cans of Diet Cokes (e.g. divide nominal GDP by $0.85, the price in our department vending machine). Or if you insist on being more accurate, divide nominal GDP by the actual dollar value of the CPI basket, and you’ll get “number of CPI baskets produced”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, if GDP is in real terms - Diet Cokes or CPI baskets - then we no longer have this confusion of the medium of exchange (dollars) and the unit of account (DC or CPI baskets). When you say you “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100”, I think it now becomes obvious that you &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; complete that statement with “…instead of buying\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Cokes or CPI baskets”. It is clear what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re not totally out of the woods. GDP is a flow concept, not a stock. So it’s impossible to specify the effect of “saving an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 instead of buying\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Coke” without saying precisely &lt;em&gt;how long&lt;/em&gt; you plan to save that money for. It is March 6th. If you “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100” today by not spending it, and don’t spend it until April 13th, then &lt;em&gt;first quarter GDP&lt;/em&gt; goes down by at least\inline&quot;/&gt;100. At least. You not spending that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 means someone else didn’t earn that\inline&quot;/&gt;100, and they cannot spend the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100, and so there may be a whole chain of transactions that don’t occur because you saved an extra\inline&quot;/&gt;100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100” on March 6th, but then spend that\inline&quot;/&gt;100 on March 8th, first quarter GDP might not got down at all. You still spent the $100 in the first quarter, and all the subsequent transactions that might be keyed off of your spending still have time to occur. Maybe the 2 day delay means that someone 15 transactions down the line doesn’t get a chance to buy a Snickers bar until April 1st, and now that transaction is not counted in first quarter GDP any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t solve our problem, because we didn’t account for the fact that maybe the producers will respond to our lack of spending by changing prices. If you “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 instead of buying\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Coke” on March 6th, then the DC distributor might notice that 117.67 cans of DC are still on the shelf on March 7th that they expected to be gone. They figure this represents lower demand, so to clear their inventory they lower the price. By March 31st, even though &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; didn’t spend $100 on Diet Cokes, somebody bought those cheaper Diet Cokes and hence real GDP (the number of Diet Cokes sold) is the same as if you hadn’t saved that money at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that there is a simple way to teach this stuff. I think you could probably spend a whole semester just going over (and over and over) the difference between GDP and the money supply. Let me take a crack at a relatively simple way of accomodating a question about what happens when you “save an extra $100”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key here is the Quantity Theory of Money. It is an identity that tells us how to determine nominal GDP. You know the formula, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MV = PY\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone says “save an extra $100”, they mean “lower velocity” by some amount. They are turning over their actual dollars more slowly (e.g. waiting until April 13th to spend them). How much velocity goes down is a question of (a) how long they wait to spend the money and (b) how crucial that spending is for everyone else’s spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, because V has gone down, it must be that either M goes up, or PY has gone down. If we assume that M stays constant, then it has to be that PY goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens to &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; GDP - cans of Diet Coke - Y? That depends on how flexible you think prices are. If P can adjust easily (the DC distributor notices quickly and lowers prices), then Y may be unaffected by your decision to “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100”. But if prices are sticky, then your decision to save\inline&quot;/&gt;100 has to lower Y by an amount proportional to how much velocity goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about that whole NIPA accounting equation &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = C + S + T\inline&quot;/&gt;? Well, what about it? S is a classification of real GDP. S is the number of Diet Cokes that you &lt;em&gt;buy&lt;/em&gt;, but do not actually &lt;em&gt;drink&lt;/em&gt;. S is “GDP that is neither consumed nor given to the government”. Yes, the BEA calls that “savings”, but that is a crappy term that just causes confusion. If we measured GDP in real units, and stopped using the term “savings” both for “dollars not spent” and “goods and services not consumed”, we wouldn’t have to keep rehashing these questions again and again every year with a new set of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I might have read Nick’s post wrong, and maybe the student was asking about spending 100 gold pieces to raise his &lt;em&gt;saving throw&lt;/em&gt; from a 17 to an 18. Easy mistake to make.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growth References</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/New-References/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/New-References/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A very quick post just to alert you that I’ve added a new page of &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/references/&quot;&gt;references&lt;/a&gt; to the site. It is essentially a dump of my own BibTeX file, broken down by topic area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s incomplete, but as I clean up and add to the references over time, they’ll populate to that page. Of course, I’ll probably be in my 70’s before I get around to it, but maybe announcing it publicly will act as a commitment device. It can’t make me go any &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; at fixing up my BibTeX file, that’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Accelerate Growth Rates</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Accelerate-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Accelerate-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A good amount of discussion takes place about how to accelerate growth, with a lot of prominent examples coming from the US presidential primaries. Jeb! promised to get the growth rate of GDP to 4%. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dollarsandsense.org/What-would-Sanders-do-013016.pdf&quot;&gt;Gerald Friedman&lt;/a&gt; said that Sanders’ plans would raise growth to 5.3%, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ineteconomics.org/uploads/general/romer-and-romer-evaluation-of-friedman1.pdf&quot;&gt;Romer’s&lt;/a&gt; have published a rebuttal saying that is almost impossible to achieve. &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/kocherlakota009/home/policy/thoughts-on-policy/2-23-16&quot;&gt;Narayana Kocherlakota&lt;/a&gt;, on the other hand, says that we can adopt policies that can achieve 5-6% growth over the next four years. I know I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/insert-policy-here-wont-boost-growth-rates/&quot;&gt;said before&lt;/a&gt; that whatever your favorite policy is, it won’t boost growth rates by maybe more than 1 percentage point, so maybe you could hit 3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what gives? Is it possible, or not, to materially boost growth rates through policy? The answer, which lets you distinguish between the links given above, is that it depends on the kind of policy. To be crude, divide policies into either aggregate supply (AS) policies or aggregate demand (AD) policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big difference between them, at least for understanding their impact on growth rates in the short run, is in whether they involve spending money &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. AS policies - reform the tax code, reduce occupational licensing, cut back regulation, etc. - are about changing incentives for people to invest in new capital (human or physical) or to reallocate that capital to higher productivity uses. AD policies - monetary policy, direct transfers - differ in that they directly involve moving money from one person or institution to another. Some policies, infrastructure spending, for example, have elements of both. The infrastructure changes incentives for investments by private business (AS), but also involves a direct transfer of money to pay for it (AD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be a little more concrete about my distinction of AD and AS policies, think of the difference between a change to tax law that lowers the tax rate on small businesses (an AS policy) and a $500 tax refund sent to every person in the US (an AD policy). The change in tax rates will presumably induce more small businesses to start or expand (arguing about the size of this effect is something for a different post, roll with it) over time, but this will take time. Nothing material is going to happen to GDP growth this quarter because of that policy change, even though over time it might result in significantly more GDP. In constrast, the tax refund is going to put money in people’s pockets &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, and so there will be a more immediate effect on GDP, although it will fade away relatively quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try and illustrate the difference, let me try some diagrams that should be familiar to anyone who has taken intermediate macro. These are basic AS/AD diagrams, but with an additional feature that comes from growth economics. Rather than one long-run AS curve (LRAS), we have two. The first is the current LRAS, and the second is the potential LRAS curve. In terms of the Solow model, the current LRAS is based on our current capital stock and productivity, while the potential LRAS is the steady state LRAS (To be really true to growth models, we’d say that the potential LRAS curve is slowly moving to the right due to trend growth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Basic AS/AD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y is the current level of GDP, determined by the intersection of the AD curve with the &lt;em&gt;short-run&lt;/em&gt; AS curve, SRAS. I’ve drawn the diagram such that we are in a situation where GDP is below current potential. I did this to be clear. Being below steady state in a growth model (Current LRAS &amp;lt; Potential LRAS) is a different thing than having “slack” in the economy (Y &amp;lt; Current LRAS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this I can think through the differences in policies that attempt to accelerate growth, meaning that Y starts to “move to the right” quickly in my diagram. Start with AS policies. These push the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; LRAS curve to the right, but have little immediate effect on the current LRAS or the current SRAS. Over time, the current LRAS will converge to the potential LRAS, but as I’ve talked about before that takes a long time to occur. Note that the fact that the current and potential LRAS are far apart in my diagram to start with is irrelevant. The policies will shift the potential LRAS curve, and we’ll still have to wait for the current LRAS curve to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas2.png&quot; alt=&quot;LRAS Shift&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because AS policies don’t shift the current LRAS and SRAS curves by much, the increase in Y is small, and hence there is only a small effect on the growth rate. In the long run, these policies can have a massive effect on living standards, but it can take decades for that to manifest itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constrast that with AD policies. These shift the AD curve directly, and close to immediately. I’m perfectly willing to concede that there is some kind of lag in when the AD curve shifts out, but that’s measured in quarters, not decades. Because this AD shift happens immediately, and because the SRAS curve slopes upwards, there is a big effect on GDP from Y to Y’. Note that this depends crucially on the assumption that the SRAS curve is upward sloping. Without that, the AD shift would have no effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas1.png&quot; alt=&quot;AD Shift&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the AD policy has no effect on either potential or current LRAS. And while I’ve drawn the SRAS curve as a line, it probably becomes vertical at some point when GDP is high enough, so you cannot just use AD policies to push up GDP arbitrarily. But if you want to boost growth &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, then the AD policies are more effective. A last point is that the size of the effect depends on how far away Y is from the current LRAS curve. Part of the Romer’s critique of Friedman is that he overstates that gap, which thus overstats the power of AD policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large part of the argument about whether you can influence growth in the short run depends on whether we are talking about AD or AS policies. Kocherlakota, for example, explicitly talks about AD policies - monetary policy - as part of his argument for being able to boost growth to 5%. Sanders’ plan is a mix of AS and AD, but I think Friedman got caught up treating all of them as AD plans, which overstated their possible effects in the short run. When I dismissed the ability of various reform plans to boost growth in the short run, it was because they are AS reforms. They will have effects over the long-run, but not in the short run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are probably few policies that are purely AS or AD policies. Monetary policy is probably - unless you don’t buy the classical dichotomy - a purely AD policy. Fiscal policy, on the other hand, seems muddier. It depends on the nature of it. Direct transfers are AD policies (although they might have incentive effects that affect the AS side). Policies that change regulations or the tax code, though, are not really fiscal policy, so much as they are AS policies. Another example might help. Changing education policy to allow teachers to be hired/fired more easily - AS policy. Hiring 1,000 teachers to start teaching this fall - AD policy. A major education reform bill, then, might be both AS and AD at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the attractions of infrastructure spending, by the way. It provides both AS and AD effects. Spend money now to repair bridges, ports, and roads, and immediately boost GDP growth. But at the same time, you are investing in public capital that can incent private business to invest as well, and you are pushing out the potential LRAS curve, which ultimately is the only one that matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What all this means is that you cannot just look at the projected growth rate of a plan to assess it. Friedman isn’t wrong because he projects 5% growth, but he’s probably wrong because he is assuming AS policies are going to have big current effects. Kocherlakota isn’t wrong because he projects 5% growth either, but his plan is more plausible because it is based in large part on AD policies. Jeb! wasn’t wrong because he proposed 4% growth, he was wrong because of how he proposed to get there. You can accelerate growth in the short run, but you have to use AD policies to do that. AS policies deliver higher living standards in the long run, but it takes them a long time to ramp up to that higher level.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Absolute Changes in Living Standards</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Absolute-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Absolute-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This may or may not be interesting, I’m not entirely sure myself. But I got a question from an undergrad in my economic growth course, and it was one of those questions that kind of catches you off guard because you hadn’t really thought about it. The question was - paraphrasing - “Why do we look at growth rates rather than how much GDP per capita actually changed?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Duh, it’s a course on growth” is what I did &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; say. But it did take me a moment to shake that feeling. In his defense, the answer isn’t obvious. Why do we focus on growth rates - percentage changes - as opposed to absolute changes in GDP per capita? Growth rates maks major differences in the absolute change in GDP per capita. For example, a growth rate of 2% implies an absolute change of 1000 in an economy with a GDP per capita of 50,000, and only a change of 200 in an economy with GDP per capita of 10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what does the distribution of aboslute changes in GDP per capita even look like? I had no idea. So I calculated the absolute growth in real GDP per capita per year for each country in the PWT. Then I plotted the kernel densities of these absolute changes for several countries. You can see the results below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_abs_growth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Densities for Absolute Growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kernel densities are basically smoothed histograms, so the height of the density curve indicates how often absolute growth in GDP per capita of a given amount occurred. As you can see, for India (the black dashed line) absolute growth tended to be very small. On average, from 1950 to 2011, GDP per capita rose by 51 dollars per year in India. The median was 42 dollars. Despite these small absolute changes, the percentage growth rate in could actually be quite high because GDP per capita is very low to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare that to the United States, where the density is much flatter and covers much larger values (both positive and negative). For the US, average absolute growth in GDP per capita was 482 dollars, with a median of 617 dollars. Of course, those large changes in GDP per capita reflect very small percentage growth rates in the US, because GDP per capita is already so large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of growth rates, the US isn’t growing very quickly compared to India, at least over the last 25 years. But in absolute terms, the increase in living standards in the US is about 10 times higher than in India in a given year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we care about these absolute changes? The answer hinges on your view on how GDP per capita translates to welfare, the utility function. It is really common to assume “log utility”, or welfare is the log of GDP per capita (or consumption per capita, or something else proportional to GDP per capita). Log utility has the very particular property that the same &lt;em&gt;growth rate&lt;/em&gt; of GDP per capita yields the same &lt;em&gt;absolute&lt;/em&gt; change in welfare. If India and the US both have growth rates of 3%, then welfare in both countries rises by 3%, even though the absolute change in GDP per capita in the US is much larger. The figure above doesn’t have any information about welfare gains, in other words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is simply diminishing marginal utility. But log utility specifies that the diminishing happens in such a way that growth rates translate directly to absolute changes in welfare. Now what if utility is “more curved” than log? That is, what if marginal utility falls very quickly as GDP per capita goes up? Then even if two countries have the same growth rate, they do not have the same absolute change in welfare. In fact, the richer country would have a &lt;em&gt;smaller&lt;/em&gt; change in welfare than the poorer country. So 3% growth in India generates &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; welfare than 3% growth in the US, even though the absolute change in GDP per capita is much smaller in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we could go the other direction, and look at utility that is “less curved” than log, or where marginal utility diminishes very slowly. Now, if there are two countries with identical growth rates, the richer country has a higher gain in welfare. The limit case here is linear utility, where marginal utility doesn’t decline at all as you get richer. Then the absolute change in GDP per capita is all that matters, and the US has (on average) much larger gains in welfare every year than India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An argument for thinking of utility as “more curved” than log is subsistence constraints. That is, let’s say that you only get utility from GDP per capita over and above a minimum level; GDP per capita at that minimum level is what we call subsistence, and it doesn’t provide any welfare, it just keeps you alive. If you have subsistence constraints, then marginal utility is incredibly high close to this constraint, and marginal utility falls very quickly as you move away from it. So India experiences much bigger gains in welfare - despite their small absolute gains in GDP per capita - because those extra 51 dollars get you farther away from that subsistence constraint. The US gets relatively little utility from its 482 dollar change, because we’re already so far above that subsistence constraint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, habit formation would be a force pushing towards “less curved” utility. In short, imagine that the subsistence constraint itself is rising as we get richer. The “minimum level” of GDP per capita that people need to meet is higher in the US than in India. If you believe that, then it is quite possible that the higher absolute growth of GDP per capita in the US is delivering bigger gains in absolute welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, then, I think the answer to the students question is that we think there is diminishing marginal utility, and so growth rate rates make sense because they tell us something about absolute changes in welfare. But…who said utility of GDP per capita has to be as curved as log? What if there are significant habit effects? Maybe the gap in welfare between places like the US and India is actually &lt;em&gt;growing&lt;/em&gt; over time, even though India’s GDP per capita is catching up slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not a “Duh” question after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
