<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 13:10:32 -0500</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>What determines value?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Value-Everything/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Value-Everything/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2z9NWXJ&quot;&gt;The Value of Everything&lt;/a&gt;, by Mariana Mazzucato, a few weeks ago, and have finally gotten around to writing up something of a review. This book made me think, so I count that as a positive recommendation. Sometimes I was thinking things like, “This is ridiculous, you cannot refuse to acknowledge the difference in stocks and flows!”, but in between those there were some genuine moments where Mazzucato got me to see things from a different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mazzucato makes the point - obvious in retrospect but easy to forget - that the value of economic activity involves a choice. A choice of what “counts” as having value, and what does not. In exploring this, she works through the systems that past writers have used, and compares that to ideas that underlay our current thinking. This is not just a question of “what gets counted in GDP?”, but intended to be broader. Her question is something like, “by using GDP what implicit decisions have we made about what has economic value?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The threads of her answer come a little undone by later in the book. After setting up the contingent nature of measuring economic value, she moves into questioning why finance is assigned too much value, while government is assigned too little. I think she intends all this to be radical, but I think the book fails to provide the real kill shot on this. A radical book would outline a new means of assigning value, even in vague terms, but I didn’t get that here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, as I said the book did get me thinking on several points. What follows then is far less in the way of review, and more speculative response. Caveat emptor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-counts-as-valuable&quot;&gt;What counts as valuable?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What became apparent to me in reading Mazzucato’s history was that in most cases, the notion of what counted as valuable in the economy had less to do with &lt;em&gt;output&lt;/em&gt;, and more to do with the &lt;em&gt;inputs&lt;/em&gt;. The Physiocrats, for example, explained that economic value came from agriculture alone. If something was produced using the land, and some sturdy peasants and perhaps some draft animals, then that something had economic value. Any other transactions that took place, like people moving or trading grain, didn’t add value. They shuffled value around between the movers or traders, but didn’t create value. You could increase value only by adding land, peasants, or animals. I’d guess that if you pressed the Physiocrat line, you could allow for technological change in agriculture to raise value, but regardless, value was assigned only to output coming from a specific set of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not a big leap from here to Marx, where value was located in the labor effort that went into a product. Marx dropped the focus on land or agriculture, per se, but retained the concept that what determined whether output had value was whether it used labor. You could have a hypothetical factory that ran on complete automation, and used no labor. That output could only have value from digging back into the labor used in producing the factory, etc.., but the point is similar to the Physiocrats. It took the “right” inputs to create value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to snort at the ideas of the Physiocrats and Marx regarding this kind of thinking. But I’d argue that the most peoples intuitive sense of “economic value” still comes back to their sense of which inputs were used. Much like Marx, most people will attribute value to output based on the perceived labor effort that went into producing it. Like the Physiocrats, production that involves extracting or processing raw materials is considered to have value. Again, it takes the “right” inputs to create value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see examples of this all over the place. To demonstrate the Physiocrat/Marxist attitude, I give you Commerce Secretary Wilbur Ross, whose Senate testimony on Trump’s tariffs is quated in this article from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/2018/06/20/wilbur-ross-canada-steel_a_23463975/&quot;&gt;Huffington Post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We don’t have a trade deficit of note (on steel),” Ross replied. “We have a surplus in dollars; we do not have a surplus in physical value.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could do a whole class unpacking the incoherence of that statement. But let’s focus on the fact that what ultimately matters to Ross is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the notion of dollars, but rather the “physical value”. Steel is built from “real” inputs, so it has a real value beyond anything that we can measure with dollars. I think you can get some traction in thinking about the motives behind tariffs (and support for them) if you consider this notion of value. We can be “losing” at trade because we import things of value (based on their input content) from abroad, even if the associated money flows don’t look so bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a different context, when people argue for a minimum wage, or a “living wage”, they often appeal to the idea that a hard days work (e.g. the input) grants the work value different from and beyond the dollar value that work earns on the open market. Support for family farms has a similar language of value based on fact that it employs physical labor and - Physiocratic-style - land. It is seen as unfair if this labor and land does not generate a large monetary value, because we assign inherent value to those inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see something of this in the original sets of national accounts, where far more attention was paid to counting up manufacturing output (based on real inputs like labor and coal and iron) that to service output (which presumably used less inherently valuable labor, and, &lt;em&gt;gasp&lt;/em&gt;, no iron ore at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sense that finance doesn’t “count” works in a similar way. The inputs that go into finance work - people sitting at desks being clever - aren’t assigned value by themselves. The notion of “bullshit” jobs is another example of judging value based on the nature of the input - presumably sitting at a desk and stapling. No one considers farming or mining or manufacturing a “bullshit” job, why? Because they involve “real” labor input, physical work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mazzucato engages in this type of argument, although she doesn’t phrase it this way. Her argument that a number of financial activities do not have value is because they involves &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; inputs. Well, a little bit of clever accounting, perhaps, but for all intents and purposes the only “input” they are using is market power. Because the output produced by finance doesn’t rely on real inputs, it cannot have real value. The opposite holds for government and public sector work. This involves real labor (e.g. police officers) and other real inputs (e.g. highways) so it has real value, even if we have trouble putting a clear number on it because of a lack of a profit and loss statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me say that there is nothing inherently wrong with Mazzucatos position, as in there being some kind of logical inconsistency. She, and everyone, is welcome to value inputs and hence the output of different sectors in any way they want. The question becomes why standard measures of economic activity, like GDP, have diverged so much from Mazzucatos notion of value, and whether there is some way to bring them back together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gdp-and-the-value-of-output&quot;&gt;GDP and the value of output&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did we get to the point where finance is valued “too much”, while government is valued “too little”? Let’s go back and think about how we would add up the value of economic activity if we did appeal to our notions of which inputs matter, or are “real” enough to count. How do you compare the value of one product to another? How do you compare the labor used in one product to another? Just time? Or does skill matter? How do you add up the value of a bushel of corn with a ton of steel? Do those values change over time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may want to value economic output based on your opinion of the inputs involved, and that’s fine. But I’m not sure you can do that, for all the reasons that Hayek laid out long ago. It’s an information problem. There are too many products, with too much heterogeneity, and too many inputs, for you to come up with a &lt;em&gt;complete&lt;/em&gt; set of rules to value output. And no, general principles don’t solve this, because you need to make particular decisions. The general principles of national income accounting are simple, but the details of how and what we count run to hundreds of pages. And what if I disagree with your opinion, how do we reconcile this? I guess we could each have our own individual measure of economic activity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you want a single measure then you need a consistent way of measuring the value of output from different activities relative to one another, so that you can add them up. The only practical way to do this we’ve come up with so far is to use relative prices. This is how GDP is calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue for Mazzucato is that by using relative prices, it breaks the link to the inherent value of inputs. Products that have high prices count for a lot, even if those high prices are due to markups from market power, rather than some “true” value of the inputs used. Hence finance, where the markups seem to represent market power to Mazzucato (e.g. net interest margin) gets a heavy weight. Government, where we don’t even have a clear measure of the true price of the output because it isn’t bought and sold like a normal good, ends up downweighted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that Mazzucatos argument about the problems with using relative prices is very compelling, for the reasons I laid out above about information. There does not seem to be a plausible way to add up economic activity without using prices. I guess to my point much earlier, if this was a radical book it would have proposed some kind of structure to add up activity that does not involve these prices. But I didn’t see that radical idea. In a lot of ways, Mazzucato’s point is just that relative prices are a poor approximation of &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; utilities, even if they are good approximations of &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt; utilities. Note, by the way, that even if there is market power and markups that relative prices are still a good indicator of marginal utilities. See my post on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox-2/&quot;&gt;paradox of markups&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, while I’d leave aside this particular criticism of using relative prices, I still think there was a lot of value (yes, that was deliberate) in the book for thinking about how inputs inform our opinions on inherent value. There is a coherent argument to make about how we could or should value certain economic activities more, in the sense of supporting or encouraging them, even if they do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; lead to higher measured GDP, but because they involve the use of some inherently valuable inputs. For example, you could argue that a jobs guarantee is valuable even if it led to GDP being lower than it would otherwise (of course, it might be higher, but that’s a different argument). That would be the case of valuing things based on the nature of the input (e.g. full time work for adults) rather than on the value of output. But using relative prices to value GDP is neither an argument for, nor against, your position.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sustained growth and the increase in work hours</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Leisure/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Leisure/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in March, I &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/When-Growth/&quot;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; a summary of some &lt;a href=&quot;https://jacobweisdorf.files.wordpress.com/2017/12/unreal-wages_humphries-and-weisdorf_dec-2017_wp1.pdf&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; by Jane Humphries and Jacob Weisdorf on the onset of economic growth. Their paper documented &lt;em&gt;annual&lt;/em&gt; labor contract terms in England over several centuries, and compared those to the typical &lt;em&gt;day&lt;/em&gt; labor rates that have been used in economic history to study the onset of growth and the effects of the Industrial Revolution. The short version of that paper is that the annual labor contracts starting seeing sustained growth in their value around 1650 or so, far sooner than the day wages indicated. This pushes back the origin of economic growth to well before the actual technological IR, and this also matches the data on GDP per capita developed by Broadberry, Campbell, Klein, Overton, and van Leeuwen in &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2GnD1Nm&quot;&gt;British Economic Growth, 1270-1870&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that I didn’t address in my post, but which came up in a few replies I saw, was whether the data on annual contracts (and on GDP per capita) indicate a rise in &lt;em&gt;living standards&lt;/em&gt;. Let’s take the day wage data as factually correct, and those day wages remained roughly constant from 1650-ish to 1850-ish. This has several implications. First, people that did work for day wages in this period would only see their annual income rise by working more days or hours per day. Second, if the value of annual contracts were tied in some way to the day wage, then annual contracts rose in value also due to rising work effort in days/hours. For both types of workers this doesn’t seem to indicate that they are better off, just working more hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what little evidence we do have on actual hours worked does seem to indicate that they increased a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; in the period around the actual Industrial Revolution. Hans-Joachim Voth, in two papers from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/cup/jechis/v58y1998i01p29-58_01.html&quot;&gt;1998&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/cup/jechis/v61y2001i04p1065-1082_04.html&quot;&gt;2001&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a book &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2JxpQLl&quot;&gt;Time and Work During the Industrial Revolution&lt;/a&gt;, provided estimates of work hours based on court records. Around 1760, annual hours were about 2500, while in 1800 and 1830 annual hours were about 3300, before dropping back to about 2700 in 1870. In the period of the actual (technological) Industrial Revolution, it would appear that work hours did rise substantially. We know the day wages did not rise until around 1850-ish. But with the rise in hours worked, the annual income of a worker would have risen during the early 1800’s. We might assume that those workers on annual contracts, if they were part of the same labor market, would also have seen their hours rise, and hence their annual income growth was due to more work time as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t settle anything, however. The HW data indicate that the value of annual contracts began to grow in the middle of the 1600’s, well before the rise in hours documented by Voth. If annual hours were consistent at 2500 from 1650 to 1750, then that means the rise in annual contracts represented growth in the implicit income per hour for those workers as well. On the other hand, you could argue that even the growth that HW document was driven by hours. In the 100 years from 1650 to 1750, HW estimate annual contracts grew in value by 67%-ish. If that was driven entirely by an increase in hours worked, then hours worked had to grow by about 67% as well. That would mean that in 1650 annual hours worked on these contracts were around 1,500. Is that reasonable? I don’t know that there is an obvious answer to that question. There is plenty of evidence for long idle periods in agricultural work, and so 1,500 hours in a year might have been the normal amount expected in 1650. On the other hand, that seems like a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; increase in hours worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s assume that even the rise in annual contract value was driven entirely by an increase in hours worked. And let’s stretch this argument out so that while annual contracts (as well as GDP per capita) started growing in 1650, it wasn’t until 1850 that this was because day/hour rates rose. Does this mean that the growth in annual contracts and GDP per capita did not represent a rise in &lt;em&gt;living standards&lt;/em&gt; until 1850?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to that depends on the reason for the rise in work hours. If they were physically coerced, then for sure you’d say that the growth in per worker annual contracts or GDP didn’t represent a rise in living standards. But on the assumption that the extra hours were not coerced, then we need to think hard about the labor supply decision of workers. Mark Koyama has a nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://mason.gmu.edu/~mkoyama2/About_files/Koyama12a.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that lays out a simple theoretical model for thinking about this, and the particular feature of this model that matters is the possibility of a backward-bending labor supply curve. When wages are very low, people provide very little labor to the market. Why bother? But as wages rise, people provide more labor to the market, because it is worth their time to work, as the wage they earn allows them to consume more goods. But on the assumption that people do enjoy non-work time, at some point the wage gets high enough that people start providing &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; labor. If you can earn enough to buy everything you want in 30 hours a week, why work 40 hours? This is the backward bending part of the labor supply curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Mark does is then work through various ways in which work hours might rise, the implication for living standards, and how these relate to different stories about economic growth. We can see which might make sense in the English case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;immiserating-growth-or-involution&quot;&gt;Immiserating growth or involution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first case is one where the wage starts (say in 1650) high enough that we are “on” the backward bending part of the labor supply curve. At this point, a negative productivity shock (e.g. a bad harvest) pushes down the wage, and because we are on the backward bending part of the supply curve, this &lt;em&gt;raises&lt;/em&gt; the amount of labor done. More hours at a lower wage would imply workers are worse off. Yet, if the elasticity of labor supply with respect to wage is &lt;em&gt;large&lt;/em&gt; enough, then the overall effect on earnings is &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt;. A large shift in L, even with a decline in w, can mean that wL (total earnings) increase. We could thus interpret the onset of annual contract growth in the HW data as an example of immiserating growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One issue with this story is that while we do not see growth in daily wages in the data, we also do not see a substantial &lt;em&gt;decline&lt;/em&gt; in wages. Yes, wages appear to decline from about 1450 to 1650, after the Black Death when population is rising, but after 1650 the wage data shows, if anything, a very small positive trend. Without clear evidence of a drop in the wage, and with the need for what seems like an unreasonably large labor supply elasticity, this story doesn’t seem to fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;involution&quot;&gt;Involution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a second theoretical case that can be used to generate more hours without rising living standards. This could occur because of an increase in the price of a necessity or subsistence good, like food. Because people have to consume a certain amount of this necessity, if it gets more expensive, they have to either work more hours, or decrease their consumption of all other goods. Under the assumption that people enjoy both leisure and consuming other things, they’ll decrease both by a little. The drop in leisure means an increase in work time, and hence we’ve got a rise in hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t require us to assume that workers are already on backward-bending part of the labor supply curve. The rise of the price of the necessity shifts down the whole labor supply curve down, and so people work more hours regardless of where they were to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether this results in an increase in measured earnings (wL) depends on the effect of the rise in the price of the necessity on the equilibrium wage, and how much the labor supply curve shifts. You can wrestle the model into giving you an increase in wL, while people are still worse off. This kind of effect has been called “involution” before, a concept that at some point in my life I’ll write a much longer post about. But for the present post, the problem is that there is no obvious rise in food prices in England starting in 1650.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;industrious-revolution&quot;&gt;Industrious revolution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leaves us with the last case that delivers an increase in work hours and living standards, which captures the intuition of Jan de Vries “Industrious Revolution”, which you can read about &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2l1dSuL&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, in one of the more enjoyable books on economic history you’ll come across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story here is that there are different kinds of consumption. Some consumption is time-intense (e.g. Netflix) in that it requires a little of your money, but a lot of your time to consume it. Some consumption is good-intense (e.g. clothes) which requires a lot of your money, but very little of your time. And no, don’t get too picky on that distinction. Yes, you might wear a shirt for 12 hours, but once it is on you don’t have to spend any time or attention to keep wearing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If time-intense consumption is cheap, then you’ll tend to buy lots of it, and that means you’ll work very little. You don’t need much money to buy these consumption items (so you don’t need to work much), and you do need time to enjoy them. The argument here would be that England prior to 1650 was a world in which time-intense consumption was cheap. Workers had little need to work more hours, because why bother? What were you going to purchase with that extra income? It made sense to buy the time-intense consumption good, leisure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But around the middle of the 17th century, in line with de Vries’ argument, new good-intense consumption goods became available, like sugar and tea. So people shifted their consumption towards these things, which did not require much time to enjoy, but did require you to purchase something. So putting more labor into the market made sense. Similarly, the price of textiles was falling at this time (yes, prior to the IR). People shifted from the time-intense activity  of making ones own clothes, towards the good-intense purchase of ready-made clothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decline in the price of these good-intense consumption items “straightens out” the labor supply curve, making the transition to backward-bending occur at a higher level. And hence for any given wage, the labor supplied is higher. In this setting, living standards are &lt;em&gt;rising&lt;/em&gt; with the increase in work time, as this is an optimal response to a drop in the price of one of the available consumption items. The drop in the price of good-intense items shifted time spent at home (and out of the labor market) into time spent in the labor market. Unlike the prior two explanations, the data work here. The prices of things like tea and sugar and clothing did fall in the period starting from the mid-1600’s, at the same time hours were rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-is-it-all-about-trade&quot;&gt;So is it all about trade?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, let’s say that we buy the story of the industrious revolution, and buy that the onset of growth in annual labor contracts and GDP per capita starting in 1650 represented a real gain in living standards. One interesting implication of this is that the origin of sustained growth was associated, in large part, with the expansion of trade in England. Rather than a series of clear technological breakthroughs (e.g. the spinning jenny, etc.) it was the “technology” of trade, by inducing a change in the available basket of consumption goods, that kick-started sustained growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a fascinating question is how important trade was in &lt;em&gt;sustaining&lt;/em&gt; sustained growth. That is, the availability of cheap trade goods could have created a period of rapid growth in the late 17th century, perhaps running through the late 18th century. But without the continued expansion of trade to bring in new goods, or finding cheaper sources of those goods, could growth have continued? Even if you could find new and cheaper imports, at some point wouldn’t people reach a limit on how much additional time they wanted to work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence you could argue that the technological Industrial Revolution of the late 1700’s and early 1800’s was necessary to keep sustained growth going after trade got things started, and that technological innovation is still necessary for growth to continue indefinitely. But you could also argue that without trade creating growth to begin with, there never would have been an incentive to make those technological changes in the first place. I’m well beyond my brainpower capacity to answer this. But the HW data, along with the Broadberry et al data on GDP per capita, by pushing back the date of sustained growth to 1650, makes the link between trade and the Industrial Revolution more salient. Did the Industrious Revolution trigger the Industrial Revolution?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the answer to that, I think it is a good working hypothesis that the growth documented by HW and Broadberry et al starting in the 1650’s was associated with real gains in living standards, as the increase in hours worked is consistent with a switch to goods-intense consumption items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-complete-aside&quot;&gt;A complete aside&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has absolutely nothing to do with the onset of sustained growth. But the logic of the industrious revolution I presented above can be used in reverse to think about changes in economic growth in the recent past. You could argue that recent innovations have made time-intense consumption items (e.g. Netflix or video games) cheaper. And in a mirror image response to the 1600’s, people are substituting more time-intense consumption for goods-intense consumption. This means that they willingly withdraw labor from the market in order to enjoy those time-intense activities, as in the proverbial 20-something male living in his parents basement playing Halo all day. Nothing terribly insightful here, I just thought I was interesting to think about this as the flip of the industrious revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The paradox of markups, part 2</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I told you I wouldn’t leave you waiting on the next post concerning markups and the paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/content_link/JCsTqiauR0JBboj3vsNFRhyw9MrxV3B0j7L3f4fURJnfAUAxSXJXASiRl8OFiU2F/file&quot;&gt;David Baqaee and Emmanuel Fahri&lt;/a&gt;, so here you go. In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I described the (at times) paradoxical nature of markups. When there is &lt;em&gt;dispersion&lt;/em&gt; in markups, output is lower than it could otherwise be, given technology. But when there is dispersion in markups, there are circumstances - like increasing markups in low-markup producers or shifting resources towards high-markup producers - where raising the average markup in the economy will be associated with higher output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that is in the BF paper, but it is not the main purpose of it. One of the main contributions of the paper is to show that you can generalize these effects of markups to almost any arbitrary model of the economy. The paradox is not just the result of making some particular assumptions about production functions or preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One application they pursue (among many) is decomposing productivity growth into terms involving technology and terms involving allocative efficiency. If you read this blog at all, you know that productivity is a big bucket of different things going on in the economy. In that bucket are true technology effects, the ability to physically produce more widgets given some set of physical inputs. But also in that bucket are things like the allocation of those inputs across firms that produce different kinds of widgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decomposing-productivity-growth&quot;&gt;Decomposing productivity growth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the economy were perfectly efficient, meaning that the inputs we use were allocated across different firms such that we were at the maximum possible output level, then productivity would measure &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; true technological improvements. Yes, inputs might move between different firms in response to technological changes, but the &lt;em&gt;efficiency&lt;/em&gt; of the economy is being held constant, and so those changes in input use have zero effect on productivity to a first approximation. The problem with using productivity to measure technology is not that inputs move around, per se, it is that the movement of inputs may not represent a move from one efficient equilibrium to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give you an example to illustrate what I mean. Let’s say that in 2004, all the inputs (e.g. labor) in the economy were allocated in an efficient manner, and output was as high as it could possibly be given the specific physical technologies available in that year. We look at this allocation and say, clearly this is the best way to allocate inputs, so let’s pass a law to freeze the allocations at the 2004 shares. If 4% of all people worked at the Gap in 2004, then 4% of all people would always be required to work at the Gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005, though, there are changes in the specific physical technologies used by different firms. Some may have better technology, some worse. Perhaps the Gap discovers a better way to fold shirts. Who knows. Because the technologies changed, there &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be changes in the allocation of inputs. In an efficient economy, there &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; be changes in the allocations. But we have this dumb law that says the allocations cannot be changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a productivity perspective, the growth in productivity - which remember is the output we can produce given a set of inputs - is affected by two things. First, there are the specific technological changes that occurred. By themselves, those should &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; productivity (remember the cool new folding technique at the Gap). Second, there are now all the distortions introduced by the law. More than 4% of the labor force should work at the Gap now, but it is confined to only employing 4%. Thus we are getting less output than we could, and hence productivity is &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Productivity growth is thus a combination of the positive technological effect, and a negative effect of the allocation law. What we’d like to do is separate out those two effects. And that is what BF propose to do, in a setting that allows for any kind of arbitrary structure in terms of production functions, links between firms acting as suppliers to one another, and preferences. The contribution of their work is not to identify this issue in measuring productivity - we’ve known about that for a while - but to develop a way to manage that issue in almost any conceivable setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do they do? Intuitively, they say you have to calculate the &lt;em&gt;efficient&lt;/em&gt; outcome in 2005 given the changes in technology. Then you compare the productivity of this hypothetical efficient 2005 economy with the efficient 2004 economy, and in that case the productivity you measure is getting the “pure” effect of technology, &lt;em&gt;holding constant the efficiency of the economy&lt;/em&gt;. In theory that is possible to do, but in practice it is hard (impossible) because you don’t know how much the true physical productivity of each firm improved over time. Hold on to that problem for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve calculated this pure technological effect, you are left with changes in productivity that are due to changes in allocative efficiency. Here, the idea is that you are comparing the &lt;em&gt;efficiency&lt;/em&gt; of the economy in 2004 to the &lt;em&gt;efficiency&lt;/em&gt; of the economy in 2005, without asking about the technological changes. What BF show is that given some readily available data on markups and factor income shares (e.g. wages as a fraction of output) you can calculate this allocative efficiency effect without too much trouble, and this is true no matter how complex the underlying economy may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall productivity growth is thus a combination of the pure technology effect and the allocative efficiency effect. The simple math is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta Prod = \% \Delta Tech + \% \Delta AE.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BF have data on productivity growth (this is just the normal thing we calculate from data on output and inputs), and they show how to calculate &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\% \Delta AE\inline&quot;/&gt;. So in the end they don’t need to measure the precise technological changes of each firm, they can just back out the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\% \Delta Tech\inline&quot;/&gt; term from the above equation. You can infer the pure technological change in the economy once you measure the allocative efficiency change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To implement this, BF need some way of measuring allocative efficiency, and they use the data on markups charged by firms. They draw this data from a paper from Gutierrez and Philippon that I talked about &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Investment/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you recall from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, markups push the economy away from the efficient allocation, and so BF can use changes in markups to measure the change in how far away from that efficient allocation the economy moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_BF_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sources of productivity growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of all this are in the figure. The blue line, labelled the Solow residual, shows how productivity itself grows over time. This is what they are trying to decompose. The allocative efficiency line (orange dashes) is the contribution to productivity from changes in how close to the efficient allocation the economy got. Notice that this term is &lt;em&gt;rising&lt;/em&gt; over time, meaning that according to their calculations the economy was more efficient in 2015 than in 1996. We’ll get back to that in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By definition, the difference between the blue line (productivity) and the orange dashed line (allocative efficiency) has to be the effect of pure technology. The purple line captures this, and you can see that this is also growing over time. But note that overall productivity grew faster than technology because of the allocative efficiency improvement. BF suggest that the each account for about 50% of the growth in productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You can also see one last source of growth in productivity, factor undercounting. I ignored this in my little analysis up above. This is capturing the fact that in the presence of markups the measure of inputs that we can calculate is not quite equal to the true level of input use. This effect can get very large - BF find it matters more using other data on markups that are larger than the Gutierrez and Philippon markups - but for the time being, lets set that effect aside.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wait-efficiency-was-going-up&quot;&gt;Wait, efficiency was going up?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that BF find allocative efficiency was &lt;em&gt;improving&lt;/em&gt; over time is perhaps surprising. To see why this was occurring, we can turn to a further decomposition that BF provide. To understand this, it helps to think of the allocative efficiency term as being determined by something like a weighted average of the markups across firms. As a weighted average, it can change over time for two reasons. The markups themselves could change, or the weights could change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next figure, BF have separated out these two effects. The blue line is the same total allocative efficiency term from the first figure. The “markup effect” in orange dashes is measuring changes just the change in markups charged by firms, effectively holding the weights constant. The general increase in the “markup effect” comes from the fact that most markups were &lt;em&gt;falling&lt;/em&gt; according to the Gutierrez and Philippon data. If you want to refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, this is telling us that all the markups in the economy were collapsing towards one (meaning no markup), and that the economy was getting closer to the point where the ratio of marginal utilites was equal to the ratio of marginal costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_BF_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sources of allocative efficiency&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we have what BF call the “cross-entropy” effect. That is not terribly informative. It refers to the fact that the &lt;em&gt;weights&lt;/em&gt; in the weighted average of markups change over time. Recall that holding markups constant, if you push more resources into high-markup firms, this &lt;em&gt;raises&lt;/em&gt; productivity because the output of those firms is very valuable. The yellow line shows that productivity was rising over time due to this effect, and that in turn implies that more and more resources were getting pushed into high markup firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shift towards higher markup firms is consistent with the rise in profit share at the aggregate level. But that shift didn’t mean that productivity was falling. There &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; situations in which the rising profit share would be associated with lower productivity; if firm-specific markups were rising this would detract from productivity while raising profits. But what appears to have happened here is that profits rose due to changes in the composition of spending towards high-markup firms, and that is associated with higher productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;revisiting-harbergers-triangle&quot;&gt;Revisiting Harberger’s triangle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The productivity accounting that BF do relates to changes in allocative efficiency, but only in a local sense. It tells us whether we are getting closer or farther from the efficient equilibrium, but it doesn’t tell us how far away the efficient equilibrium is to begin with. How much higher would output be if there were no markups?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BF use their setting to answer this question. The exact numbers depend on the precise set of markups they use, and some assumptions about the structure of the economy, but the answer is that output would be about 40% higher without markups. This is much, &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt;, higher than the traditional answer, usually attributed to Harberger, who said the losses from monopoly were around 0.1%. Harberger’s number was always a bad estimate, as it was based on looking across sectors (not firms) only within manufacturing. It was an other example of assuming that what occurs within manufacturing is the only thing that matters. But even so, the scale of the effect that BF find is significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question is whether this substantial departure from the efficient equilibrium is worth it. We believe that markups are &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to induce economic growth, as they provide the reward to those who innovate. Is operating 40% below the efficient outcome worth it, in the sense that the markups pushing us down there are in turn generating rapid growth? I have no idea what the answer to that question is. You’d need to build some more structure on top of the BF model to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another interesting thing about their calculations, and it is an aspect of the paradox of markups. The 40% number BF calculate is for 2014. For 1997, they find that the loss associated with markups is only 4.5%. The loss associated with markups rose from 1997 to 2014, and yet allocative efficiency improved from 1997 to 2014, which is what the productivity calculations showed. How can those two things both be true?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BF’s productivity calculations show that the economy was moving &lt;em&gt;towards&lt;/em&gt; the efficient equilibrium over time, and hence this contributed to productivity growth. But at the same time, the efficient equilibrium was moving farther and farther away. Think of me running a 100 meter race against Usain Bolt. He’s much faster, but I am running in the same direction, at least. My allocative efficiency improves, in the sense that I’m headed in the right direction. But my absolute efficiency declines, in the sense that Bolt gets farther and farther ahead of me every moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, without some more information, you can’t say whether falling further behind the efficient equilibrium is good or bad, but it is an interesting piece of information to throw into the mental wood chipper. It may be worth it to be further behind if that is associated with greater incentives to innovate. Or perhaps it is a correlate of the lack of dynamism in business formation and employment turnover that has been documented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not even begun to scratch the surface of the interesting applications of the BF paper. I focused on the productivity accounting just because it is something I find to be of particular interest. The power of the paper is, to repeat, that these findings hold without having to make any strong assumptions about what production functions look like or how firms fit together into an input/output matrix. The only annoying thing about the paper is that it is forcing me to see how limited my understanding of the role of markups was in the economy. But it is well worth the effort to read it (so much notation!) if you’re into this kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The paradox of markups</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten the lag time between posts down from 6 months to six weeks. Progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topic that comes up often here is the effect of markups on aggregate productivity. And there is a recent-ish paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/content_link/JCsTqiauR0JBboj3vsNFRhyw9MrxV3B0j7L3f4fURJnfAUAxSXJXASiRl8OFiU2F/file&quot;&gt;David Baqaee and Emmanuel Fahri&lt;/a&gt; that has approached the relationship of markups (and distortions in general) with aggregate productivity from a very general perspective. By that I mean they show how to assess the impact of markups in an economy that may have some arbitrarily complex input-output structure for production, and in which it may be impossible to write down a coherent aggregate production function. In other words, they can assess the effect of markups on something approaching an actual economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intention was to walk through some of their main theoretical results on how to track the effect of markups, and show you what they come up with when they use those results to quantify the effect of rising markups over time. And I’m going to get to that in a future post, which I promise will arrive in fewer than six weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in working on that post, I started to write up a short section to lay out how markups affect real GDP in the first place. This post is that section, and as you’ll see I failed completely on the “short” thing. It’s well over 2000 words and at some point involved a python program to draw the figure you’ll see below. So this review of the effect of markups is getting put up as its own post, and then I’ll use this to jump off into a more complete discussion of the BF results in the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key things that comes up in studying the role of markups is an apparent paradox. The presence of markups can mean the value of aggregate output is lower than it otherwise would be, as it leads to a misallocation of inputs. But at the same time, it is possible that raising the &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; markup in the economy will increase the value of aggregate output. It would appear as if markups can be both bad and good for output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice the hedges in those statements - “can mean” and “it is possible”. That is because these are not universal truths, but rather hold in specific circumstances. Once you understand how markups work in general, the circumstances under which this paradox arises will be more clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In explaining all this, I’m going to pursue exact opposite strategy of the BF paper, and show you how markups work in one very particular setup with only 2 goods and no interesting input-output structures between them. Keep in mind that BF establish how the intuition behind my simple example extends to more complex situations, and everything I’m doing here would still hold in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bad-effect-of-markups&quot;&gt;The bad effect of markups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we’ve got an economy where there are two goods, 1 and 2. People want to consume both goods, but have diminishing marginal utility in consuming more of either one. Producers can make either good by using some input, and call it labor to be concrete. The technology to produce either good is simple. There is a constant marginal cost in terms of labor for producing one additional unit of a good, but that marginal cost might be different for the two goods. For example, if &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC_1 = 3\inline&quot;/&gt;, then it takes 3 units of labor to produce one more unit of good 1. Note that if we flip this over, then &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/MC_1 = 1/3\inline&quot;/&gt; is additional output of good 1 we get from using 1 more unit of labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having now dealt with preliminaries, what is the efficient outcome for this economy? And by efficient, I mean the outcome where the economy achieves the highest level of utility possible given the technology available and the stock of labor available. That outcome will be the point - the amount consumed of goods 1 and 2 - where the trade-off in utility between the two goods (the ratio of their marginal utilities) is exactly equal to the technological trade-off between the two goods (the ratio of their marginal costs). If you took intermediate economics, you might be familiar with this as the condition where the marginal rate of substitution equals the marginal rate of transformation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{MU_1}{MU_2} = \frac{MC_1}{MC_2}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is helpful to rearrange this to see what is going on. So write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;MU_1 \left(1/MC_1\right) = MU_2 \left(1/MC_2\right).&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the left, this is the additional utility you would get if you put one more unit of labor to work producing good 1. You’d get, as mentioned, an additional &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/MC_1\inline&quot;/&gt; units of good 1 from that extra labor. Multiplying those units of good 1 by &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MU_1\inline&quot;/&gt; tells us how valuable they are in terms of utility. If you did use one more unit of labor on good 1, though, you’d have to take that labor away from producing good 2. How much would you lose? You’d lose &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/MC_2\inline&quot;/&gt; units of good 2, and multiplying that by &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MU_2\inline&quot;/&gt; would tell you how much utility you just sacrificed. When the utility gained from extra good 1 just equals the utility lost from less of good 2, then you haven’t improved your situation at all. And once we’re at the point where you can’t improve your situation at all, we’re at the efficient outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig-markup-A.png&quot; alt=&quot;Markup equilibrium&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a lot of words. It is so much easier to see in a figure. What you can see labeled as the point “Efficient” is just the point at which the slope of the indifference curve (which is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?-MU_1/MU_2\inline&quot;/&gt;) is equal to the slope of the production possibilities frontier (which is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?-MC_1/MC_2\inline&quot;/&gt;). There is no feasible point we can produce (which is what the PPF captures) that gives us a higher level of utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible for the economy to reach that efficient outcome if no one is forcing it to reach that point? Sure, under some very specific conditions that boil down to the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{MU_1}{MU_2} = \frac{P_1}{P_2} = \frac{MC_1}{MC_2}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have that consumers take the prices of the goods as given, then they will buy goods until the ratio of their marginal utilities are equal to the ratio of prices. This is the point where their trade-off in utility is equal to the &lt;em&gt;market&lt;/em&gt; trade-off between the two goods. On the other side, we need that for producers, the prices they charge are equal to the ratio of their marginal costs, or the technological trade-off is also equal to the &lt;em&gt;market&lt;/em&gt; trade-off. In my figure, you can think of these conditions as saying that the budget constraint facing consumers (which tells consumers the ratio of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_1\inline&quot;/&gt; to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_2\inline&quot;/&gt;) has the same slope as the PPF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what happens when firms are charging markups? By definition, a markup of price over marginal cost, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt;, means that the price charged is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_1 = \mu_1 MC_1\inline&quot;/&gt; for good 1, with a similar expression for good 2. If there are markups, then we’ve got&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{MU_1}{MU_2} = \frac{P_1}{P_2} = \frac{\mu_1 MC_1}{\mu_2 MC_2}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, you can see that even though consumers are doing their thing setting the ratio of marginal utilities equal to the ratio of prices, that ratio of prices is not necessarily equal to the ratio of marginal costs. And if the ratio of marginal utilities is not equal to the ratio of marginal costs, the economy cannot be at the efficient point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look back at the figure, you an see what is happening. What I’ve done there is assume that there is a markup on good 1 relative to good 2. This means that the ratio of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_1\inline&quot;/&gt; to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_2\inline&quot;/&gt; is &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; than the ratio of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC_1\inline&quot;/&gt; to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC_2\inline&quot;/&gt;. For consumers, the budget constraint they face is steeper than the PPF, and so they naturally make the choice to consume less of good 1 and more of good 2. In the figure, I’ve shown the pure substitution effect of this change in prices with the point labeled “Hicks”. This holds their utility constant, but shows how choices shift when good 1 is pricier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the “Hicks” point is that it is not feasible to produce. It lies outside of the PPF. We have to slide the budget constraint facing consumers backwards until their choices of what to consume given the marked up price for good 1 are possible to produce. That point is labeled “Markups”, and is where the economy ends up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few important notes on this “Markups” outcome. First, the economy is still &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; the PPF (the thick gray line). The problem with markups is not that they make the economy less &lt;em&gt;technologically&lt;/em&gt; productive, or that they somehow push us inside the PPF (which would imply that we aren’t using all of our labor), but that they skew where along the PPF that we produce. Hence “misallocation” is the right way to characterize the effect of markups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it is not the existence of markups that creates a misallocation, it is &lt;em&gt;dispersion&lt;/em&gt; in markups that creates a misallocation. To see this, go back to the last equation I showed. What would happen if &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; goods charged the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; markup? Then &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1 = \mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt;, and we are back to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MU_1/MU_2 = MC_1/MC_2\inline&quot;/&gt;. The economy would operate at the efficient outcome. Markups would imply that producer surplus had been increased at the expense of consumer surplus - there would be distributional consequences - but the economy would not be inefficient. Markups lower aggregate output when they &lt;em&gt;differ&lt;/em&gt; across producers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, note that I did not mention anything about &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; markups exist, or what kind of market power or market structure might allow them to exist. What the BF paper helped give me some clarity on was that, from the perspective of aggregate output, it is neither relevant nor necessary to know why markups exist, it is sufficient to know that they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A real quick aside here before I jump into the paradox of higher markups. I bounced back and forth a little above in talking about how markups lower the “value of output” or lower “utility”. Those are precise synonyms here. Measuring the value of output, as we try to do with real GDP, is measuring utility. We can argue about whether the BEA gets the calculations exactly right for the aggregate economy, but the principle still holds. So when I say that markups lower the value of output or utility in my little model here, that implies that measured real GDP would be lower as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-higher-average-markups-are-associated-with-higher-output&quot;&gt;Why higher average markups are associated with higher output&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the situation I just described, how is it that higher average markups are associated with higher output? There are two ways this could work. To see the logic behind both, let me first define what I mean by &lt;em&gt;average markup&lt;/em&gt;. This is the weighted average of the markups for the two goods, where the weights are their share in total spending. This would be something like &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_1 \mu_1 + s_2 \mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt;, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_1\inline&quot;/&gt; is expenditures on good 1 relative to total expenditures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(In practice, and to be consistent with BF, what we really want is the weighted harmonic mean of the markups. This is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(s_1/\mu_1 + s_2/\mu_2)^{-1}\inline&quot;/&gt;. But while this is the technically accurate way of doing things, all the intuition you need to understand the paradox flows from the simple weighted average I started with.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the situation I set up in the figure, I said that the markup on good 1 was higher than on good 2, so &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1 &amp;gt; \mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt;, and that dispersion in markups lowered output. So we could raise output by &lt;em&gt;raising&lt;/em&gt; the markup on good 2. If we got to the point where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_2 = \mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt; again, then as I mentioned above, this would restore us to the efficient outcome. Raising &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt; up to the size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt; would obviously raise the average markup in the economy as well. Hence we have one example of the paradox of how higher average markups could be associated with higher output, even though “markups” (really, their dispersion) are associated with lower output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second possibility is that we leave the size of the markups themselves alone, but increase the expenditure share on good 1 with the high markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_1\inline&quot;/&gt;. This will raise the average markup in the economy, which should be obvious. But at the same time, this will act to raise total output, and hence give us the paradox again. How does this work? Remember, because of the fact that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1 &amp;gt; \mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt;, it is the case that the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MU_1 (1/MC_1) &amp;gt; MU_2 (1/MC_2)\inline&quot;/&gt;. In other words, we can gain utility by taking one unit of labor away from producing good 2 and switching it to producing good 1. In the figure above, the market didn’t make this move happen because as far as consumers are concerned the (marked up) prices of the goods are such that there is no gain to their utility from moving expenditure away from good 2 towards good 1. So anything that can induce a shift of expenditure away from 2 and towards 1 would raise the value of output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What might induce such a change in expenditure? One thing would be if the productivity of producing good 1 increased, and hence &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC_1\inline&quot;/&gt; fell. This would make good 1 cheaper (the PPF and budget lines in the figure would become flatter), and people would buy more of good 1 than before, raising its expenditure share. The average markup would rise, and output would go up. You can see some of this logic by running the mental experiment out to an extreme. Let’s say that the marginal cost of producing good 1 fell towards zero, so that everyone consumed &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; good 1. Then we’re at a case where the economy is efficient - consumers want to consume only good 1, and the producers only make good 1 - but the average markup in the economy is exactly &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt;. That situation might mean that producers are capturing most of the surplus, but as I said above, all we’re talking about here is the relationship of markups and the value of output, not its distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are thinking through the possibilities, you’ll see that there is still a case where raising the average markup would &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; the value of output. If the dispersion of markups gets &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt; gets even higher, then the average markup would rise, and the economy would end up at a point with lower utility. You can see this if you think of making the budget line facing consumers in the figure steeper. Hence all the qualifications I made in the beginning of this post about the nature of the paradox of markups. There are circumstances in which higher average markups can hurt the economy, and circumstances in which it can help the economy (in terms of the value of output).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology-productivity-and-markups&quot;&gt;Technology, productivity and markups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last thing I want to make clear is the distinction between productivity and technology, which I’ve been beating on for a while. Productivity is defined as the value of output divided by some measure of input use. Hence for my little toy economy, it is just utility divided by the units of labor used in production. Because the “Markups” point produces less utility than the “Efficient” point, but they use the same amount of labor, productivity in the “Markups” case is necessarily going to be lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt; in use at the “Markups” point is &lt;em&gt;identical&lt;/em&gt; to the technology used at the “Efficient” point. The PPF did not move anywhere or change its slope because of the markups, and hence technology is the same at “Markups” and at “Efficient”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think instead in terms of changes, or growth, then this intuition shows that productivity could grow (or not grow) for two reasons. First, technology could grow, meaning that the PPF shifts out, and then regardless of the markups we’d achieve higher utility. Second, the markups could change, and we could move &lt;em&gt;along&lt;/em&gt; the current PPF, which would also change utility, and hence measured productivity. BF provide a way of breaking down changes in measured productivity into that contribution of the PPF itself versus the contribution of changes in markups, similar but not identical work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/eecrev/v46y2002i6p963-991.html&quot;&gt;Basu and Fernald&lt;/a&gt; from 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll get to all of that - and more! - in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>When did sustained growth start?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/When-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/When-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You know how when you get older, time seems to move faster? Well, imagine how that feels, and now pretend that you write a blog. It’s been about six months since I last posted something, and that was not a conscious decision, but just something that kind of happened as I kept putting it off while I worked on classes or research. If I want to blame something in particular, I have been helping to coach my kids lacrosse team for the last few months, and you’d be shocked at how much mental real estate U-12 lacrosse eats up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the reason, I’m back. And it was a working paper that I finally got around to reading that prompted me to get back on the wagon. Jane Humphries and Jacob Weisdorf have put out “Unreal wages? Real income and economic growth in England, 1260-1850”, which you can find an ungated version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jacobweisdorf.files.wordpress.com/2017/12/unreal-wages_humphries-and-weisdorf_dec-2017_wp1.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As they set it out, there is a disparity in the data sources we use to think about the timing and evolution of sustained economic growth. The basic problem can be see in their figure, reproduced below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/HWfig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;GDP per capita and wages&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using aggregated data, Broadberry, Campbell, Klein, Overton, and van Leeuwen in &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2GnD1Nm&quot;&gt;British Economic Growth, 1270-1870&lt;/a&gt; come up with a series for GDP per capita, plotted in the open circles in the figure. This shows a take-off to growth around 1650. However, the standard data used to establish the path of living standards has been wage data, and here a paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/bla/ehsrev/v60y2007i1p97-135.html&quot;&gt;Clark&lt;/a&gt; from 2007 is their source. As you can see, the wage data indicate no take-off in the 1600’s, and even by 1850 there is little to indicate that wages are experiencing sustained growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two data series tell very different stories about the origin of economic growth. And it seems as if one of them must be wrong. What Humphries and Weisdorf (HW) suggest, in short, is that the wage data are incorrect. The underlying issue is that the most of the discussion about living standards for workers over this period is based on observations of &lt;em&gt;day&lt;/em&gt; wages drawn from various sources, which are then multiplied through by some estimate of the number of working days in a year - typically 250 - to get an implied annual income. But this of course has all sorts of issues. How many days of work was truly typical, and did it vary significantly over time? Even if the day wages recorded in the data are accurate, should we believe that any worker could earn that wage for as many days as they wish during a year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What HW do is dig back into the data and pull out evidence on actual &lt;em&gt;annual&lt;/em&gt; labor contracts. Many farm workers had annual, or permanent contracts, and the farm owner padded out that work force with day laborers as necessary. But annual contracts existed outside of agriculture as well. These annual contracts are, in theory, a much better way of measuring labor’s living standard. However, they have the issue that these contracts often included not just a monetary payment, but payments in-kind, in terms of housing and food allowances. The big issue that HW have is trying to value those in-kind payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, they make the assumption that all annual workers received in-kind payments that had a monetary value equal to a “respectability” basket of goods. This set of goods (and services in the form of rent) was defined by Bob Allen, and you can find the details of it in the HW paper. It consists of a a certain amount of specific foods (e.g. 234 kg of bread), as well as things like soap, linen, lamp oil, fuel, and rent. The monetary value of this basket is added to the actual observed money wages in the annual contracts, and that forms the annual earnings of a worker for HW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the element of the paper you should be most concerned with. HW check the value of this respectability basket of goods against the few contracts they have that are more specific about the in-kind benefits that a worker receives, and for those cases Allen’s basket doesn’t look too far off. But that’s not the same as saying that all workers received exactly this same kind of basket, and more important for HW, that’s not the same thing as saying that all workers received this basket &lt;em&gt;over time&lt;/em&gt;. If the in-kind payments were declining over time, then they are overstating the growth in the value of annual earnings. If the in-kind payments were increasing, then they are understating the growth in annual earnings. I don’t know enough about the historical sources to make an educated criticism here; I’ll leave that to the economic historians. What HW do given the lack of data is reasonable, but that doesn’t make it accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this post, let’s assume that this issue is not significant issue, and see what their numbers tell us. The punch line of the paper is really the following figure. The dark line is the annual wage series developed by HW, and the other two lines are identical to the first figure. You can see that the annual wages track the GDP per capita data very well. And as HW point out, there are two significant things to draw from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/HWfig2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Annual earnings, GDP per capita, and wages&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the reaction of wages to the Black Death (around 1350-1450) is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; smaller in terms of annual wages compared to day wages. We (and by we, I mean me in most of my classes) have used the day wage data for years to illustrate the Malthusian reaction of living standards to population shocks. As the Black Death killed off between one-quarter and one-third of the population, wages shot up, but as the population recovered after that (in the 1500s) wages dropped back to their roughly stagnant level. The HW annual earnings data show that the reaction was more muted. It still existed (look at 1350 to 1400 in particular), but was not as dramatic. In fact, it does not look like annual wages &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; fell back to the pre-Black Death level. This doesn’t mean that the Malthusian model is wrong; there are a lot of other changes going on in the economy over the 200 years following the Black Death. But it isn’t the neat illustration of the mechanism it once was. A different way of looking at this is as follows; assuming that the Malthusian model is &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt;, then the annual earnings data tell us that there must have been &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kind of significant change in the English economy in that period, otherwise the earnings should have dropped back to the 50-75 range in the figure by 1650.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, and probably most noticeable, is the onset of sustained growth in annual earnings &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; earlier than the actual Industrial Revolution. Both the GDP per capita and the annual earnings series being to accelerate around 1650. The Broadberry et al series of GDP per capita does not just reflect an increase in land rents or payments to capital, but appears to also represent an increase in the real living standards of workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That increase predates even the most aggressive dating of the industrial revolution in terms of specific technologies (e.g. Newcomen’s engine in 1712), and is well before dates in the 1760’s based on the spinning jenny or water frame. Steam power was invented in the 1700’s, but it wasn’t really until the early 1800’s that it became a significant source of motive energy for industry in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What HW’s data does, in its strongest interpretation, is firmly sever the connection of the Industrial Revolution - a technological event - from the onset of sustained growth - an economic event. I’ve made this case &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/unified-growth-theory-is-not-the-enemy/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, and the HW findings only reinforce it. The day wage data had already sawed through most of that connection, because day wages had lagged technological change by so many decades. But notice that the HW data suggest the disconnect is not that earnings &lt;em&gt;lagged&lt;/em&gt; the technological change, it is that they &lt;em&gt;predated&lt;/em&gt; the technological change. This is consistent with the GDP per capita data, and that has a very different set of implications for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One story that would need a rethink is human capital as the origin of sustained growth. The idea here has been that it was not until the industrial processes of England, in the mid 1800’s, started to require more human capital that the quantity/quality trade-off for families tilted towards quality, allowing for sustained growth. But if sustained growth began in 1650, then it cannot be that the change in industrial demands for human capital of the mid-1800’s led to sustained growth. Now, you could rescue this by saying that &lt;em&gt;whatever&lt;/em&gt; was going on in 1650 was human-capital intense, and that while the timing of the story was wrong, the theory itself if right. But now we’ve got to establish what was going on with the nature of human capital in 1650 to cause this. At the same time, you need to account for the fact that population growth in England did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; slow down starting in 1650, and on the basis of much data, accelerated not long afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second story that needs some rethinking is the institutions hypothesis. Here’s what you don’t want to do. Don’t look at the HW data and decide that it must have been the murder of Charles I in 1649, or the ascendancy of Oliver Cromwell that “caused” the acceleration to sustained growth. One, the HW data in the figure look precise, but you need to imagine some kind of errors bars around their earnings series, so the take-off to growth is probably safely situated somewhere between 1600 and 1700. Two, that’s not how causal inference works. That said, I probably need to update my prior on the plausibility of the institutional changes associated with the Glorious Revolution of 1689 having an important effect on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another story that comes to mind with respect to origins of sustained growth is the role of discoveries or early colonization. By pushing back sustained growth into the 1600’s, the timing fits as a reaction to the growing colonization of the Americas. The Pilgrims were in 1620, and Massachusetts Bay Colony was organized around 1630. So one could take more seriously that the Americas were an important feature of sustained growth. At the same time, it seems hard to believe that the scale of migration and trade between the Americas and England was so big that it could show up in an appreciable change in English wages even by the late 1600’s. But like the institutional hypothesis, let’s say that I would update my prior on the importance of the colonies. I’m still not sold, but I’m a little less skeptical than I was a few days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A last story that seems to benefit from this kind of data is Bob Allen’s theory about wage pressures and industrial technology. In thinking about why England &lt;em&gt;adopted&lt;/em&gt; certain technologies in the late 1700’s and early 1800’s, and many continental countries did not, Allen cites the relatively high wages in England (compared to relatively low energy prices). The annual earnings data are consistent with his hypothesis, conditional on those technologies (e.g. the jennies and water frames and steam engines) having been invented when they were. There is still a different story to tell about why those inventions were made in the first place, but that probably will stray off too far into the weeds for this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the HW data shakes up the stylized facts about the take-off to sustained growth enough that it should change our ideas of what caused it. It at least got me to start thinking hard about this again. We should separate the notion of sustained growth (i.e growth in annual earnings) from the notion of industrial revolution (i.e. the invention or adoption of specific technologies). Yes, we think growth depends on technological changes, but no, it does not mean it &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to be the technologies involved in cotton production that led to sustained growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really big question, though, is whether I can get out the next post in under six months. Stay tuned. But not too closely, because you might waste a few months waiting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Where did all the investment go?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Investment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Investment/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The fact that economic growth has slowed in the last few decades is not news, at least not on this blog. And I’ve been through a series of possible explanations over the course of the last few years. One bit of data that I played around with a few years ago was the decline in the growth rate of capital per worker. In this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/describing-the-decline-of-capital-per-worker/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; I looked at some figures using BLS data that showed the amount of capital per worker was &lt;em&gt;declining&lt;/em&gt; in 2010-2013. That was unprecedented, as even during recessions in the past it was the case that capital per worker kept growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new working paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/2_gutierrezphilippon.pdf&quot;&gt;German Gutierrez and Thomas Philippon&lt;/a&gt; (GP) has taken on this same topic, only in much more detail, and with a lot of effort put into understanding &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; investment has been low recently. Moreover, they document that investment by firms has been falling over a longer period of time, coincident in large part with the productivity slowdown of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;investment-is-lower-than-youd-expect-given-profits&quot;&gt;Investment is lower than you’d expect given profits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GP start by documenting that firms remain profitable over time, but that their investments are declining over time. This first figure shows the net operating return on capital for non-financial firms (which do the bulk of non-residential investment). “Business” here is the umbrella covering both corporate and non-corporate firms. What is apaprent from GP’s first figure is that the net operating return on capital has remained constant, or grown, over time. For corporations, it is about 10% throughout this period, while for non-corporate firms it has gone up from about 20% to almost 30%. So the decline in investment by firms is not because they are unprofitable. Even the financial crisis in 2009 only produces a slight dip in the net operating returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net operating return on capital&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second figure shows the crux of the story in GP. Net investment (investment spending minus deprecation) relative to net operating surplus appears to have shifted down after 2000. Prior to that, net investment averaged roughly 20% of net operating surplus, while afterwards it averaged only about 10%. I’m not sure how hard to think about the spike in this ratio in the 1990’s - this may be a temporary thing driven by the same technology surge that appears to have driven productivity growth - but you might be able to argue that the average net investment rate got down to 10% as early as 1990. Regardless, it is clear that the investment rate out of operating surplus fell, and stayed low, in the 2000’s. This, derived from more finely-grained data, is the equivalent of what I was talking about in my post from a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net investment relative to net operating surplus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as GP point out, it is not the case that we should expect this ratio of net investment to net operating surplus to be constant over time. Firms are (presumably) optimizing their investment behavior to maximize profits, and based on changing conditions it might make sense to invest more or less of their net operating surplus. What GP work through is a standard model of firm behavior, and link net investment to Tobin’s Q. This metric is, roughly, the market value of a firm relative to the replacement cost of its capital. If Q is more than 1, then the firm should be investing enough to &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; its capital stock, because market value they get from having capital is more than what it costs to install it. If Q is less than one, the firm should let its capital stock run down (allow depreciation to outweigh investment) as the they are not generating as much market value with their capital as they would pay to replace it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two measures of Q&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation, then, for the decline in net investment relative to net operating surplus is just that Tobin’s Q fell. And Tobin’s Q would fall if people expected particularly low future earnings (and hence gave firms lower market values) or if the replacement cost of capital was rising. But as GP show, Q wasn’t falling. It was &lt;em&gt;rising&lt;/em&gt;, at least for corporate firms. The two measures of Q differ by how exactly GP calculate it, as it isn’t obvious how to treat a set of miscellaneous assets and liabilities at firms in order to come up with the market value part of the Q ratio. Regardless, however Q is measured, it is now relatively high compared to the 1980’s, and only lags the very high values seen in the late 1990’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net investment versus Q ratio&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GP then use the data on investment rates and Q from 1990 to 2001 to get a baseline relationship of the two. Given that relationship, they look at what the net investment rate &lt;em&gt;would have been&lt;/em&gt; given the Q values we had in the 2000’s, if investment had continued to follow that 1990-2001 relationship. In the above figure, this is plotted as the orange dashed line. Compared to that is the solid green line, which is the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; net investment rate. You can see that starting in 2000 the observed investment rate is always &lt;em&gt;below&lt;/em&gt; the predicted investment rate, and sometimes by substantial amounts. Based on this, GP conclude that firms are under-investing compared to how they used to. This, despite the fact that they are profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blame-it-on-concentration-and-institutional-ownership&quot;&gt;Blame it on concentration and institutional ownership&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; are firms investing less given their Q ratio and profitability? GP go through an extensive list of possible explanations, which I will not repeat here. Let me jump ahead to the two explanations that hold up across all of their analysis: concentration and institutional ownership. Before I get on to that, let me say that their analysis consists of regressions of net investment rates at either aggregate, industry, or firm level on various sets of control variables. In each case, they control for Q itself, to capture the natural fluctuations in net investment rates. The other control variables are there to see if they are significantly &lt;em&gt;correlated&lt;/em&gt; with net investment rates. GP have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www8.gsb.columbia.edu/faculty-research/sites/faculty-research/files/finance/Macro%20Lunch/IK_Comp_v1.pdf&quot;&gt;companion paper&lt;/a&gt; which does more work trying to see if those significant correlations are in fact causal. For the time being, let’s just hang in there with the correlations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across all these regressions, what keeps showing up is a significant correlation between net investment rates and measures of concentration and measures of institutional ownership, while other possible correlations are insignificant or disappear once you control for other variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For concentration, what GP mean is fewer firms within small sub-industries, implying that each remaining firm has possibly more market power. At the aggregate level, the following figure shows that the rate of firm entry and exit has declined over time, consistent with all the evidence that the John Haltiwanger-led posse of researchers has been banging on for several years. Less entry means fewer new competitors entering, and less exit means fewer firms are being forced out of business. This is consistent with higher concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Establishment exit and entry rates&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would concentration limit investment? The simple intuition is that if you don’t have to worry about competing with anyone, why bother to blow any money investing in a better product? Think of a cable company (&lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt; Comcast &lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt;) which has a monopoly in a local market. What incentive do they have to either upgrade their technology to make it more reliable or faster, and what incentive do they have to invest in, say, more repair vans and extra technicians? None, because they know you can’t go anywhere. Be careful to not run too far in the other direction, however. If firms have &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt; market power, they also will have no incentive to invest, because any advantage they get will be immediately competed away. Somewhere in there is some kind of market power/concentration level that maximizes firms incentives to invest (and innovate, by the way). GP’s results suggest we are on the “back side” of the curve, and increasing concentration is leading to less investment (i.e. more Comcasts) rather than creating incentives for firms to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second significant correlation GP find is with institutional ownership of firms, which can include mutual funds and pension funds. Since 1980, these institutional investors have taken on larger and larger stakes in corporations, to the point that the average firm has about 60% ownership by institutions as opposed to individuals. I’ll admit to not being quite clear on what a “transient” institution means, but the “quasi-indexers” are things like actual index funds as well as widely-diversified mutual funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp10b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Institutional ownership&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the share of quasi-indexers rises, GP find, the rate of net investment falls. Now, you can tell yourself a lot of stories about this, both good and bad. The bad is that quasi-indexers are pushing firms to think only about short-term ((e.g. quarterly) results, and as such firms are loath to spend on long-term investments. The good is that quasi-indexers are pushing management to be more thoughtful about exactly what they invest in, which would imply that the high rates of net investment before were probably &lt;em&gt;too high&lt;/em&gt;. It isn’t obvious which one of those interpretations is correct, on the face of it. The prima facie evidence would be that the growth rate of GDP has fallen in the same period in which the net investment rate has fallen, suggesting the bad interpretation is correct. But there could be other forces at work that kept the growth rate high in the 1980’s, even though the net investment rate was too high. So don’t pull out the torches and pitchforks just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Buybacks and payouts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the intepretation of the institutional ownership, what GP do document is that share buybacks have climbed over this period. Mechanically, spending more on doing share buybacks means less money left over for net investment. It appears that firms, since the early 1980’s, have been using more of their net operating surplus to buy back existing shares (driving up the market value for existing owners) and less on investment. The total payouts/assets in this last figure include buybacks and dividends, and after 1982 you can see that the trend upward in total payouts/assets is driven by an increase in buybacks. GP note in the figure 1982 as an important point because this is when the SEC passed a rule (10b-18) allowing companies to repurchase their own shares on the open market without any regulatory limit. Prior to that, there were restrictions on how much they could repurchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a major shareholder of a firm, you can think of two major ways of making money off your holding. First, you could pursue long-term investments to grow the business and/or expand your market. This would raise the value of your shares by increasing the assets of the firm. Second, you could get the firm to buy back existing shares, driving up their price, and the value of your shares would increase proportionately. This second strategy is faster (you don’t need to wait to install the capital) and arguably less risky, because you don’t have to make a commitment to a new plant or location that may or may not prove to be profitable. Of course, you could go back and argue again that firms were over-investing in the past, and that the buybacks allow those shareholder who were bought out to reinvest their money in higher-return projects. Again, the prima facie evidence is working against you here, but that doesn’t mean you’re wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note here is that GP look separately at the effect of concentration and institutional ownership on capital expenditures (e.g. physical equipment) and R&amp;amp;D spending. Higher concentration and more institutional ownership are correlated with lower rates of spending on both. The decline in investment they document is not just for physical equipment (which perhaps one could argue is becoming less relevant for production) but also for R&amp;amp;D (which one could not argue is becoming less relevant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-it-really-matter-for-growth&quot;&gt;Does it really matter for growth?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last section of GP covers the implications of this for growth. I’m not going to go through their work in detail, as they are trying to line it up with some work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/fernaldtextsp17bpea.pdf&quot;&gt;Fernald, Hall, Stock, and Watson&lt;/a&gt;, and that gets more complicated than I want to cover in a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But GP do sneak in an interesting point in their discussion about the importance of falling investment for growth. If we think that the underlying growth rate of productivity has fallen, which is what appears in the data regarding productivity growth, then this implies that the long-run capital/output ratio should &lt;em&gt;rise&lt;/em&gt;. For those of you who grok the Solow model, the capital/output ratio is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K/Y = s/(n+\delta+g)\inline&quot;/&gt; in steady state. Lower g, higher K/Y ratio. Except that we do not see a higher K/Y ratio over time. It has remained relatively constant, even as the trend growth rate of productivity has fallen. So something else must be going on, and one possibility is that “s” has fallen. In the Solow model, that “s” is the share of output that is turned into investment goods (“saved”) every period. Consistent with the GP story, if s has fallen at the same time g has fallen, then the K/Y ratio will remain roughly constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that the growth rate of GDP gets pulled down even more than it would be through just the decline in g. If s stayed constant, then the drop in g would lower the growth rate of GDP, but the increase in the K/Y ratio would offset that by a little. With the coincident drop in s, we don’t get that offset, and so the effect of the drop in g is particularly pronounced. GP speculate that increased market power of firms can explain why s dropped at the same time as g. That story is consistent with the data that is accumulating, for sure. I have not worked through their companion paper on causality in detail yet, so I can’t offer any opinion on whether increased concentration or market power appears to &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; the decline in s. For now, let’s leave it out there as a very plausible story for what has occurred. Whatever the causality, their initial evidence is clear that there has been a decline in net investment, and that warrants attention if we’re trying to account for why the growth rate of GDP has fallen over the last few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why don't tax cuts boost growth?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxing-GDP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxing-GDP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Relative to current events, this probably seems less important at the moment, and a week or so too late, but the tax cut proposed by th Trump administration is still kicking around. There have been any number of responses to it, and responses in particular to the claim that it will “supercharge” economic growth, and ultimately pay for itself. In short, it won’t do either of those things, which is the conclusion you come to after reviewing all the evidence available. I did so here, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxes-Growth/&quot;&gt;prior post&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/posteverything/wp/2017/09/28/i-helped-create-the-gop-tax-myth-trump-is-wrong-tax-cuts-dont-equal-growth/&quot;&gt;Bruce Bartlett&lt;/a&gt; just posted an article where he also comes to that conclusion, and recants his earlier stand in the 1980’s pushing the whole “tax cuts increase growth” line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is not to rehash the arguments and evidence showing that tax cuts do not increase growth. Rather, I want to think a little about &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they do not increase growth. Because the claim that they do &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; right, but fails in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with some basics. If you want to raise economic growth - meaning an increase in real GDP - then you need to increase the amount of capital, labor, and/or productivity. Whether that is pulling new capital, labor, or innovations into the economy, or putting idle capital, labor, and innovations back to work is irrelevant. You want to increase the inputs to increase GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of economics is that people respond to incentives. In the case of inputs, the incentives to provide them are the returns they earn, like wages, dividends or interest, or profits. If you tax those returns, that lowers the returns, and people will provide less labor, capital, or innovations. So if you lower that tax, the idea is that people will provide &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; labor, capital, or innovation. Nothing here is rocket science. Why does it not work the way we think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;small-elasticities&quot;&gt;Small elasticities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think that if you lower the tax rate, and hence raise the returns to inputs, we should get more of them. But to “supercharge” growth in GDP, or to have any appreciable effect on GDP at all, you need that the elasticity of that input supply with respect to those returns is really big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For labor, there appears to be good evidence that this elasticity is in fact &lt;em&gt;small&lt;/em&gt;. There is not some pent-up store of workers and human capital out there that is just a 35% tax bracket away from getting off their ass and going to work. This labor supply elasticity is found to be essentially zero in almost every case, with the exception of married women. You can see some citations on this in the review paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/jeclit/v50y2012i1p3-50.html&quot;&gt;Saez, Slemrod, and Giertz&lt;/a&gt; (SSG).  With an elasticity close to zero, no matter how much you lower the tax rate, and raise the return to labor (i.e. the wage), you can’t induce a substantial increase in labor supply. And without a substantial increase in labor supply, you don’t get a big increase in GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the capital side, this is tougher to estimate because while it is easy to assert that reported wages are payments for real labor, it is much harder to say what part of reported business income is a payment to “capital”. Dividends are probably one of the cleanest things to look at, as they are direct payments to stockholders. But when &lt;a href=&quot;https://eml.berkeley.edu/~yagan/DividendTax.pdf&quot;&gt;Yagan&lt;/a&gt; looked at the 2003 dividend tax cut, he found there was no effect on corporate investment (i.e. real capital inputs). In other words, the elasticity of real capital inputs to the tax rate was zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For innovation, there is some better evidence of an effect of taxation on R&amp;amp;D activity (although we have to be careful to distinguish between R&amp;amp;D activity and innovation itself). &lt;a href=&quot;http://economics.mit.edu/files/12817&quot;&gt;Dechezlepretre, Einio, Martin, Nguyen, and Van Reenan&lt;/a&gt; have a working paper that uses a change in the threshold for qualifying for an R&amp;amp;D tax credit in the UK on both R&amp;amp;D spending &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; patenting, meaning they are trying to see an effect on actual innovation. They find significant effects of R&amp;amp;D tax incentives on R&amp;amp;D and patenting. Now, tax incentives (like an actual tax credit or allowing firms to write off R&amp;amp;D spending) are not exactly the same as tax rates. And the current tax proposal, so far as I can tell, does not include a specific change to R&amp;amp;D incentives. Changing the marginal tax rate on individual income or corporate income is not the same as providing R&amp;amp;D tax incentives. But, if you are looking for an avenue for tax policy to spur growth, then creating incentives for R&amp;amp;D and innovation appears more plausible than lowering tax rates on labor and capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-tax-financial-flows-not-inputs&quot;&gt;We tax financial flows, not inputs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing reducing the impact of tax cuts on GDP is that taxes are not levied on only the transactions that are part of GDP, they are levied on all kinds of transactions. Think of the fact that every year there are billions (and maybe trillions) of individual transactions that take place in the economy. &lt;em&gt;Some&lt;/em&gt; of those transactions involve payment for a real input like labor or capital, which means they are part of GDP. But &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of those transactions are purely financial, and so are not. But the tax code does not make this distinction; you are not taxed only on your transactions that contribute to GDP, you are taxed on all (okay, most) of your transactions where you receive some money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break this down to four different kinds of transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taxed, and income is from providing a real input. Your paycheck is an example. You provide a real input (labor) to your employer, and hence this income is part of GDP. The income you earn is also subject to taxation. So if you lower the tax rate on this income, you presumably will supply more labor, which will raise GDP. As we saw above, this response would be small for both labor and capital, so GDP would not go up by much. Lower taxes on R&amp;amp;D or innovation might have a more tangible effect.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Untaxed, and income does not come from providing a real input. Think of a small gift of cash, under the IRS threshold, from your grandparents to you. This is income, in the sense that you have an inflow of money, but it is not in return for a real input. It is untaxed because it happens to be small in size.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Untaxed, and income is from providing a real input. You could think of small scale payments for work that fall below IRS reporting thresholds, like babysitting or some home services. Now, because they do not have to be reported to the IRS, they are untaxed, but its also likely they don’t get picked up and &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; as part of GDP. But technically, because they involve someone providing a real input like labor, this income &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be measured as part of GDP. Regardless, because they are untaxed, lowering tax rates would do nothing to change the real inputs people provide here; your babysitter is not going to offer to do a 2nd night a week if the marginal tax rate falls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taxed, and income does not come from providing a real input. Here we’ve got a whole world of financial transactions. If you buy shares of stock for cash, there is no real input provided, so this transaction does not add to GDP. But, this transaction is taxed, in the sense that the capital gain to the seller is subject to tax. If you lower tax rates, then you will get more of these financial transactions, but that will not add anything to GDP. [A side note is that the &lt;em&gt;commissions&lt;/em&gt; on this trade &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; get counted as part of GDP, because they are made for providing a real service.]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big reason that tax cuts do not boost growth in GDP is that tax cuts apply to transactions of type 4, as well as type 1. Lowering the tax rate should increase transactions of both types In practice, the elasticities involved in type 1 transactions are small, so there is little change in &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; inputs provided by tax cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But tax cuts may have a big effect on those type 4, financial, transactions. Those type 4 transactions may boost &lt;em&gt;taxable incomes&lt;/em&gt; by making the transactions more attractive, but have no impact on the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; provision of inputs which would go into raising GDP. SSG use the example of the 1986 tax reform to demonstrate this. In response to this, there was a surge in reported S-corp income (i.e. “pass-through” income), which implies a legal shift from corporations to S-corp’s, but this had no practical effect on the supply of inputs to the economy. It is just reshuffling the paper ownership of companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, you &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; make the argument that if you want to raise GDP it would be ideal to raise taxes on financial transactions (a la the Tobin tax) to reduce the incentives to do those type 4 transactions, but lower taxes on type 1 transactions dealing with the provision of real inputs, and definitely provide incentives to R&amp;amp;D spending and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to convince me that these financial transactions of type 4 &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have an important effect on real GDP growth, then you’d have to talk me into believing that facilitating the exchange of ownership leads to a more efficient allocation of management ability, or something like that. For that to be true, it would have to be that there are a lot of exchanges of ownership that are not currently taking place because they are not worth it due to high taxes. But the prima facie evidence works against you, because you’d want to show me that there has been some kind of decline, or stagnation in financial transactions like this over time, and that is just not the case. But that’s your in, if you are looking for one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That aside, I think it’s key to reiterate that claiming tax cuts will not have an effect on growth is not a denial of the basic theory. Rather, the claim is based on the low elasticities, which mean that the responses are small, and a disconnect between the returns that are &lt;em&gt;taxed&lt;/em&gt; and the returns that are paid to real inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Harvey</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Harvey/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Harvey/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You may or may not realize that the global headquarters of Growthecon.com is in Houston. So it’s been an interesting few days, to say the least. This post has nothing to do with economics. It’s just things that keep running through my head as we clean up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live a charmed life, for so many reasons. But most recently, it’s the fact that we made it out of the storm with a dry house (barely) and with everyone safe. Lots of our neighbors are not so lucky, so we’ve been doing what we can to help. It doesn’t feel like much. I hope it makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this post is me documenting things I don’t want to forget, which includes a lot of raw emotions in response to some amazing events. So farther down you are going to find me taking some shots that maybe one day I’ll regret. Maybe. But right now I don’t think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-is-what-lucky-looks-like&quot;&gt;This is what lucky looks like&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday night, the 26th, is when the rain started hard in the Houston area. We didn’t sleep. We just watched the rain come down, and ran outside during breaks to clear debris away from the storm drain in front of our house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Houston Flood Control district has an online system recording rain totals around the bayous in the city. If you watched the news, you know the bayous are a series of artificially widened creeks that drain the city into the Gulf. Here’s the time series of rainfall totals from the Braes Bayou near Stella Link road, the closest gauge to our house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_rain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rainfall totals&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already had 1.32 inches during the morning of the 26th, and then before midnight we added another 3.56 inches. For some sense of scale, 4.88 inches is right around the typical &lt;em&gt;monthly&lt;/em&gt; total for August in Houston. And that was before the heavy stuff came. Between midnight and noon on Sunday, the 27th, we took 9.92 inches, most of that between midnight and 3am. I cannot describe for you how fast and how hard the rain came down in the first few hours of Sunday. And our area wasn’t the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a break Sunday morning, and this was the view out of our front door. That front areas of bricks was under an inch of water that you can’t quite make out in the picture. Under the street light, on the left, is the storm drain. When I waded out there to check it for blockages, the water was at my waist. Across the street from the light is supposed to be a fire hydrant. It was under water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_worst.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flooding&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That water rose not just because it rained hard, but because the bayou overflowed, and there was no place for it to go. The flood district also provides plots of the level of each bayou at certain stations, and here’s the time series of Braes Bayou. You can see the essentially vertical rise right around midnight of the 26th, into the 27th. At that point the rains continued, and the bayou, thanks to our rain, rain upstream flowing down, and rain downstream backing it up, stayed above flood level into Monday the 28th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_bayou.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bayou level&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you flip back to the rain chart, you’ll see that we still got 3.2, 2.28, and 6.24 inches of rain in the 36 hours &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the heavy stuff. Believe it or not, this is where we got lucky. That let-up of 3.2 and 2.28 inches allowed the bayou to recede, just a little. It bought us a few inches to spare, so when the 6.24 came, our house was able to survive. When I wandered downstairs at about 1:30am on Monday morning, the water had at retreated about one foot from our house, and it wouldn’t come closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its height, we came within 1-3 inches of flooding, depending where exactly around the house you looked. Over the rest of the morning of the 28th, Monday, the water retreated further, and we (personally) were out of trouble. Some tense moments occurred on Tuesday as we took more rain, but never enough to flood the bayou near us again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said, this is a story of amazing luck. Through all that, we didn’t flood. We didn’t even lose power throughout the storm. We didn’t do anything special, it just turns out that our house is one or two inches higher than a few others on our street. People just a few doors down our street are now ripping out carpet and drywall. I don’t know the exact number of people we know who flooded, but it’s more than I can count up quickly in my head. We’ve tried to help people out, but it feels like very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;people-really-are-amazing&quot;&gt;People really are amazing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just about a week ago, I was still reading stories about alt-right neo-Nazi shitheads with brittle egos and tiki torches. And right as Harvey was hitting land the first time, known terrorist Joe Arpaio was getting pardoned for taking a dump on the Constitution. But for each and every one of those people, I saw over the last week hundreds and thousands of decent human beings put everything they had on the line to help perfect strangers. Hundreds and thousands. Remember that when the news gets back to publicizing the worst among us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a few of the best:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everyone with a boat. They came from Houston itself, from the rest of Texas, from Louisiana, from Kentucky, from Michigan, and hundreds of places I missed. Brave, selfless, and inexhaustible. These people drove &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; the shitstorm that was Harvey and got to work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jeff Lindner and everyone at the Houston Flood Control District. Step by step, Lindner came on TV or radio and talked everyone through the situation with the bayous and rivers. Never flustered, never hyperbolic, never flippant, he is part of the reason this didn’t turn out more chaotic than it already was.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;City of Houston and Harris County emergency response teams. I hope you all can go home and sleep for six months. I hope &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; families and &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; homes are safe and dry. And yes, that includes Mayor Turner and Judge Emmett (the county administrator). Those two somehow kept it together the whole time. I’m sure you can find some mistake they made along the way, but anyone who wants to nitpick their decisions should be invited to kiss both of their asses.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eric and Matt at &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacecityweather.com&quot;&gt;Space City Weather&lt;/a&gt;. Those two were a beacon of sanity and reality throughout the weekend. The TV weather guys were not over the top, but were often just struggling to keep up with the constant series of tornado and flood warnings. Eric and Matt were able to put out clear and concise summaries, about every 3-4 hours, of what was coming.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The National Weather Service. Without the information provided by these people, this and every hurricane (not to mention most tornadoes) are mass casualty events. Keep this in mind when you start getting antsy to cut funding at federal agencies to support a tax cut. Weather information doesn’t “trickle down”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I haven’t mentioned all the people that are out right now volunteering their time to clean out their neighbor’s houses, or cook them food, or help evacuees fill out FEMA forms, or … everything else they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every editor of every newpaper, magazine, and website out there, here’s the deal. Go out and find every single one of these magnificent people. Go find them and tell their story. Until you do that, I don’t want to see or hear another piece that involves the term “real America”, or how some unnamed official is “distressed” at something happening in the White House, or provides a profile of some shitbag neo-Nazi with a self-esteem issue. And until you find all these people, I don’t want to read any Vox or Atlantic columns on “What Harvey says about …”. It’s a catastrophe, not a fucking metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you wondering why the whole city didn’t evacuate, do you really think that the city was shocked to discover it could be hit by a massive hurricane? Sheltering in place was not some shoot-from-the-hip wild guess of a strategy. It’s the best of bunch of crappy options. If you want to have a discussion, say a month from now after the worst of this is all over, about whether there are ways to effect an evacuation during the next Harvey-like event, great. Let’s do it. In the meantime, your homework is to devise a plan to evacuate the &lt;em&gt;entire state of Massachusetts&lt;/em&gt; subject to the following constraints. (A) you have 48 hours, (B) you can’t use Rhode Island, Connecticut, or New York, and (C) everyone needs shelter for up to 10 days. Go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read this far, thanks. It was a self-indulgent brain dump from someone with exactly zero problems right now. I should be outside finding a better way to help than generating a blog post. If you have a mind to help, one charity that my wife has been involved with, and does a great job locally, is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.houstonfoodbank.org&quot;&gt;Houston Food Bank&lt;/a&gt;. Go there, give them money. Let them feed people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rising Markups and Falling Productivity</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/DE-Markups/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/DE-Markups/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In between checking weather updates here in Houston, I finally got around to reading the new working paper by Jan De Loecker and Jan Eeckhout (DE), on “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.janeeckhout.com/wp-content/uploads/RMP.pdf&quot;&gt;The Rise of Market Power and the Macroeconomic Implications&lt;/a&gt;”. The authors find that the markup of price over marginal cost charged by public US firms has been rising steadily since 1960, and in particular after 1980. It has generated a lot of commentary already, as in this &lt;a href=&quot;http://noahpinionblog.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by Noah Smith, this &lt;a href=&quot;https://niskanencenter.org/blog/markups-market-power/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by Karl Smith, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2017/08/rise-market-power.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; from Tyler Cowen. A lot of the discussion so far has been about how to interpret their results, and whether it indicates a rise in “market power”, and that devolved somewhat into a discussion of how to define “market power” in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to jump in with some of my own thoughts on the paper, but I’m going to avoid getting into this “market power” interpretation thing. I’m more interested in what DE’s results have to say about the productivity slowdown. Let’s start with how DE get these numbers in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;estimating-markups&quot;&gt;Estimating markups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing; you can’t observe these markups. While the price of a specific good might be knowable, the marginal cost of that good is not. The average cost of producing that good - total costs divided by number of goods sold - is not the same thing as the marginal cost. I’d be willing to bet that a lot of firms would be hard-pressed themselves to tell you the marginal cost of an additional good. And that doesn’t even get into the issue with multi-product firms, where their aggregated financials cannot tell you about the specific prices and costs associated with specific products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when DE are talking about estimating markups, they are extracting the markup of a firms “price” over the firms “marginal cost”, where the price is some agglomeration of the prices of their various products, and the cost is some agglomeration of the cost of their various inputs. That’s not a knock on the approach, but it should be kept in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you extract this markup if you don’t have the exact costs, or even prices? DE assume that firms are cost-minimizers, a less forceful assumption than strict profit maximization. Whether firms are pricing their goods to maximize profits or not is immaterial to DE, but they assume that firms are trying to produce their goods or services using the lowest-cost combination of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the logic involved in the firm’s decision pretty easily. If a firm’s markup is the price relative to marginal cost, then for the marginal good it produces, it should be that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Rev = Markup \times MC \times Inputs&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Rev\inline&quot;/&gt; is the revenue from that marginal good, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Markup\inline&quot;/&gt; is the … markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC\inline&quot;/&gt; is the cost of an additional bundle of inputs, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Inputs\inline&quot;/&gt; are the bundles of inputs it takes to produce that marginal good. Simply rearrange this to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Markup = \frac{Rev}{MC \times Inputs}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you’ve got it. DE have data on firm-level revenues, and they have data on firm-level costs for inputs. There is an extra step, which is that this kind of condition should hold for each separate input (i.e. labor and capital) as opposed to “Inputs” the way I’ve described it. All this does is insert a parameter into this expression that weights revenues by how important that specific input is to production. If we were working with labor, for instance, we might say that the revenue &lt;em&gt;attributable to labor&lt;/em&gt; is only 60% of total revenues, and so divide 0.6 times revenues by the cost of labor to arrive at the markup. For the purposes of this post, though, I think you can easily stick with the idea that markups are obtained from ratios of revenues to costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DE do this for all the public firms they have data for, for all the years running from 1960 to recently. The figure below is the central result, which is that markups rose steadily from 1960’s - when they were about 1.18 on average - to today, when they are about 1.67 on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DE_2017_Fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Evolution of Markups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those papers where it shocks you that no one has done this before. This paper takes some relatively off-the-shelf techniques, and uses them to generate an incredibly interesting set of estimates. Granted, the authors are some of the people who put those techniques up on the shelf in the first place, but the innovation in this paper is the application to the long panel of US public firms, not the techniques. The results in this figure are what have generated a lot of commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the big empirical caveats. If you want to disbelieve DE’s results, then you’d have to think hard about the effect of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sample is only public firms. Probably the biggest question mark. The average markup charged by &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; firms in the economy may not have changed much over time, but if there was a distinct change in the choice to either go public, or stay public, starting around 1980, and that change was related to markup sizes, then this could just be sample selection. For example, you could argue that as investors became laser-focused on quarterly earnings, this meant that the only firms willing to go public or stay public were those with large markups that could generate the expected earnings growth. All the low markup firms are private, and so don’t show up in the DE dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Industry production functions are assumed to be identical for all firms and over time. I mentioned above that DE actually use specific inputs in the calculation, and for that they need these weights (like the 60% for labor I mentioned). To get those, they estimate production functions for each industry using their data. And that estimation assumes that the weights are identical for all firms in an industry (i.e. American and United each have a weight of 44% on labor) and over time (i.e. United’s weight on labor is 44% every year from 1960 forward). DE have an appendix where they relax this assumption, and show that the growth in markups over time (but not their level) is unchanged, so this is unlikely to be driving the results.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cost minimization may not hold. This doesn’t seem like a strong assumption, and it is certainly weaker than assuming full profit maximization. But it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an assumption. If the firms in the DE dataset are not operating to minimize costs (perhaps they just care about maximizing market share or executive compensation?) then the first order condition DE use would be picking up something other than the true markup. I don’t have a great sense of how the bias would work here, or a great sense of whether this could be a big or a small problem. But it could be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to take the DE results as indicative of what is happening in the US as a whole, then the second half of their paper is for you. Here, they break down several secular trends in the economy (e.g. declining labor shares, declining productivity growth) and show how the rise in markups can account for them. As the association of markups with productivity is something I’ve been banging around on for a few years - you could start with this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Cake/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; and work backwards - let me focus on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;productivity-accounting&quot;&gt;Productivity Accounting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presence of markups - and changes in markups - have implications for measured productivity growth. And DE corroborate that, while offering the data to be more precise about the effects. But they do it using a slightly different line of attack than I have in the past, so let me digress for a moment to try and link this all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways we could describe aggregate output. The first is using a production function, like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = T X&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T\inline&quot;/&gt; is &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X\inline&quot;/&gt; is an index of &lt;em&gt;inputs&lt;/em&gt;. Technology, T, is the for-realisies measure of how good we are at transforming inputs into useful output. It is what we really would like to measure. Based on this production function, we could back out technology as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = \frac{Y}{X}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave that aside for the moment, we’ll come back to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also describe aggregate output using incomes, meaning we can write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = \Pi + wX&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\Pi\inline&quot;/&gt; are economic profits, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w\inline&quot;/&gt; is the “wage” of inputs. For those wages, think of something like a weighted average of actual wages (to labor) and payments to capital and/or natural resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are profits? Well, let’s assume that there is a markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu\inline&quot;/&gt;, which recall measures the ratio of price to marginal cost. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu = 1.5\inline&quot;/&gt;, then firms are charging 50% over cost. So profits are equal to 50% of costs. Another way of saying this is that profits are &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu - 1\inline&quot;/&gt; times costs,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = (\mu - 1)wX + wX = \mu w X&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or total output can be expressed as the markup times the wage times the inputs used. We’re still the world of pure accounting, by the way. No behavioral assumptions have been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, go back and compare the original production function version of output, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = T X\inline&quot;/&gt;, to this markup version, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = \mu w X\inline&quot;/&gt;. From these, it shows us that we could write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = \mu w.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or technology is equivalent to the markup times the wage. I like to think of this expression this way: technology (or an increase in technology) can be used for one of two things (a) raising the markup or (b) raising the wage paid to inputs. One quibble with DE is that they say something along the line of “if markups go up, this raises technology”, which should more accurately be phrased “if markups go up, this implies that tecnology was higher”, which eliminates the implicit causal statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve got two ways of backing out technology, T, from the data. Either use &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T = Y/X\inline&quot;/&gt;, or use &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T = \mu w\inline&quot;/&gt;. In terms of growth rates, the first says that the growth rate of technology (using little hats to denote growth rates) is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{T} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X}\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the second says that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{T} = \hat{\mu} + \hat{w}\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s great, but when we go to the data is it quite plausible that we make mistakes. That is, we go to the data and calculate residual &lt;em&gt;productivity&lt;/em&gt;, P. And unless we are exactly right about how the world works, our measure of P may not be equal to T. Here’s what I mean. Take the production function version of things, which I’ve talked about a lot before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{P} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X}^{wrong} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X} + (\hat{X} - \hat{X}^{wrong}) = \hat{T} + (\hat{X} - \hat{X}^{wrong})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of productivity is the growth rate of output minus the growth rate of &lt;em&gt;a possibly mismeasured index of input use&lt;/em&gt;. This mismeasurement may be because we really don’t know how to count units of capital or human capital correctly, or because we are weighting those counts incorrectly. The point I’ve made in a few posts in the past is that by ignoring markups, you could may be making a weighting mistake, and this would lead to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{X}^{wrong} &amp;gt; \hat{X}\inline&quot;/&gt;, so productivity growth understates technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you instead were going to try and measure productivity growth using the real wage, then you could get something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{P} = \hat{\mu}^{wrong} + \hat{w} = (\hat{\mu}^{wrong} - \hat{\mu}) + \hat{\mu} +  \hat{w} = \hat{T} + (\hat{\mu}^{wrong} - \hat{\mu})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where you might be making an error about how fast markups are growing. If you do, and in particular if you assume &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{\mu}^{wrong} &amp;lt; \hat{\mu}\inline&quot;/&gt;, which you might do if you assumed markups were unchanging over time, then your productivity growth term understates technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what DE essentially do in the very last part of the paper. They say that by falsely assuming markups are constant, productivity growth measured using changes in real wages is understating true technological growth. When they make an adjustment to allow for the real growth in markups they observe, they find that true technological growth was around 3-4% per year over the last few year, as opposed to almost 0% growth in measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a massive difference, and suggests that (a) technological progress is clipping along very nicely, thank you, and (b) that almost all of the gains from this are being leveraged into higher markups rather than higher real wages to inputs like labor. Entirely consistent with stories of increased market power and concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t a glaring issue with the analysis that DE do here, but they could go further with it. The papers that establish the discrepancies between growth in productivity, P, and technology, T, point out that much of the problem stems from trying to do this at the aggregate level alone. If you had individual firm-level (or plant-level) data on technological growth, then you could add those up directly (suitably weighted by their size), to arrive at &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T\inline&quot;/&gt; directly. No need to back it out from aggregate information on inputs used, or wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And DE have all the data to do this. When they estimate the production functions that allow them to recover the markups, they also recover an estimate of technology for each firm. It would be straightforward to find technological growth from the “bottom-up”, and compare it to what we get using aggregate methods. This would give us (a) a true(r) measure of technological growth and (b) help identify what precisely we are doing wrong with the aggregate measures of productivity growth. I’ll let DE add that to the near-infinite list of things that people have suggested they do with this data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-are-markups-higher&quot;&gt;Why are markups higher?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of productivity, and for most of the other secular trends DE talk about, the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; of the markup is irrelevant. Arguing about whether markups represent market power or not, or whether monopolistic competition is equivalent to market power, adds nothing to the discussion of the implications. They would matter if we were talking about how to change markups. But at this stage DE are simply documenting the growth in markups and showing that these can be associated with a number of phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much of the discussion about the markups has circled around market power, let me point out two additional possible sources of markups, and growth in markups. First, scale. If there are increasing returns to scale, then the markup will be above one. Think of a firm with big fixed costs. They have to charge above marginal cost in order to recover those fixed costs. You could imagine that what has changed over time is that the firms in the DE dataset invested in some fixed costs that gave them increasing returns to scale, and the markups are covering those costs. The problem with this explanation is that you wouldn’t expect labor’s and capital’s share of output to be declining over time in this case, which they are. So perhaps it doesn’t matter much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it could be us. That is, the markup could be rising because consumers are getting more particular about their bundle of purchases. Whether these firms are true monopolists, or involved in monopolistic competition, or compete in some kind of strategic game with one another, the more inelastic our demand gets for their product, the bigger the markups they can charge. I think of this as a caveat of structural change. As our basic material needs get met more easily over time, we get pickier about the goods and services we consume, making our demand more inelastic. This could explain some of the rise in markups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take seriously the DE findings, then decomposing this rise in markups into different sources is the natural next step. The other step is to find ways to confirm that this rise in markups is robust to non-public, and possibly non-US, firms. Tracking similar changes across countries would help eliminate or confirm some explanations (US-specific anti-trust policies). Nevertheless, I found the DE paper an intriguing (and very large) step forwards.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Are some places &quot;More Malthusian&quot; than other?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Constraints/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Constraints/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve got a new working paper out (&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2017-06-28-Constraint.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/hou/wpaper/2017-192-55.html&quot;&gt;repec&lt;/a&gt;), co-authored with Ryan Johnson, on Malthusian constraints. There is some material that we’re cutting from the paper, because it is already getting too long, but I kind of like the graphs and the results, so I figured I would write them up here. Fair warning: there will be some math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Malthus/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; I wrote not too long ago on what “Malthusian” means, I said that a key feature of a Malthusian economy was that living standards are &lt;em&gt;inversely&lt;/em&gt; related to population size. Typically, we’d think of this as being due to fixed (or very expensive to acquire) amounts of agricultural land. What Ryan and I are trying to figure out is exactly how sensitive living standards are to population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is related directly to the elasticity of agricultural output with respect to land. That is, by what percent does ag output go up if I increase the supply of land by 10%? Now, I just said you &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; change the supply of land, but that doesn’t mean we cannot think about a hypothetical where you could. So what Ryan and I do in the paper is try to estimate that elasticity very carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see the logic, and how we get there, let me lay out a little math. Agricultural production is given by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = A X^{\beta} L^{1-\beta}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where A is productivity, X is the amount of land, and L is the number of people. The value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is the elasticity I was talking about. If you divide both sides of this equation by L, you get an expression for output per worker (i.e. living standards) of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y/L = A (X/L)^{\beta}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which says that living standards depend inversely on population size, L. That’s the Malthusian assumption. What this expression also says is that the elasticity of &lt;em&gt;living standards&lt;/em&gt; with respect to L is equal to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this fairly intuitive. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; tells us how important land is for producing food, relative to labor. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is close to one, then land is the only thing that matters. It’s as if the land produces a fixed amount of food every year, regardless of how much work we put in. In that case, adding extra people reduces living standards by a lot, because there is no extra food to go around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is close to zero, then land doesn’t matter much at all. Most of what drives food production is the effort of the workers. In that case, if we add population, living standards only fall by a little, because each new person is able to produce a lot of extra food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the paper, we refer to an economy where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is large as having “tight Malthusian constraints” because living standards are very sensitive to the number of people. In constrast, an economy with a a low &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; has “loose Malthusian constraints” because the number of people doesn’t affect living standards by much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To figure out the size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;, we do the following. Think of a bunch of economies with a similar living standard, so Y/L is a constant, and call that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\overline{y}\inline&quot;/&gt;. Then rearrange the equation for living standards above to be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;L/X = \frac{A^{1/\beta}}{\overline{y}^{1/\beta}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This says that population density will be high where productivity, A, is high, holding constant living standards. But notice that the strength of this relationship depends on the size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. In areas with “tight” Malthusian constraints, and high &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; values, the sensitivity of population density to productivity should be &lt;em&gt;low&lt;/em&gt;. Because land matters a lot to production, the population gets spread evenly over all the land available, even if that land has fundamentally different productivity levels. If everyone tried to crowd into the highest productivity place, they’d drive down living standards by a lot. We should see similar population density across places with different inherent agricultural productivity levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In places with “loose” Malthusian constraints, the opposite logic holds. The sensitivity of population density to productivity will be &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt;. Everyone can crowd into the small area of land with the best natural fertility, and living standards remain high, because living standards aren’t very sensitive to the size of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a slightly more complicated setup, this is the logic that Ryan and I use to estimate the size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. We look at how the density of rural population is related to measures of inherent land productivity, and we do that for districts within states (i.e. compare all the counties in Texas to one another), using data from all around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can also do this a little more loosely using historical data on the density of population by country, and this analysis isn’t going to fit in the paper. What we do is take the data from the paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v101y2011i5p2003-41.html&quot;&gt;Quamrul Ashraf and Oded Galor&lt;/a&gt; that I mentioned in the Malthusian post, which establishes that population density in 1500CE is positively related to productivity across countries, just as the last equation predicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those guys, though, threw all the countries in the world together to do their analysis, and what Ryan and I did was look at the relationship of density and productivity in their data for specific regions, like Europe, Africa, etc.. Here’s the graph showing what we found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_ag_regions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Density and Productivity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “residual agricultural productivity” term on the x-axis is variation in agricultural productivity after we controlled for all the other things that Ashraf and Galor control for (latitude, etc..). Agricultural productivity is an amalgam of things related to how much of a country is suitable for cultivation. It’s based on climate characteristics and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that Europe looks a lot different than the other three regions plotted: Asia (really South and Southeast Asia), Sub-Saharan Africa, and the Mideast/North Africa. For Europe, there is no distinct relationship between density and productivity. This, using the logic I laid out above, says that the land constraint in Europe was very “tight”, with a high &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. If you take the math seriously, it says that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is approaching infinity, as the slope of the line should indicate a value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. That is probably wrong, and is one of the reasons we like our district-level data for this job instead. Regardless, compared to the other regions, Europe looks like a place where living standards were very sensitive to population size. The other regions show a higher slope, indicating that more productive places were a lot more densely populated, and that is consistent with “loose” Malthusian constraints. Their living standards were apparently less sensitive to population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference in the average level of density (i.e. all of Europe’s dots are shifted up compared to the other regions) is capturing other unobserved “stuff” about Europe that just made it have high population density. For our purposes this shift isn’t as interesting as the relationship within each region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, great, Malthusian constraints were tighter in Europe than in other regions historically. So what? To see the importance, let’s go back to the relationship of living standards, Y/L, with productivity and land, and realize that there is more to life than food. That is, Y/L is my little model here is &lt;em&gt;agricultural&lt;/em&gt; output per person &lt;em&gt;in agriculture&lt;/em&gt;. For lots of historic economies, nearly everyone is in agriculture, and food is a massive share of what they consume, so just talking about “output” and “population” is fine. But to see the influence of constraints on development, we can be a little more subtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be specific that we’re talking about agricultural output per agricultural person, so&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y_A/L_A = A (X/L_A)^{\beta}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, let N be the total population, which includes both agricultural workers, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?L_A\inline&quot;/&gt;, and non-ag workers (e.g. urban dwellers, etc..). I’m going to multiply and divide the left-hand side by N, and do some re-arranging of this equation. You can check my work, but I’m pretty sure this holds up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{Y_A}{N}\left(\frac{N}{L_A}\right)^{1-\beta}\left(\frac{N}{X}\right)^{\beta} = A.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the right is just productivity. The left side tells me what I can do with that productivity. If productivity goes &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt;, for whatever reason (i.e. the Glorious Revolution! The Columbian exchange! The Pope bans consanguinous marriages! Horse collars are invented! Someone planted turnips!) I can translate that into any or all of three things: increased food per person, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_A/N\inline&quot;/&gt;, increased population per agricultural worker, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N/L_A\inline&quot;/&gt;, or increased population density, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N/X\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; features here in the trade-off between increasing population per ag worker or population density. In places with “tight” constraints, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is large, a small increase in population density would “eat up” the productivity gain very quickly. At the same time, because &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is small, it takes a big increase in the population to ag worker ratio (i.e. urbanization) to “eat up” the productivity gain. A tight Malthusian constraint makes urbanization relatively cheap compared to increasing density. The opposite logic says that a loose Malthusian constraint makes density relatively cheap compared to urbanization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence places with tight contraints, like Europe, may have had a built-in advantage in &lt;em&gt;development&lt;/em&gt;, even if they didn’t have an advantage in &lt;em&gt;productivity&lt;/em&gt;, A. It could be &lt;em&gt;part of&lt;/em&gt; the explanation for why Europe took off relative to the rest of the world, given that other areas had high productivity levels and productivity growth at least during some periods of their history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a lot to load onto one figure and a couple of equations. Ryan and I think we do a good job in the paper of establishing that the differences in &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; across regions of the world are robust, and those differences appear related to underlying geographic characteristics (i.e. Malthusian constraints are tighter where winters are colder). The implications of those differences are harder to get at, of course, but we think there’s a plausible story floating around in there somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application of this isn’t confined to historical development, either. For current developing countries, the tightness of the Malthusian constraint dictates the relative cost of urbanization versus density. We find very loose land constraints in tropical areas of Sub-Saharan Africa and Central America, perhaps offering some clue as to why they fell behind areas like East Asia, despite having similar starting conditions in the mid 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Return of Peasant Mentality?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Peasant/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Peasant/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Without intending to, I ended up taking a blog hiatus (blacation?) for about a month. But in that month I built up a whole reserve of speculative energy that I now need to disgorge all at once. So strap in, because this one gets hairy towards the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thing that has interested me since grad school is the clear gap in labor productivity between urban and rural areas, or between non-agricultural workers and agricultural workers. There are two big questions that come up given that fact. Why do those gaps exist? What effect do those gaps have, if any, on development? I’ve taken a couple of swipes at the second question &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/JDE_Final.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/dvhc2014.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those papers, I did have to think about the first question, why the gaps exist at all. It seems like if there were big labor productivity gaps, then there should be big wage gaps, and if there were big wage gaps, then people would have moved from the low-wage rural areas to high-wage urban areas already. One possibility is that those gaps exist because of differences in human capital of workers between the two sectors. If rural workers have less human capital, then their &lt;em&gt;labor&lt;/em&gt; productivity (output per hour, say) will be lower than urban workers, even if the &lt;em&gt;human capital&lt;/em&gt; productivity (output per unit of HC) is identical in rural and urban areas. In this case, the labor productivity gap may not represent any distortion or friction, as the return to a unit of human capital is identical across sectors, and therefore would not imply any kind of macro-level inefficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And over the years, I’d say that more and more evidence accumulates that this is the case. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/oup/qjecon/v128y2013i4p1727-1785.html&quot;&gt;Alwyn Young&lt;/a&gt; has a recent paper showing that there is a ton of movement back and forth between rural and urban areas in developing countries, and so it seems unlikely that some kind of friction, or moving cost, is keeping people from responding to any gaps in wages that might exist. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v104y2014i5p165-70.html&quot;&gt;Gollin, Lagakos, and Waugh&lt;/a&gt; find that gaps in human capital productivity are smaller than the gaps in labor productivity, although there is still a gap. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/red/sed014/364.html&quot;&gt;Schoellman and Herrendorf&lt;/a&gt; look at raw wage gaps - which should be related to labor productivity - across sectors in a number of countries, and find that they are explained almost entirely by differences in human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one issue with these studies is that they (and me in my earlier papers) are comparing two different groups of people: rural workers and urban workers. There may be unobservable differences in their human capital that we cannot account for using things like education or experience, and so we don’t really know if our measures of human capital productivity are accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to a recent working paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/nbr/nberwo/23253.html&quot;&gt;Hamory-Hicks, Kleemans, Li, and Miguel&lt;/a&gt;. The authors use longitudinal data from Indonesia and Kenya, meaning they can track the same individuals over time. This allows them to look at people who move from rural to urban areas, and hence have an identical set of human capital in both places, by definition. As their human capital is identical in both locations, if they earn more in one place than another then this indicates a difference in their human capital productivity, and not a difference in some unobservable human capital. So when people move from rural to urban, or urban to rural places in these countries, do their wages change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Indonesia, they do not. Once you are effectively comparing the same person in two different places (i.e. using individual fixed effects) the authors find a zero gap in wages. If they compare individuals who switch between agriculture and non-agriculture (as opposed to rural vs urban), there is also effectively no wage gap. The wages of individuals do not change when they move sector of employment or from rural areas to cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Kenya, some small gaps remain, but they are small compared to the raw difference in wages between areas. There seems to be about a 13% wage premium to either living in an urban area or working in non-agriculture, even for an otherwise identical individual. That number, though, is not a statistically significant estimate, so it could be zero (or it could be a 20 or 30% gap, we don’t know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HHKLM paper is consistent with the earlier research, in that when you just look at the average wage gap (i.e. labor productivity) between urban and rural areas in Kenya and Indonesia, it is quite large (on the order of a 60-80% wage premium for urban/non-agricultural work), but when you control for human capital, it falls. The HHKLM paper is better at controlling for human capital (because they compare people to themselves), so it validates a lot of this earlier work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of facts tells you that there is selection out of rural/agricultural work and into urban/non-agricultural work for people with lots of human capital. There is not some distortion that prevents rural people from moving to higher wage positions, apparently, its just that all the really skilled or smart people move off the farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Indonesia, the people who start rural and stay rural have the lowest levels of education. The people who start urban and stay urban have the highest levels of education. People who go either rural-to-urban or urban-to-rural have similar levels of education, and its about in the middle of the other two groups. The same holds for Kenya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s really interesting is that this pattern shows up in the Raven’s Z-scores as well. If you read Garett Jones’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2uscIem&quot;&gt;Hive Mind&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll know this is a crude, but effective, proxy for IQ. It’s a simple test that you can administer in the field, and correlates well with broader measures of intelligence (it’s a non-verbal pattern recognition test). So it’s not just that people who are lucky enough to get an education in an urban area stay there, and people unlucky enough to miss out on schooling in rural areas stay there. People with better measures of inherent smarts tend to end up in the city, or are in cities to begin with. HHKLM don’t have information on urban residents for Kenya, but the data for the rural stayers and leavers conforms to the Indonesian data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Everything that follows is all me riffing on the result in HHKLM. Don’t blame them if it doesn’t make sense.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So urban places and/or non-agricultural work looks far more productive than rural/agricultural work because the people doing the urban/non-agricultural work appear to have more human capital, both inherent (Raven’s) and acquired (school). And by explaining the gap between these areas this way, it leads back to an concept that was often invoked in the early 20th century to explain the raw productivity gap: the peasant mentality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As industrialization started, and these raw productivity gaps opened up for the first time, people started to speculate about why they existed if people could move back and forth relatively freely. Chayanov, in 1925, published &lt;a href=&quot;https://vertov14.files.wordpress.com/2016/08/alexander_chayanov_the_theory_of_peasant_economy.pdf&quot;&gt;The Theory of the Peasant Economy&lt;/a&gt;, which speculated about peasant farm organization. In it, he suggested that you cannot think of peasant families as acting according to typical economic logic (maximizing consumption or profits), rather they had a “peasant logic” or “peasant mentality”, which was focused on eking out enough to subsist year to year, but without much thought towards expanding, saving, or growing. One of James Scott’s earlier books, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2urVdLm&quot;&gt;The Moral Economy of the Peasant&lt;/a&gt; provides a study of peasants in southeast Asia, how their motivations were driven by subsistence constraints, and paints a similar picture to Chayanov.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of those authors are sympathetic to the peasants. Others looked at the same situations and get frustrated with the peasants ignorance, stubborness, and unwillingness to experiment with new techniques or technologies. For some, it was the small-town peasant mentality that was holding back economic development. When Ted Schultz published &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2tyjVNW&quot;&gt;Transformaing Traditional Agriculture&lt;/a&gt; in 1965, he attacked both interpretations of the peasant mentality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, he said, peasants were very much rational maximizers, just as economics would assume. They might have additional constraints (subsistence needs) and face more uncertainty unlike “normal” people, but they were maximizing their utility nonetheless with respect to those constraints. Schultz said we should be analyzing peasants with the tools of modern economics; we did not need different theories for them. That brought development into mainstream economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, in questioning the idea that peasants operated on some kind of different set of rules from other people, he attacked the idea that peasants were different at all. They were just like anyone else. The implicit assumption in Schultz’s work is that if you dropped an urban person into one of their villages, they’d make the same choices as the peasants. Peasants were not different, their environment was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if they are different? That seems to be an implication of the HHKLM study. If people are sorting themselves between rural and urban areas, or between agricultural and non-agricultural work, based on some inherent characterstic captured by the Raven score or some other aspect of their human capital, then doesn’t that imply the people in the rural areas &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; different than the people in urban areas?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t mean that rural people are not rational maximizers, but do they come to different conclusions about how to maximize, or what to maximize? If you look at the literature in Jones’ book, you’ll see that things like the Raven score are correlated with other characteristics like patience. Does the sorting of people across locations mean that in rural areas the people are less patient, and so they decide - rationally - to invest less? Are the things that frustrated outside observers of these peasant economies - unwillingness to experiment, ignorance - a result of the selection of low Raven-score, or low human capital individuals, into those areas? Were they right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your gut reaction is “No, or course not”, I get it. So was mine. But let’s not confuse a positive (i.e. factual) finding with a normative conclusion. Finding that rural residents score low on the Raven, and that people with low Raven scores select into rural areas, should change nothing about your opinion regarding interventions to aid development/health/etc in these areas. It doesn’t change Schultz’s conclusion that aggregate development probably requires a massive investment in those rural peasant villages. But the HHKLM data do suggest that the nature of those investments, and how you design the incentives to make them, might need to be different than in urban areas. Think of it like tailoring a class to match the learning styles of different kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the HHKLM study is replicated in other contexts - which may be a big “if” - then perhaps we need to walk back some of the changes in thinking that Schultz initiated fifty years ago. Perhaps we should take seriously the idea that peasants are really different, not just in their constraints (which the development literature has explored in great depth), but in their underlying preferences as well (which has been done far less).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding the Cost Disease of Services</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/What-You-Spend/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/What-You-Spend/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As my internal clock is not on internet time, I’m only now getting up a post in reaction to the death of William Baumol, who has been a consistent reference on this blog over the years. My topic page on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Productivity-Slowdown/&quot;&gt;productivity slowdown&lt;/a&gt; is in many ways an extended riff on his work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can share no personal stories about the man, as I never met him. What I can do is spend some time digging through what I consider the key paper of his most famous idea, the “cost disease of services”. I’d like to think that as an academic, he’d appreciate this as much as an anecdote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, Baumol was one of the handful of towering figures of economics who recently passed, along with Ken Arrow and Allan Meltzer. In response, I would like to suggest that someone move Robert Solow to a secure underground bunker, and encase him in bubble wrap, just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to Baumol. The central paper is “&lt;a href=&quot;http://piketty.pse.ens.fr/files/Baumol1967.pdf&quot;&gt;Macroeconomics of Unbalanced Growth: The Anatomy of Urban Crisis&lt;/a&gt;”, published in 1967 in the American Economic Review. For me, this contains a handful of insights that allow you to understand much of the story of economic growth in the fifty years since it was published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, Baumol divides economic activity up in the following way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The basic source of differentiation resides in the role played by labor in the activity. In some cases labor is primarily an instrument - an incidental requisite for the attainment of the final product, while in other fields of endeavor, for all practical purposes the labor is itself the end product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first case, labor as an instrument, you can read “manufactured goods”. He uses the example of an air conditioner. Just by looking at the A/C unit, or using it, there is no way for you to assess how much labor went into producing it. The labor is just incidental from your perspective as a consumer of the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast that with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On the other hand there are a number of servics in which the labor is an end in itself, in which quality is judged directly in terms of amount of labor. Teaching is a clear-cut example … An even more extreme example is one I have offered in another context: live performance. A half hour horn qunitet calls for for the expenditure of 2 1/2 man hours in its performance, and any attempt to increase productivity here is likely to be viewed with concern by critics and audience alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, labor is the very essence of the product. If you go see the horn quintet, then you are buying the 1/2 of each of those players time. Likewise, for a class you are in many ways buying the teachers time. At a (nice) restaurant, you are often purchasing the time and attention of a waiter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first big conclusion, which is really an assumption of Baumol’s, is that labor productivity growth in the first kind of production (goods) is relatively fast, while labor productivity growth in the second kind (services) is relatively slow. This is just due to the nature of the work involved. For most services, you cannot do “more with less”. No one wants to see the 1/2 hour horn quintet played in only 12 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does the cost disease come in? The next crucial assumption Baumol makes is that labor costs (wages) in the two kinds of activities move together. To be clear, he doesn’t assume (or need to assume) that wages are identical in the two sectors, only that a wage increase in one sector puts upward pressure on wages in the other sector. This would be the case if labor was somewhat mobile between the two activities. Another way of saying this is that workers could work in either sector. (They may not be equally productive in both sectors, as in Alwyn Young’s recent paper, which raises the possibility that Baumol is wrong about relative productivity growth. Maybe go read &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Roy/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; and his paper after you finish this one.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re done. Productivity growth in the goods sector raises the wage in that sector, but also raises the output of that sector. So the ratio of wage to output - a measure of the &lt;em&gt;cost&lt;/em&gt; of a unit of output - stays constant over time. Higher wages in the goods sector put pressure on wages in the service sector, so wages rise over time there. But (taking the exteme position) productivity is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; growing in services, and so &lt;em&gt;output&lt;/em&gt; is not growing. The ratio of wages to output in services - a measure of &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; - is thus rising over time. This is the “cost disease of services”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crucial elements are, again, the assumption that labor productivity growth is relatively slow in services, and the assumption that labor is mobile between sectors. Given this, the cost of services will rise over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my money, the biggest insight Baumol had was to to notice the differential in how labor matters to production in goods and services. The subsequent logic is, by itself, not a major breakthrough. The Balassa/Samuelson effect - developed by those authors in articles published in 1964 - is the same idea. They distinguish between tradable and non-tradable goods, rather than goods and services per se, and they are thinking about a cross-sectional comparisons of countries, rather than one country over time, but the outcome is identical. Countries that are very productive in tradable goods will tend to have high aggregate price levels (an empirical regularity known as the “Penn Effect”), as that productivity drives up costs in their non-tradable sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is worth noting that labels matter. If you call this “cost disease”, it sounds like a problem. If you call this “the Penn Effect”, it means that rich countries have higher prices, and is just an empirical oddity. “Cost disease” sounds bad, but is a lot like dying in your 90’s from old age. It’s awful that you are dying, but let’s not overlook that you made it into your 90’s. Baumol’s cost disease is a result of incredible affluence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precise symptoms of the cost disease depend on further assumptions. Baumol traced out the possibilities in the rest of the paper. We have that the costs (and thus prices) of the service sector are rising relative to the goods sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We may inquire what would happen if despite the change in their relative costs and prices the magnitude of the relative outputs of the two sectors were maintained … if the demand for the product in question (&lt;em&gt;services - DV&lt;/em&gt;) were sufficiently price inelastic or income elastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the next essential insight, which is that demand for services is price inelastic and/or income elastic. What this means is that despite the rising costs, people continue to consume services, and may in fact &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; their expenditure on services as they get more expensive. Baumol traces out the implications of the demand for services on the aggregate economy. In the following quote, the “progressive sector” is the goods sector, with rising productivity, and the “nonprogressive sector” is services, with slow productivity growth. Italics are Baumol’s original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If productivity per man hour rises cumulatively in one sector relative to its rate of growth elsewhere in the economy, while wages rise commensurately in all areas, then relative costs in the nonprogressive sectors must inevitably rise, &lt;em&gt;and these costs will rise cumulatively and without limit&lt;/em&gt;. … Thus, the very progress of the technologically progressive sectors inevitably adds to the costs of the technologically unchanging sectors of the economy, unless somehow the labor markets in these areas can be sealed off and wages held absolutely constant, a most unlikely possibility. We see then that costs in many sectors of the economy will rise relentlessly, and will do so for reasons that are for all practical purposes beyond the control of those involved. … If their relative outputs are maintained, an ever increasing proportion of the labor force must be channeled into these activities and the rate of growth of the economy must be slowed correspondingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to summarize this in my own words three or four times, but I don’t think I did a better job than Baumol. Many posts on this blog have been about the realization of Baumol’s prediction regarding slowing productivity growth as we transition into the non-progressive sectors. I’ll just reiterate that the slowdown in aggregate growth implied by Baumol’s cost disease is driven by the nature of demand, not a technological limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often people interalize the cost disease part of Baumol’s paper, without taking into consideration the second part regarding the effect of the demand for services. Scott Alexander has a recent post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2017/02/09/considerations-on-cost-disease/&quot;&gt;cost disease&lt;/a&gt; from a few months ago that demonstrates this. Alexander’s post is not unique, it just happened to be the last thing in my reading list on this topic, and so I’m using it to illustrate a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a (very) long post, but Alexander goes through education, health, and government services, effectively documenting the cost disease. He crystallizes this by asking the following kind of question. “Which would you prefer? Sending your child to a 2016 school? Or sending your child to a 1975 school, and getting a check for $5000 each year?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He then does this with college; modern college, or your parent’s college plus 72,000 dollars? And then with health care; modern health care, or your parent’s health care (plus ACE inhibitors and some other now off-patent technologies) plus 8000 dollars each year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander’s implicit answer to all these questions is that you would choose the the second option; the older level of service plus the cash. Much of the post is spent explaining that the service offered today is of no better quality than the service offered a generation ago. And while I’d quibble with that broad conclusion, that’s not the point. Let’s stipulate that the quality of healthcare and education have not changed in a generation, which is like taking Baumol’s thought experiment as a precise statement about the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the question that Baumol implicitly asked himself. What do people spend all that extra money on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They could use it towards a new car or a major appliance, both manufactured goods. Perhaps this is what Alexander has in mind; he never says what he thinks happens to the extra money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they might spend that extra five or eight thousand dollars to finally take a well-deserved vacation, meaning it is spent on tourism and hospitality services. Or they may well decide to spend that money sending their kids to a better (and more expensive?) school, or putting them in a full time daycare rather than part-time. Or in sending one of their kids to college who might not otherwise have gone. Perhaps the savings are used to send someone back to get a Master’s degree to get a promotion at work, or acquire a new certification that increases their wage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some of those savings might be spent on health services. Individuals may undertake procedures to permanently deal with chronic problems rather than only alleviating symptoms. Maybe the kids get full orthodontic treatment, rather than the partial work that only straightened one tooth. The savings Alexander proposes could be spent on seeing specialists to deal with persistent health issues, rather than relying on a GP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Baumol’s second insight, the demand for these kinds of services is &lt;em&gt;income elastic&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;price inelastic&lt;/em&gt;. Which means that a huge part of the money people get back from Alexander’s thought experiment is plowed &lt;em&gt;right back into education and healthcare&lt;/em&gt;. What does that do? It shifts the demand curve out for healthcare and education. And then what happens? The price goes up, and the actual amount of new health care or education acquired is not that large. Moreover, there is no appreciable decline - and there may be an increase - in the share of total GDP accounted for by healthcare and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the same outcome Baumol described, even though for him the origin of this was a productivity increase in the goods sector. But the origin of the productivity increase is unimportant, what matters is the structure of demand for services. So long as our demand for services is income elastic and price inelastic, the share of healthcare and education in GDP are going to rise as we get more productive, no matter where that productivity improvement comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a claim that healthcare or education are efficiently run, by the way. I can list, off the top of my head, a good five or six university administrators that I would get rid of tomorrow without any noticable effect. We could spend the next week swapping stories of ridiculous medical bills for $20 band-aids and the like. But their high costs are not entirely due to deliberate inefficiency, and lowering these costs would not lower their share of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Alexander’s post is one example (of many) taking the “disease” part of “cost disease” too literally. Rising costs in education and healthcare do not always represent a pathology. In a lot of ways we are the victims of our own prosperity and preferences here. There is nothing about Baumol’s analysis that implies living standards are lower or welfare is impaired by the cost disease. Remember that the cost disease is a consequence of productivity improvements in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While “cost disease” may not have been the best choice of names, Baumol has to be credited with anticipating the path of economic growth and structural change in developed countries over the late 20th century. He did this without resorting to any math beyond what I could use in an intermediate college course, and in language accessible to anyone. If you’re interested in economic growth, it is well worth finding some time to sit down are read through his body of work.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sigh....No, tax cuts won't boost growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxes-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxes-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I guess we need to go over this again. No, cuts to corporate tax rates and/or the reforms/cuts proposed on individual income taxes will not boost economic growth in any appreciable way. Not to 4%, nor 4.5%, nor 5%. There is no evidence supporting this claim. And even theoretically, there is no reason to believe that these tax reforms/cuts can boost growth to those rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prima-facie-evidence&quot;&gt;Prima Facie Evidence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with a simple smell test. The figure below plots two series: the backward-looking 5-year average growth rate of real GDP and the forward-looking 5-year growth rate of real GDP. For example, in 1981, the backward looking series is the average growth rate of real GDP from 1976-1981, and the forward looking series is the average growth rate of real GDP from 1981-1986. For any given year on the graph, we can compare the growth rate people had experienced in the recent past (backward looking) to what they would experience in the near future (forward looking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_growth_tax.png&quot; alt=&quot;Growth and Taxes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also on the figure are red lines indicating when significant tax legislation was passed, and whether it was considered a tax cut, or a tax increase. 1981 and 1986 are the “Reagan tax cuts”, 1990 is the Bush tax increase, 1993 is the Clinton budget agreement that raised top tax rates, 2001 and 2003 are the younger Bush tax cuts, and included the 2012 “fiscal cliff” agreement under Obama that raised taxes on those earning over 400,000 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you can look at is whether the forward-looking growth rate differed appreciably from the backward-looking one. If the argument about tax cuts stimulating growth is correct, then you’d expect to see that the forward-looking rate exceeds the backward-looking rate. In 1981, this looks true. Growth from 1981-1986 was about 3.5% per year, versus 2.8\% per year in 1976-1981. But examining the other tax cuts, you’ll see the opposite is true. In 1986, growth was slower &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the tax cut than before. In 2001 and 2003, growth is lower &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the tax cut than before. For the 2003 cut, the difference is very striking because of the onset of the financial crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, look at the three tax increases. For Bush (the elder) in 1990, there was essentially no difference in the forward and backward growth rate. For the 1993 increase, growth was &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; higher after the tax increase than before, and for the 2012 increase we’d need to get data through the end of 2017 to make the same comparison. But for what it is worth, growth in the four years from 2012-2016 has been a shade over 2%, meaning it is much higher than the five years prior to the tax increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You cannot take this as any kind of definitive proof of anything, of course. Tax cuts &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; boost growth, but each time we passed a tax cut it just so happens that some other big negative shock hit the economy at the same time, masking those positive effects. That’s … possible. The more likely answer is just that substantial tax cuts have small effects on economic growth. On the other side, the last time we averaged 4% growth over a 5-year period was the late 1990’s, right after the tax increase of 1993.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the smell test, this isn’t a new question, and people have picked around at the relationship of tax rates and growth rates before. I reviewed a few studies in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/taxes-and-growth/&quot;&gt;early post&lt;/a&gt; here on the blog. Short answer, there is no relationship of the tax rate to the growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this same question on from a narrower pespective, Menzie Chinn has a recurring series of posts tracking Kansas’ economic growth and employment since Brownback became governor and signed off on a massive tax cut. The short version of these posts is that employment and growth in Kansas has stagnated and/or outright fell since the cut. There are several similarities between the Kansas cut and the one proposed by the current administration. Most notably, lowering the tax rate on “pass-through” income from partnerships and proprietorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2017/04/kansas-employment-rises-to-0-3-below-previous-peak&quot;&gt;Kansas employment rises to 0.3% below peak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2017/03/kansas-employment-decline-continues-2&quot;&gt;Kansas employment decline continues (part 2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2016/12/trends-in-kansas-gdp&quot;&gt;Trends in Kansas GDP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2016/12/kansas-employment-decline-continues&quot;&gt;Kansas employment decline continues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2016/10/the-kansas-economy-three-pictures&quot;&gt;The Kansas economy: three pictures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2016/10/more-on-the-kansas-employment-collapse&quot;&gt;More on the Kansas employment collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lower tax rate on pass-through income was supposed to generate a burst of growth in Kansas. The TL;DR version of Menzie’s posts is that it hasn’t happened, which you can probably tell from the post titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-dont-tax-cuts-boost-growth-by-much&quot;&gt;Why don’t tax cuts boost growth by much?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, the evidence doesn’t support the idea that tax cuts boost growth, but at least &lt;em&gt;theoretically&lt;/em&gt; it’s true, right? Kinda sorta. Smarter people than I have tried to estimate how sensitive people’s work efforts are to income tax rates, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://eml.berkeley.edu/~saez/saez-slemrod-giertzJEL12.pdf&quot;&gt;they find&lt;/a&gt; very, very small effects. The main effect of changes in tax rates and/or reforms is that people with the means to do so shift the legal definition of their income (e.g. from personal income to profits at a proprietorship). The effect on hours worked is very small, and that is the margin we’d care about if we want to study economic growth. From the corporate side, there isn’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://eml.berkeley.edu/~yagan/DividendTax.pdf&quot;&gt;any evidence&lt;/a&gt; that the 2003 dividend tax cut had any effect on corporate investment, or on labor earnings. Rather, the dividend tax cut generated a substantial amount of payouts to existing shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s say that these guys are all wrong, and &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; tax reform/cut proposed by the current administration is * different&lt;em&gt;. For realsies, it is going to incent lots of firms to invest more, employ more people, and stimulate the economy. *That&lt;/em&gt; is going to boost growth to 4%, or maybe more, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrong. The issue is that the effects of any tax cut are going to take time to manifest themselves. In particular, corporate tax cuts that have the stated purpose of raising investment will need years or &lt;em&gt;decades&lt;/em&gt; to manifest themselves in higher GDP, assuming that the savings are actually used for investment spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been over this before on this blog, and now that I have my handy Topics pages, you can go see all the gory details &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Converge-Reform/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The short story is that tax cuts/reforms change &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; GDP (possibly), and it takes a long time for us to converge from today’s GDP to that potential GDP. The analogy is to think of GDP like your weight. If you cut “taxes” on your weight by exercising less, then you will gain weight. But not all at once. It will take months or years to reach your new potential, heavier, weight. The same thing happens with GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you think the effects of these tax cuts on potential GDP are massive, which is unlikely, you can’t generate significant changes in growth rates. There are several posts on the Topics page that do this, but let me repeat the basic calculation. Real GDP in the US is just about 17 trillion (2009 chained) dollars as of Q1 2017. A generous estimate of the current growth rate of real GDP would be about 2.5% per year, without the tax cuts. Now, let’s say the proposed corporate and individual tax cuts/reforms raised &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; GDP to something like 18 trillion dollars. In other words, what if there was 1 trillion in extra economic activity that was not taking place because a bunch of people have John Galt-ed themselves out of investing or working due to the current tax system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much faster would growth in real GDP be after the proposed tax cuts/reforms? To figure this out we need one extra piece of information, the convergence rate. This rate is the percent of the gap between current GDP and potential GDP that closes every year, and it is commonly estimated to be about 2%. In the weight example, if your current weight was 150 pounds, and your potential weight is 300 pounds thanks to your cut in exercise, then this 2% convergence rate says that in the first year, you will gain .02&lt;em&gt;(300-150) = 3 pounds. And next year, you’ll gain .02&lt;/em&gt;(300-153) = 2.94 pounds. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can do the same calculation for GDP, and figure out the growth rate of GDP implied by this convergence. Current GDP is 17 trillion, and potential GDP is 18 trillion, so the economy should add an extra .02&lt;em&gt;(18-17) = .02 trillion, or about 20 billion in economic activity. Now, remember, GDP was going to grow at 2.5% anyway without the tax cut. So GDP next year was going to be 1.025&lt;/em&gt;17 = 17.425 trillion. Add the extra 20 billion on top of that, to get 17.445 trillion in economic activity next year. So overall growth in GDP would be 17.445/17 - 1 = .0262, or 2.62%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s …. not 4%. Or really anywhere close. It is hard to move the growth rate of GDP, in the same way that it is hard to change the heading of an oil tanker. But maybe I’m just being pessimistic. So let’s play around with some numbers. What if the convergence rate is 4% per year? Then growth would be 2.73% next year. What if the convergence rate is 10%? 3.09% growth. Which is still not 4% per year, and there is no evidence that the convergence rate is 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you’re worried I’m underselling the effects of the tax cut itself. So let’s say that the proposed reforms raise the potential GDP of the US to 19 trillion - which is ridiculous by the way - but whatever. With a 2% convergence rate, that would lead to a growth rate of … 2.73%. How about potential GDP of 20 trillion, meaning that tax rates &lt;em&gt;alone&lt;/em&gt; are keeping GDP &lt;em&gt;three trillion&lt;/em&gt; under where it could. Then growth might hit … 2.85%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental issue here is that it takes time for all that pent-up investment (if it exists) to manifest itself. Firms cannot expand production overnight. It takes time to generate the plans for a new location, or plant, or product. And this all assumes, contrary to the available evidence, that there are substantial effects of tax cuts or reforms on the willingness of firms to invest and/or people to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no magic elixir of tax rules that will generate 4% growth. You don’t need to see anything more than the one-page outline put out by the current administration to get to this conclusion. Filling in the details will not change the fact that their plan, if passed, will have no appreciable effect on economic growth in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Topics in Economic Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Topics-Pages/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Topics-Pages/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Less of a post, and more of an announcement. I just created some new pages here at Growthecon.com that collect resources and materials related to specific topics regarding growth. See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/topics/&quot;&gt;Topics&lt;/a&gt; link in the header of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an exercise in intellectual housecleaning, and a way to organize some materials for possible use in classes in the future. Each topic has links to my own posts on the subject, links to other web articles or resources, and some selected academic citations. The topics are thus more accessible, but less comprehensive, then the pages of &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/references/&quot;&gt;references&lt;/a&gt; that are also posted on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, the topics include&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Are-We-Rich/&quot;&gt;Are we rich?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Converge-Reform/&quot;&gt;Can you reform your way to higher growth?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Comp-Assumptions/&quot;&gt;Does growth depend on competition?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Dev-Growth/&quot;&gt;Does economic growth mean economic development?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Productivity-Slowdown/&quot;&gt;Productivity slowdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Manuf-Special/&quot;&gt;Is manufacturing special?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Robots-Jobs/&quot;&gt;Robots and jobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Inst-Geography/&quot;&gt;Deep determinants of development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Growth-Nature/&quot;&gt;Does economic growth harm the environment?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a decent start, and there may be a few more topics to show up. The first job is probably to split the topic on productivity slowdown into separate pieces, maybe just on measuring TFP, and then on the Baumol effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aggregate Productivity versus Aggregate Technology ... Again</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/TFP-With-Profits/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/TFP-With-Profits/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You can file this as another example of how measured aggregate TFP growth is like a trash can. It happens to include aggregate technology (which got tossed in there by accident while cleaning up kitchen), but also all sorts of other junk (like leftover coffee grounds). Today’s example shows that even if you are smart about how you construct your measure of aggregate TFP growth, you can still end up with some garbage in there because of aggregation issues. I know this is pushing the analogy, but actually measuing aggregate &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt; is like trying to wipe up just the waffle crumbs your kids left behind, but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the drops of syrup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me try to give the English-language, and non-garbage related, version of this before turning to the math. To calculate TFP growth, we look at how fast aggregate GDP grew relative to how fast aggregate input use grew. But there is a discrepancy about how we measure GDP growth and how we measure input growth. Aggregate GDP growth is a summation of the growth rate of each individual sector, with each weighted by how big a part of GDP they are. Manufacturing is about 12% of GDP, so a 3% growth rate of manufacturing output would add 0.12 x 0.03 = 0.0036 to total GDP growth, or about one-third of one percentage point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, aggregate input growth is the summation of the growth rate of inputs of each individual sector, but with each weighted by how big a part of total &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; they are. So if manufacturing is about 10% of total costs, a 2% growth rate of input use would add 0.10 x 0.02 = 0.002 to total input growth, or about one-fifth of one percentage point. Why costs, and not GDP? We want our measure of total input growth to reflect how inputs are really used across sectors, not how output is valued across sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we’re measuring aggregate GDP growth by weighting sectors by their share of GDP, but measuring input growth by weighting sectors by their share of costs, we’ve created a problem. If there are differences in market power (and hence profits) between sectors, then a sector’s share of GDP is no longer equal to its share of costs. For a sector with a big profit share, it would look over-weighted in GDP growth, but under-weighted in input growth. If its input use is growing, this will show up as &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; aggregate TFP growth. The opposite case can also happen. If we have a sector with a very small profit share, it will look under-weighted in GDP growth, but over-weighted in input growth. If it has rapid input growth, this will show up as &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; aggregate TFP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But neither case reflects any actual technological change. We’re just moving inputs from one sector to another. Once we start aggregating sectors, all the differences in market power between sectors are going to stick to aggregate TFP like the drops of syrup to the waffle crumbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This holds true even though we’re being really smart about how we calculate the input growth, and I was reminded of this in class when a student presented a paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aejmac/v3y2011i2p29-74.html&quot;&gt;John Fernald and Brett Neiman&lt;/a&gt; that happens to be about Singapore. They construct a measure of aggregate TFP growth, and show how it contains both aggregate technology growth but also an adjustment term that picks up on these differences between sectors in their cost and GDP shares. This is true despite the fact that using cost shares for input growth is the right thing to do (as opposed to just using the GDP shares over again, basically).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows next is the math behind this, and then I’ll pick up again on the English explanation and try to think through how this might be applicable to the US productivity slowdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-math&quot;&gt;In Math&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s back up a step, to review what the issue may be. If I want to calculate a measure of TFP growth, then I want to calcualte the difference between the growth rate of output and the growth rate of “inputs”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta TFP = \% \Delta GDP - \% \Delta Inputs&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But constructing the growth rate of inputs is non-trivial. There are multiple inputs (capital and labor, at least), and so I need some way to sum up the growth rate of all the inputs into a single measure of the growth rate of inputs. Basically, I need to subtract off the growth rates of all the inputs, but I need to scale each of them by how important they are to production. To be more precise,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta TFP = \% \Delta GDP - \omega_K \% \Delta K - \omega_L \% \Delta L&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I’m assuming there are two inputs, capital and labor. The &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt; measure how important each is to production. I need those because a 10% increase in capital, for example, doesn’t translate directly into a 10% increase in GDP, because of diminishing returns. I want the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt; to capture these diminishing returns, meaning I want the elasticity of GDP with respect to capital. And there is a similar story for labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve mentioned before here that a traditional way of measuring these is to assume that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt; is equal to labor’s share of GDP, meaning total wages divided by GDP, and that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt; is just &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 - \omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt;. This would be fine only under some very specific conditions: zero profits and constant returns to scale. And the world might not work that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more robust way of doing this is to use the capital’s share of total &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; to measure &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt;, and labor’s share of total &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; to measure &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt;. This doesn’t require an assumption about either profits or constant returns to scale. All we need to believe is that firms are cost-minimizers. With cost minimizers, the cost share of an input will be equal to the elasticity of GDP with respect to that input, and we’re all good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that we might not be good. The problem is that when we have multiple sectors (or firms), to add up to find the growth rate of GDP, we use each sector’s share of GDP as a weight. For an example, I’m going to go with two sectors, manufacturing and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta GDP = \frac{P_M Y_M}{GDP}  \% \Delta Y_M + \frac{P_S Y_S}{GDP}  \% \Delta Y_S&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger the fraction of GDP made up of services, for example, the more important the growth rate of services is for aggregate growth in GDP. If you’re unsure about that, just ask yourself what the growth rate of GDP would be if there were no manufacturing sector, only services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the measure of TFP growth, I still need those &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt; weights. And for those weights I need the cost share of capital and labor at the &lt;em&gt;aggregate&lt;/em&gt; level. To calculate the aggregate cost share of capital, for example, I would use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\omega_K = \frac{Costs_M}{Costs}\frac{RK_M}{Costs_M} + \frac{Costs_S}{Costs}\frac{RK_S}{Costs_S}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where R is the rental rate of capital, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K^M\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K^S\inline&quot;/&gt; are the actual amounts of capital used by manufacturing and services. Writing it this way, the ratio &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?RK^M/Costs^M\inline&quot;/&gt; is the share of capital in the costs of manufacturing, and similar for services. But I weight those by manufacturing’s (or service’s) share of total costs. Again, the effect of an individual sector depends on how big it is in the economy, except now we measure that size by costs, not by GDP. There is an essentially identical equation for &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt;, only using total wages instead of the total cost of capital within each sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can start to get a flavor of the problem now. We are aggregating GDP growth by using shares of &lt;em&gt;GDP&lt;/em&gt;, but we are aggregating cost shares by using shares of &lt;em&gt;Costs&lt;/em&gt;. This is a problem once we have either sector earning profits, and thus their share of GDP is not the same thing as their share of costs. In particular, if manufacturing (say) earns profits, then its share of GDP is necessarily bigger than its share of total costs. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_M Y_M / GDP &amp;gt; Costs_M/Costs\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fernald and Neiman work out just the effect that this has on measured TFP growth. To kind of match their analysis, and because it helps simplify, let’s assume that manufacturing earns profits, while services do not. Then what they show is that you can write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta TFP = \% \Delta Technology + \frac{s_{\Pi}}{1-s_{\Pi}}\left(1 - \frac{P_M Y_M}{GDP}\right)\left( \% \Delta Inputs_M -  \% \Delta Inputs_S \right).&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; TFP (the thing on the left) combines two terms. The first term on the right is the “true” growth rate of technology. The second term captures the effect of having sectors with different profit shares. We can take each part of that second term in turn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\Pi}/1-s_{\Pi}\inline&quot;/&gt;: This is the ratio of profits to costs in the aggregate economy. The larger this is, the bigger an impact this adjustment to TFP growth gets. This ratio will be relatively big when manufacturing is a big fraction of the economy, and relatively small when manufacturing is a small fraction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 - P_M Y_M/GDP\inline&quot;/&gt;: This captures how important manufacturing is in the economy. If manufacturing made up all of GDP, then this whole second term would disappear, as the aggregate economy would look exactly like the manufacturing sector. But the smaller is manufacturing, the bigger the effect this term has.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\% \Delta Inputs_M -  \% \Delta Inputs_S\inline&quot;/&gt;: I know I dropped in some new notation here. This is the difference in the growth rate of total input use in manfucturing and services. Technically, there are separate terms in here referring to capital and labor, but this does the job. This last difference is what determines whether the whole second term is positive or negative. If input use in manufacturing is growing faster than in services, then this term would be positive, and it would make measured aggregate TFP growth higher. On the other hand, if services have higher input growth, then measured aggregate TFP growth would be lower.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-to-english&quot;&gt;Back to English&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the math confirms (I hope), is that aggregate TFP growth depends not only on aggregate technology, but also an adjustment for whether input use is growing faster in a high-profit sector (i.e. manufacturing) or a low-profit sector (i.e. services). To the extent that services have faster input growth, measured TFP growth will be &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; than actual technology growth. This is because input use in services is a little over-weighted compared to manufacturing, but the share of GDP in services is a little under-weighted. When inputs flow into services, it is like we are counting the input use more than we count the GDP growth that comes with it, and since TFP growth is just GDP growth minus input growth, it looks like TFP is growing more slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is an additional effect of moving into services, over and above the plausible story that services have relatively low “true” technological growth. It’s also complete speculation, because I’m just spitballing this idea that the profits in manufacturing are larger than services. It might make more sense to just think about high-profit and low-profit sectors, and ask if inputs are shifting from the former into the latter. Either way, once you’ve got sectors tha differ in their profit shares, your measure of aggregate TFP growth has this possible problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the lesson here is that you really cannot use only aggregate data if you want a measure of aggregate technology growth. You will always run into the garbage can issue. If you want a measure of aggregate technology growth, you should calculate technological growth for each individual unit (firm or sector) separately, and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; add those up, if you want any chance. Since I know you were hoping for another breakfast food analogy, imagine using a tweezers to pick up each individual crumb of waffle to ensure you do not touch any syrup.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
