<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Growth Economics Blog</title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description>Dietrich Vollrath Economic Growth Blog</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2016 16:56:14 -0500</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>You Saved What?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nick Rowe just had a &lt;a href=&quot;http://worthwhile.typepad.com/worthwhile_canadian_initi/2016/02/does-saving-count-towards-gdp.html#more&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about the effect of savings on GDP. I&amp;#39;m paraphrasing, but a student asks him whether &amp;quot;saving an extra \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100&amp;quot; raises GDP (or not), because the national income product accounts can be written as\inline&quot;/&gt;Y = C + S + T&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?. I think Nick nails the issue, which is that you &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; specify &amp;quot;instead of what?&amp;quot; when you say you &amp;quot;save an extra \\inline&quot;/&gt;100&amp;quot;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve run into the same question before, and I&amp;#39;ve gone back and forth on how best to explain the answer (which, strictly speaking, is &amp;quot;it depends&amp;quot;). This also gives me a chance to rant a little about my pet peeve of measuring GDP in dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem we have is that &amp;quot;save an extra \$100&amp;quot; means &amp;quot;keep 100 slips of green paper in my wallet rather than spending them&amp;quot; to any normal human being. This is a statement about how you use the medium of exchange. It&amp;#39;s a statement inherently related to the turnover of that medium of exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the word &amp;quot;savings&amp;quot; and the symbol &amp;quot;S&amp;quot; are also used as a concept in national income product accounts to stand for &amp;quot;the value of goods and services that are neither consumed nor handed over to the government as taxes&amp;quot;. Because you typically measure the value of good and services using dollars, this creates confusion. But &amp;quot;\&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 of S&amp;quot; is a statement that uses dollars as a unit of account, and has nothing to do with \\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of the medium of exchange. &amp;quot;\&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 of S&amp;quot; means that you purchased \\inline&quot;/&gt;100 worth of goods and services, &lt;em&gt;and then saved those goods and services&lt;/em&gt;. It does not mean you kept 100 slips of green paper in your wallet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question from Nick&amp;#39;s student isn&amp;#39;t easy to answer, and it should be easier. He wants to know the effect on GDP if he &amp;quot;saves an extra \$100&amp;quot;, and right now the answer gets confusing because of this confusion in medium of exchange and unit of account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be clearer if we didn&amp;#39;t insist on measuring GDP (and its components like S) in units of dollars. Yes, we tell everyone they are &amp;quot;2005 dollars&amp;quot; or something like that, but we all hear &amp;quot;dollars!&amp;quot; in our head and think of little slips of green paper. I really think a better way to do this would be to just measure GDP as physical units of output. You can do this in a crude (but effective) way by just measuring GDP as the equivalent number of cans of Diet Cokes (e.g. divide nominal GDP by \$0.85, the price in our department vending machine). Or if you insist on being more accurate, divide nominal GDP by the actual dollar value of the CPI basket, and you&amp;#39;ll get &amp;quot;number of CPI baskets produced&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, if GDP is in real terms - Diet Cokes or CPI baskets - then we no longer have this confusion of the medium of exchange (dollars) and the unit of account (DC or CPI baskets). When you say you &amp;quot;save an extra \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100&amp;quot;, I think it now becomes obvious that you &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; complete that statement with &amp;quot;...instead of buying \\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Cokes or CPI baskets&amp;quot;. It is clear what you are doing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we&amp;#39;re not totally out of the woods. GDP is a flow concept, not a stock. So it&amp;#39;s impossible to specify the effect of &amp;quot;saving an extra \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 instead of buying \\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Coke&amp;quot; without saying precisely &lt;em&gt;how long&lt;/em&gt; you plan to save that money for. It is March 6th. If you &amp;quot;save an extra \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100&amp;quot; today by not spending it, and don&amp;#39;t spend it until April 13th, then &lt;em&gt;first quarter GDP&lt;/em&gt; goes down by at least \\inline&quot;/&gt;100. At least. You not spending that \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 means someone else didn&amp;#39;t earn that \\inline&quot;/&gt;100, and they cannot spend the \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100, and so there may be a whole chain of transactions that don&amp;#39;t occur because you saved an extra \\inline&quot;/&gt;100. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you &amp;quot;save an extra \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100&amp;quot; on March 6th, but then spend that \\inline&quot;/&gt;100 on March 8th, first quarter GDP might not got down at all. You still spent the \$100 in the first quarter, and all the subsequent transactions that might be keyed off of your spending still have time to occur. Maybe the 2 day delay means that someone 15 transactions down the line doesn&amp;#39;t get a chance to buy a Snickers bar until April 1st, and now that transaction is not counted in first quarter GDP any more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;#39;t solve our problem, because we didn&amp;#39;t account for the fact that maybe the producers will respond to our lack of spending by changing prices. If you &amp;quot;save an extra \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 instead of buying \\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Coke&amp;quot; on March 6th, then the DC distributor might notice that 117.67 cans of DC are still on the shelf on March 7th that they expected to be gone. They figure this represents lower demand, so to clear their inventory they lower the price. By March 31st, even though &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; didn&amp;#39;t spend \$100 on Diet Cokes, somebody bought those cheaper Diet Cokes and hence real GDP (the number of Diet Cokes sold) is the same as if you hadn&amp;#39;t saved that money at all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know that there is a simple way to teach this stuff. I think you could probably spend a whole semester just going over (and over and over) the difference between GDP and the money supply. Let me take a crack at a relatively simple way of accomodating a question about what happens when you &amp;quot;save an extra \$100&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key here is the Quantity Theory of Money. It is an identity that tells us how to determine nominal GDP. You know the formula, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MV = PY\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone says &amp;quot;save an extra \$100&amp;quot;, they mean &amp;quot;lower velocity&amp;quot; by some amount. They are turning over their actual dollars more slowly (e.g. waiting until April 13th to spend them). How much velocity goes down is a question of (a) how long they wait to spend the money and (b) how crucial that spending is for everyone else&amp;#39;s spending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, because V has gone down, it must be that either M goes up, or PY has gone down. If we assume that M stays constant, then it has to be that PY goes down. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens to &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; GDP - cans of Diet Coke - Y? That depends on how flexible you think prices are. If P can adjust easily (the DC distributor notices quickly and lowers prices), then Y may be unaffected by your decision to &amp;quot;save an extra \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100&amp;quot;. But if prices are sticky, then your decision to save \\inline&quot;/&gt;100 has to lower Y by an amount proportional to how much velocity goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about that whole NIPA accounting equation &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = C + S + T\inline&quot;/&gt;? Well, what about it? S is a classification of real GDP. S is the number of Diet Cokes that you &lt;em&gt;buy&lt;/em&gt;, but do not actually &lt;em&gt;drink&lt;/em&gt;. S is &amp;quot;GDP that is neither consumed nor given to the government&amp;quot;. Yes, the BEA calls that &amp;quot;savings&amp;quot;, but that is a crappy term that just causes confusion. If we measured GDP in real units, and stopped using the term &amp;quot;savings&amp;quot; both for &amp;quot;dollars not spent&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;goods and services not consumed&amp;quot;, we wouldn&amp;#39;t have to keep rehashing these questions again and again every year with a new set of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I might have read Nick&amp;#39;s post wrong, and maybe the student was asking about spending 100 gold pieces to raise his &lt;em&gt;saving throw&lt;/em&gt; from a 17 to an 18. Easy mistake to make.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growth References</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/New-References/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/New-References/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A very quick post just to alert you that I&amp;#39;ve added a new page of &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/references/&quot;&gt;references&lt;/a&gt; to the site. It is essentially a dump of my own BibTeX file, broken down by topic area. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s incomplete, but as I clean up and add to the references over time, they&amp;#39;ll populate to that page. Of course, I&amp;#39;ll probably be in my 70&amp;#39;s before I get around to it, but maybe announcing it publicly will act as a commitment device. It can&amp;#39;t make me go any &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; at fixing up my BibTeX file, that&amp;#39;s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Accelerate Growth Rates</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Accelerate-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Accelerate-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A good amount of discussion takes place about how to accelerate growth, with a lot of prominent examples coming from the US presidential primaries. Jeb! promised to get the growth rate of GDP to 4%. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dollarsandsense.org/What-would-Sanders-do-013016.pdf&quot;&gt;Gerald Friedman&lt;/a&gt; said that Sanders&amp;#39; plans would raise growth to 5.3%, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ineteconomics.org/uploads/general/romer-and-romer-evaluation-of-friedman1.pdf&quot;&gt;Romer&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt; have published a rebuttal saying that is almost impossible to achieve. &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/kocherlakota009/home/policy/thoughts-on-policy/2-23-16&quot;&gt;Narayana Kocherlakota&lt;/a&gt;, on the other hand, says that we can adopt policies that can achieve 5-6% growth over the next four years. I know I&amp;#39;ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/insert-policy-here-wont-boost-growth-rates/&quot;&gt;said before&lt;/a&gt; that whatever your favorite policy is, it won&amp;#39;t boost growth rates by maybe more than 1 percentage point, so maybe you could hit 3%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what gives? Is it possible, or not, to materially boost growth rates through policy? The answer, which lets you distinguish between the links given above, is that it depends on the kind of policy. To be crude, divide policies into either aggregate supply (AS) policies or aggregate demand (AD) policies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big difference between them, at least for understanding their impact on growth rates in the short run, is in whether they involve spending money &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. AS policies - reform the tax code, reduce occupational licensing, cut back regulation, etc. - are about changing incentives for people to invest in new capital (human or physical) or to reallocate that capital to higher productivity uses. AD policies - monetary policy, direct transfers - differ in that they directly involve moving money from one person or institution to another. Some policies, infrastructure spending, for example, have elements of both. The infrastructure changes incentives for investments by private business (AS), but also involves a direct transfer of money to pay for it (AD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be a little more concrete about my distinction of AD and AS policies, think of the difference between a change to tax law that lowers the tax rate on small businesses (an AS policy) and a $500 tax refund sent to every person in the US (an AD policy). The change in tax rates will presumably induce more small businesses to start or expand (arguing about the size of this effect is something for a different post, roll with it) over time, but this will take time. Nothing material is going to happen to GDP growth this quarter because of that policy change, even though over time it might result in significantly more GDP. In constrast, the tax refund is going to put money in people&amp;#39;s pockets &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, and so there will be a more immediate effect on GDP, although it will fade away relatively quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try and illustrate the difference, let me try some diagrams that should be familiar to anyone who has taken intermediate macro. These are basic AS/AD diagrams, but with an additional feature that comes from growth economics. Rather than one long-run AS curve (LRAS), we have two. The first is the current LRAS, and the second is the potential LRAS curve. In terms of the Solow model, the current LRAS is based on our current capital stock and productivity, while the potential LRAS is the steady state LRAS (To be really true to growth models, we&amp;#39;d say that the potential LRAS curve is slowly moving to the right due to trend growth). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Basic AS/AD&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y is the current level of GDP, determined by the intersection of the AD curve with the &lt;em&gt;short-run&lt;/em&gt; AS curve, SRAS. I&amp;#39;ve drawn the diagram such that we are in a situation where GDP is below current potential. I did this to be clear. Being below steady state in a growth model (Current LRAS &amp;lt; Potential LRAS) is a different thing than having &amp;quot;slack&amp;quot; in the economy (Y &amp;lt; Current LRAS). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this I can think through the differences in policies that attempt to accelerate growth, meaning that Y starts to &amp;quot;move to the right&amp;quot; quickly in my diagram. Start with AS policies. These push the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; LRAS curve to the right, but have little immediate effect on the current LRAS or the current SRAS. Over time, the current LRAS will converge to the potential LRAS, but as I&amp;#39;ve talked about before that takes a long time to occur. Note that the fact that the current and potential LRAS are far apart in my diagram to start with is irrelevant. The policies will shift the potential LRAS curve, and we&amp;#39;ll still have to wait for the current LRAS curve to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas2.png&quot; alt=&quot;LRAS Shift&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because AS policies don&amp;#39;t shift the current LRAS and SRAS curves by much, the increase in Y is small, and hence there is only a small effect on the growth rate. In the long run, these policies can have a massive effect on living standards, but it can take decades for that to manifest itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constrast that with AD policies. These shift the AD curve directly, and close to immediately. I&amp;#39;m perfectly willing to concede that there is some kind of lag in when the AD curve shifts out, but that&amp;#39;s measured in quarters, not decades. Because this AD shift happens immediately, and because the SRAS curve slopes upwards, there is a big effect on GDP from Y to Y&amp;#39;. Note that this depends crucially on the assumption that the SRAS curve is upward sloping. Without that, the AD shift would have no effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas1.png&quot; alt=&quot;AD Shift&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the AD policy has no effect on either potential or current LRAS. And while I&amp;#39;ve drawn the SRAS curve as a line, it probably becomes vertical at some point when GDP is high enough, so you cannot just use AD policies to push up GDP arbitrarily. But if you want to boost growth &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, then the AD policies are more effective. A last point is that the size of the effect depends on how far away Y is from the current LRAS curve. Part of the Romer&amp;#39;s critique of Friedman is that he overstates that gap, which thus overstats the power of AD policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large part of the argument about whether you can influence growth in the short run depends on whether we are talking about AD or AS policies. Kocherlakota, for example, explicitly talks about AD policies - monetary policy - as part of his argument for being able to boost growth to 5%. Sanders&amp;#39; plan is a mix of AS and AD, but I think Friedman got caught up treating all of them as AD plans, which overstated their possible effects in the short run. When I dismissed the ability of various reform plans to boost growth in the short run, it was because they are AS reforms. They will have effects over the long-run, but not in the short run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are probably few policies that are purely AS or AD policies. Monetary policy is probably - unless you don&amp;#39;t buy the classical dichotomy - a purely AD policy. Fiscal policy, on the other hand, seems muddier. It depends on the nature of it. Direct transfers are AD policies (although they might have incentive effects that affect the AS side). Policies that change regulations or the tax code, though, are not really fiscal policy, so much as they are AS policies. Another example might help. Changing education policy to allow teachers to be hired/fired more easily - AS policy. Hiring 1,000 teachers to start teaching this fall - AD policy. A major education reform bill, then, might be both AS and AD at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the attractions of infrastructure spending, by the way. It provides both AS and AD effects. Spend money now to repair bridges, ports, and roads, and immediately boost GDP growth. But at the same time, you are investing in public capital that can incent private business to invest as well, and you are pushing out the potential LRAS curve, which ultimately is the only one that matters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What all this means is that you cannot just look at the projected growth rate of a plan to assess it. Friedman isn&amp;#39;t wrong because he projects 5% growth, but he&amp;#39;s probably wrong because he is assuming AS policies are going to have big current effects. Kocherlakota isn&amp;#39;t wrong because he projects 5% growth either, but his plan is more plausible because it is based in large part on AD policies. Jeb! wasn&amp;#39;t wrong because he proposed 4% growth, he was wrong because of how he proposed to get there. You can accelerate growth in the short run, but you have to use AD policies to do that. AS policies deliver higher living standards in the long run, but it takes them a long time to ramp up to that higher level.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Absolute Changes in Living Standards</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Absolute-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Absolute-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This may or may not be interesting, I&amp;#39;m not entirely sure myself. But I got a question from an undergrad in my economic growth course, and it was one of those questions that kind of catches you off guard because you hadn&amp;#39;t really thought about it. The question was - paraphrasing - &amp;quot;Why do we look at growth rates rather than how much GDP per capita actually changed?&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Duh, it&amp;#39;s a course on growth&amp;quot; is what I did &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; say. But it did take me a moment to shake that feeling. In his defense, the answer isn&amp;#39;t obvious. Why do we focus on growth rates - percentage changes - as opposed to absolute changes in GDP per capita? Growth rates maks major differences in the absolute change in GDP per capita. For example, a growth rate of 2% implies an absolute change of 1000 in an economy with a GDP per capita of 50,000, and only a change of 200 in an economy with GDP per capita of 10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what does the distribution of aboslute changes in GDP per capita even look like? I had no idea. So I calculated the absolute growth in real GDP per capita per year for each country in the PWT. Then I plotted the kernel densities of these absolute changes for several countries. You can see the results below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_abs_growth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Densities for Absolute Growth&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kernel densities are basically smoothed histograms, so the height of the density curve indicates how often absolute growth in GDP per capita of a given amount occurred. As you can see, for India (the black dashed line) absolute growth tended to be very small. On average, from 1950 to 2011, GDP per capita rose by 51 dollars per year in India. The median was 42 dollars. Despite these small absolute changes, the percentage growth rate in could actually be quite high because GDP per capita is very low to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare that to the United States, where the density is much flatter and covers much larger values (both positive and negative). For the US, average absolute growth in GDP per capita was 482 dollars, with a median of 617 dollars. Of course, those large changes in GDP per capita reflect very small percentage growth rates in the US, because GDP per capita is already so large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of growth rates, the US isn&amp;#39;t growing very quickly compared to India, at least over the last 25 years. But in absolute terms, the increase in living standards in the US is about 10 times higher than in India in a given year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we care about these absolute changes? The answer hinges on your view on how GDP per capita translates to welfare, the utility function. It is really common to assume &amp;quot;log utility&amp;quot;, or welfare is the log of GDP per capita (or consumption per capita, or something else proportional to GDP per capita). Log utility has the very particular property that the same &lt;em&gt;growth rate&lt;/em&gt; of GDP per capita yields the same &lt;em&gt;absolute&lt;/em&gt; change in welfare. If India and the US both have growth rates of 3%, then welfare in both countries rises by 3%, even though the absolute change in GDP per capita in the US is much larger. The figure above doesn&amp;#39;t have any information about welfare gains, in other words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is simply diminishing marginal utility. But log utility specifies that the diminishing happens in such a way that growth rates translate directly to absolute changes in welfare. Now what if utility is &amp;quot;more curved&amp;quot; than log? That is, what if marginal utility falls very quickly as GDP per capita goes up? Then even if two countries have the same growth rate, they do not have the same absolute change in welfare. In fact, the richer country would have a &lt;em&gt;smaller&lt;/em&gt; change in welfare than the poorer country. So 3% growth in India generates &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; welfare than 3% growth in the US, even though the absolute change in GDP per capita is much smaller in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we could go the other direction, and look at utility that is &amp;quot;less curved&amp;quot; than log, or where marginal utility diminishes very slowly. Now, if there are two countries with identical growth rates, the richer country has a higher gain in welfare. The limit case here is linear utility, where marginal utility doesn&amp;#39;t decline at all as you get richer. Then the absolute change in GDP per capita is all that matters, and the US has (on average) much larger gains in welfare every year than India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An argument for thinking of utility as &amp;quot;more curved&amp;quot; than log is subsistence constraints. That is, let&amp;#39;s say that you only get utility from GDP per capita over and above a minimum level; GDP per capita at that minimum level is what we call subsistence, and it doesn&amp;#39;t provide any welfare, it just keeps you alive. If you have subsistence constraints, then marginal utility is incredibly high close to this constraint, and marginal utility falls very quickly as you move away from it. So India experiences much bigger gains in welfare - despite their small absolute gains in GDP per capita - because those extra 51 dollars get you farther away from that subsistence constraint. The US gets relatively little utility from its 482 dollar change, because we&amp;#39;re already so far above that subsistence constraint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, habit formation would be a force pushing towards &amp;quot;less curved&amp;quot; utility. In short, imagine that the subsistence constraint itself is rising as we get richer. The &amp;quot;minimum level&amp;quot; of GDP per capita that people need to meet is higher in the US than in India. If you believe that, then it is quite possible that the higher absolute growth of GDP per capita in the US is delivering bigger gains in absolute welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, then, I think the answer to the students question is that we think there is diminishing marginal utility, and so growth rate rates make sense because they tell us something about absolute changes in welfare. But...who said utility of GDP per capita has to be as curved as log? What if there are significant habit effects? Maybe the gap in welfare between places like the US and India is actually &lt;em&gt;growing&lt;/em&gt; over time, even though India&amp;#39;s GDP per capita is catching up slowly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not a &amp;quot;Duh&amp;quot; question after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Inferences about Tropics, Germs, and Crops</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/oid-test/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/oid-test/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the long-running arguments in growth is &amp;quot;geography versus institutions&amp;quot;. A lot of ink and a tiny amount of computing power was thrown at this question. The early stages of this involved a lot of cross-country regressions that attempted to figure out empirically whether measures of institutions or geography had explanatory power for GDP per capita. (By the way, I&amp;#39;m talking here just about the economic growth literature&amp;#39;s take on this. The general question goes back centuries.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tweet by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GarettJones&quot;&gt;Garett Jones&lt;/a&gt; recently reminded me of one of the entries in this literature, Bill Easterly and Ross Levine&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/moneco/v50y2003i1p3-39.html&quot;&gt;Tropics, Germs, and Crops&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; paper. EL want to assess the role of geography in explaining cross-country incomes per capita. Their main questions are summed up nicely in the abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does economic development depend on geographic endowments like temperate instead of tropical location, the ecological conditions shaping diseases, or an environment good for grains or certain cash crops? Or do these endowments of tropics, germs, and crops affect economic development only through institutions or policies?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their conclusion is that geography has no effect, other than through its relationship to institutions. This conclusion, though, doesn&amp;#39;t follow from the empirical tests they run. Let&amp;#39;s run through the empirics on these questions, and see how to answer them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m going to do this with precisely the dataset that EL use. I don&amp;#39;t recall when or where I picked up the data, but I believe it was from Easterly&amp;#39;s old website, where he had a nice set of links to datasets. Regardless, it&amp;#39;s the right dataset because I can perfectly replicate their results. You can download my version &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/east_levine_2003.dta&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and play around with it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Is geography even related to GDP per capita?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we have to establish that geography has a relationship to income per capita in the first place. If it doesn&amp;#39;t, the answers are clear. EL&amp;#39;s three primary measures of geography: (log) settler mortality, latitude, and a dummy for being landlocked. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these are questionable as measures of &amp;quot;geography&amp;quot;, and they are certainly incomplete. But for the purposes of this exercise, we&amp;#39;ll stick with them. Settler mortality is from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v91y2001i5p1369-1401.html&quot;&gt;Acemoglu, et al&lt;/a&gt;, and is intended to capture the nature of the disease environment (of Europeans, at least). Latitude is supposed to capture whether the country is tropical or not, and landlocked is there to account roughly for access to shipping. The &amp;quot;Crops&amp;quot; of the title of the paper could be added by including a series of dummies for producing different crops, but including those doesn&amp;#39;t really change the point of this post, so I&amp;#39;m going to skip them for brevity&amp;#39;s sake. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regress log income per capita on the three geography measures. You get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;------------------------------------
                              .   
Dep var: GDP p.c.            b/se   
------------------------------------
Log Settler Mortality      -0.610***
                          (0.111)   
Landlocked                 -0.711   
                          (0.359)   
Absolute Latitutde          2.377*  
                          (1.027)   
Constant                    9.695***
                          (0.612)   
------------------------------------
R-squared                   0.509   
N                              72   
------------------------------------
* p&amp;lt;0.05, ** p&amp;lt;0.01, *** p&amp;lt;0.001
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick apology that the results aren&amp;#39;t formatted better. That aside, in case you aren&amp;#39;t familiar, the first number listed for each variable is the estimated effect (e.g. -0.610 for settler mortality), and the number in parentheses is the standard error of that estimate. The stars show you whether the estimated effect is statistically significant. So settler mortality is significant at less than 1/10th of 1 percent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we see a clear effect of two measures of geography: settler mortality and latitude. The R-squared for this regression is 50.9%, meaning half of the variation in GDP per capita is associated with variation in &amp;quot;geography&amp;quot;. At a minimum, it suggests that geography &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; explain varation in incomes. But of course we don&amp;#39;t know if this acts only through institutions, or is a direct of geography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Is there an indepdent effect of geography outside of institutions?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s our second question. This has a clear empirical set-up. Regress GDP per capita on geography &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a measure of institutions. Look at the estimated effect of geography. Is it significant, even with institutions in the regression? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is entirely straightforward. The whole point of regressions is to do this kind of thing: separate out the effect of one variable from another. I ran that regression, using the EL measure of institutions, which is pulled from &lt;a href=&quot;http://info.worldbank.org/governance/wgi/pdf/govind.pdf&quot;&gt;Kaufman, Kraay, and Zoido-Lobaton&lt;/a&gt;. This is an averaged index of 6 different measures of &amp;quot;institutions&amp;quot;. I&amp;#39;ve made my views on the silliness of these indices &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/the-skeptics-guide-to-institutions-part-1/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, so I won&amp;#39;t belabor the point here. We&amp;#39;ll just accept it as is for this post. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;------------------------------------
                            .   
Dep var: GDP p.c.            b/se   
------------------------------------
Log Settler Mortal~y       -0.302** 
                      (0.102)   
Landlocked                 -0.530   
                      (0.291)   
Absolute Latitutde          0.698   
                      (0.870)   
Institutions                1.163***
                      (0.189)   
Constant                    8.639***
                      (0.521)   
------------------------------------
R-squared                   0.682   
N                              72   
------------------------------------
* p&amp;lt;0.05, ** p&amp;lt;0.01, *** p&amp;lt;0.001
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see that institutions are indeed significant (three stars!!). But so is settler mortality (at 1%), and landlocked is actually significant at 10% (but no stars for you!). &amp;quot;Geography matters&amp;quot; here, even after you control for institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect size of geography is definitely smaller than before. Look at the coefficient on settler mortality, which dropped from -0.610 to -0.302. This is showing that some of the effect of mortality on GDP per capita in my first regression was actually just picking up the effect of institutions (and by implication, mortality and institutions are negatively related, as AJR would suggest). But what the regression also shows is that the remaining effect of mortality is still statistically significant. Yes, there is an independent effect of geography on GDP per capita, even controlling for geography&amp;#39;s correlation with institutions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether the estimate of &amp;quot;Institutions&amp;quot; here is in fact a causal estimate is a different question. We might be concerned that institutions are endogenous, either because GDP per capita improves institutions, or because we&amp;#39;ve left out some other control variable that institutions is picking up on (culture, etc..). And if the estimate of institutions is wrong, then the conclusion about the geography variables could be wrong too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So.....&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Does geography still matter even if institutions are instrumented?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this concern about institutions being endogenous, we&amp;#39;d like to find some pure exogenous variation in institutions to use in our empirical analysis. In other words, we&amp;#39;d like to find another variable that both (a) (imperfectly) predicts the level of institutions and (b) is unrelated to the problematic unobserved variation in GDP per capita. We want an instrument. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we had such an instrument (IV), the process here is clear. We&amp;#39;d regress institutions on that IV and get the fitted values, which would represent variation in institutions that is &lt;em&gt;by assumption&lt;/em&gt; unrelated to the problematic unobserved variation in GDP per capita. Regress GDP per capita on this fitted value of institutions, and &lt;em&gt;et voila&lt;/em&gt;, we&amp;#39;ve got a true estimate of the effect of institutions. We could run the regression with the geography variables included as well, and see if geography matters for GDP per capita once we control for &lt;em&gt;instrumented&lt;/em&gt; institutions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is we need an instrument, and this is where EL run into a problem. The instrument for institutions that they propose to use is exactly the measures of geography: settler mortality, landlocked, and latitude. Which means they &lt;strong&gt;assume&lt;/strong&gt; that these three measures have no relationship to GDP per capita outside of their influence on institutions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They answered their question by assuming the answer was no. There is no getting around the fact that condition (b) above is an assumption. There is literally &lt;strong&gt;nothing&lt;/strong&gt; you can do to test if it is true or not. To use settler mortality, landlocked, and latitude as IV&amp;#39;s, you are, without fail, assuming they have no independent effect on GDP per capita. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about this over-identification (OID) test that EL use? Isn&amp;#39;t that evidence that their assumption is correct, and in fact geography has no effect on GDP per capita outside of institutions? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s why. The OID test has the following null hypothesis: settler mortality, landlocked, and latitude are &lt;em&gt;jointly&lt;/em&gt; unrelated to unobserved variation in GDP per capita. If you find enough evidence to reject this null, then you have evidence that one or more of your instruments are related to the unobserved variation in GDP per capita. In other words, your assumption is wrong. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But EL do not reject the null. EL report that they fail to reject the null.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeat after me. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not evidence that geography does not matter. It&amp;#39;s not. It&amp;#39;s not even kinda-sorta evidence, and well, you know, it probably means that geography doesn&amp;#39;t matter. That&amp;#39;s not how statistics work. There is no evidence, so there is &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt; conclusion to draw. A failure to reject is an absence of information, so you cannot infer anything from it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;So geography totally matters, right?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe. We don&amp;#39;t know. We haven&amp;#39;t solved the problem we had in the 2nd regression I ran. Our estimated effect of institutions might be biased. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is true is that &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt; the true effect of institutions were larger (say a coefficient of 2.22 versus 1.16), then the estimated effects of geography would end up statistically insignificant. How do I know that? Because I can run a regression where I force the coefficient on institutions to be 2.22, and see what happens to the geography variables. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;------------------------------------
                                .   
Dep var: GDP p.c.            b/se   
------------------------------------
Institutions                2.220   
                              (.)   
Log Settler Mortal~y       -0.022   
                          (0.107)   
Landlocked                 -0.366   
                          (0.348)   
Absolute Latitutde         -0.828   
                          (0.994)   
Constant                    7.681***
                          (0.592)   
------------------------------------
R-squared                           
N                              72   
------------------------------------
* p&amp;lt;0.05, ** p&amp;lt;0.01, *** p&amp;lt;0.001
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see that all the geography variables are not statistically significant (no stars!). Why does this happen? Because institutions are now explaining so much, there really isn&amp;#39;t anything &amp;quot;left over&amp;quot; for geography to explain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.22 is the value that EL actually find for the effect of institutions. But how do they get that? By running an IV regression that assumes geography has not effect. It&amp;#39;s circular. If they assume that geography doesn&amp;#39;t matter, then they find a big effect of institutions. And then they use this big effect of institutions to conclude that geography doesn&amp;#39;t matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the hypothesis: &amp;quot;Geography does not matter outside of its influence on institutions.&amp;quot;&amp;quot; I can&amp;#39;t prove that hypothesis wrong, certainly not with this data. But using the OID test from the El regressions doesn&amp;#39;t prove that this statement is right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Isn&#39;t the Whole World Developed?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Clark-Cotton/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Clark-Cotton/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s the title of Greg Clark&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/cup/jechis/v47y1987i01p141-173_04.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; from 1987 on cotton production in the early 20th century. Clark uses that specific industry to study the sources of variation across countries in real wages. I revisited it recently because I want to use it in my graduate course, and because I think it lays out a clear case for what could be loosely called a &amp;quot;cultural&amp;quot; explanation for differences in development. In short, the paper is going to come to the conclusion that poor countries are poor because of some unknown cultural source that supports a norm of low efficiency of labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to the paper is that Clark can compare outcomes across different countries that are using essentially identical technology. The spinning machines and looms being used by cotton manufacturers in essentially all countries at this time were designed, built, and commonly installed by English engineers. If anything, because they were relatively young industries, other countries in the early 20th century had &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; machines than their English peers. So Clark is able to compare the performance of different countries in producing cotton using an identical technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, Clark works comes at the problem from a slightly different direction than the typical macro/growth paper would. Take a look at Clark&amp;#39;s Table 1, which contains most of the information we need to talk about the story here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/clark_tab1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clark Table 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s start with Clark&amp;#39;s method, and then below I&amp;#39;m going to compare that to the macro/growth approach. He asks two questions, one kind of obvious and one not so obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What rate of return on capital (&amp;quot;implied profit rate&amp;quot;) would an English cotton factory earn if it faced the same input prices in country X?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What price could a factory in country X charge for cotton cloth and still earn an 8% return on capital (&amp;quot;manufacturing cost&amp;quot;)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 1:&lt;/strong&gt; To answer the first, it is crucial to realize that Clark is assuming that the English factory is going to use the exact same proportions of workers, capital, and coal no matter the input cost. They are going to produce the exact same amount of output, sell it for the exact same price, and earn the exact same revenue. In other words, this technology is Leontief in this experiment. The only difference is going to be in how much they pay for inputs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other nit-picky point is that the column in Table 1 called &amp;quot;Plant and Machinery&amp;quot; is the cost of capital in the sense of paying for depreciation costs. It is not the amount of capital used (which is listed in Clark&amp;#39;s Table 2). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final row of Table 1 gives you the cost shares for an English firm, and we need this to back out the implied cost shares for other countries. For example, in England 61.8% of revenues get paid to labor. But in China, because wages are 0.54/5.0 = 0.108 of English wages, the share of revenues being paid to labor is only 0.108 x 0.618 = 0.067. Using a similar calculation, the share of revenues paid out for capital depreciation is 0.159 in China, and the share for coal is 0.044. In total, 0.067 + 0.159 + 0.044 = 0.270 of revenue is paid to inputs, meaning that 0.73 of revenue is paid to owners of capital. In comparison, only 0.224 of revenues are paid to owners of capital in England, mainly because wages are so high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Clark&amp;#39;s Table 2 (not shown), the actual capital used in China is 17.76, while in England it is 15.06. Since 0.224 of revenue in England is assumed to provide an 8% return on 15.06 units of capital, revenues must be 0.08x15.06/0.224 = 5.379. This number is meaningless, except that it allows us to calculate the return on capital in China, which is 0.73x5.379/17.76 = 0.221. Hence the 22.1% implied profit rate for China in Clark&amp;#39;s Table 1. Lather, rinse, and repeat for the other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did firms in China actually earn 22.1% on their capital? No! That&amp;#39;s the whole point of the paper. They didn&amp;#39;t. If they did, we&amp;#39;d expect to have seen a massive shift of cotton cloth production towards China, or Japan, or any of the many other places earning higher profits than England or the US. But we did not, so there must be something that kept the majority of cotton cloth production in England. In short, they must not have been able to produce as much given those same inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 2:&lt;/strong&gt; What I&amp;#39;ve called Clark&amp;#39;s second question is not something he says explicitly in the paper. But I find it a better way to understand what is going on in his &amp;quot;manufacturing cost&amp;quot; column. Very simply, set the English price of cotton to 1.0. What price would a given country have to charge to earn exactly 8% on their capital? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, for China to earn 8% on their capital, only 17.76x0.08/5.379 = 0.264 of their revenues would need to be paid to capital owners. Their inputs are taking up only 0.270 of revenues. So Chinese firms need to only generate 0.264+0.270 = 0.534 of the revenues of an English firm to create an 8% return on capital. In other words, they could cut revenues to 53% of an English firm (perhaps by lowering the price to 53% of English prices) and still match the 8% return. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Clark means by &amp;quot;manufacturing cost&amp;quot;. It&amp;#39;s the cost of producing an 8% return to capital, matching his assumed norm for English firms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, it is clear that Chinese, and most other countries, were relatively low cost and/or could have offered lower prices &lt;em&gt;if they in fact could produce as much as English firms&lt;/em&gt;. But they cannot, and the whole rest of Clark&amp;#39;s paper is exploring reasons for why they could not produce as much as English firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s start with two things that do not explain the differences across countries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology. Like I said above, the beauty of this paper is that Clark can establish quite clearly that the firms in all countries used essentially identical machines. For all intents and purposes, they were operating with identical technology and capital. So this doesn&amp;#39;t explain the difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capital utilization. Perhaps China or other countries worked fewer hours, and we&amp;#39;ve incorrectly assumed that they worked as many hours as English workers. But Clark shows in his Table 2 that most other countries worked for &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; hours than England. The mystery is in fact even deeper. With high hours in China, it should have made them even more profitable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we get to the heart of Clark&amp;#39;s explanation, worker efficiency. He shows, in his Table 3 copied below, that the amount of capital per worker was very different across countries. His original question assumed it was identical (Leontief). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/clark_tab3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clark Table 3&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that English (and US/Canada) used far more machines per worker than China or India or other countries. So the labor cost for China was in fact very different than England. Paying a Chinese laborer 0.54 didn&amp;#39;t get you the same amount of work as paying an English laborer 5.0. In England, to operate 2.04 machines, you hired one worker. In China, to operate 2.04 machines you had to hire 2.04/0.48 = 4.25 workers. And so the true labor cost in China was 4.25*0.54 = 2.3. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This changes the implied profit and cost calculations in the final two columns. Note that the vast majority of the countries now are &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; cost than England, and earn a much &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; implied profit rate. In the US, this is because labor is expensive. In China and others, it is because workers don&amp;#39;t operate as much capital as in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now Clark asks why machines per worker are so low in some places. Or if you like, why there are so many workers operating each machine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substitution of labor for capital? In this case, not only is production not Leontief, but there is a high degree of substitution allowed. Perhaps India/China used lots of labor in place of capital, and hence could achieve high output per unit of capital, even though output per unit of labor was low. Except, no. Clark shows evidence that they did not produce more per unit of capital. It really is a low efficiency of labor used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differences in cotton quality? No, it doesn&amp;#39;t appear that India/China used extra labor because they were using higher quality cotton that required more attention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worker experience? No, this doesn&amp;#39;t appear to make sense. Average years of experience were higher in England, but not by much, and not universally compared to the other countries. Moreover, Clark provides some evidence that the returns to experience within mills was relatively low, as evidenced by some places relying almost exclusively on young women who only worked for a few years before they got married. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worker quality? No, interestingly enough. Clark&amp;#39;s evidence here is that immigrants to the US from these other countries earned just as much as their peers. French immigrants (who in France were only 54% as efficient as English workers) earned essentially an identical wage to English immigrants in the US. Simliar for Mexican, Russian, Italian, and Japanese workers. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last point is telling. The workers in other countries are entirely capable of working at the efficiency of an English or US worker, but for some reason they do not. (You might worry about selection of immigrants; Clark argues that the selection effect would have to be ridiculously large to account for this data.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are left with what Clark calls &amp;quot;local effects&amp;quot;. Workers in China or India, for example, are just as inherently skilled as anywhere else, but the norm in China or India is that they do not work as efficiently. Clark has a quote (from India) referring to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operatives in this mill refuse to attend to more machinery. I watched two ring frames for three minutes; there was not a single end down, yet the workpeople would not look after more than one side. They said they were satisfied with the present wage, and that there were too many men who want work and cannot get it that it would be unfair if they were to attend to more machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this &amp;quot;culture&amp;quot;, as Clark later alludes to? If you think this is something particularly &amp;quot;Indian&amp;quot;, then I guess so. But I&amp;#39;m not sure that the attitude expressed here necessarily varies by culture. It is entirely plausible that India, with a dearth of capital, saw workers expressing an attitude that any country with a dearth of capital would express. The explanation may still be a feature of low capital stocks, not something cultural. If there is something Leontief about cotton technology, then the limit on cotton employment is the stock of machinery, which is something that conforms with the quote. And we could certainly imagine that if English workers faced the same dearth of capital, they could take the same attitude towards work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there is something about the &amp;quot;local effects&amp;quot; to be explained. Why did the cotton industry persist so long in Britain, despite the drag of high wages. Surely at some point it had to make sense to try and relocate capital to low-cost countries? Could it be an institutional friction - risk of expropriation - that prevented people from taking advantage of the high implied returns in other countries? If it is cultural, then this culture doesn&amp;#39;t apparently travel with natives, otherwise the immigrants to the US wouldn&amp;#39;t have been as productive. This is different than what most modern research on culture would suggest; it tends to find that cultural traits travel with migrants. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big story of the Clark paper is that technology is not sufficient to explain massive differences in outcomes. And this sets it up as an alternative story to the one from &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/&quot;&gt;Comin, Easterly, and Gong&lt;/a&gt; that I recently posted about. For CEG, technology itself differs, and this difference persists. If you extrapolate Clark&amp;#39;s work, technology is similar, but the local effect of culture varies, and that is what presumably creates persistence in outcomes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Comparison to Growth/Macro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick aside about how a modern macro/growth paper would approach this. In short, you&amp;#39;d be doing a variance decomposition on the real wage in Clark&amp;#39;s data. More precisely, you&amp;#39;d be doing a variance decomposition of the log of real wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variance of log real wages in Clark&amp;#39;s data is 0.645, a number that means nothing by itself. The question is what fraction of the variance could be explained by variation in capital per worker or coal per worker. The remaining fraction is then attributed to the residual. To calculate this, you need the weighted variance of log capital per worker and log coal per worker. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;weighted&amp;quot; part of this is the importance of capital or coal in production. How do you find these weights? You look at the cost shares. And here is the crucial difference between what a macro/growth paper would do and what Clark did. Macro/growth is going to take the English cost shares and assume that these are the same for all countries. In other words, we&amp;#39;d assume Cobb-Douglas production functions, as opposed to Clark&amp;#39;s implicit Leontief. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Aside: We don&amp;#39;t know the actual amount of coal used, but to get around that we might assume that the coal/capital ratio is the same across countries. If we can&amp;#39;t, then I don&amp;#39;t know how to proceed, so bear with me. This simply means that the variance of log coal per worker is identical to the variance of log capital per worker.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the weighted variance of log capital and log coal per worker is either 0.0188 (if you use Clark&amp;#39;s index of capital) or 0.0381 (if you use Clark&amp;#39;s data on looms equivalents). Either way, this is only 2.92% or 5.90%, respecitively, of the total variance in real wages. A tiny fraction of variation in real wages is driven by differences in capital per worker, and the rest must be explained by technology, human capital, or something else. Clark has disposed of technology as an explanation, so it could be human capital. Clark eliminates big human capital differnces (at least in terms of age structure or experience), so it has to be &amp;quot;something else&amp;quot;. That something else is either local effects or culture, depending on your choice of terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this a better method? No. Clark&amp;#39;s initial assumption of Leontief technology may be more appropriate here. Or it may not. We don&amp;#39;t actually know. Both Clark and the macro/growth literature are making assumptions about production functions that partly drive their results. In either case, we get that differences in the stocks of capital per worker are not entirely sufficient to explain why some places are rich and some are poor.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Site Upgrades</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Site-Upgrades/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Site-Upgrades/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Cavs/Spurs game turning into a snorer, I distracted myself by fixing up a few things on the new site. Rocking Saturday night, I know. I&amp;#39;m old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SSL&lt;/strong&gt;: The site is now using SSL, which means you&amp;#39;ll see &amp;quot;https&amp;quot; in the web address. You don&amp;#39;t need to do anything, the site automatically redirects you to the https link. If you want to save yourself a millisecond, change your link to the site to say &amp;quot;https&amp;quot; explicitly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSS Equations&lt;/strong&gt;: One thing that came up in the transition was that the RSS feed was not rendering equations. You&amp;#39;d see markup code in your RSS reader, not a nicely formatted equation. This is fixed....I think. In fact, here&amp;#39;s a little test. If you can see &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y = x^2\inline&quot;/&gt; in your RSS feed as a nicely formatted equation, then apparently things are working well. If not, then I know what I&amp;#39;m doing next Saturday night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, thanks for reading, and thanks for the patience with the tweaks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Persistence of Technology</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the papers I use to introduce several ideas into my graduate growth and development course is by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aejmac/v2y2010i3p65-97.html&quot;&gt;Diego Comin, Bill Easterly, and Erick Gong&lt;/a&gt;, titled &amp;quot;Was the Wealth of Nations Determined in 1000BC?&amp;quot;. If we were being strict about things, the answer is no. But the longer answer is &amp;quot;Well, not really 1000BC. But there is a surprising amount of explanatory power in technology measures from 1500AD&amp;quot;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What CEG document is that technology levels are incredibly persistent, and that technology levels reaching back centuries retain some predictive power for explaining variation in income per capita in 2002. I&amp;#39;ll hit back below on this idea of predictive power, and how that differs from &amp;quot;causal explanation&amp;quot;. For the moment, focus on that word &amp;quot;persistent&amp;quot; and think about what it means. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to think about two kinds of persistence. What I&amp;#39;ll call &amp;quot;time-series persistence&amp;quot; is the idea that for a given country or economy, their technology level in the past is highly predictive of their technology level today. This is different than &amp;quot;cross-sectional persistence&amp;quot;, which is the idea that gaps between countries persist over time. You could have time-series persistence without cross-sectional persistence (e.g. slow convergence to a common technology level) or cross-sectional without time-series (e.g. fixed level differences in technology). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CEG are going to, in the end, provide some evidence of both kinds of persistence. Let&amp;#39;s start with the cross-sectional persistence, which is the main theme of their paper. Here let&amp;#39;s stop to describe exactly how they measure &amp;quot;technology&amp;quot;. CEG use several sources, including the Murdock Ethnographic Atlas, to pull out binary measures of technological use for different ethnic/cultural groups. Did your group use wheeled wagons in 1500? Yes? You get a 1. Did you use paper? No? You get a zero. Did you produce steel? No? You get a zero. Average these 0/1 measures across the different measures of technology, and you get an overall score that lies between 0/1 based on how many of these technologies you had. There is no intensive measure here (i.e. how widespread the use of the technology was within your group), only a coding for whether you used it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/ceg_figure1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 2&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Figure 2 gives you essentially the whole thrust of the paper. They use the ethnic group technology measures, assign each country a technology level based on the highest scoring ethnic group in their country, and then adjust the country level scores based on the fact that country populations are different in 2002 from in 1500 (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/bro/econwp/2008-15.html&quot;&gt;Putterman and Weil, 2002&lt;/a&gt;. Thus they have &amp;quot;migration-adjusted technology in 1500AD&amp;quot; on the x-axis, and log income per capita in 2002 on the y-axis. There is a strong positive relationship. The higher the technology in 1500AD, the higher the expected level of income per capita in 2002. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few open questions I have is whether this is robust to (a) using the minimum, average, or median ethnic group technology level for a country, rather than the maximum, (b) using all the ethnic group technology data, and run that through the Putterman/Weil matrix to find a country&amp;#39;s technology level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their empirical results are in the following table. When they regress 2002 current income per capita on technology levels in past years, they find significant effects. This holds for technology in 1000BC, 0AD, and 1500AD. Note that the coefficients rise as the time span becomes shorter. This isn&amp;#39;t surprising, as technology levels are imperfectly persistent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/ceg_table8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table 8A&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of the effect is surprising. Take the 1500AD result in column (3). The coefficient is 3.261, which means that if the technology index goes from 0 (no technologies) to 1 (all the original technologies), log income per capita goes up by 3.261 log points, or by a factor of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?exp(3.261) = 26\inline&quot;/&gt; times. Technology doesn&amp;#39;t vary between 0 and 1 in their index, but this gives you a sense of how strong the effect is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also notice the R-squared, which is 50% for the 1500AD results. That&amp;#39;s a big number. Half the variation in income per capita in 2002 is associated with variation in technology in 1500AD. It is worth stopping here to say something about what CEG are saying empirically. This is not a &amp;quot;policy experiment&amp;quot; paper, and I don&amp;#39;t think it is appropriate to evaluate it as such. This is a paper about forecasting, basically. What their result says is that if you tell me the level of technology in 1500AD, I can predict with a good amount of accuracy your income per capita in 2002. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s different than saying that if one could increase technology in 1500AD by &amp;quot;1 unit&amp;quot;, you could raise income per capita today by a factor of 26. First, as is obvious, there is no way to actually do that. Second, this isn&amp;#39;t the interesting research question here. CEG are trying to establish that old technology levels have predictive power for current income per capita. They are not looking for explanatory power, or forecasting power, and not a strict causal effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Should&lt;/em&gt; they be looking for a strict causal impact? That&amp;#39;s a fair question, but one without an obvious answer. Ultimately, you might want to argue that we want strict causal explanations for why some countries are rich in 2002. But an explanatory paper like this is valuable to that search. Knowing that &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; in 1500AD has strong predictive power for incomes today is informative. It tells us that we have to look back to 1500AD for at least some of those causal forces. Even if it turns out that technology in 1500AD is just a proxy for institutions, or geography, or culture, or whatever, this is a time period we should be looking at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that CEG have evidence of cross-sectional persistence. Gaps in technology in 1500AD appear to persist for centuries. This doesn&amp;#39;t mean the gaps are perfectly persistent (i.e. will last forever), just that they take a loooooong time to dissipate. Is this surprising? Perhaps not, if you think that there is a lot of &lt;em&gt;time-series&lt;/em&gt; persistence in technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And CEG provide some evidence of that time-series persistence. Not just in their baseline results from the table I showed, but in a secondary analysis that uses the fact that they have multiple categories of technology. With multiple categories, they have multiple observations on each country in each year. Which means they can look at technology-level regressions while pulling out country-time effects (i.e. England in 1500 and England in 2000 just happened to both be lucky) and technology-country effects (i.e. England is just really good at transport technologies). Here, I need to be clear that their measure of technology in 2000 is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same as their measure in 1500AD. The measure in 2000 comes from other work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/hbs/wpaper/10-035.html&quot;&gt;Comin and Bart Hobijn&lt;/a&gt; that is richer in measuring how many modern technologies a country has adopted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, they show that if a country-technology level is high in 1500AD, then it also tends to be high in 2000. Given the fixed effects included, that is saying that if a technology in England in 1500 was slightly about the average tech level in England in 1500, then it also tends to be above average in 2000. This is a little stronger evidence of time-series persistence, because they are not actually comparing one country to another any more, but one country to itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All well and good. But like I said above, time-series persistence doesn&amp;#39;t imply cross-sectional persistence. Why do we see so much cross-sectional persistence. CEG provide a list of theories of time-series persistence, but I don&amp;#39;t know that this is really adapted to the job of explaining the cross-sectional persistence. Many of the theories they document posit no limits on the flow of ideas (spillovers, complementarities, recombinations, etc..) between sectors, people, or technologies. And this makes sense in explaining time-series persistence. But if the ideas can flow, then why not over borders?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For cross-sectional persistence, you need something that actually limits the flow of ideas to different populations/countries. For cross-sectional persistence, it seems unlikely that it really is an inability to invent or copy new technologies; they are out there, easy to see. You need some friction that lies outside of a narrow view of technology. And I think that this pushes you towards theories that are based on culture and institutions (both loosely defined). It seems there must be non-technological factors that prevent adoption of technologies, perhaps because of norms (&amp;quot;we refuse to use things invented by infidels&amp;quot;) or entrenched interests (&amp;quot;we refuse to use things that threaten our monopoly power&amp;quot;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that sense, it isn&amp;#39;t the technology in 1500AD &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt; that matters in the CEG regressions, this is an indicator of some kind of variation in culture or institutions (or something else?) that matters. To return to the earlier discussion, it seems likely that their results won&amp;#39;t ultimately turn out to be causal, but the predictive power is telling us to something about how powerful those cultural/institutional factors are.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to GrowthEcon</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Welcome/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is both a welcome message to my new site - &lt;a href=&quot;http://growthecon.com&quot;&gt;growthecon.com&lt;/a&gt; - as well as a test that everything is working out alright. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth Economics Blog is now located here, but the old &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Wordpress site&lt;/a&gt; will linger on for a while. I know people have links set up to old posts that they may use in classes. I&amp;#39;ll provide some warning of when those links will die. And they may never die, because I will probably forget to ever close down the old Wordpress site. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, if you are still along for the ride, I appreciate it. In terms of following the new site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email&lt;/strong&gt;. I&amp;#39;ve set up a new mailing service for all the existing subscribers. You should have to do nothing. If you would like to subscribe via email, there is a link at the bottom of the home page to do that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSS&lt;/strong&gt;. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://growthecon.com/feed.xml&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the new feed, or copy and paste the link into your favorite reader.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt;. New posts will continue to get pushed to Twitter, so follow me at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DietzVollrath&quot;&gt;@DietzVollrath&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments are enabled here, and the old comments have all been imported. You may have to create a new login for the new commenting service. I apologize for that, but I didn&amp;#39;t have any way around it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Declining Marginal Product of Capital</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/the-declining-marginal-product-of-capital/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/the-declining-marginal-product-of-capital/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.wordpress.com/2015/11/24/describing-the-decline-of-capital-per-worker/&quot;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about the recent decline in capital per worker in the U.S. The short summary is that from 2009-2013 capital per worker has been &lt;i&gt;shrinking&lt;/i&gt;, and this is at odds with most of historical experience. This shrinking capital per worker contributes to higher measured productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The illustrious &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bus.lsu.edu/achanda/&quot;&gt;Areendam Chanda&lt;/a&gt; asked, in response, what the marginal product of capital looked like given the decline in capital per worker in this series. This is straightforward to calculate given the BLS data, and it shows what I think is an interesting pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I calculate the MPK as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MPK = \alpha \frac{Y}{K}&quot; alt=&quot;MPK = \alpha \frac{Y}{K}&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\alpha}\inline&quot;/&gt; is capital&#39;s share of output. If the world is roughly Cobb-Douglas, this should describe for us the extra amount of output we could get from one additional unit of capital. This is an aggregate concept, and doesn&#39;t necessarily map to any specific use of capital (e.g. the marginal product of a laptop can be different than the marginal product of a shovel). This is the marginal product of dumping an extra unit of homogenous ``capital&#39;&#39; into the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the figure showing the time path from 1960 to 2013:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_MPK_1960.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marginal Product of Capital&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of the recent decline in capital per worker, the uptick in the actual series (black line) from 2000-2013 makes some sense. Declining capital per worker should be associated with a higher return on capital. But what appears to be true is that the recent uptick in MPK is driven by a change in capital&#39;s share in output. I plotted in gray an alternative MPK that assumes capital&#39;s share is constant at 0.31 (a rough long-run average), and as you can see this continues the downward trend of the prior decades. The uptick is due almost entirely to the increase in capital&#39;s share of output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What seems far more interesting in this figure is the general drift downward in the MPK since 1960. I can come up with two different interpretations of this, which depend a lot on the time frame you consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Secular shift in MPK:&lt;/b&gt; Essentially, interpret this as evidence of some kind of sustained, secular change in the US economy. The drift down in the MPK isn&#39;t consistent with the US being on a balanced growth path (BGP). As a quick reminder, traditionally a BGP is a situation where GDP per worker is growing at a roughly constant rate, the return on capital (MPK) is constant over time, and the share of output going to capital is constant over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we almost always presume that the US is on a BGP. I will be telling my undergrads this in a week or so, I&#39;m sure. Almost every growth model is written so that it delivers a BGP eventually, because people feel that this represents what we see in the data. And when they say ``BGP&#39;&#39; in their model, they almost always mean that the MPK is constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a standard Solow model, the steady state is a BGP, and the model tells us what determines the MPK on that BGP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MPK = \alpha\frac{n + g + \delta}{s}&quot; alt=&quot;MPK = \alpha\frac{n + g + \delta}{s}&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\alpha}\inline&quot;/&gt; is capital&#39;s share of output, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{n}\inline&quot;/&gt; is population growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt; is productivity growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\delta}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the depreciation rate, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the savings rate. Note, this equation is for the MPK in steady state, not necessarily at any given point in time, but it is useful for thinking about what might drive the decline in MPK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steady decline in the MPK over time is consistent with declining &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{n}\inline&quot;/&gt; (because capital&#39;s marginal product is lower when there are fewer people around), declining &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt; (slower productivity growth), and higher &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; (more savings). In this story we are transitioning from the immediate post-war era of relatively rapid population and technological change, to a new era of relatively low population and technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth remembering here that the MPK is calculated using the BLS data, which excludes the government sector and the residential housing stock. So this represents a decline in the non-residential-housing MPK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Return of MPK to Long-run trend:&lt;/b&gt; But from a long, long-term perspective, maybe the decline in MPK since 1960 is just a reversion to a steady state value? The MPK should be roughly a proxy for the return on capital. One other rough proxy for that is the earnings yield on the S&amp;amp;P 500, which represents how much you get in earnings for buying a ``unit&#39;&#39; of capital by purchasing a basket of stocks. The figure below, which I grabbed from Brad DeLong&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bradford-delong.com/2015/02/i-understand-where-martin-feldstein-starts-i-do-not-understand-where-he-ends-up-focus.html&quot;&gt;site&lt;/a&gt;, plots this earnings yield from 1880 until today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_yield.png&quot; alt=&quot;SP Earnings Yield&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this it seems to me that the earnings yield has a ``normal&#39;&#39; level of about 6%, and that while there are sustained deviations from this value, it always appears to head back to 6%. The first figure shows that MPK has been declining from 1960 until now, matching the decline in the earnings yield from rouhgly 1970 until today. Was the MPK just on walkabout, and is coming back to its long-run BGP level? And no, I&#39;m not terribly worried about the fact that the MPK is always higher than the earnings yield. They are both proxies, so the fact they don&#39;t agree on levels isn&#39;t terribly meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earnings yields suggests that what is abnormal about the figure for MPK is the high values in the 60&#39;s and 70&#39;s, not the low values now. The S&amp;amp;P evidence is consistent with that, although the match-up is imperfect. Why was the MPK so high in the 1960&#39;s, while the earnings yield didn&#39;t rise until the 1970&#39;s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, in this interpretation, the steady state MPK has stayed roughly the same, but for some reason we deviated in the 60&#39;s and 70&#39;s to having a high MPK. Perhaps it was atypical shocks to productivity (over and above the regular trend growth rate &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt;), or atypical shocks to population growth (Baby Boomers?), and we&#39;re now coming back down to normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The caveat here is that the S&amp;amp;P earnings yield might be a badcomparison for the MPK. But given that the MPK is ex-residential-housing-capital and ex-government, perhaps not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know that there is a way to distinguish between the two stories, not without doing more research that I don&#39;t have time to do right now. Without taking a firm stand on this, one important point here is that the explanation depends crucially on what you take to be ``normal&#39;&#39;. And that depends in part on how far back you graph the data. The S&amp;amp;P data suggests a different story than the MPK series (and the MPK series doesn&#39;t go back any further because the BLS doesn&#39;t have the requisite data any further back). I guess it is a caution that the starting point of your data series is not necessarily the same thing as the ``starting point&#39;&#39; of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 21:17:16 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Do You Need More Money for Economic Growth to Occur?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/do-you-need-more-money-for-economic-growth-to-occur/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/do-you-need-more-money-for-economic-growth-to-occur/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR version: No.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another entry to file under &quot;notes for undergrads&quot; and/or &quot;explaining things to your neighbor&quot;. A very common question I get about growth is: how does growth occur if there is not any &quot;more money&quot; in the economy. Another common question I get is: how is it economic growth if spending on one product just replaces spending on another?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions come, I think, from continued confusion about (a) nominal versus real GDP, (b) nominal GDP versus the stock of money, and (c) absolute versus relative prices. In short, things an economist might call money illusion. In the defense of students and my neighbors, it isn&#39;t terribly easy to think in relative prices and real terms when every single transaction you undertake involves absolute dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s start with an economy that produces exactly 10 cans of Budweiser, and nothing else, in a year. They each sell for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1, meaning that nominal GDP in this economy is \\inline&quot;/&gt;10 for the year. What is real GDP? Well, we already really know the answer - it&#39;s 10 cans of Budweiser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real GDP is measured in &quot;real units&quot;. That&#39;s obvious in this example, because the real units are obvious - cans of Bud. To do this more formally, we find real GDP by dividing nominal GDP by a price index. In this case, the price index is easy to figure out. It&#39;s \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 per can of Bud. So real GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;10/\$1 per can of Bud = 10 cans of Bud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One confusion with real GDP is that the BEA and economic textbooks insist on talking about it in terms of dollars. That is because the price index they use is not something like &quot;\&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 per can&quot;, but is something like &quot;\\inline&quot;/&gt;1.37 per \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 of output in 2005&quot;. So real GDP is\inline&quot;/&gt;10/&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1.37 per 2005 dollar = 7.3 units of 2005 dollars, which would be reported as &quot;\\inline&quot;/&gt;7.3 (2005 dollars).&quot; But despite being reported in terms of dollars, real GDP has nothing to do with money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sometimes think that we should save our effort at coming up with good price indices, and just use something like the price of a can of Bud, or a pair of Levi 501 jeans, as the price deflator in national accounts. Because then real GDP would be reported in real, tangible units, and would save us from confusing it with a nominal number. For example, if the price of a can of Bud was \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.50, then real GDP in the US for 2014 would be \\inline&quot;/&gt;17,615 billion/ &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.50 per can on Bud = 35,230 cans of Bud. Nominal GDP through Q3 2015 is \\inline&quot;/&gt;18,060, so that&#39;s real GDP of 36,120 cans of Bud, a 2.5% increase in real GDP from 2014. I&#39;m laboring this point because when it comes to explaining how growth works, this confusion between nominal and real concepts becomes a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s go back to our simple 10-can economy, with a price per can of \$1, and see how growth works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Growth through expanding production of existing products:&lt;/b&gt; This is the easiest to explain. Something happens at Anheuser-Busch that lets them produce even more cans of Bud with their given inputs. Perhaps they water it down even more than it already is. Whatever the reason, the economy produces 12 cans of Bud this year. We &lt;i&gt;know&lt;/i&gt; that real GDP went up, from 10 cans to 12 cans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&#39;s walk through how to do this calculation using nominal GDP and a price index. Think of two possibilities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nominal GDP stays constant.&lt;/b&gt; That is, nominal GDP is still \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10. Then it &lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt; be that the price of a Bud fell to \\inline&quot;/&gt;0.83. The supply curve of Bud shifted out, and hence the quantity of Bud went up and the price of Bud went down. Real GDP is \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10/\\inline&quot;/&gt;0.83 per can = 12 cans of Bud. For the given flow of money through the economy - &lt;i&gt;which does not have any necessary relationship to real GDP&lt;/i&gt; - the price of a can of Bud must adjust to make supply equal demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The price of Bud stays constant.&lt;/b&gt; Let each can still be \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1. The it &lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt; be that nominal GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;12, and real GDP is \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?12/\\inline&quot;/&gt;1 per can = 12 cans of Bud. Here, the supply curve of Bud has shifted out, but apparently the demand curve shifted out as well, leaving the price unchanged and the quantity higher. Why would this happen? Who knows, and who cares. It&#39;s possible. For a given flow of money through the economy, the price of a can of Bud must adjust to make supply equal to demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it is irrelevant whether nominal GDP goes up or stays constant (it could even fall). Whether nominal GDP rises or not is &lt;i&gt;completely irrelevant&lt;/i&gt; to whether real GDP goes up. If we could observe the real quantity of cans consumed, we wouldn&#39;t need nominal GDP at all. But we don&#39;t actually observe the number of cans of Bud consumed. All we observe is nominal GDP and the price of a can of Bud. So when the BEA reports a nominal GDP of \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10, and a price of \\inline&quot;/&gt;0.83 per can, we divide and infer that real GDP is 12 cans of Bud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your question now is where people get the &quot;extra money&quot; to afford 12 cans of Bud when their price stays at \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1, take a moment to meditate on the equation\inline&quot;/&gt;MV = PY$. We&#39;ll come back to that in a few paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Growth through addition of new products:&lt;/b&gt; This one will stretch the mind a little more, but the same principles are going to hold. Rather than Bud watering down their beer even further, we&#39;re going to introduce a new beer into the market. Someone - and God bless them - invents &lt;a href=&quot;https://realalebrewing.com/beers/coffee-porter/?age-verified=a3ffaebbbf&quot;&gt;Real Ale Coffee Porter&lt;/a&gt;. In response, people with functioning taste buds buy 5 cans of Coffee Porter, and everyone else still buys 5 cans of Bud. So we&#39;ve still only got 10 cans of beer being sold. Is this economic growth, meaning that real GDP is higher?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It depends on relative prices. If those cans of Coffee Porter are more expensive than cans of Bud, then this represents real economic growth. Why? Because if the relative price of Coffee Porter is higher than that of Bud, then the relative marginal utility of Coffee Porter is higher than that of Bud. Assuming that utility for both has typical properties (declining MU), then we know the MU of the 5th can of Bud is higher than the 10th can. And since Coffee Porter has a higher MU than that, it follows that we are better off in utility terms. More intuitively, if we &lt;i&gt;weren&#39;t&lt;/i&gt; better off, then why were we willing to substitute away from Bud even though Coffee Porter costs more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which suggests that if Coffee Porter and Bud sold for the same amount, then we aren&#39;t any better off. In this case it&#39;s a perfect substitute, and the choice of 5 of each is just random. It&#39;s the difference in relative prices that a new product introduces that defines it&#39;s contribution of real growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So eocnomic growth is just about things getting more expensive? No. Note that I didn&#39;t say anything about the absolute price of Bud or Coffee Porter - because that is irrelevant for real GDP. So long as Coffee Porter is more expensive &lt;i&gt;than Bud&lt;/i&gt;, we&#39;ve experienced real growth. That holds if Porter costs \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?2 to Bud&#39;s \\inline&quot;/&gt;1, or \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?20 to Bud&#39;s \\inline&quot;/&gt;10, or \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.02 to Bud&#39;s \\inline&quot;/&gt;0.01.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we&#39;ve established that there is a relative price difference, then the same questions about nominal GDP from before come up. Let&#39;s say that we observe that Coffee Porter costs twice as much as Bud. How do we calculate real GDP?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nominal GDP stays constant.&lt;/b&gt; It must be that Bud costs \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.67, and the porter is \\inline&quot;/&gt;1.33, so nominal GDP is \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10 (multiply it out and you can see it). What is real GDP in this case? Sticking with our standard of using the price of Bud, real GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;10/\$0.67 per can of Bud = 15 cans of Bud. It is &lt;i&gt;as if&lt;/i&gt; our economy produced 15 cans of Bud, where before it only produced 10. There is real GDP growth due to the introduction of Coffee Porter - even though all Coffee Porter does is replace consumption of Bud and total beer drinking stays constant at 10 cans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The price of Bud stays constant.&lt;/b&gt; If Bud still costs \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1, then the porter is \\inline&quot;/&gt;2. So nominal GDP is \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?15 (again, just multiply it out). What is real GDP? \\inline&quot;/&gt;15/\$1 per can of Bud = 15 cans of Bud. Real GDP has gone up. It is irrelevant what the nominal price of Bud is, we observe real GDP growth because the introduction of Coffee Porter introduced a relative price difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that if all the BEA reports to me is nominal GDP and the price of Bud, I can infer real GDP regardless of what exactly happens. Our &quot;Bud-based&quot; measure of real GDP goes up to 15. I don&#39;t actually have to observe the number of cans purchased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example of adding a new product brings up one issue with price indices, which is product replacement. If - as would be logical if people tasted them - the introduction of Coffee Porter completely eliminated Bud from the market, then we cannot calculate real GDP. There will be no price of Bud to divide nominal GDP by. And we can&#39;t just use the price of Coffee Porter, because yesterday all we had was Bud, and there was no price for Coffee Porter. One of the reasons we use more sophisticated price indices (that combine the price of Bud and Coffee Porter in some way) is so that we always have a price index to use. But that sophisticated price index, by putting things in &quot;2005 dollars&quot; or something like that, creates confusion between real GDP and nominal GDP. Always think of real GDP as being &quot;cans of Bud&quot;, rather than in dollar terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, If you are still wondering where people get the &quot;extra money&quot; to buy the Coffee Porter in this example, then the next section is for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Where does the extra money come from?&lt;/b&gt; Nowhere. There is no extra money. Nominal GDP is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; a measure of &quot;how much money we have&quot;. Nominal GDP is the flow of dollars through the economy. The stock of money is, well, a stock. In all the examples above, what is the stock of money? You can&#39;t answer that question, because I never said anything about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s say that this economy has a stock of 4 one-dollar bills. Here&#39;s the transactions flow in this economy in the initial stage, with only 10 can of Bud consumed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person A starts with the \$4. (Nominal GDP is zero)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person A buys 4 Buds for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person B. (Nominal GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person B buys 4 Buds for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person C. (Nominal GDP is now \\inline&quot;/&gt;8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person C buys 2 Buds for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?2 from person D. (Nominal GDP is now \\inline&quot;/&gt;10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person D ends up with \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?2 and person C with\inline&quot;/&gt;2. (Final nominal GDP is \$10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then next period we start again, only now C and D hold the money stock. The money stock is always \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4, and it gets turned over and over, resulting in \\inline&quot;/&gt;10 of nominal transactions, or GDP. (No, it doesn&#39;t matter that the circle isn&#39;t closed here, with different people ending up with the actual dollars.) Real GDP is 10 cans of Bud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we have the case where Coffee Porter gets introduced, things look like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person A starts with the \$4. (Nominal GDP is zero)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person A buys 2 Porters for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person B. (Nominal GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person B buys 4 Buds for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person C. (Nominal GDP is now \\inline&quot;/&gt;8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person C buys 2 Porters for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person D. (Nominal GDP is now \\inline&quot;/&gt;12)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person D buys 1 Bud for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 and 1 porter for \\inline&quot;/&gt;2 from person E. (Nominal GDP is now \$15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person D ends up with \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 and person E with \\inline&quot;/&gt;3. (Final nominal GDP is \$15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No &quot;new money&quot; is necessary. Real GDP is 15 cans of Bud. The same \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 gets recycled over and over again, this time used to purchase both Buds and Porters. Different people end up with money stock at the end. We could easily write out an example where the growth occurred because of just an increase in the number of Buds. And if you prefer that nominal GDP not increase, you can easily go back and work out the same set of transactions, lower the absolute prices, and get nominal GDP to come out to exactly \\inline&quot;/&gt;10. And yes, I made up these examples. But I just need to show you that it is possible to get economic growth even though there is no new money in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic growth occurs either because we produce more of existing things, or because we introduce new things that that are more valuable than the old things we produced - which shows up in &lt;i&gt;relative&lt;/i&gt; price differences. The level of absolute prices is irrelevant. The level of nominal spending is irrelevant. The stock of money is irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any modern economy, it is effectively impossible for there to be &quot;not enough money&quot; to let growth occur. The economy as a whole can always turn over the money stock faster to allow for the extra transactions if necessary. Whether that turnover involves &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt;, and means that &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt; can afford to buy some Coffee Porter, is a different question, and involves your own productivity and/or ownership of a Bud- or Coffee Porter-producing machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 20:06:18 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
