<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Growth Economics Blog</title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description>Dietrich Vollrath Economic Growth Blog</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 17:15:25 -0500</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Update on the Profits from Housing</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Ricardian-Housing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Ricardian-Housing/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Profit-Accounting/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; I used some findings by &lt;a href=&quot;http://home.uchicago.edu/~barkai/&quot;&gt;Simcha Barkai&lt;/a&gt; and the BLS to infer that housing may a major source of the rise in the share of profits in GDP. I got an e-mail from Simcha regarding the post, and the upshot is that I’m wrong. First, and foremost, it turns out that I got confused reading his paper, and all his calculations &lt;em&gt;exclude&lt;/em&gt; residential housing. This means that my inference from comparing the BLS profit share to his profit share is invalid. You cannot conclude that residential housing profits are driving a rise in profits share of aggregate GDP, because there is no information on housing in Barkai’s number. He documents that the profit share of the non-financial corporate sector is rising over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my bad on that. Simcha also made a point in his e-mail about how the BLS calculates profit shares, and it makes me lean towards his calculations as being correct. But let’s leave that for another day and post. For the time being, you should go forth and freak out about the increasing profit share in the non-financial corporate sector, whatever your preferred explanation for that may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still had housing on the brain, though, so I wanted to figure whether I was wrong about profits rising in the housing sector. Effectively, I’d like to recreate Barkai’s analysis, but now for the housing sector only. To figure that out, I need to look at the data on the stock of residential housing capital (K), and the imputed flow of value-added from housing (Y). The other thing I need to calculate is the required rate of return on housing (R).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the stock and flow, which I pulled down from FRED. The stock, K, is the “Current-Cost Net Stock of Fixed Assets: Residential” from the national income accounts. That includes all privately owned residential assets, which encompasses both owner-occupied and tenant-occupied. The flow, Y, is “Gross housing value added”, which comes from Table 1.3.5 of the national accounts. This is the BEA’s estimate of the total flow of housing services (including imputed rents for owner-occupied housing) minus the cost of any intermediate goods. Those intermediates would include maintenance and repairs on your house, or the cost of property management services if you owned a rental building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_housing_ky.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing YK&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first figure is the ratio of Y/K, or roughly the average product of housing capital. On average, the flow of housing services is equal to around 8% of the stock of housing. But there are clear fluctuations, with a big dip after WWII, and then subsequent dips around 1980 and 2009. But there is also a tendency for the ratio Y/K to rise from WWII to today, from maybe 6% to 9%. This tendency of Y/K to &lt;em&gt;rise&lt;/em&gt; means that the ratio of K/Y is going to &lt;em&gt;fall&lt;/em&gt;, and that is going to matter in my little profit share calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want profit’s share of the flow of housing output. I’m going to assume that no labor is used in providing housing services. Don’t get freaked out by that, the flow of housing services is not the same thing as construction. Construction - which does use lots of labor - is the flow of &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; housing (or other structures) into the stock. What we’re talking about here is the flow of services provided by &lt;em&gt;existing&lt;/em&gt; housing, which does not involve much labor at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means I am assuming that the flow of housing can be split as follows, &lt;strong&gt;Y = RK + Profits&lt;/strong&gt;. In shares, this is just &lt;strong&gt;1 = RK/Y + Profits/Y&lt;/strong&gt;. If I know RK/Y, I can figure out the profit share easily. Note that RK/Y depends on K/Y, which was falling over time, based on the prior figure. So that, by itself, suggests the profit share was rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, it seems likely that R was falling over time. If you remember from the prior post, we could write &lt;strong&gt;R = i - g + d&lt;/strong&gt;, where R is the return on capital, i is the nominal interest rate, g is the expected inflation in the capital price, and d is depreciation. For i, the obvious choice here is the mortgage rate. I (or rather FRED) does not have mortgage rate data going back as far as 1930, but it does have it for the 1970’s forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_housing_mort.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing Mortgage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a big surprise that mortgage rates have fallen over time, much like any other nominal interest rate. They’re under 5% now, from a high of around 17% in 1981. By itself, this is going to drive R lower over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other information I need is on g and d. I’ve played around a lot with these, and I can’t come up with any reasonable assumptions about them that can overcome the drop in nominal mortgage rates over time. That is, if you really wanted to make R go &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; over time, you’d need people to believe that housing prices were going to &lt;em&gt;fall&lt;/em&gt; significantly (so g&amp;lt;0) or that depreciation rates on houses have risen significantly over time. I can’t get my head around how either of those could be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the figure I’ll show below, I’m assuming that g = 3% at all times (not true) and d = 1% at all times (not true). I’m not going to get hung up on the actual numbers, because what we’re interested in is the change in R over time, not the actual level. It’s also a blog post, not a paper. So take the data on the mortgage rate, and combine that with my assumption on g and d to get a measure of R over time. Use that R, and combine it with the data on K/Y, and you’ve got a time series for RK/Y. With that time series, you can solve for &lt;strong&gt;Profits/Y = 1 - RK/Y&lt;/strong&gt;, and I’ve got my profit share in housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_housing_profit.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing Mortgage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to get your eyes off the gigantic negative number in 1981. According to this calculation, the profit share on housing was negative 100%. To be more concrete, what this is saying is that the rent you could get on a house (Y) in 1981 was equal to about half of the cost of the mortgage (RK). You were implicitly losing money owning a home, but if it was owner-occupied, you were losing money to yourself. That dramatic negative profit share is a function of the spike in mortgage rates during the Volcker disinflation, and as I said, it is hard to see around it in the figure. But notice that the profit share started to climb around 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_housing_profit90.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing Mortgage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled the 1990-2016 period out to show the evolution of the profit share more clearly. Here the rise in the profit share is apparent, from about 20 to about 80% from 1990 to 2016. I don’t want to get too stuck on the precise level of these numbers, which depend in part on my assumption regarding 3% expected house price inflation and 1% depreciation. But the trend is clear. Because of the decline in the mortgage rate, the cost of owning a home fell, but the flow of output produced by houses did not. In essence, you can rent out your owner-occupied home for more than you’d pay in mortgage costs, and you are profiting. You may be paying those profits to yourself, but there is a profit involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s round this back to the discussion of profit shares in the wider economy. Barkai found that the profit share is rising in the private, non-housing, sector. My mini-analysis here suggests that the profit share in the housing sector is rising as well. Combined, that means the profit share in aggregate GDP is rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference from the last post is that the rise in housing profits is not mutually exclusive with the rise in profts in the private, non-housing, sector. The source of the rise in profits is similar in both cases, as it turns out. The drop in nominal interest rates means that the required return for capital (housing or non-housing) is falling over time, but the flow of output produced in part by that capital is not, so the profit share is rising.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is Housing Driving the Rise in Profits?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Profit-Accounting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Profit-Accounting/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Um, this has nothing to do with health care or repealing the ACA. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Markups/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; was on the profit share in GDP. I drew on some work by &lt;a href=&quot;http://home.uchicago.edu/~barkai/&quot;&gt;Barkai&lt;/a&gt;, who calculated that the profit share in GDP had been rising steadily over the last thirty years. To save you the bother of clicking any links, here is his figure showing the profit share over time, rising from about 2.5% of GDP in 1985 to over 15% in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/barkai3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Barkai figure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while back, I also did some &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/the-changing-composition-of-productivity-growth/&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; about how the BLS calculates multi-factor productivity. As part of that the BLS also provides a breakdown of GDP into payments to labor, capital, and profits. Here’s that figure, which runs back to 1950.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_output_share.png&quot; alt=&quot;BLS figure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of the two figures isn’t the same, but I don’t believe it is too hard to see that there is a significant difference in the profit share of output in the two analyses. There is, for all intents and purposes, no increase in the profit share using the BLS data, while Barkai finds that dramatic increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can explain the difference? To answer that, I have to dig into how both sources construct their estimates of the profit share. The method is similar between the two, but they differ in the data they use, so it turns out that the difference is all in the data, and that will have an interesting implication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;calculating-profits-share-of-output&quot;&gt;Calculating Profits Share of Output&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let me outline the method they use, and why. Both the BLS and Barkai want to decompose output into something like &lt;strong&gt;Output = Wages + Capital Payments + Profits&lt;/strong&gt;. This would be easy if national income accounts reported those three separate components, but they don’t. National accounts will tell you that &lt;strong&gt;Output = Wages + Proprietors Income + Rental Income + Corporate Profits + Net Interest + Taxes on production&lt;/strong&gt;. Accounting-wise, it must be that &lt;strong&gt;Capital Payments + Profits = Proprietors Income + Rental Income + Corporate Profits + Net Interest + Taxes on production&lt;/strong&gt;, but there is no way to know how big Capital Payments and Profits are from this. No, “Corporate Profits” are not equal to Profits. The former is &lt;em&gt;accounting&lt;/em&gt; profits, and the latter refers to &lt;em&gt;economic&lt;/em&gt; profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both the BLS and Barkai, the solution to getting economic profits is to combine data on the total capital stock, K, with an assumption about the return to capital, R. The Capital Payments are then defined as RK, and once you know the Capital Payments, you can back out the Profits. In other words, &lt;strong&gt;Profits = Output - Wages - RK&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Barkai, the value of K is taken directly from the BEA. That stock of capital, K, is broken down into a lot of categories and sub-categories are structures, equipment, and intellectual property. Structures include non-residential structures like warehouses, lodging (e.g. hotels), and amusement and recreation (e.g. Six Flags), among others. Structures also include residential structures like single family homes and apartment buildings. Intellectual property includes things like software, as well as (as of 2013), a capitalized value of R/D spending by different industries. Finally, equipment includes all the things that you normally think of as capital, like computer equipment, engines and turbines, metalworking equipment, ships, railroad, oil wells, and photocopiers (which get their own sub-category under “information processing equipment”, which I find humorous for some reason).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For R, he constructs an implicit rate of return, something like what you’d do if you tried to come up with the implicit rent an owner pays themselves if they own their home. He follows &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~rehall/Tax-Policy-AER-June-1967.pdf&quot;&gt;Hall and Jorgenson&lt;/a&gt; (1967), which assumes that investment decisions are not made randomly, but rather must reflect some economic logic, and so the rate of return R is described by &lt;strong&gt;R = i - g + d&lt;/strong&gt;. i is the nominal interest rate. g is the growth rate of the price of the capital good (capital gains), and d is depreciation. The intuition of the effect of these three terms is straightforward if you spin this around into &lt;strong&gt;i = R + g - d&lt;/strong&gt;. Think of a firm borrowing money to buy a capital good. They pay i as a nominal interest rate. That asset yields a return of R to them for using it, plus they get the capital gain (or loss) that goes along with the asset. The asset also depreciates at the rate d. In equilibrium, the cost of borrowing (i) should be equal to the benefit (R + g - d).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barkai makes some assumptions to solve for R. He uses the interest rate on triple-A rated corporate bonds to stand in for the nominal interest rate i. He uses the observed inflation in the price of capital goods, available from the BEA’s data, to get his value for g. And the BEA also provides a number for the depreciation rate of different types of capital goods, based on their expected years of service, which he can use to get d. He solves for R for each of the three main types of capital goods - structures, equipment, and intellectual property - allowing each to have different values for g and d. At that point he can calculate RK for each type of capital, and then add up those total payments to get aggregate payments to capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once he knows the capital payments, he can back out the Profits. And once he knows Profits, he simply calculates Profits/GDP to get profits share of output, which is what you see plotted in that first figure. There is nothing that immediately jumps out about Barkai’s method that would suggest it is wrong. Could you use a different series for the nominal interest rate? Sure. But if you jump onto the FRED database, and look at any series of nominal interest rates over time, they decline sharply from the early 1980’s until today. Is the required return to capital, R, not related to i + g - d? Maybe. But it would be weird if somehow the return paid to capital deviated a lot from that value. If the R value were in fact much &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; than what Barkai calculates, then this would lower the Capital Payments even further, and in turn make profits share rise by even more, and the deviation from the BLS data would be more pronounced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, to solve for the profit share you need to infer something about the payments to capital. What the BLS does is quite similar to Barkai. They use some different values for i, g, and d, but that isn’t what is really driving the difference in the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-drives-the-difference&quot;&gt;What drives the difference?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key distinction is in the overall scope of their analysis. For Barkai, &lt;strong&gt;Output = GDP&lt;/strong&gt;. For the BLS, &lt;strong&gt;Output = Private Business Output&lt;/strong&gt;. The distinction is, very roughly, &lt;strong&gt;GDP = Private Business Output + Government + Imputed GDP from Owner-Occupied Housing&lt;/strong&gt;. The concept of output is wider for Barkai than it is for the BLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This difference carries through to the capital stock that the BLS uses. For the BLS, the capital stock is a subset of the capital stock that Barkai uses. The BLS uses equipment, intellectual property, and tenant-occupied housing (e.g. apartment buildings). They exclude the stock of owner-occupied housing, which is included in Barkai’s calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically the reason Barkai gets a rising profit share is that he finds a fall in the share of GDP going to Capital Payments over time. For the BLS, the share of output going to capital, as you can see in the second figure, does not change much - and when it changes, it is offset by changes in the labor share, and so there is no big change in the profit share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does Barkai find a fall in the capital share compared to the BLS? It may be due to an increase in the imputed value of housing in GDP. This is going to be more clear if I drop in a real equation, so here we go&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{(RK)^{BLS}}{Y^{BLS}} &gt; \frac{(RK)^{BLS} + (RK)^{Houses}}{Y^{BLS} + Y^{Houses}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fraction on the right is the capital share in output calculated by the BLS, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y^{BLS}\inline&quot;/&gt; stands for private business output. This fraction is bigger than the fraction on the right, which is meant to capture what Barkai is calculating as the capital share. In the numerator, he has both the return on capital that the BLS would capture, but also the return on capital going to owner-occupied housing. In the denominator, Barkai has “GDP”, which is - very roughly - the sum of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y^{BLS}\inline&quot;/&gt; and the imputed flow of GDP from owner-occupied housing, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y^{Houses}\inline&quot;/&gt;. For this inequality to be true, we need that the payments to capital for houses are not “too big”, but the imputed flow of GDP from owner-occupied housing, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y^{Houses}\inline&quot;/&gt; are “very big”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing. If the imputed GDP from owner-occupied housing is very high, but the payments to capital required by housing are small, then by implication the &lt;em&gt;profits&lt;/em&gt; on owner-occupied housing are high. The rise in profits share seen in the Barkai paper could well be driven by the market power of house owners, and not by the market power of corporations, which is the intuitive response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;profits-on-housing&quot;&gt;Profits on housing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to jive with other information. The figure below is from Matt Rognlie’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattrognlie.com/brookings_capitalshare.pdf&quot;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt;. Rognlie is looking not at the separate shares of output going to profits and capital, but rather their sum. If you like, he is interested in the share of GDP &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to labor. What he did was to decompose this total non-labor share into a part accounted for by housing, and for a part accounted for by non-housing. As you can see in the figure, the share of GDP going to housing (either as a return to capital or as profits) was increasing from 1950 to today. It rose from about 3% of GDP to about 10% in this period of time, while the share of GDP going to non-housing capital (either as a return to capital or as profits) was declining slightly. Combined, these two trends lead to a rise in the share of GDP going to capital as a whole, and was one of the key elements of Piketty’s book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/rognlie.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rognlie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rognlie’s decomposition is consistent with the story about rising profits in owner-occupied housing. The total amount of GDP getting paid to owners of homes is rising over time (Rognlie). But at the same time, the required rate of return on capital is falling (Barkai and BLS), which means that the &lt;em&gt;profits&lt;/em&gt; on owner-occupied housing must be rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by profits? Remember that these are &lt;em&gt;economic&lt;/em&gt; profits, not accounting profits. Owners of homes are not seeing an increase in their cash flow. As a home owner, I can assure you that my house does nothing but suck &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; cash, as opposed to producing it. Those economic profits are coming in the form of a higher imputed flow of GDP from my house over time. This implicit flow of value, a rent I’m charging myself, is getting cranked upwards over time, even if I don’t see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To think about how this works out as an economic profit, consider the following example. Let’s say you can take out a mortgage at 4%. That’s the nominal interest rate i. Let’s say houses depreciate at 1% per year, and you expect capital gains on your house to be something like 2% per year. Then the required rate of return to break even would be &lt;strong&gt;R = 4 - 2 + 1 = 3%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your house is worth 500,000, a 3% return would mean charging 15,000 in rent per year, or 1,250 per month. Now, if you look out at the market and find out that you could actually rent your house out for 2,000 per month, you are making 750 in &lt;em&gt;economic&lt;/em&gt; profit. The price you can charge for your house, 2,000, is higher than the marginal cost to you, 1,250. Profits!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter if you are paying &lt;em&gt;yourself&lt;/em&gt; that rent or not. If your house can rent for more than the marginal cost, then you are making profits. The rise in the profit share in the Barkai analysis may be driven in part - or maybe mostly? - by the rise in the imputed value of rents going to owner occupied housing. If the BEA is overstating the value of the flows going to home-owners, fine, but then the implied increase in the profit share in Barkai’s analysis is overstated as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications of an increasing profit share coming from owner-occupied housing are a lot different from the implications of an increasing profit share coming from corporate market power or concentration. I need to think a lot harder about housing, it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Profits and Productivity</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Markups/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Markups/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the running topics here has been the relationship of markups and measured productivity growth. See prior efforts &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Cake/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/labors-share-profits-and-the-productivity-slowdown/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Those posts talked about how markups of price over marginal cost may skew the calculation of the growth rate of productivity. And I speculated here or there about how the falling labor share of output might show up in slower productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I want to draw on some new evidence regarding the &lt;em&gt;rise&lt;/em&gt; in the share of profits in output, a complement to the decline in labor costs, and how that might influence measured productivity. Evidence that the profit share is rising is important, because it doesn’t &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; follow that a falling labor share lowers productivity growth; that was always just a possibility. With a rising profit share, though, I think you can trace a more direct line to lower measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evidence-on-higher-profit-shares-and-markups&quot;&gt;Evidence on higher profit shares and markups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent paper by job-market candidate &lt;a href=&quot;http://home.uchicago.edu/~barkai/&quot;&gt;Simcha Barkai&lt;/a&gt; provides new evidence that not only is labor’s share of output falling, but so is capital’s share. This combination implies that profit’s share of output is rising. And by profit, he means economic profits (i.e. rents) as opposed to accounting profits. Prior work documenting a falling labor share either punted on whether than meant a higher profit share, or implicitly assumed that it meant a higher capital share. Barkai makes the case that there has been a significant uptick in the profit share over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His first figure shows the decline in capital’s share of output. This isn’t something as easy to observe (unlike wages and employment), so there is some mild theorizing used to generate the measure of the return to capital he uses. But Barkai understands this, and a good chunk of the paper is spent exploring whether the assumptions he uses are driving this result. The fall in the capital share seems to be robust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/barkai2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Capital&#39;s Share&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second figure here shows the implied rise in profit’s share of output. It is fairly close to a mirror image of the capital share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/barkai3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Profit&#39;s Share&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rise in the share of output being paid out as profits seems consistent with some other evidence on corporate savings. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nber.org/papers/w23133&quot;&gt;Chen, Karabarbounis, and Neiman&lt;/a&gt; document that the source of savings in the global economy has flipped from being primarily driven by households, to primarily driven by corporations. Given that investment behavior stayed relatively similar over time, this means that corporations have seen an improvement in their net lending position. That is, they went from being net debtors (borrowing money from households to buy investment goods) to net creditors (using their own money to buy investment goods).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ckn1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Savings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their figure gives you the basic story. On the left is the ratio of savings to total GDP for each sector (corporations, households, and government). You can see the rise in the corporate savings rate from 1980 to 2015 from almost 10% to close to 15%, matched by a decline in the household saving rate from almost 15% to under 10%. On the right, though, corporate investment as a fraction of total GDP has remained constant (and note that by 2015 it is smaller than corporate savings as a fraction of GDP). Note that these are global numbers, not US specific. What CKN also document is that the expanded corporate savings are not being used to pay dividends or interest. They represent a build-up of actual savings (think Apple’s cash pile).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ckn2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Savings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is consistent with the Barkai result on profits. You would expect corporate savings, as a whole, to build up if the labor share was falling, which it is. But in addition, the fact that these extra savings are not being turned into interest or dividend payments would suggest that they are not just being used to pay for capital. I can’t prove anything here, but the rise in corporate savings fits with the profit share being higher. They do some further analysis with firm level data to show that for every dollar of additional corporate savings, about 32 cents ended up as cash holdings by firms (as opposed to share buybacks or debt paydowns). Again, consistent with the story of higher profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you could go in an interesting direction here by asking what this says about the nature of the principal-agent relationship of owners and managers. If firms really are earning more in profits, why isn’t that all turned back over to owners in the form of dividends or share buybacks? Do the managers benefit from keeping a large portion of these profits inside the corporation as cash?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m not going to go in that direction. Rather, I want to see what this rise in profits implies about measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-effect-of-markups-on-productivity-levels&quot;&gt;The effect of markups on productivity levels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firms generate profits by marking up prices over marginal costs. So if profits are higher, it implies that the markup has increased. To say something about the effect that higher markups could be having on productivity, we need some conception of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; firms are able to charge a markup over marginal cost, and also some conception of what drives those markups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;, we assume that firms have some market power based on …. something about them. Maybe they have a patent on a product, meaning they are the monopoly provider. Or maybe they have created some kind of brand, or reputation for quality (deserved or not), that makes people want to only buy &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; product. Think Apple. Or maybe they have some kind of locational advantage, like being a coffee shop in a busy train station. Whatever the reason, these firms have enough market power to charge a markup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What determines the level of that markup, and why would it change? In general, the price elasticity of demand for their product is what matters here. The higher the price elasticity (the “flatter” the demand curve), the less market power a firm has, and the smaller a markup they can charge. The lower the price elasticity (the “steeper” the demand curve), the more market power a firm has, and the bigger a markup they can charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high price elasticity would be the case if there were lots of close substitutes for the product, so people were willing to abandon a firm’s specific product if the price went up just a little. Think of gas stations, which have a tiny bit of market power due to location. But lots of people would stop going to a gas station that raised its price by 1 or 2 cents per gallon. A low price elasticity would be the case if there were few substitutes for the product, or the product was a strong complement to other things people buy. Then, no matter what the firm charges, people will buy some. Think of an iPhone. Apple has convinced people - whether you believe it or not - that there is no substitute for an &lt;em&gt;iPhone&lt;/em&gt;; other smartphones just aren’t the same. So they can charge 600 bucks for one, while the marginal cost is something closer to 100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the evidence says that markups have gone up, then one interpretation is that the price elasticity of demand for different goods has gone &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt;. I think of this as meaning that people have gotten very picky. I want an &lt;em&gt;iPhone&lt;/em&gt;, not a Samsung. I want a double chai skim latte, not a coffee. I want a Lululemon pair of yoga pants, not the ones from Target. Just imagine that everyone has become a 13-year-old girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if markups are higher because the price elasticity of demand for individual goods is lower, what does this imply for measured productivity? Well, in most typical settings, this would lower measured productivity. Why? The low price elasticity of demand comes from a low elasticity of substitution across different products. And a low elasticity of substitution across products means that most of our inputs (labor, capital) end up thrown at the &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; productive firms or sectors. Measured productivity gets pushed down in this case because of the concentration of inputs in these low productivity sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the story, then we should see this show up as Baumol’s “cost disease” symptoms. Inputs (capital and labor) should be moving into low productivity sectors, and the relative price of the output from these sectors should be rising. Here I think you’d appeal to the rapid rise in the price of child care, education, and health care, among others, to support the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up this line of thinking. The elasticity of substitution across products has declined over time. This results in (1) higher profits, as firms enjoy more market power when people are unwilling to substitute away from their products, and (2) lower measured productivity, as resources get concentrated in low productivity sectors. In this case, the higher profits are not a &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; of lower productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this explanation is that it depends on changing preferences. It isn’t clear why the elasticity of substitution between products &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; broad sectors would be getting lower. I can see that perhaps we are getting less willing to substitute between goods and services as broad categories. But what would be making the elasticity of substitution between different services decline over time? More effective branding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;concentration-and-market-power&quot;&gt;Concentration and Market Power&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An alternative explanation to make sense of higher profits and lower productivity would be the concentration of firms within industries. Let’s say that you have a number of industries: health care, transportation, manufacturing, education, etc. And preferences are such that the output of these industries are complements, with a small elasticity of substitution across them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within each industry, though, people are willing to substitute between different firms’ output. The firms engage in Cournot competition, meaning they try to pick a profit-maximizing amount to produce taking the others firms reactions into account. The basic result in a Cournot setting is that the markup charged by firms increases as the number of firms &lt;em&gt;decreases&lt;/em&gt;. Fewer firms, less competition, higher markups. One could read the evidence of higher profit shares from Barkai as consistent with a decline in the number of firms competing with one another within industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think this would lead to lower aggregate productivity. For the industries with fewer firms, they would produce less output, and given a constant marginal cost as in a typical Cournot set-up, this means fewer inputs used. Because the output of industries are complements, we don’t like having less output of any given industry, so in order to convince the industry to produce more, we have to jack up the price we pay. A higher price for the output of a given industry is like a lower productivity level in that industry. And because different industries are complements, aggregate productivity is weighted towards the lowest productivity industries. Concentration in a few industries will thus drag down productivity in the aggregate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that sounded a little tortured. I’m not sold I’ve got the logic right. But thinking of Cournot competing firms embedded in a larger economy turns out to be …. not easy. At some point I will try to digest &lt;a href=&quot;http://users.ox.ac.uk/~econ0211/papers/iefs.htm&quot;&gt;some work&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Neary on this, and do a better analysis. For now, let’s just say that I think that concentration leading to lower aggregate productivity (and higher profits) is a working hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;factor-supplies-and-gdp&quot;&gt;Factor supplies and GDP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait, there’s more! Productivity might be affected by the rise in markups, but even if it was not, overall GDP is going to be affected through factor supplies. Higher markups and higher profits came at the cost of a lower share of output going to capital and labor. Which means that the return to providing capital and labor is lower. And if there is any elasticity to the supply of these factors, then presumably people provided less capital and labor to the market in response to the fall in capital and labor shares. Having less capital and labor would mean that total GDP (and GDP per capita) would be lower, even if productivity were the same. If productivity were lower as well, then the effect on GDP from higher profit shares would be even larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum the whole post up, a documented rise in the profit share (either directly or as an implication of the rise in corporate savings) could well explain part of the slowdown in productivity and GDP growth of the last 20-30 years. Putting a firm number on this is beyond my ability at this point, but it seems to be worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Who are you calling Malthusian?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Malthus/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Malthus/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had a student ask me if I was a “Malthusian”. It’s not the first time someone has asked me that, and I’m never quite sure what to make of it. It’s always asked in a way that implies it is a belief system, similar to “Christian”, “Muslim”, or “Packer Fan”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how to reply. I’m not a Malthusian “believer”, because that isn’t a thing. But I do think that several of Malthus’ assumptions about how economies function, in particular prior to the onset of sustained growth during the 1800’s, are well founded. And those assumptions have implications that help make sense of the world in that period of time. Some of the assumptions Malthus made may still be relevant today, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is therefore an attempt to lay out what I think Malthusian means, and then I’ll touch on a few alternate uses of the term that are not quite right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stagnation-in-living-standards&quot;&gt;Stagnation in living standards&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My concept of a Malthusian economy involves two characteristics. First, living standards are negatively related to the &lt;em&gt;size&lt;/em&gt; of population. This would occur if we had some sort of fixed factor of production. Typically, one might say it was agricultural land, but you could just say resources if you like. It isn’t even important that they are truly fixed. So long as the resources are inelastic, whether due to a physical limit or because bringing them into use is prohibitively expensive, you’d satisfy the first characteristic of a Malthusian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that there is much controversy around whether this holds, in particular in the era prior to sustained growth. I cribbed the figure shown here from Oded Galor’s book, which took if from Greg Clark. When population crashes after the Black Death, wages spike. They stay high while population is low, and then fall once population rises again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/clark2001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clark wage and population&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second characteristic is that population growth is positively related to living standards. This may be because kids are a normal good, and so fertility rises when people have higher incomes. Or it may be because health is a normal good, so people take better care of themselves (and their kids) when they have higher income. Higher fertility and/or lower mortality rates would lead to more rapid population growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or maybe people don’t make concious choices like that. Maybe it is purely biological, and women with higher living standards (e.g. healthier diets) will bring more babies to term, and those babies will be more likely to survive to become parents themselves. It isn’t important here whether the fertility and mortality outcomes are subject to rational calculation or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malthus’ original work involved this positive relationship, and he seemed to have in mind a combination of choice and biology. His preventative checks were choices made by people to have fewer children, or marry later, in response to poor living standards (hence living standards and fertility are positively related). His positive checks were lower fertility and higher mortality that would occur somewhat automaticallywhen living standards fell sufficiently far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the first characteristic, the evidence for the second is ambiguous. The major issue is that there is little data available on fertility and mortality at the individual level from the period prior to 1800, and so it is difficult to test the relationship of those demographics with living standards. England is one of the places that has some data, and hence the debate on this tends to be over English demographics. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/services/aop-cambridge-core/content/view/S0022050712000678&quot;&gt;Kelly and O Grada&lt;/a&gt; (2012) find evidence of preventive checks (i.e. marriage rates), and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cesifo-group.de/DocDL/cesifo1_wp6167.pdf&quot;&gt;Cinnirella, Klemp, and Weisdorf&lt;/a&gt; (2016) find evidence that births were spaced in response to living standards. But there are a number of studies that conclude the marriage rates were not responsive to living standards. &lt;a href=&quot;http://wrap.warwick.ac.uk/28332/&quot;&gt;Crafts and Mills&lt;/a&gt; (2009), for example, conclude there is no positive check operating, and that preventive checks break down by the 1700’s. If you are looking for reasons to “dis-believe” Malthusian economics, then this is the spot. Perhaps population growth isn’t positively related to living standards after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this characteristic holds, then you’ve got what I’d call a Malthusian economy. At this point, everything else follows. If there are only a few people, then from the first characteristic we know that living standards are high because the resources per person are high. But high living standards mean high population growth rates, so the number of people expands, and this pushes down resources per person, and hence pushes down living standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are a lot of people, then the opposite logic holds. Things are crowded, so living standards are low. Low living standards means slow population growth. When things are sufficiently crowded, it will mean negative population growth, and the population falls. Falling population means more resources per person, and so living standards rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything in the system is pushing back towards some middle ground where the resource per person, and hence the living standard, is at just the right level so that population growth is zero. With no change in population, there is no change in living standards, so there is no change in population growth, so there is again no change in population. The economy becomes &lt;em&gt;stagnant&lt;/em&gt; at the living standard which delivers zero population growth. If you’d like a nice treatment of this mathematically, I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/aer.101.5.2003&quot;&gt;Ashraf and Galor&lt;/a&gt; (2011) is the cleanest description you’ll get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m rambling on about Malthusian economics, let me offer a few observations that are not immediately obvious from what I just described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The stagnant level of living standards is not necessarily at a biological minimum.&lt;/strong&gt; Malthus, being something of an eternal pessimist, thought that living standards would be driven down to some bare minimum to survive. This isn’t a necessary conclusion from his two assumptions. Population growth can respond positively to living standards, even if the living standard at which population growth is zero is quite high. It all depends on preferences for kids. All Malthusian economies do not stagnate at the same level of living standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shocks to technology/productivity will only temporarily raise living standards, but will permanently raise population size.&lt;/strong&gt; Positive shocks to productivity raise living standards immediately for those alive, but this induces them to have more kids (or induces their kids to not die as quickly, so to speak), leading to population growth, which lowers living standards. Variation in productivity across countries will thus show up in higher population, but not necessarily in higher living standards. This is what Ashraf and Galor (2011) showed in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first shows that population density is positively related to a measure of land productivity across countries in 1500 CE, consistent with the long-run effect of productivity on population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ashrafgalor2011a.png&quot; alt=&quot;AGone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second shows that living standards (GDP per capita) are not related to the same measure of land productivity across countries in 1500 CE, consistent with no long-run effect of productivity on living standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ashrafgalor2011b.png&quot; alt=&quot;AGtwo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The adjustment back to the stagnant level of living standards can take a long time&lt;/strong&gt;. This means that a given Malthusian economy may have living standards that wander all over the place in the data. Nippe Lagerlof has a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nippelagerlof.com/research/happening/Waves_August_2016_post.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; showing that a Malthusian economy with random shocks to productivity and a realistic age structure will display living standards that do look Malthusian in the sense of being fixed and close to some stagnant level, but display waves of growth and collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/nippe2017.png&quot; alt=&quot;nippe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nippe has built a tendency for all economies to move towards sustained growth, but the point is that the four different economies have waves of growth and collapse that last for decades, even though they have the exact same underlying Malthusian structure. The random shocks to living standards persist over time because of the effect on age structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you ask me if I’m a Malthusian, then I guess the answer is yes, if you mean everything I just said in this section. Now what about other uses of the term Malthusian? Let’s take a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;population-and-factor-prices&quot;&gt;Population and factor prices&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term Malthusian has been applied at times to people who assert that changes in population size, acting through factor prices, influence social relationships. Historians like Postan and Le Roy Ladurie advance this kind of thesis, but I think that &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2kIGVT9&quot;&gt;North and Thomas&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;The Rise of the Western World&lt;/em&gt; may be the purest example of this, and the most known to economists. North and Thomas argue that changes in population, by changing relative wages and the bargaining power of peasants, were instrumental in changing institutions in Western Europe prior to the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like Robert Brenner and Guy Bois took issue with this explanation (and each other), arguing that Postan and Le Roy Ladurie (and North and Thomas by extension) were ignoring the issue of class in explaining changes in relative wages and the institutions governing labor. Glossing this “Brenner Debate” is well beyond the scope of this post, so suffice it to say that Brenner and Bois argue that changes in population are not sufficient to change institutions. The effect of population changes on labor conditions depended on the actual political power of peasants, which was not necessarily affected by population. See the compilation &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2lp39Zh&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for all you’d ever want to know about this debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the details of that argument, and it is a fascinating read, Brenner and Bois use the term Malthusian to describe their opponents and their theories. And to me, this is an incorrect use of Malthusian. The concept that population size influences wages is not Malthusian, it is economics-ian. There is nothing Malthusian about Postan, Le Roy Ladurie, and North and Thomas, at least when it comes to their explanation of institutional change. This doesn’t make Brenner and Bois wrong. It makes them semantically confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;limits-to-growth&quot;&gt;Limits to Growth&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third way I think Malthusian gets used is in terms of &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2kIQ269&quot;&gt;limits to growth&lt;/a&gt;, environmental collapse, and the like. Here, the authors or speakers believe firmly that there is a fixed supply of resources available, and hence living standards must be negatively related to population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can class the limits to growth people into two groups. The first takes population growth as given, and doesn’t think much about whether it responds to living standards. The fact that population growth is positive - at the global level - is sufficient to create declining living standards, and thus we need to either conserve resources or exert some kind of birth control policy. The second group has internalized the post-demographic transition &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; relationship of living standards and population growth. Once the planet gets so crowded that living standards fall, this will &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; the population growth rate, and we’ll be in a death spiral towards misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view, of either group, is often called Malthusian because of the negative effect of population on living standards. And that, it seems, is only about half right. There is no stagnation in the sense that I described above, as in either case population growth continues (slowly or in an accelerating manner) until the living standard is zero. Which I guess would be stagnant, if it stayed at zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I don’t consider myself a Malthusian in this sense of the word, and that is because the finite limit of resources gets progressively looser over time. This post is already stretched out too long, so I don’t want to get into a lot of detail here. But there are two reasons for this. First, because technological change will make some resource constraints less binding or eliminate the need for certain resources. Second, because the income elasticity of demand for resource-intense goods is low, our use of those resources will not grow as fast as limits to growth types would suggest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that my original description of Malthusian economies ignores this second effect, coming through income elasticities. Ashraf and Galor’s model, for example, would suggest that no matter how high productivity got, we are always producing goods using the same resource-intense production function. That may be fine if you are just describing the stagnant economies prior to sustained growth - or maybe it isn’t fine, if you read Lemin Wu’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://behl.berkeley.edu/files/2015/02/WP2015-01_Wu.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; - but breaks down if you allow for any appreciable non-resource based sector (e.g. services of any kind).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yes, ideas are harder to find. Don&#39;t panic yet.</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Idea-TFP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Idea-TFP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nick Bloom, Chad Jones, John van Reenen, and Michael Webb have a new &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.stanford.edu/~chadj/IdeaPF.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on how productive we are at producing “ideas”, which one can argue are the ultimate source of all economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The splash graphic from the paper, which I believe made a brief tour of the Twitter-verse a month or so ago, is shown below. It shows that the TFP growth rate (in blue) peaked around the 1940’s, and has declined since then. The axis measurement here is a big funky, as you could see more of the details of this line if they had made the left axis go up to say 5%, rather than 25%. Regardless, the TFP growth rate is smaller than it was in the past, following Robert Gordon’s numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In green is the relative number of researchers compared to the number in 1930. This isn’t the &lt;em&gt;number&lt;/em&gt; of researchers, its a measure of &lt;em&gt;effective&lt;/em&gt; researchers, found by dividing total R and D spending by the nominal wage of high-skilled workers. Relative to 1930, we have almost 25 times as many (effective) researchers at work today. This leads to the author’s title question - “Are ideas getting harder to find?”. And the author’s answer is “Yes”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jones_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Idea TFP and TFP Growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;measuring-idea-tfp&quot;&gt;Measuring Idea TFP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BJvRW measure how “hard” it is to find ideas by looking at what they call “idea TFP”. This is easy to back out from some data. Let’s write the growth rate of ideas (I) as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{I}_t}{I_t} = \alpha_t S_t&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where the left side is the growth rate of ideas at time t, and on the right-hand side we’ve got the determinants of that growth. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S_t\inline&quot;/&gt; is research effort, and here think of the measure of effective researchers. How much work do we put into coming up with new ideas? The second term is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_t\inline&quot;/&gt;, which is the “idea TFP”. It tells you how much idea growth you get out of those researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you tell me the growth rate of ideas (the left) and the number of effective researchers (S), then I (well, the authors) can back out the measure of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_t\inline&quot;/&gt; year by year. And this is what BJvRW do, in a variety of contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they do first is to equate the growth rate of ideas with the growth rate of TFP (actual aggregate TFP in producing GDP). That doesn’t mean that each idea is equal to one “unit” of TFP, it just means that if the number of ideas grows by 10%, then TFP grows by 10%. This is a big leap - but let’s not get hung up on this. It isn’t important in this first context. With the data from the first graph on the TFP growth rate (&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{I}/I\inline&quot;/&gt;), and the number of effective researchers (&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S_t\inline&quot;/&gt;), we can back out &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_t\inline&quot;/&gt;. This “idea TFP” is, awkwardly, the “TFP TFP”, or our productivity at producing TFP given a set of researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jones_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Idea TFP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second graph plots the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_t\inline&quot;/&gt; they back out, relative to 1930. You can see that it falls to about 1/64th of the level in 1930. Because we are 1/64th as effective at turning researchers into TFP, but we only have 32 times as many researchers, our growth rate of TFP is about 1/2 as high as it was in the 1930’s/1940’s. Hang on to the “why” question for a moment. For now, we’re just looking at the pure accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first exercise using (actual) TFP as the measure of ideas is a bit crude, and what BJvRW go on to do is examine individual industries or types of products to establish that the “idea TFP” is in fact falling within each of these as well. This is relevant because the first result using TFP does not tell us what is happening at the “micro” level. We could have constant (or even rising) “idea TFP” within individual industries or lines of research, and yet in aggregate falling “idea TFP”. It may be that ideas are not perfectly translated to TFP, or it may be that the we are spreading our research efforts over an ever-expanding list of industries or lines of research. In the latter case, idea growth in individual industries/lines may be falling because of the decline in numbers of researchers, not because of declining idea TFP. But in aggregate, this would look like declining idea TFP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus looking at individual industries/lines will help us sort out what is happening. The first example is transistors, and the count of transistors per square inch on a chip. Famously, this appears to obey Moore’s Law, which is that the number of transistors per square inch doubles every 18 months. If we count the number of transistors per square inch as “ideas”, then this translates to a growth rate of 35% per year. At the same time, the effective number of researchers working at chip companies (Intel, AMD, etc..) has grown by a factor of about 80 since 1970. Plotting this together yields their next figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jones_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Moores Law&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative to the first graph, there is no decline in the growth rate of transistors. But there also isn’t an increase, despite the increased number of researchers. What this means is that “transistor idea TFP” is falling over time, at about 10% per year. As they point out in the paper, Moore’s Law still holds, but it takes 78 times more researchers to figure out how to double transistor density than it did in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, the paper works through several other examples. I’ll leave it to you to look at the specifics. But overall, the message becomes clear. For crop yields, idea TFP is falling at between 3% and 9% per year, except for cotton, where it rose slightly over time. For “new molecular entities” (e.g. drugs) idea TFP has fallen to about 1/4 of its value in 1970, or about 3% per year. BJvRW also look at firm size, measured in different ways, which should be related to their productivity (and ideas). In each case, their size is not growing as fast as their RD spending, implying their idea TFP is falling at about 8-15% per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;implications-for-economic-growth&quot;&gt;Implications for Economic Growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The looming question here is whether this implies economic growth is due to slow down to zero. And the answer is “No”. It is possible for ideas to have a constant growth rate (and GDP per capita to have a constant growth rate as well) even if idea TFP is falling over time. For “semi-endogenous growth theory”, a term often associated with Chad Jones, this falling idea TFP is consistent with constant, positive growth in GDP per capita.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what is in the Jones/Vollrath &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2k0pcbz&quot;&gt;textbook&lt;/a&gt; (buy 1, buy 10, buy 1000!) when we teach how ideas accumulate. Modify that first equation I showed you to look like the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{I}_t}{I_t} = \frac{\alpha}{I_t^{\beta}} S_t.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where idea TFP is now the ratio of a constant, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the number of ideas, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I_t\inline&quot;/&gt;, raised to the power &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. The value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is quite important. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta=0\inline&quot;/&gt;, then the level of ideas has no effect on idea TFP, and idea TFP should be constant. This is what was in the original Romer model, by the way. What Jones did was to say that this implies a very knife-edge condition, and there was no reason to assume that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta=0\inline&quot;/&gt;. When &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta&amp;gt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, as we accumulate more ideas, the growth rate of ideas falls - idea TFP goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just because idea TFP falls as we get more ideas doesn’t mean the &lt;em&gt;growth rate&lt;/em&gt; of ideas (the left hand side) is falling. Why? Because &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S_t\inline&quot;/&gt; is rising over time due to population growth. If the share of people working as researchers is constant, then their absolute number is rising over time. In that case, there is a growth rate of ideas such that the growth rate of ideas stays constant over time, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{I}/I = n/\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n\inline&quot;/&gt; is the growth rate of population (and hence of researchers). Idea growth need not slow down just because idea TFP falls over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence the “don’t panic yet” comment in the title. Falling idea TFP may well be the natural course of things, without resulting in lower actual TFP growth. The observed fall in actual TFP growth would have to come from some other forces involved in generating research effort. Start with an explanation that might imply a permanent fall in the TFP growth rate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The growth rate of the effective population has fallen&lt;/strong&gt;. If the population that provides researchers (and it is best here to think of the total population of advanced countries, not just the US) starts to grow more slowly, then S grows more slowly, and the long-run growth rate of ideas is going to be lower. Maybe the slowdown in TFP growth is due to slower population growth in developed countries. A counterargument would be that this is offset by the increasing shares of Chinese and Indian populations that are in the pool of possible researchers. A counter-counterargument would be that age distributions matter too, and we’ve got too many stodgy old people, and not enough inventive young whipper-snappers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other explanations might imply that the drop in the TFP growth rate will be temporary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A downward shift in the share of that population that is doing research&lt;/strong&gt;. This would generate a lower measured short-run growth rate of ideas because S would have a lower short-run growth rate for a while as we moved to a lower share of people doing research. This doesn’t appear to be true in the data, where an increasing share of workers are reported as doing RD work over time - and that should be pushing &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; the short-run growth rate of ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An exogenous drop in the level of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In this case, the growth rate of ideas would eventually rise back up to what it was before, after we had lower measured TFP growth for a while on our way to a new equilibrium. If we’re going to argue about the value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt;, though, then we should start over with our theory about how ideas get generated, as saying “it was a random exogenous shock” ends up being kind of useless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, maybe semi-endogenous growth theory is wrong. Maybe this just isn’t the way to look at things. Alternative theories might say idea growth could be affected by policies (subsidies for basic research, tax policy regarding treatment of RD spending, etc..) and what we’ve seen is a continuous deterioration of the policies supporting idea generation. This one is a little hard to square, though, just because it seems odd that there would be such growth in the number of researchers if the returns to that research at the firm or individual level were going down so much. I can see how taxes on RD would lower the resources devoted to it, but why would that affect how effective RD efforts are? You’d have to argue that policies were incenting companies to work on useless ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The returns to societal capital</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Society-Dividend/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Society-Dividend/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Brad DeLong had a &lt;a href=&quot;http://equitablegrowth.org/equitablog/regional-policy-and-distributional-policy-in-a-world-where-people-want-to-ignore-the-value-and-contribution-of-knowledge-and-network-based-increasing-returns/&quot;&gt;recent post&lt;/a&gt; that contained a number of ideas regarding how we view redistribution in a market economy. I picked up on some comments he made towards the end of that post, in which he points out that much of our prosperity comes from a stock of societal capital that we unknowingly rely on every day. And because that societal capital is unseen and uncompensated, we are all in some way overpaid for what we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he says societal capital, I think of it in two broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt;: I think this is much of what DeLong has in mind. We are lucky to be in the “trust” or “cooperate” equilibrium in our repeated game of exhanging goods and services. If you like, call it the “stag hunt” equilibrium &lt;a href=&quot;http://worthwhile.typepad.com/worthwhile_canadian_initi/2016/12/staghunt-and-the-irs.html&quot;&gt;Nick Rowe&lt;/a&gt; talks about. Regardless, we benefit from the decisions of our ancestors to play this equilibrium, so that it is the default. If you want to say this is due to some institutions, or culture, or pure luck, it doesn’t matter. We’ve found our way to the trust equilibrium, and benfit from that immensely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scale&lt;/strong&gt;: He doesn’t mention this explicitly, but I think it is as relevant as trust. Scale influences the potential profits from innovations, and so is crucial to growth. Bigger market, more profits, more incentives to innovate. But scale is not the same thing as trust, or institutions, or culture. If you doubt that, ask yourself why no firm is spending millions to get into New Zealand, paragon of free market institutions, but they are falling all over themselves to do business in China. Living in the US, or EU, or China, is to reap the benefits of living with scale.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heart of DeLong’s point is that neither trust nor scale are things that are owned by any firm or individual. You could say that we inherited them from our ancestors, or you could say these are emergent properties, or you could say that they are designed by the institutions we choose for ourselves. Regardless, trust and scale are “ideas” in the broadest sense, and are inputs into the production process in that trust and scale mean our set of rival inputs (labor, capital) can produce more with them than without.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is it that scale and trust mean we are overpaid? Here I’ll borrow an idea from DeLong, and “hoist one from the archives” of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/what-assumptions-matter-for-growth-theory/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just to refresh, a production function tells us that output is determined by some combination of non-rival inputs and rival inputs. Non-rival inputs are things like ideas that can be used by many firms or people at once without limiting the use by others. Think of blueprints. Rival inputs are things that can only be used by one person or firm at a time. Think of nails. The income earned by both rival and non-rival inputs has to add up to total output. Okay, given all that setup, here are three statements that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Output is constant returns to scale in &lt;em&gt;rival&lt;/em&gt; inputs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Non-rival inputs receive some portion of output&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Rival inputs receive output equal to their marginal product&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pick two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas of trust and scale are non-rival inputs to production. If we assume that output is constant returns to scale in rival inputs (point 1), then we have to pick wither 2 or 3. As neither trust nor scale receive payments, we have essentially chosen 3. And in that sense DeLong means that rival inputs (our labor and our capital) are overpaid. We are not compensating anyone for the trust and scale that we inherited or created as a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first aside is that in my set-up choosing 3 implies that rival inputs earn their marginal products, and DeLong is saying that our labor is earning &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than its marginal product. I don’t think this is actually a meaningful difference. DeLong is saying that labor is overpaid because it earns returns that could be going to ideas like trust and scale. Whether we say that what it earns is the marginal product or not is irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second aside is that it isn’t really as stark as saying we chose option 3. Some ideas - the patent for an iPhone, the trademark on Coca-Cola - are protected and receive compensation. All I’m saying here is that scale and trust are ideas that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; receiving compensation, and in that sense rival inputs like labor are overpaid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third aside is you may be wondering how the increasing returns to scale that DeLong mentions fits in here. Note that point 1 only says production is constant returns to scale in rival inputs (labor and capital). In terms of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; inputs (labor, capital, and ideas) production is increasing returns to scale. If I doubled all of them, output would more than double.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the main story. What DeLong does with this is to provide what I found to be a unique justification for the public sector. That is, taxes are a way of collecting the royalties on trust and scale that we inherited and/or create ourselves. Taxes are the rents to idea of playing “cooperate” or having scale. And the proper use of those rents, if I am reading him correctly, is in ensuring that those endowments are perpetuated and handed off to our own children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to perpetuate trust and scale? Part of it, I think, is in providing the insurance against the fluctuations that are the necessary corrollary of the markets we create with trust and scale. Those fluctuations play havoc with local communities and ways of life, a la Polyani. Hence individuals or communities may be tempted to defect from the cooperate/trust equilibria, or hive themselves off on their own and reduce the scale of the economy. If we spend the rents of trust and scale supporting those communities, we can incent them to stay in the good equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue with this, as DeLong spends most of his post working out, is that simply handing out those rents to people creates issues for everyone involved. Those paying taxes feel that they are being taken as suckers. Those receiving the rents - the members of disrupted communities - feel like deadbeats. No one wants to be in either of those positions. We have built-in preferences that make deviation from trust and scale look attractive. Which is why being in the good equilibrium is such a delicate thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How then, do you justify the collection of the rents that, arguably, rightfully belong to all of us, and ensure that we pass on the trust and scale necessary for prosperity to the next generation? And do so in a way that is palatable to all parties?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea is that you can use the idea of rents or royalties as a positive justifcation of taxation. We are collecting on the royalties due to us as a citizenry for our trust and scale, the same way that Apple collects royalties due to them as a designer of useful touchscreen emoji delivery machines. In this concept, taxation is not theft, or a necessary evil, but rather the enforcement of our intellectual property rights over trust and scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other end, the distribution of those rents is perhaps more palatable when seen not as a handout (which makes people feel like a deadbeat) but as something like a dividend on shared ownership of an asset. I feel like this would be one way to think of how a universal basic income could be framed - everyone is getting their share of the collective dividend payment due to the owners of the “ideas” of trust and scale. It is a sign of ownership, not dependence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Can you do historical counter-factuals?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Causality/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Causality/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warning: rank speculation lies ahead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I fell hopelessly behind in an on-going Twitter-storm surrounding history and economics, and how the two fields think of causality and counterfactuals. The culprits filling up my notifications page included &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pseudoerasmus&quot;&gt;Pseudoerasmus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/leah_boustan&quot;&gt;Leah Platt Boustan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RichardALJones&quot;&gt;Richard Jones&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kevinhorourke&quot;&gt;Kevin O’Rourke&lt;/a&gt;. This is my uber-Tweet response, and I’m going to leave the 140 character limit in the dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The origin of the Twittering was an article in the Chronicle of Higher Education by Marc Parry that on a battle between economists and historians. He speaks with historian Eric Foner, and says “Foner considers counterfactuals absurd. A historian’s job is not to speculate about alternative universes, he says. It’s to figure out what happened and why.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the record, the context of the article is about the debate between economists and historians on the role of slavery in supporting capitalism, with (some) historians implying capitalism was impossible without slavery and (some) economists responding that capitalism would have proceeded just fine without it. You can see a little summary in the Economist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/blogs/freeexchange/2016/12/pain-past&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What appeared to get people going on Twitter was the idea that Foner “considers counterfactuals absurd”. The response to this is best summarized by the immortal Inigo Montoya: “I do not think that word means what you think it means.” The criticism is that &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; historians do counterfactuals when they suggest that factor X (e.g. slavery) caused Y (e.g. capitalism). By saying X caused Y, you are saying that if X failed to exist/happen - which would be counter to the facts of history - Y would not have existing/happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are the economists (many of them) so comfortable with, and happy to think about, counterfactuals? And why are historians (some of them) not happy with the concept? My proposal here is that the economists approach these questions from the perspective of a standard empirical setting with lots of observations, and they extend that to thinking about history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of a big cross-sectional dataset on individuals, let’s say with information on wages, education, and the like. It also has a dummy variable for gender: 0 for males, 1 for females. You could run a regression of (log) wages on years of education, age, lots of other control variables, and the gender dummy variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An economist trained in empirics will look at this and say that the gender dummy variable indicates the counter-factual effect of gender on wages. That is, if you could take a man, and counter-factually make them a woman while holding everything else about them the same, how much would their wage fall? Or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this is of course ridiculous as an actual policy change. You cannot simply flip someone’s gender, and even if you could, the other variables related to this person would likely change as well. If you could go back and change the gender of a person at birth, they would have almost certainly have had different education experiences, different job experiences, different health outcomes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with a large cross-sectional dataset, we could page through the data and find a woman with the same, or very similar characteristics, to the man we started looking at. And then we could just compare the man to the woman with similar characteristics, and look at their wage difference. That is plausible in an intuitive way. And when economists think of doing a counter-factual, this plausible comparison is what they often have in mind. Or at least, this is what empirical training has embedded in their brains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we take that kind of counter-factual to historical studies, where the plausible intuitive way doesn’t make sense. Studying slavery and capitalism, for example, we do not have thousands of different societies or cultures to page through to find one that looks &lt;em&gt;almost exactly&lt;/em&gt; like the Anglo-American industrializing societies, but doesn’t have slavery. We cannot compare like to like, and do the plausible counter-factual comparison like we did with gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only have the more dramatic counter-factual. What if we took the observed Anglo-American industrializing societies and somehow “switched off” slavery, just like taking the man in the wage data and “switching” his gender to female. The experience and implications of slavery are entwined with every other aspect of the industrializing societies, and pulling it out would entail massive shocks to all these other aspects. “Doing the counterfactual” looks like a big mess, and perhaps this is what Foner is objecting to because it sounds like writing some sort of alternative history novel. And it would be pure speculation to write such a novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would, but this is a second point at which concepts drawn from large dataset empirics make economists more comfortable with counter-factuals. We don’t have to think about writing down an alternative history novel. We need to think about lots and lots of possible novels in which slavery did not exist, and lots and lots in which it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And based on those thousands of alternative history novels, is it true that when slavery remains present into the 1800’s, that capitalism develops? And is it true that when slavery fails to persist (or maybe never really exists?) that capitalism fails to develop? We wouldn’t even have to be strict about the relationship between one and the other, we could ask if - statistically speaking - alternative histories without slavery tended to be without capitalism, and alternative histories with slavery tended to have capitalism. When economists are talking about historical counterfactuals, I think this is what they have in mind. At least, it is what I have in mind to make sense of claims like “slavery was necessary for capitalism”, or any claim that “X was necessary for Y”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The claim that slavery was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; necessary for capitalism is not meant to be an iron-clad statement of truth. At least I hope that those who make the claim do not mean it this way, because that would be wrong. What it does mean is that of all the alternative histories we could have gotten, the ones without slavery most likely would still have gotten capitalism anyway. And the proposed explanations for that - Indian and Egyptian supply responses, alternative labor arrangements in the US South - are arguments about the probability of capitalism occurring in those thousands of alternative histories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see why this can be frustrating to those coming at this from the history side of things. This seems to reduce historical work, which is in part the patient documentation of the particular, to a sideline. How could you possibly conceive of thousands of different alternative histories, when we as yet know so little about this one? The economist’s approach appears dismissive. Much the same way that telling someone who failed to find a good job after college, and is getting by working part-time at Pizza Hut, that their wages are approximately 50% higher in expectation because of their degree. Guess your particular error term draw just sucked. ¯_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, one advantage of thinking explicitly about this in terms of many-alternative-histories is that you can avoid falling into arguements about mono-causality. If you say that slavery is necessary for capitalism, and then say that in a counterfactual history without slavery capitalism would not have existed, you a careening perilously close to saying that slavery was the &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; cause of capitalism. You might try to swerve to avoid this by saying that speculating about that counterfactuals is silly in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you think about many alternative histories, it is much easier to avoid making mono-causal statements. Saying, “If we compared histories with slavery and without slavery, I believe that a statistically significant difference would exist between them in the appearance of capitalism” is wishy-washy, poor writing, and not exactly attention-getting. But it is clear that slavery is not the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; possible cause of capitalism, because you are allowing for the idea that some non-slave histories could have found their way to capitalism anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot get my head around asking “why”, as Foner does, without being able to undertake any kind of counter-factual exercise, whether in the data or in my head. But perhaps the concept of thinking in terms of many-alternative-histories, rather than feeling you must commit to a single one, is a way of making the idea of counterfactuals more palatable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growth links of interest</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Links-1612/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Links-1612/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick post to vent some of the pressure from my reading list before it explodes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Greg Ip has an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/the-economys-hidden-problem-were-out-of-big-ideas-1481042066&quot;&gt;extensive piece&lt;/a&gt; in the WSJ on being “out of big ideas”. One quality of this article is that it gives some plausible ideas for &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the pace of innovation may have slowed down in some areas. We may be plowing resources into things like medical research that have apparently small returns in terms of years of life saved. But, given our relative wealth, this may be entirely optimal. Adding a week to a cancer victims life may be worth more than inventing a better dishwasher. One quibble. Ip states early on that despite historically high number of scientists and engineers, “None of this has translated into meaningful advances in Americans’ standard of living.” We don’t know that. It may not appear to have generated advances in the growth rate of GDP per capita, GDP per capita need not be the same thing as meaningful advances in standards of living.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the benefits of Twitter (yes, they exist) is following very smart people as they argue a point. I fell behind during an on-going discussion of Robert Allen’s concept of a “high-wage economy” in England driving the adoption of machines leading to the industrial revolution. &lt;a href=&quot;https://notesonliberty.com/2016/12/07/the-high-wage-economy-hypothesis/&quot;&gt;Vincent Geloso&lt;/a&gt; did the Lord’s work in providing a fair summary of Allen’s position and some of the associated Twitter-commentary, and then catches you up on the possible holes in Allen’s argument. As a place to start reading about Allen’s hypothesis, this is quite nice, and provides many links to research questioning the assumptions behind Allen’s ideas. Then follow it up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://pseudoerasmus.com/2016/12/01/allen/&quot;&gt;Pseudoerasmus’&lt;/a&gt; post on the same subject, and with a similar, honest, approach.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT is starting a “micro-masters” &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.mit.edu/2016/mitx-micromasters-program-development-economics-masters-degree-1205&quot;&gt;program in development&lt;/a&gt;. Low-cost enrollment on-line for students in developing countries, with the possibility for exceptional students being offered physical positions at MIT. As a means of expanding the availability of education, this is great. As a way of tightening the net that excellent students may slip through, it is even better. I do admissions for the PhD program at UH, and I am sure that I have let slip students who would be incredible economists. But their applications just cannot show that. Giving students a low-cost way of signalling their quality ahead of time is the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Piketty, Saez, Zucman machine rolls on, with their &lt;a href=&quot;http://equitablegrowth.org/research-analysis/economic-growth-in-the-united-states-a-tale-of-two-countries/&quot;&gt;new paper&lt;/a&gt; trying to reconcile national income accounts (GDP, etc..) with individual wealth/income distribution data. If you are reading this blog, you likely already have perused the paper or summaries based on it. It’s stark in how the fortunes of various percentiles of the income distribution have fared over time. What I also would like to applaud these authors for is writing papers that are about simple accounting. This the kind of economic research that you could explain to your neighbor in about 20 minutes, and that should be seen as a feature, not a bug.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://voxeu.org/article/production-fragmentation-and-global-trade-slowdown&quot;&gt;Timmer, Los, Stehrer, De Vries&lt;/a&gt; have a nice post of their current research regarding the change in trade over the last 15 years. In short, if I’m getting this right, the surge in trade from 2000-2008 was in large part due to the increasing fragmentation of production in goods - lots of parts coming from lots of different countries - and then this trend stopped after the crisis in 2008. Trade growth is slowing down because production is not increasing the number of sources for parts any more, to again over-simplify. Some of this slowdown in fragmenting of production appears due to demand effects, as countries (incl. China) shift demand towards goods (or services) that use fewer differentiated parts as inputs. Baumol strikes again?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Useless, but fun. Selected &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freepatentsonline.com/crazy.html&quot;&gt;stupid patents&lt;/a&gt; that have actually been granted.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href=&quot;http://voxeu.org/article/piketty-s-housing-capital-results-new-us-facts&quot;&gt;piece of evidence&lt;/a&gt; that much of the increase in capital’s share of income over time is due to housing. Gianni La Cava narrows it down further to an increase in the share of income going to owner-occupied housing. Now, this income is imputed from the value of housing, so La Cava is finding that the run-up in the value of the housing stock is creating a noticeable shift in the distribution of income towards capital. Here’s a good question, then, which I may try to tackle at some point. What is the capital/labor split of income &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; housing - or any other imputed value - included? Is the labor share shrinking as well?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A nice &lt;a href=&quot;https://timeline.com/robots-have-been-about-to-take-all-the-jobs-for-more-than-200-years-5c9c08a2f41d#.6kz8o2jlp&quot;&gt;timeline&lt;/a&gt; of various reporting on the possibility that machines will steal all the jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Would you pay to save a job?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Trade/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Trade/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mike Konczal has a nice &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@rortybomb/learning-from-trump-in-retrospect-dce431b23ed0#.70zws6ugy&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about how important it is to distinguish “jobs” from “the economy”, and how Trump used that to his advantage. Noah Smith had a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-12-02/a-job-is-more-than-a-paycheck&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt; of the idea that a job is “more than a paycheck”. In my head, this is a complement to the arguments that Dani Rodrik has been making for years, as in his 1997 book &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2gzJqH4&quot;&gt;Has Globalization Gone too Far?&lt;/a&gt;. In economist terms, the easiest way to say this is that having a job actually enters the utility function separately from the real wage it generates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have one idea to add to this, which is that even the “winners” of trade (or technological shocks) are unhappy about other people losing their jobs. If you like, the job status of others has an effect on the utility function of those &lt;em&gt;with jobs&lt;/em&gt;. And it means they are willing to trade off some other source of utility (real wages) in order to give those people jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’m not sure I’m explaining this terribly well, let me give you an example of a choice I posed to a number of “regular people” in my neighborhood, and during the after-game-beer-drinking phase of my hockey league. I’ve been doing this for a year or two, but recent events have made the responses more salient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not claiming that I had some sort of insight a few years ago. This all started because of a random conversation with Kenny, one of the guys in my hockey league, which led to him saying that he’d “absolutely” pay $100 more for a TV if it meant more American workers didn’t have to go on welfare. After that, I started posing the same kind of question to others in an ad hoc manner. I realize that this all has a very David Brooks-ish bullshit man-on-the-street vibe. Feel free to discount accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the essence of the choice I posed to people regarding a hypothetical trade deal (I typically didn’t use such precise numbers, but this gives you a concrete idea of what I was asking):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option A&lt;/strong&gt;. With the trade deal, let’s say that the income of a winner - people who stay employed - is 1000. The price index with trade is 0.8. Let’s say there are four winners for every loser - the ones who lose jobs - but we organize a redistribution of the gains from trade to make sure the losers are compensated. We tax every winner 200, and use that to give every loser 800. The winners, after their tax of 200, are also making 800. With an price index of 0.8, every person - winners and losers - has a real wage of 800/0.8 = 1000.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option B&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t do the trade deal. Everyone is still employed, but their income is 700, which is lower than what a winner makes under the trade deal, and means that in aggregate, total income is lower than with the trade deal. Also, the price index is higher without trade, because we don’t get cheap imports. So let the price index be 1, and every person has a real wage of 700/1 = 700.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which option would you choose? The pure economist answer is A, because obviously everyone is better off in terms of real consumption, with a real wage of 1000 versus 700. Noah’s post was about how job losers would probably prefer B. Most people would rather take the lower real wage of 700 with an actual job, versus a transfer with a real value of 1000. If you want to call this a form of money illusion, fine, but that doesn’t make it wrong. It is easy to say that their utility function puts more weight on income that is received from working versus income received as a hand out. It is not a stretch to get your head around this. I have spent years trying to instill this &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; preference set into my kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was more interesting in posing this question to various people I knew was the response of “winners”. Most of the time, I told people that they should imagine that they would be a “winner” under the deal. And for the most part, the people I was talking to were already winners with respect to trade, or were professionals relatively immune from the effects (e.g. doctors or lawyers). Regardless, &lt;em&gt;even winners preferred B&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would potential winners prefer B? Anecdotally, they don’t like the idea of having to hand over some of their own wages to subsidize people who are &lt;em&gt;not working&lt;/em&gt;. They know these people lost their jobs due to the trade deal or technological change, and a number of people I spoke with said they would be in favor of some kind of subsidy for the losers, but only for a very limited time. But it doesn’t seem fair to them that the job losers don’t have to do &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;, even if it wasn’t the job losers fault in the first place. People care about the job status of others. This is, I would venture, some of the reason that individuals care about their &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; job status in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hypothetical winners also tend to express a sort of endowment effect. Once you pay them 1000, it is much more tangible to them that they are giving up some of “their” money to subsidize job losers. On the other hand, under plan B they pay the subsidy implicitly through higher prices and lower nominal wages, and there is no endowment effect for them. And the people I asked this question are completely aware, like Kenny, of the fact that they are paying a subsidy through higher prices. The winners are for redistribution, but they care a lot about how that redistibution takes place. Again, this sounds like money illusion, but that doesn’t make it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the answers I got are in line with what Konczal, Smith, and Rodrik (and others) have said before about the value of jobs versus GDP. I’d suggest that even those with secure employment have preferences that would lead them to support jobs &lt;em&gt;for others&lt;/em&gt; at the cost of some GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean we should scrap every trade deal? No. The implication of my little study is that people are willing to trade off &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of the gains from trade to keep more people employed. That doesn’t mean they are willing to trade off &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the gains from trade. If Option B were to scrap all trade deals and lower the real wage of everyone to 200, rather than 700, you would probably get a different answer from both potential winners and losers. And given the embedded nature of imports in supply chains, you could well make the case that the losses would be astronomical, and thus not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other policies relating to job creation would face the same questions. Noah brought up the idea of incentives for long-term contracts, and noted the worry that you can take this too far. If you incentivize long-term contracts, do you gum up the labor market so much that new firms cannot afford to get stated or grow, and old ones cannot afford to shut down? Or do you end up getting the same issues we have now with trade; a class of “winners” that get long-term contracts and a class of “losers” that do not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of doing economics, I’m not sold that building the concept of this job preference into models would amount to much more than slapping some math around. I think our job is a little more humble. Be really clear about the economic costs and benefits of Options A and B on things like real wages and GDP that we have some hope of actually quantifying, and then let people decide if they are willing to pay those costs to save jobs or not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Employment Going South. Literally.</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Jobs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Jobs/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From 1990 to 2015, the US economy as a whole increased employment by about 30 million (30,056,664 according to the BLS). Employment in 1990 was 118,900,000, so that meant that there was a roughly 25% increase in employment over that 25 year period, with a little more than 1 million jobs added per year, on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to surprise anyone by saying that these 30 million jobs were not spread equally across the entire US. What I didn’t have a good sense of, personally, was how disparate the change in employment was across the US. This post is just some documentation about the absolute size of the change in job distribution across the US. I don’t know that I have a broader point, but I don’t really internalize the information until I play with it, so this is me trying to internalize the information on shifts in jobs within the US over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BLS provides county-level employment totals for 1990-2015, hence the time frame I’m looking at. And I can calculate the change in total employment in that 25 year period for each county. I could use the size of the labor force instead (employed plus unemployed) but the patterns I’m going to show you here don’t change appreciably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/county_loss.png&quot; alt=&quot;Binary job gain loss&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, of the 3,133 counties for which I have data, 909 of them &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; jobs in absolute terms from 1990 to 2015. The map highlights those 909 counties in pink. The location of these counties are not terribly surprising, although I don’t think I realized how much upstate New York’s employment numbers had dropped over time. You can see the smudge of pink in coal country of West Virginia and Kentucky, along with a big set of job-losing counties in the deep, deep south of Mississippi, northern Louisiana, and southern Arkansas. Downstate Illinois and a swath across the Great Plains also saw absolute declines in the number of employees over 25 years. In total, those counties saw employment fall by 1,471,436 jobs in this period, from a base of about 19.5 million jobs to just over 18 million jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the 909 counties that lost jobs in absolute terms, a number of counties lost jobs in relative terms. What I mean by relative loss is as follows. Total employment in the US grew by 25% from 1990 to 2015. If the distribution of jobs across counties stayed fixed at the 1990 distribution, then all counties should have seen job growth of 25% as well. A county that had job growth below 25% then saw a relative decline in employment compared to the rest of the country, and one with job growth above 25% saw a relative increase in emploment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 2,188 counties that saw a &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; decline in employment over this period, or roughly two-thirds of the counties in the US, and includes the 909 counties with absolute losses. Those counties started with roughly 73 million jobs, and finished with 78.4 million in 2015, an increase of about 5.4 million jobs, or about 7.4%. If those counties had instead grown at 25%, like the US as a whole, they would have had about 91 million jobs, an increase of 18 million jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 2,188 counties fell about 13 million jobs “short” of what we’d expect given the 1990 distribution of jobs. Which means that jobs moved out of those 2,188 counties, and moved into the other 944 counties that gained in &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those 944 counties started with 45.5 million jobs in 1990, and ended in 2015 with 70.5 million jobs, for a gain of about 25 million jobs, which is a percent gain of 55%. The 944 counties that gained in relative terms over this period gained 13 million &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; jobs than we would expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/county_scale.png&quot; alt=&quot;Relative job bins&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map here plots the relative job change, in number of jobs, for each county in the US over this period. I didn’t include the legend because it got too busy, and shrinking it down made it unreadable. The darker green the county, the more jobs, in relative terms, that it gained over this period. The darker the pink/red the county, the more jobs, in relative terms, that it lost over this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harris county (Houston), where I live, is a dark green smudge down on the Gulf Coast of Texas. It gained 663,757 jobs over 1990-2015. That is 291,540 more jobs than you would have guessed based on the 1990 distribution of employment, the relative job change. Other counties with big relative gains include Maricopa County, AZ (Phoenix) with 566,974 extra jobs, Clark County, NV (Vegas) with 477,942 extra jobs, and Riverside County, CA (greater LA) with 341,434 extra jobs. You’ll also see dark green counties in North Carolina (Charlotte and Raleigh), Texas (Dallas, San Antonia, Austin), Colorado (Denver), and Florida (basically everything but the panhandle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest relative losers in job terms are generally older cities. LA County came in 628,796 jobs under what you would have thought - it gained only 441,710 jobs but we would have guessed it should have gained over 1 million based on the distribution in 1990. Cook County, IL (Chicago) lost 558,190 jobs in relative terms. Wayne County, MI (Detroit) lost 378,043 jobs in relative terms. Cuyahoga County, OH (Cleveland) lost 225,300 in relative terms. Other big relative losses happened in Philadelphia, Milwaukee, Pittsburgh, St. Louis, Baltimore, Hartford, and big swaths of upstate New York (Buffalo and Rochester, mainly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These big losses are dominated by big cities because they start with big populations. We can look instead at scaled relative change of jobs. That is, take the relative change in jobs (e.g. -225,300 relative jobs lost in Cuyahoga County) and divide by the initial level of jobs in that county in 1990 (e.g. 642,367 in Cuyahoga County) for a scaled loss (e.g. -0.35 for Cuyahoga).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/county_perc.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scaled changes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map shows these scaled changes, and the message is similar to before. It was relative loss in the Upper Midwest, Northeast, and some core parts of the South and relative gains in very concentrated urban areas that generally lie in the Sunbelt, plus Denver. So it is not only&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I’m not claiming that this is some kind of revelation here. The movement of population, and hence jobs, from the Northeast/Midwest to the Sunbelt is well known. What I found interesting was putting some tangible numbers of the shift. The little counter-factual I’m doing here is not very rigorous; there is no particular reason to believe that the 1990 distribution is the “right” distribution of jobs to compare against. But the 1990 distribution does have the feature of being prior to NAFTA and prior to China’s accession to the WTO, both of which are at times cited as sources of manufacturing job losses in the upper Midwest and Northeast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of the relative job changes, though, indicates that more of the losses have to do with free trade &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the US than free trade &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; of the US. The areas with relative decline lost 13 million jobs compared to the 1990 distribution of jobs. In total the US shed 6 million manufacturing jobs from 1990 to 2015 (18 million to 12 million, roughly). So this relative decline cannot possibly be a function only of manufacturing and international trade in manufactured goods. There is just too much relative movement out of the declining counties to attribute to this. This is a sloppy way of thinking about how this would work counter-factually (I’m ignoring spillovers entirely), but if you magically added 6 million extra jobs to those counties in relative decline, &lt;em&gt;they would still be in relative decline&lt;/em&gt; compared to the Sunbelt in terms of jobs. They’d have 84.4 million jobs (as opposed to 78.4 million), but you’d expect them to have 95.6 million based on the 1990 distribution, so they would still be 11.2 million jobs off the pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breadth of relative loss, though, seems striking, and is the one thing I did not appreciate prior to looking at this data. 909 counties &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; jobs in absolute terms, which is 29% of all counties. Another 1,279 counties, 41% of all counties, gained jobs in absolute terms buy lost in relative terms. 944 counties, 30%, gained in relative terms. Just as many counties gained in relative terms as lost in absolute terms. The winning locations - Houston, Dallas, Atlanta, Miami, Phoenix, Denver, Vegas - won big, but the losing was spread across a wide area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More jobs in 2015 are still located in places in relative decline (78.4 million) than are in places in relative ascent (70.5 million). Of those 78.4 million, 18 million (or about 12% of jobs) are in counties that experienced absolute job losses over the last 25 years. &lt;em&gt;Most&lt;/em&gt; jobs are still in places that look to be losing out to Sunbelt cities over time. To the extent that your local economy plays a role in forming your opinions, this seems relevant, although I am going to stop now before I try to do any amateur political science or sociology.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ethnic fractionalization and growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Ethnic/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Ethnic/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is not a post about Donald Trump or the election, except tangentially. I have thoughts on Trump - so, so many thoughts - but most of them have been said, meaning I will provide little value added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garett Jones did a &lt;a href=&quot;http://economicsdetective.com/2016/07/costs-ethnic-diversity-garett-jones/&quot;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; with The Economics Detective recently on the costs of ethnic diversity. It is particularly worth listening to given that racial identity has re-emerged as a salient element of politics. A quick summary - and the link above includes a nice write-up of relevant sources - would be that diversity within workplaces does not appear to improve outcomes (however those outcomes are measured).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, there is a parallel literature, touched on in the podcast, about ethnic diversity (or fractionalization, as it is termed in that literature) and economic growth. But one has to be careful drawing a bright line between the two literatures. It does not follow that the results for workplace diversity imply the results regarding economic growth. And this is because the growth results, to the extent that you believe they are robust, all operate through political systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here let me walk through some of the core empirical relationships that have been found regarding ethnic fractionalization and economic growth, and then talk about why you need to take care with over-interpreting them. This is not a thorough literature review, and I realize there are other papers in the same vein. What I’m after is characterizing the essential results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baseline-empirics&quot;&gt;Baseline empirics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hks.harvard.edu/fs/pnorris/Acrobat/stm103%20articles/Easterley_Levine_Ethnic_Divisions.pdf&quot;&gt;Easterly and Levine&lt;/a&gt; did one of the first studies of fractionalization and its relationship to economic growth, with a focus on Africa. To measure fractionalization they used a simple index that has become the de facto norm for measuring this kind of thing going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Frac = 1 - \sum_i s_i^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_i\inline&quot;/&gt; is the share of group i in the population of a given area. You can interpret the fractionalization measure as the probability that two random people in an area belong to different groups. If there is only one group, then the summation term is 1, so Frac is zero. If every single person is in a unique group, so there are N groups, then the summation term approaches 1/N, and Frac approaches 1. EL constructed indices like this for a set of countries using data that originally came from Soviet ethnographers. As I’ll mention in more detail below, their index thus depends on choices made by those ethnographers about what constitutes and ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EL then looked at basic growth regressions. That is, they looked at the relationship between the average growth rate of GDP over a long period of time and how that correlated with their measure of fractionalization. In doing this, they controlled for initial GDP per capita and several other characteristics of countries. What they found was that higher fractionalization was associated with lower growth when only basic controls were included. To take the extreme, going from 0 fractionalization to total fractionalization was associated with a growth rate 2 percentage points lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a quick aside, note that this doesn’t mean a permanently lower growth rate. EL are working with a standard growth regression, controlling for initital income. What they are finding is that places with high fractionalization had lower balanced growth paths. In their empirical setting, every country has the same long run growth rate, but highly fractionalized ones will be poorer than homogenous ones. This shows up as a lower growth rate for fractionalized places because they are closer to their balanced growth paths to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EL go on to explore the idea that the reason for fractionlization’s effect on balanced growth paths is due to the interference in public goods provision. Their hypothesis is that fractionalization implies conflicts between groups, which implies an inability or unwillingness to get broad public support for things like education or infrastructure, and this makes them poorer in the long run. And what EL find is that once you control for public goods provision (crudely, using things like the number of telephones per capita) the effect of fractionalization is no longer significant or as large. For EL, this shows that the impact of fractionalization works through the provision of these public goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stronger support for that idea comes from a different Easterly paper. He, with Alesina and Baqir, published &lt;a href=&quot;http://isites.harvard.edu/fs/docs/icb.topic700742.files/Alesina_Baqir_Easterly_Pub_Goods_Ethnic_Division_QJE_114_1999.pdf&quot;&gt;Public Goods and Ethnic Divisions&lt;/a&gt; in 1999. This looked directly at US cities, counties, and metro areas, and the share of government expenditures at those levels being spent on various public goods. They found that higher fractionalization was associated with a lower share of spending on roads (about minus 5%), welfare (minus 5%), and education (minus 10-17%). On the other hand, there was a higher share of spending on police (plus 2-4%) and health services (13-25%). The increased police and health share is not always enough to explain the lower shares in all the other areas of spending, implying that places with high fractionalization have a larger share of local government expenditures on “everything else”. That “everything else” includes debt payments and other poorly classified spending. The authors speculate it could be related to patronage, but there is no way to look at that directly. In terms of actual levels of taxes and spending, there found conflicting results. At the city level, fractionalization is associated with both higher taxes and spending per capita, but at the metro area and county levels fractionalization was associated with &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; taxes but &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; spending per capita. Either way, fractionalization was generally associated with higher spending per capita. And no, that wasn’t simply due to city/metro/county sizes, as this held while controlling for the total population of the city or metro area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the country level, where Alesina, Devleeschauwer, Easterly, Kurlat, and Wacziarg &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.harvard.edu/files/alesina/files/fractionalization.pdf&quot;&gt;extended&lt;/a&gt; increased the amount of data available on a cross-country basis, including ethnic, linguistic, and religious measures of fractionalization. Similar to Easterly and Levine, they find that fractionalization implies a lower steady state growth path. Also similar, this negative effect dissipates as you control for crude measures of public goods spending and government effectiveness. The authors appeal to a similar argument to before: fractionalization makes consensus hard to build, and so public goods do not get provided at a level more homogenous societies can manage. A few correlates of ethnic fractionalization include lower literacy, lower levels of education attainment, and lower indices of democracy and political rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting note to their paper is that &lt;em&gt;religious&lt;/em&gt; fractionalization has almost the exact &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; effects of ethnic and linguistic fractionalization. More religiously heterogenous countries tend to have higher growth paths, more education, and better measure of political rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problems&quot;&gt;Problems?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with a basic measurement issue. The fractionalization index is sensitive to the number of groups you divide everyone up into. That is, if your country has two ethnic groups, then the maximum value of the fractionalization index is 0.5. If your country has 10 ethnic groups, the maximum index is 0.9. That seems to make sense. More groups, more possible fractionalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that the definition of what counts as a group is not a fixed characteristic. If I give people in the US the options of white, black, Asian, Native American, or Other, then I am allowing for 5 groups, and max fractionalization of 0.8. We could double the number of groups to 10 by allowing each racial group to report as either Hispanic or non-Hispanic, and now the max index is 0.9. Or we could sub-divide white into “German-American”, “Irish-American”, and so on, and get ourselves up to like 40 or 50 groups if we really wanted to, and this would automatically drive up the fractionalization index to one. Or we could say f$&amp;amp;# it, and stop tracking racial identity completely, and get a fractionalzation index of zero by definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that the degree of fractionalization is not immutably fixed by arbitrary racial or ethnic groups designed by the Census Bureau. James &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/group/fearon-research/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Ethnic-and-Cultural-Diversity-by-Country.pdf&quot;&gt;Fearon&lt;/a&gt; has an excellent paper addressing the arbitrary nature of building an index of ethnic fractionalization. There is no &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; fractionalization index for any country. The number of ethnic groups tracked in a census or survey may not map to any meaningful political groups. The Hutus and Tutsis in Rwanda were are included in a single ethnic group in the original Soviet data, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to the empirical work, this raises some questions on how to interpret the results. When Alesina, et al, collected their updated measures of fractionalization, they noted that ethnic fractionalization in much of the Americas is based on racial definitions (black versus white), while in Europe and Sub-Saharan Africa ethnic fractionalization is based primarily on languages (think of Switzerland). So the ethnic fractionalization measures are not comparable across countries. What does it mean to compare fractionalization in Belgium (French versus Flemish speakers) with fractionalization in Bolivia (Mestizos versus Aymara versus Quechua)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alesina et al mention that they go out of their way to find the most disaggregated data on ethnic groups possible. That is, they make sure they maximize the number of groups in each country, thus maximizing the measure of fractionalization. This has the virtue of being a consistent strategy, but suffers because it is subject to variation in the level of disaggregation tracked by country, which is an inherently political decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could easily turn all of the empirical results I talked about around in the following way. Places with relatively dysfunctional political systems benefitted from setting ethnic groups against each other, preventing effective opposition. They thus focused on ethnic or linguistic differences, and made sure to track these carefully when they did censuses. It need not even be nefarious. Former colonies who were left with dysfunctional governments may also have inherited a tradition of close ethnic group tracking from their colonizers. Either way, places with dysfunctional governments would to have mechanically high fractionalization indices along ethnic lines. And their dysfunction also leads to poor economic outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don’t forget those results on religious fractionalization, which was associated with better political and economic outcomes. The effect of diversity can go either way, depending on how you define it. If you started measuring fractionalization along as many dimensions as possible - ethnicity, religion, language, home state, favorite Beatle, height, extroversion/introversion - you’d eventually come across some of them that were positively related, and some negatively, to things like public goods spending or growth, just by chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overarching point here is that even taking the studies on workplace diversity seriously, this does not imply that poor political outcomes and/or economic growth are a necessary outcome of ethnic fractionalization. At the political level, ethnic fractionalization and its salience to public policy is a choice variable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GDP, Productivity, and Financial Performance</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Accounting-Profits/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Accounting-Profits/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In my last &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Manufacturing/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, I got upset because people were using measures of productivity as measures of firm or industry financial performance. And as part of that, I made the point that GDP (which is part of measuring productivity) has nothing to do with profits, or financial success in any way. A few people asked me about this, because it wasn’t obvious to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think part of the issue is that lots of people interested in economics are business literate, meaning they understand what is on financial statements, and want to translate those concepts to the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the economy as a whole is not just one big aggregate business. But, you can get some insight into what GDP is actually measuring by building it up from business accounts. So let’s give that a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a stylized example of an income statement you could find from any firm:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Rev - COGS - Exp - Wage - Int - Div - Rent - Dep - Tax - Bull = Earn&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The individual items are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rev&lt;/strong&gt;: Revenues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COGS&lt;/strong&gt;: Cost of goods sold. Think of raw materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exp&lt;/strong&gt;: Expenses, specifically those which are paid to other firms, like advertising costs, legal costs, and the like.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wage&lt;/strong&gt;: Salaries and wages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Int&lt;/strong&gt;: Interest payments on any loans or bonds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Div&lt;/strong&gt;: Dividends.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rent&lt;/strong&gt;: Rent on property and/or items of intellectual property like patents or copyrights.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dep&lt;/strong&gt;: Depreciation of fixed assets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tax&lt;/strong&gt;: Corporate income taxes. It’s important here to note these are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sales taxes or excise taxes like tariffs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bull&lt;/strong&gt;: All sorts of other bulls%&amp;amp;^ that firms use to limit the earnings they need to pay taxes on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earn&lt;/strong&gt;: Reported net earnings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In evaluating a firm, you probably look first at &lt;em&gt;Earn&lt;/em&gt;, which indicates wow much money did they made. &lt;em&gt;Earn&lt;/em&gt; is the number you would use in a P/E ratio if you were evaluating the a public firm’s stock. You might also look at different concepts of earnings, like EBIDTA, which would be like &lt;em&gt;Earn + Int + Dep + Tax + Bull&lt;/em&gt;. Regardless, the purpose of this income statement is to evaluate the financial success of the company. You are interested in the bottom line number, earnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take this and use it to build up GDP. All that’s required is basic addition and subtraction. First, rearrange the income statement in the following way&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(Rev - COGS - Exp) - (Wage + Int + Div + Rent + Dep) = Earn + Bull + Tax&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two groupings on the left-hand side, and we’ll get to those in a moment. Before that, note that I’ve put &lt;em&gt;Earn + Bull + Tax&lt;/em&gt; together on the right-hand side. I’m going to rename this combined term as &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(Rev - COGS - Exp) - (Wage + Int + Div + Rent + Dep) = Profits&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of questions here. Why is &lt;em&gt;Bull&lt;/em&gt; part of &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt;? Because &lt;em&gt;Bull&lt;/em&gt; is purely accounting gimmick stuff to mitigate taxes. So while they list it like any other expense, we will not. Next, why is &lt;em&gt;Tax&lt;/em&gt; part of &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt;? Because what happens to those profits after they are made is a different question than how big those profits actually are. &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt; is really &lt;em&gt;Profits before corporate income taxes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, move that grouping of wages and interest and other items over to the right-hand side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Rev - COGS - Exp = Wage + Int + Div + Rent + Dep + Profits&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term on the left-hand side is called &lt;em&gt;value-added&lt;/em&gt;. The firm sells goods and services for &lt;em&gt;Rev&lt;/em&gt;, and that is the total value of those goods and services. But those goods and services required the value of &lt;em&gt;COGS&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Exp&lt;/em&gt; to produce, so the &lt;em&gt;value-added&lt;/em&gt; of the firm is the difference of their revenues and these expenses. Now we’ve got:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;ValueAdded = Wage + Int + Div + Rent + Dep + Profits&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great. At a firm level, we have that their value-added is, by definition, equal to their wages, interest payments, dividends, rents, depreciation, and profits. Whether that &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt; term is positive or negative is unknowable without knowing the other terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this equation holds for all the firms in the economy. It holds even for those firms who don’t produce formal financial statements, like your local food truck. It holds for federal, state, and local governments, who differ in how they assign money to different categories. Sum up both sides of the equation across all firms or entities that produce value added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;GDP = \sum Wage + \sum Int + \sum Div + \sum Rent + \sum Dep + \sum Profits&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left-hand side is GDP, because GDP is the sum of value-added across all firms, by definition. Go backwards, and note how GDP is built up. It is the sum of value-added across firms. Value-added is &lt;em&gt;Rev - COGS - Exp&lt;/em&gt;, which does not tell you anything about profits at the firm level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GDP can be decomposed among all those things on the right-hand side. And in fact the BEA reports exactly the right hand side in their Gross Domestic Income (GDI) estimate, which is equal to GDP except for a small statistical discrepancy (because adding up all these things across firms is hard).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GDP (or GDI) tells you nothing about the financial health or success of firms. &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt; could be big, or small, or negative, or positive. As a company, Amazon lost about 240 million dollars in 2014. But that doesn’t mean the services it provided didn’t count in GDP. They provided about 26 billion in value-added the same year. Sears Holding Company lost 1.13 billion dollars in 2015, which was better than the 1.68 billion they lost in 2014. At the same time, Sears Holding contributed about 5.8 billion to GDP in 2015, and 7.1 billion to GDP in 2014. It is not GDP’s problem that Sears seems to have more combined costs, like wages, rent, and interest, than can be covered by their value-added. It doesn’t change the fact that Sears provided goods and services to the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this a problem with GDP? The answer to that depends entirely on what you are trying to measure. If you are interested in knowing the value of all the goods and services produced in an economy, then GDP is what you want. To borrow a British phrase, it does what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you are interested in knowing if firms (or industries) in the economy are “doing well” or “successful” or “healthy”, then you should look at firm financial statements, and things like net earnings, or EBIDTA, or net income from continuing operations, or operating income, or gross profit, or whatever is your favorite financial indicator. Using those, you might decide that Amazon or Sears will go out of business in the future because they lose money. Or decide to sell or buy stock in those companies. Or decide to sue their CEO, or vote for a new board. But GDP isn’t here to tell you those things. GDP doesn’t care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why productivity measures like multi-factor productivity (MFP) or labor productivity are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; measures of firm health, success, or financial performance. These measures take GDP (in aggregate, or at the industry level) and divide it by numbers of inputs used. As GDP is not a measure of firm financial success, productivity cannot be a measure of firm financial success either.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Productivity measures productivity ... that&#39;s it</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Manufacturing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Manufacturing/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Justin Fox at Bloomberg put up a few articles (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-10-19/no-u-s-manufacturing-isn-t-really-booming&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-10-26/manufacturing-s-productivity-myth&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) recently digging into trends in productivity in the US manufacturing sector. The overarching theme of the two articles is that claims regarding the success of the manufacturing sector in the US (he cites Binyamin Applebaum’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobile.nytimes.com/2016/10/09/magazine/why-are-politicians-so-obsessed-with-manufacturing.html?referer=https://t.co/vEnqUjWznf&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; specifically) are overstated. Fox’s first article is titled “No, U.S. Manufacturing isn’t Really Booming”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to tell you that manufacturing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; booming. I’m also not going to tell you that Fox is right about it &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; booming. I am going to tell you that making claims about the business or financial success of manufacturing based on things like multi-factor productivity (MFP) or labor productivity, as Fox does, is using these measures incorrectly. The “health” or “success” or “boominess” of manfucturing are not things one can infer from productivity statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll pick on Fox’s articles here because they were recent, not because he’s done something especially egregious. They are two of many examples of how measures like MFP and labor productivity get misused to make points about financial or business performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message is that you all need to just let productivity &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; productivity, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mfp-is-about-value-added-not-numbers-of-goods&quot;&gt;MFP is about value-added, not numbers of goods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox takes issue with the measures of manufacuring multi-factor productivity because they involve quality adjustments made the BLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… the numbers are skewed by huge gains in real output in computer and electronics manufacturing that mainly reflect quality adjustments made by government statisticians, not increases in real-world sales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are couple of problems with this. One reflects some ambiguity. When Fox says “increase in real-world sales”, is he asking for a measure of business performance? I think, although I’m not sure, he means “increases in the number of physical &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt; shipped”. And if he means increases in the number of physical things, then this is precisely &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the BLS makes these quality adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multi-factor productivity is simply a ratio of value-added to an index of inputs. Value-added in the manufacturing sector is a mesure of the economic value of all the goods produced. Not the physical number, the economic value. And hence manufacturing MFP is a measure of how much economic value that sector produces - not the physical number of goods - per unit of input used. I know this paragraph was redundant, but it is crucial to keep the distinction between value-added and the actual number of things clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all we were doing was counting units, then no quality adjustments would be necessary. But we are trying to measure value-added, so they are. You cannot just add the 50 or so million iPhone 7’s that will be sold this quarter to the 20 million or so iPhone 6’s that will be sold to get 70 million phones. That ignores the fact that these items are different goods. And this problem gets exacerbated when I try to compare value-added over time. How do I compare the 50 million iPhone 7’s to the 5 million IBM PC’s produced in 1986? The BLS makes these adjustments to try and make the measure of value-added - and hence the measure of MFP - comparable over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could quibble with their exact method - I think an iPhone 7 is roughly equivalent to 400 IBM PC’s, but the BLS thinks it’s equivalent to 500 - but without these quality adjustments, MFP would be uniquely scaled in each year. It would be impossible to compare MFP in 2016 to MFP in 2015, and hence to know if it grew or not. While imperfect, you can’t skip the quality adjustment if you want to make any comparisons over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other sectors are not “more real” than computer equipment because they have smaller adjustment factors. You could easily argue that the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; sectors are “less real” because they have improper quality adjustments. The BLS could be missing all the wonderful innovations we’ve made in refrigerator construction, for example, and understating MFP growth in that sub-sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignoring computer equipment in MFP does not give you a better read on what is “really happening” in the manufacturing sector. MFP is what is really happening to …. MFP. If you mean “are manufacturing firms profitable or successful or expanding or exporting”, then you mean something different than MFP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mfp-has-nothing-to-do-with-corporate-accounting&quot;&gt;MFP has nothing to do with corporate accounting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prior section hints at how people make the mistake of evaluating the economy as if it were a business. The following quote shows what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… but the adjustments do raise questions about what exactly the productivity numbers signify. They don’t necessarily mean, for example, that computer and electronics manufacturers in the U.S. are actually growing, or succeeding in international competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, they don’t. They’re not intended to. MFP is not a measure of whether firms or industries are “succeeding”, in any corporate or financial sense of that word. MFP is a measure of how much value-added the manufacturing sector produced for a given set of inputs. That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value-added is not profits, in any financial accounting sense. The &lt;em&gt;closest&lt;/em&gt; you can get to an analog in financial accounts is to take revenues minus cost of goods sold. And revenues minus cost of goods sold is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; profits. Why? Because the firm still has to pay wages, interest costs, taxes, and dividends, among other things. So firms could easily be losing money, either in the sense of having negative net profits or a negative cash flow, even though their value-added is positive. Or maybe they are making money, and then good for them. But it is &lt;em&gt;irrelevant&lt;/em&gt; to MFP whether the firms are making money or not. MFP and firm or industry “success” are fundemantally different things. One implies nothing about the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get back to the prior section, the BLS is not trying to produce a quality adjustment so that their numbers reflect the financial accounting position of manufacturing firms. They are producing a quality adjustment so that MFP reflects a measure of how much value-added we get per unit of inputs. If their MFP number doesn’t mesh with your intuition or knowledge of the financial position of manufacturing as a sector, then … so? It’s not intended to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mfp-is-not-about-competitiveness&quot;&gt;MFP is not about competitiveness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox quotes Michael Mandel, of the Progressive Policy Institute, on why one should pay attention to MFP as opposed to labor productivity,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because it includes a wider scope of inputs and costs, multifactor productivity is a better indicator of how innovative and competitive an industry really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, it’s not. It has precisely zero to do with how competitive an industry is. First of all, “competitive” is a word devoid of meaning. “Competitive” could mean “cheap”, like textile firms in Southeast Asia, which have lower MFP than US firms. “Competitive” could mean “very low profits can be made” because entry of competitors is easy, like gas stations or coffee shops. That has nothing to do with whether MFP is high is low in those industries. “Competitive” could mean “produces a product that has an export market”, but that could just mean that the industry holds patents or other IP that makes it hard for others to replicate their product. And having intellectual property rights over a product doesn’t mean your MFP is large or small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Mandel probably means is “profitable” or “growing in revenues”, but I don’t know for sure. If his meaning is along those lines, then MFP doesn’t tell us anything about that, for the reasons I outline in the prior section. MFP is not a measure of profitability or market size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also isn’t a measure of how innovative an industry is, because as I’ve mentioned before on this blog, MFP is not a pure measure of technology or innovation. MFP is a garbage dump for everything we don’t know how to measure, including technology. So MFP can be stagnant even if an industry is innovative, or vice versa. If there is any imperfect competition in the industry so that markups exist, then MFP is affected by the growth rate of labor and capital, and the direction of this effect is indeterminate without knowing more about input growth. If there are re-allocations of inputs across firms within industries, then this influences MFP, and again the effect is indeterminate until you know which firm is shedding inputs and which one is gaining them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mfp-is-a-ratio-not-a-story&quot;&gt;MFP is a ratio, not a story&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because they are ratios, both MFP and labor productivity can rise because the numerator (value added) rises or because the denominator (all inputs or just labor) falls. It doesn’t matter which one moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On the whole, the U.S. manufacturing sector does not appear to have been a hotbed of innovation and productivity gains in recent years. It has gotten by with fewer workers, but in many cases that seems to have been more about managing decline through layoffs and plant shutdowns than boldly leaping into the automated future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we’ve learned, you cannot say anything about “innovation” from looking at MFP. But this is accurate that manufacturing has not been a hotbed of MFP or labor productivity growth in recent years. But then there are a couple things to unpack in the last sentence of this quote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If MFP is stagnant but the manufacturing sector has shed workers, then this means either value added in manufacturing has fallen (it has not) or the other inputs like capital have risen (they must have). This indicates that labor productivity, value-added divided by number of workers only, must be rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s it. We’re done. It is irrelevant to MFP or labor productivity what the story is behind the decline in labor and the increase in capital. The fact that you cannot attribute the decline of labor to lasers or robots or AI or hologram technology doesn’t change the fact that labor use declined, labor productivity went up, and MFP stayed stagnant. Closing a plant reduces labor in manufacturing, and if value-added doesn’t fall by enough, labor productivity in manufacturing just went up. It’s irrelevant for productivity that this is layoffs or shutdowns versus automated whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just let productivity be productivity. It measures value-added - not profits, not sales, not cash flow - relative to inputs, and therefore tells us how effectively the economy - not businesses - turns inputs into value-added. Slower MFP growth means slower MFP growth, not anything about competitiveness or the future business success/failure of US manufacturing. Heck, it doesn’t even tell us anything about the &lt;em&gt;past&lt;/em&gt; business success or failures of US manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coda-manufacturing-is-a-relatively-small-sector&quot;&gt;Coda: Manufacturing is a relatively small sector&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last point isn’t directly related to the main post, but I like to harp on this, and its my blog, so you’re kind of stuck with it. Manufacturing represents a small slice of economic activity in the United States. And there is no reason why we should be particularly worried or concerned with productivity in this sector relative to other sectors, many of which employ more people and are responsible for larger portions of value-added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing used about 9% of the hours worked in the US in 2015 (all numbers from the BLS). That makes it about as important, in employment terms, to retail (10%) and the recreation, accommodation, food service sector (9%). It employs less than education and health (15%), government (15%), and profession and business services (14%). But no one seems to write articles worrying about the MFP numbers in any of those other sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drilling down, durable goods manufaturing - like, you know, “real” economic output - employed about 6% of hours worked in 2015. That means it is as large as … administrative and waste services (6%) and profession and scientific services (6%), and slightly ahead of the “other retail” sector (5%) and construction (5%). It’s behind accomodation and food (8%) and state and local government (12%). The vast majority of hours, and workers, are employed doing anything &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; putting together durable goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of value-added, manufacturing accounts for about 11% of the aggregate, comparable to profession and business services (13%) and government (12%), and well less than finance and real estate (20%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing is not the dominant origin of employment or value-added. Which means that any action in labor productivity or MFP in manufacturing has a small effect on aggregate labor productivity of MFP. For labor productivity, you’d use the share of hours worked to weight manufacturing, and for MFP, you’d use the share of value-added. So as a rule of thumb, the reported change in manufacturing only counts for about 1/10 of that in the aggregate. Labor productivity rises by 3% in manufacturing? Then this adds about 0.3% to aggregate labor productivity. Manufacturing MFP falls by 1%? Then aggregate MFP falls by about 0.1%. There is nothing magic or special about manufacturing that priviledges its hours or value-added above other sectors in the aggregate calculations. It’s a relatively small part of the pie.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Labor Recovery and the Productivity Slowdown</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Labor-Prod/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Labor-Prod/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone loves talking about productivity, and how it doesn’t grow as fast as it used to. Very low productivity growth rates, in same cases negative, have been used very recently as evidence of this long-run slowdown and why perhaps it will get worse. But inferring something about long-run trends in productivity growth from a few years of data, especially years that represent a recovery from a deep recession, is probably unwise. Now that I have the 2015 BEA data on sector-specific output and employment, let me try to illustrate what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Productivity growth is just output (value-added) growth minus input (however measured) growth. In this post I’m working with BEA data on value-added and full-time equivalents, so when I say productivity that is short-hand for “value-added per full-time equivalent”, which some might refer to as a measure of labor productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of the post is really just to point out that a notable feature of the slow growth in productivity in 2013 and 2014 was the incredibly &lt;em&gt;rapid&lt;/em&gt; growth in full-time equivalents. Aggregate value-added growth did not drop off appreciably. Rather, the growth rate of full-time equivalents was high, and hence measured productivity growth was very low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_bea_fteprod_Aggregate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Aggregate prod growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure shows the growth rate of productivity (value-added per FTE) as the thick black line, and then also includes the separate growth rates of value-added (thin gray line) and FTE’s (thin dashed line). What you can see in 2013, and in 2014 especially, is that productivity growth dropped to about -2% per year. But value-added growth was still about &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; 2% per year, and the entire reason for the decline in productivity growth was that FTE growth was over 3%. Compare that to the numbers from the rest of the time period I plotted, and that is an exceptional number. Labor force growth drove the decline in productivity, purely from an accounting perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, once the growth in FTE’s ebbs to only about 1%, and there is a slight uptick in the growth rate of value-added, we see productivity growth rise to positive 1%. It sure looks like the drop in productivity growth in 2013/14 was temporary and driven almost entirely by the acceleration of growth in FTE’s as the economy starts to recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the BEA data, I can dig backwards into the sector-by-sector contributions to productivity growth. And there are a few select sectors that appear to be driving this phenomenon. First, take a look at “Government”, which includes federal as well as state and local government spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_bea_fteprod_Government.png&quot; alt=&quot;Government&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of value-added declines noticeably from 2008 to 2013 before experiencing a slight uptick in 2014 (the light gray line). The growth rate of FTE’s in government also bottoms out in 2011 at about -1.5%. After that, the growth rate recovered, and by 2014 FTE’s in government were growing at 1% per year. As long as FTE’s are growing faster than value-added, productivity growth will be negative, and you can see the precipitous drop in productivity growth for government in the 2013/14. In 2015, with a smaller growth rate of FTE’s in government, productivity growth recovers closer to zero, but is still negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side note about “value-added” for government. This is going to include both salaries for public employees like teachers, cops, and fireman, and also capital spending like roads, bridges, and other infrastructure. The effect you see in the overall government sector is driven almost entirely by state and local governments. They shed workers like crazy after the recession, and in 2014 that reversed dramatically. Growth in state/local FTE’s went from -1.5% in about 2011 to +2% in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail is another sector with a dramatic acceleration of the FTE growth rate in 2014, illustrating this point. In this case the discrepancy between value-added growth (consistently around 2% per year) and FTE growth in 2014 (pushing 15%!) is very stark. The massive addition of labor to retail in 2014 explains everything about the massive &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; growth rate of productivity in retail, about -11%. And as retail work makes up about 20% of aggregate FTE’s, this negative growth rate of productivity puts a big drag on aggregate productivity growth. In 2014, the negative growth rate of retail productivity can essentially explain &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the negative growth in aggregate productivity in the same year. But this is all due to the massive expansion of employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_bea_fteprod_Retail.png&quot; alt=&quot;Retail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, with the reversal of FTE growth (-10%), productivity growth bounces up to positive 12%, which means it contributes about 2.4 percentage points to aggregate productivity growth. But these fluctuations are entirely due to the fluctuations in the FTE growth rate in retail. Note that growth in value-added remains roughly constant in these last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one other sector with a pattern is construction. Again, productivity growth is negative in 2014 (and 2013), but this is driven almost entirely by the higher growth rates of FTEs in construction in those years. In 2015, as FTE growth abates in construction, productivity growth looks positive again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_bea_fteprod_Construction.png&quot; alt=&quot;Construction&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other sectors have this effect present, but it looks pretty small (Manufacturing, Utilities, Wholesale trade). Some, like transportation and mining, have similarly large shifts in FTE’s, but these tend to act in the opposite direction to those in retail and construction. That is, in 2013/14, the growth in FTE’s was &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt;, and so calculated productivity growth was very &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt;. In 2015 recovery in the FTE growth in both sectors is associated with much lower productivity growth, as in both cases value-added growth doesn’t change a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One response to these figures is that this reflects some error in calculation or reporting. And believe me, I’ve gone back and forth with the BEA website to confirm that this is really what they are reporting for 2014 and 2015, and that I’m using the right data. I’ve picked over my Stata code a few times to see if I’m getting this wrong somehow, but this is what the data say. If I was calculating things wrong, you’d expect to see some &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; odd surges in growth rates in other years, at least for some sectors. And since we don’t, I believe I’m accurately reporting the right growth rates given the BEA data provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on the assumption that these figures are a good representation of what was going on with productivity growth, what does it tell us? The first reaction I have is that this is precisely why you shouldn’t get worked about a single year’s productivity growth rate. In 2014, it was negative in the aggregate thanks in part to retail and government as well as several other sectors. But given that this was driven entirely by a surge in FTE growth associated with a recovering labor market, I don’t know that there is any long-run information here. It certainly doesn’t provide any evidence that innovation is slowing down. Productivity is just a residual, so short-run productivity growth rates will always be subject to surges in short-run FTE growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second reaction may be, if these industries are adding all these FTE’s, then why isn’t value-added rising faster? Does this make sense for firms to hire these people (or raise their hours) if they are not getting more value-added? Perhaps the people they are hiring are relatively low-skill and low-productivity? Think of the Roy model idea I mentioned in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Roy/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about Alwyn Young’s recent paper. If the people who are being added are relatively bad at working in their sectors - because all the good people already work there - then putting them to work may not boost value-added growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were feeling optimistic, you might look at this as evidence that innovation &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; occurring. Perhaps firms have been adding labor quickly because they anticipate needing them over the next few years due to innovations coming on-line. They presumably are somewhat forward-looking, and so maybe this represents firms investing in building up a labor force in anticipation of new markets and new customers? Note that the drop in FTE growth in 2015 does not wipe out the FTE gains of the prior two years. FTE’s are still growing at the aggregate level in 2015, just at a slower rate. For Retail, FTE’s actually did fall in 2015 relative to 2015, but are still higher than in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you might take away regarding innovation, these graphs suggest that perhaps the drop in productivity growth in 2014 was really an aberration. If FTE growth returns to more typical rates, then productivity growth - remember, just a residual - would return to more typical rates as well. And just a note, this doesn’t provide an explanation for why long-run productivity growth has been lower over the last few decades, but simply an explanation for why very recent productivity growth looks weak. I think the message is to not get hung up on year-to-year productivity growth rates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Soooo...maybe the service sector isn&#39;t a drag on productivity growth after all?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Roy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Roy/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the running themes on this blog is that productivity (called total factor productivity or multi-factor productivity by those in the biz) is basically a garbage dump for all the stuff we do not know how to measure in the real economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s post provides another example of this. Alwyn Young published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/aer.104.11.3635&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; in 2014 on the “cost disease of services” and productivity growth. In short, the cost disease of services is an idea from William Baumol, and it is intended to explain why productivity growth tends to slow down during a structural transformation from manufacturing to services. The idea is that services have low inherent productivity growth compared to manufacturing, mainly because services are often provided in fixed units of time (you can’t get a one-hour massage in less than one hour). Combine that with the fact that services are highly income elastic, meaning we demand more and more of them as we get richer, and labor moves into services over time. Hence the average growth rate of productivity falls because everyone is now working in this low-growth sector. It is certainly one of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Baumol/&quot;&gt;leading candidates&lt;/a&gt; for an explanation of why productivity growth is relatively low in the last 15-20 years compared to prior periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young’s paper questions whether in fact services really do have slower productivity growth than manufacturing. His argument is going to be that we may be falsely under-stating productivity growth in services because we are not accounting for the fact that the labor flowing into services is, compared to existing service workers, relatively bad at doing service work. What looks like low productivity growth is in fact low growth (or negative growth) in average human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, productivity growth in manufacturing is over-stated because the workers that remains behind in manufacturing as people leave are only the very best workers, and hence the average ability of manufacturing workers (to do manufacturing work) is going &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; over time. What looks like high productivity growth is in fact high growth in average human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea comes from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/2662082&quot;&gt;Roy model&lt;/a&gt; (1951), a classic economics paper about the distribution in earnings. At it’s heart, the Roy model is about self-selection. Imagine that each person has some built-in ability to work in manufacturing, and some built-in ability to work in services. There may be some elements of these abilities that are correlated (maybe you are really smart and could figure out how to do either efficiently), but regardless you’ll have a comparative advantage in one of them. Yes, the same idea of comparative advantage as in trade. You may be good at both activities, but relatively speaking you’ll be better at one or the other when I compare you to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young works out an exact case of the Roy model where your comparative advantage is positively correlated to your absolute advantage. That is, people who are relatively good at manufacturing are &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; absolutely good at manufacturing. Let me be specific, because I know I always found these concepts hard to keep straight in my head. My daughter once took a few hockey lessons, but now has been swimming her whole life. She has a comparative advantage in swimming over hockey. I’ve played hockey for a long time, but I never really took swim lessons as a kid, and I’m always worried about losing my contacts in the water, so I know just enough to keep myself from drowning. My comparative advantage is in hockey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not only that, our absolute advantages are correlated with our comparative advantages. If we had a swim race, my daughter would win - absolute advantage matches comparative advantage. If we played hockey, I would win - absolute advantage matches comparative advantage. (This wasn’t true a few years ago. Despite my lack of swimming skill, when she was 7 I could still outswim her just because I was bigger. Not any more. But I can still &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; her on the ice.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Roy model, if there was demand for one swimmer and one hockey player, my daughter would self-select into the swim sector and I would self-select into the hockey sector. Now, if the economy changes and the demand for hockey falls and swimming rises (global warming?), then I will have to switch. This will unambiguously &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; the average skill level of swimmers, as I suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When comparative advantage and absolute advantage are correlated in a Roy model, any movement of a worker from one sector to another will &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; the average skill of the &lt;em&gt;receiving&lt;/em&gt; sector, and &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; the average skill of the &lt;em&gt;sending&lt;/em&gt; sector. If I get moved from hockey to swimming, I lower the average skill of swimmers. The dudes that remain in my hockey league will be the ones who are still better than me (i.e essentially all of them), and so I just raised the average skill level of my league by leaving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the essence of Young’s story, and he shows that if this is how things work, then it has an effect on &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; productivity growth in each sector. Just another example of how measured productivity growth is a garbage pile of all the things we don’t know how to keep track of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past on this blog, I’ve referred to measured productivity growth as the “residual”, R, and true productivity growth as A. So to be consistent with the blog, but not with Young’s paper, he finds that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{R}_j = \hat{A}_j + \xi \hat{s}_j&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the growth rate of the residual productivity measure (what you see reported by the BLS) for sector j. So &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}_{Manuf}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the residual productivity measure for manufacturing, as an example. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{A}\inline&quot;/&gt; is true productivity growth in sector j. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the growth in the share of labor working in sector j.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is how average worker ability/skill responds to a change in sector j’s share of the labor force. Young establishes empirically that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is less than zero. He has his own estimates based on using sector-level data from Europe and the US, and this is consistent with several other estimates drawn from the literature. These estimates come from regressing measured productivity growth, the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}\inline&quot;/&gt; things from many sectors over many years, on measures changes in labor shares, the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; things. An important element of this is that Young actually has these labor terms for 60 &lt;em&gt;types&lt;/em&gt; of labor, differentiated by gender, age, and education. Thus his estimate of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is not just picking up on the fact that perhaps manufacturing workers are older, male, and less educated, for example. It has to be mentioned here as well that Young’s estimates are very imprecise, with standard errors big enough that you cannot reject zero in many cases - his case is really made on the fact that the negative estimates are so consistent across different samples and specifications. So you could easily remain suspicious of these results pending some more precise way of nailing down the value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is estimated to be less than zero implies that measured productivity growth in a sector goes &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt; when more labor (of any of the types) is added to the sector. This is consistent with the theoretical case Young discussed within the Roy model of comparative advantage and absolute advantage being correlated. And now that we know &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is negative, we can see what kind of an effect the Roy effects have on measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take manufacturing, which has a shrinking share of labor, meaning &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{s}&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt; for that sector. Combined with &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, this means that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}&amp;gt;\hat{A}\inline&quot;/&gt; for manufacturing. Measured manufacturing productivity growth is higher than true productivity growth. Flip the logic around for services, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{s}&amp;gt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, and you get that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}&amp;lt;\hat{A}\inline&quot;/&gt;. Measured productivity growth is &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; than true productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young provides a table where he recovers the true productivity growth rates in each sector. This depends on the value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt;, and his estimates suggest that this parameter is somewhere between -0.5 and -1.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/young.png&quot; alt=&quot;Young&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the table, the first row just gives the regularly reported values for productivity growth in the US and the EU for manufacturing and service productivity growth. In the US, manufacturing (goods) has reported productivity growth of 1.57 percent per year, and services only 0.73. However, if Young’s estimate of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; of -0.5 is right, then in fact true productivity growth is more like 1.10 in manufacturing and 0.84 in services. If -0.75 is right, then services have a small advantage at 0.90 percent per year, manufacturing has 0.87, and they are basically equal. You get a similar pattern for the EU, where manufacturing and services show similar productivity growth once the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; parameter is big enough in size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This analysis suggests that perhaps Baumol’s story is wrong. Services may not have a built-in tendency towards slower productivity growth over time. Rather, we are measuring it wrong. Remember that residual productivity measures are junk piles, and what Young is suggesting is that service productivity measurement had a big load of crap dumped on it because of these Roy effects. Manufacturing does not necessarily have better productivity growth, because it also had a big load of crap dumped on it by the Roy effects. If you take Young’s work seriously, then he’s showing you that productivity growth across all sectors is roughly similar over time, and hence there is no need to worry about the shift from manufacturing to services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what Young doesn’t do is decompose his table by time periods, so we cannot examine the effects when aggregate produtcivity growth was large (the 90’s) and when it was small (the 10’s). Has the Roy effect gotten bigger or smaller over time, or is it unchanged? And these Roy effects don’t necessarily offer any explanation for the aggregate productivity slowdown we’ve seen in the last few decades. Note that adjusting for the Roy effects may make the true aggregate productivity growth rate go up (the EU) or down (the US). The best this table can do is explain that the slowdown &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; due to “Baumol effects” of moving into services. But that’s important, because it means that we are not somehow doomed to slower productivity growth just because we’ve moved into services. We’re doomed for entirely different reasons, apparently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few other notes about this paper. David Lagakos and Mike Waugh use this &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v103y2013i2p948-80.html&quot;&gt;same concept&lt;/a&gt; to explain why there is such a large gap in productivity between agriculture and non-agriculture in developing countries, and why that gap tends to disappear as countries develop. And that makes me wonder about accounting for productivity growth rates in sectors in the early part of the 20th century, when agriculture was the shrinking sector and manufacturing was growing. Based on Young’s logic, this means we were probably over-stating agricultural productivity growth and &lt;em&gt;under-stating&lt;/em&gt; manufacturing productivity growth. So perhaps Bob Gordon’s story of high mid-century productivity growth is even more extreme than I thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, if you want to learn how to write a lucid economics paper, read this one, or really any of Young’s work. It’s just so coherently organized and explained compared to the vast, vast, vast majority of what gets published.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
