<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 10:07:59 -0600</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>The deep roots of development - Part 2</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Deep-Roots-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Deep-Roots-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Look at me, two posts in less than two weeks! I’m back with the second part of the series I’m writing on the deep roots of comparative development. Part 1 is here, and gave an overview of this literature. Here I’m gonna tackle some of the basic evidence on crude living standard differences that I think motivates studying those deep roots in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;modern-living-standards&quot;&gt;Modern living standards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variance in measures like GDP per capita across countries today is well known. This variance is the source of the question “Why are some places rich and some places poor?”. To get some sense of this variation, here’s a density plot of log real GDP per capita across countries from Angus Maddison’s dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/fig_dens_maddison.png&quot; alt=&quot;Density plots of GDP per capita&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line from 2010 ranges from about 6 (400-ish real dollars) to 10 (22,000-ish real dollars), or a factor of about 55. That takes into account some extremes, but the 90th/10th ratio is around 22, and even the 75th/25th ratio is still around 4. That is the scope of what we are trying to explain. How is it that some places produce four, or twenty, or fifty times as much as others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look backward in time, say at 1913 or 1820, then you still see variance, but it is lower. In 1913 the distribution spans almost 3 log points (6 to 9), meaning a ratio of about 20 between top and bottom countries. The 90/10 ratio is about 6 in 1913. Going back to 1820, you still see variation, although the span is only about 1 log point (6 to 7), for a ratio of about 2.7, and a 90/10 ratio of about 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/fig_dens_maddison_lim.png&quot; alt=&quot;Density plots of GDP per capita&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One issue with the first figure is that it may be skewed a little by the fact that more and more countries are included as the year becomes more recent. The second figure here shows the same kind of plots using only the same 48 countries that appear in the 1820 data. What that does is lop off the bottom end of the distribution in 2010. The 48 countries that Maddison calculated GDP per capita for in 1820 are all somewhat well off in 2010, although not universally so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we learn from these figures? First, we can see that the very wide distribution of GDP per capita today (2010) was much narrower about 200 years ago, which was right around the time the Industrial Revolution hit northwest Europe. (NB: Arguing about the timing and scope of the IR is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; what I’m interested in here - 1820 is correct +/- 40 years either way). So with the onset of industrialization a major divergence took place that exaggerated the distribution of GDP per capita.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What isn’t obvious from the figures is whether it was the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; countries leading, and the same countries lagging, at each point in time. It could well be that the leading countries in 1820 got overtaken by poor countries in 1820, who are now rich. But that doesn’t appear to be the case. Rather than look at the density plots, the next figure shows log GDP per capita in 2010 against log GDP per capita in 1820 for the 48 countries that have data in both years. There is a clear positive relationship, meaning that the countries at the top end of the distribution in 1820 were still around the top of the distribution in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/fig_comp_maddison.png&quot; alt=&quot;1820 versus 2010&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not label these points with country names on purpose, because that way lies niggling arguments about specific cases, and for the time being that is not what I want to get into. Suffice it to say that there is evidence that leaders of 2010 were also likely to be leaders in 1820, although not universally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, a perfectly valid question here is whether we should buy Maddison’s numbers for 1820. It could well be that Maddison decided &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; that there &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be a positive relationship, and then backed out his 1820 numbers to make sure the figure ended up right. I don’t think he explicitly did this, but it could well be that his implicit ideas about relative incomes based on his impression of history were leading him one way or another. But I think there is sufficient data from wage series accumulating to support the idea that Maddison’s numbers are &lt;em&gt;roughly&lt;/em&gt; right in how they order countries in 1820.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second thing to learn from these figures - or at least the first one - is that the bottom end of the distribution is about the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; in 2010 as it was in 1820. The poorest places in both time periods have real GDP per capita of around $400. It’s not just that the top end saw faster growth from 1820 to 2010 than the bottom end, it’s that the bottom end doesn’t appear to have grown &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is trying to be too subtle, but I think this leads to a distinction in the following questions. “Why did poor countries today grow slower than rich countries from 1820 to 2010?” is not the same thing as “Why did poor countries today not grow at all?”. The latter question is more relevant to this deep roots literature. It is about what conditions led some countries to (eventually) make the jump to sustained growth, and what conditions have prevented (so far) others from making that same jump. I think the deep roots literature takes as a given that once you do make the jump, that there are strong convergence forces at work that will carry you to the neighborhood of rich countries, a la South Korea or Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So perhaps to explain growth &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;, we need to reach back to 1820 or earlier and identify what created the variation in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rich-populations-and-poor-populations&quot;&gt;Rich populations and poor populations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data in the prior figures is all based on country borders. And if you think about which ones are rich and which ones are poor, there are some regularities based on the origins of the people in those countries. Europe, and especially western Europe, is relatively rich. But so are places like the U.S., Canada, New Zealand, and Australia that are referred to as “Neo-Europes” because they are populated mainly be former Europeans. Looking down the range of GDP per capita, places like the southern cone of South America (Argentina, Chile, Uruguay) all have large groups of European descent, and they tend to be somewhat richer than places without European-descended populations, as in much of South Asia and Sub-Saharan Africa. Exceptions do exist, of course, as with South Korea or Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can look at some data to see that this is a bit more systematic, although don’t confuse this for any kind of causal claim, just an observation. Using data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/oup/qjecon/v125y2010i4p1627-1682..html&quot;&gt;Putterman and Weil&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve created two plots. The first shows log GDP per capita in 2000 against the fraction of population in 2000 in a country that was descended from Europeans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/fig_pw_europe.png&quot; alt=&quot;Density plots of GDP per capita&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a positive relationship, dominated by the two groups at the tails with either 0% or close to 100% European population, but there are a fair amount of countries lying in the middle, and you can see that the relationship is consistent across the whole range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, next is the plot of log GDP per capita in 2000 against the fraction of population in a country that was descended for Sub-Saharan Africa. Here the relationship is negative, again dominated by countries in the tails, but with a consistent message through the middle of the figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/fig_pw_africa.png&quot; alt=&quot;Density plots of GDP per capita&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no way that, by chance, places with a high fraction of European descendants all happened to stumble onto the same package of institutions and technologies that stimulate sustained growth. Rather, this suggests that Europeans in general had, or developed, some institutions, technologies, or characteristics that were conducive to sustained growth. These features may have existed in some form or other back in 1500, which is how far back the migration data behind the figures goes, and Europeans just carted them around with them wherever they went. In that case, we’d want to look backwards in time to try and figure out what those characteristics were. On the other hand, it may be that the keys to sustained growth were not known in 1500, but that once some Europeans figured them out, it was easy to diffuse them amongst other Europeans. In that case, we still want to figure out what those charactersitcs were, but we’d also want to think about why diffusion was so easy amongst European populations (and so hard to other populations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be very clear that this is not a justification for doing ex-post reasoning about why Europeans are “better” than other populations. The leap to sustained growth by mainly European populations did not happen in a historical vacuum. The remaining populations of the world were not afforded an opportunity to see if they would find their way to sustained growth, and if that would diffuse among them in a similar manner, because the Europeans stepped in and colonized many of those populations first. As will be clear from this deep roots literature, colonization had significant and persistent effects on institutions, technologies, and other characteristics of these populations. It could well be that the only thing Europeans figured out and diffused among themselves was the willingness and ability to colonize other populations, and extract resources from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reversals-and-persistence&quot;&gt;Reversals and persistence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That colonization experience should make us wary of assuming that the characteristics of rich, European-descended populations today are instrumental for development. The variation in living standards that shows up in Maddisons data in 1820 is correlated with whether a country took off to sustained growth or not after 1820, but that variation reflects the experience of colonization that took place prior to 1820 as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can go backwards to a period prior to colonization, then this can tell us more about the differences in 1820, and hence today. And it opens up the question of whether the places that did reach sustained growth today really were &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; richer or better off (persistence), or whether they in fact were behind, and then overtook other economies (reversal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/oup/qjecon/v117y2002i4p1231-1294..html&quot;&gt;Acemoglu, Johnson, and Robinson&lt;/a&gt; posed this question, and argued for a reversal. In order to do this, they had to use proxies for development, as GDP per capita numbers are not available for a lot of countries back to 1500, and furthermore they are going to be very noisy estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an aside to talk about why those might (or might not) be relevant measures of living standards. What we know from other areas of the growth literature is that the urbanization rate is highly correlated with living standards. The causation here is not clear - do cities drive growth, or does growth drive cities? - but the relationship shows up consistently over time. What Remi Jedwab and I did in a &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/EEH_2015.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; was to look back at this correlation in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/fig_jv_urbrates.png&quot; alt=&quot;Urbanization and development&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure plots urbanization and log GDP per capita for three different years: 1500, 1950, and 2000. Yes, you should be wary of the 1500 relationship because of data issues, but a similar line is going to show up for 1700 or 1820 or 1850. The point is that the correlation is positive over a long span of history. In our paper we talk more about why the slope changed over time, and the baseline &lt;em&gt;level&lt;/em&gt; of urbanization rose across all countries, but for the purposes here we just want to see that urbanization and development are crudely correlated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That takes care of urbanization. The other proxy is population density. That one is a little tougher to argue is a good measure of &lt;em&gt;living standards&lt;/em&gt;, even though it might be a very good proxy for the overall level of productivity or technology. For the period of time that AJR are thinking about, 1500, we think that the world was operating in a Malthusian state, as most production relied directly on fixed natural resources and population growth was positively associated with living standards. We could do the theory on this, as in &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v101y2011i5p2003-41.html&quot;&gt;Ashraf and Galor&lt;/a&gt;, to show that those living standards, in equilibrium, are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; related to productivity or technology, but rather to the parameters governing fertility and mortality behavior. On the other hand, population density &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; be related to productivity or technology. Rather than looking at their theory, you could also read &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Malthus/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; on Malthusian mechanics I did a while ago. The point is that population density isn’t a very good metric for living standards, although it does give us some indication of economic possibilities, perhaps, of a country/nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to AJR, they showed that &lt;em&gt;among colonies&lt;/em&gt;, places with high urbanization rates or high population density in 1500 (e.g. North Africa, Mexico) were relatively &lt;em&gt;poor&lt;/em&gt; in GDP per capita by 1995. At the same time, places with low urbanization and population density in 1500 (e.g. Australia, Canada) were relatively &lt;em&gt;rich&lt;/em&gt; by 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a more recent paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aejmac/v6y2014i3p1-28.html&quot;&gt;Chanda, Cook, and Putterman&lt;/a&gt; has revisited this result in light of &lt;em&gt;populations&lt;/em&gt;, as opposed to countries. These authors took the migration data from Putterman and Weil, and came up with the ancestry-adjusted measure of urbanization and density in each country in 1500. For example, in the original AJR data, the urbanization rate in Argentina in 1500 was essentially zero, and the population density was very low. But that reflects the populations that lived in Argentina in 1500. In the time from 1500 to today, Argentina was colonized and settled by the Spanish, and then received a major migration of Europeans like Italians. So the population in Argentina &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt; is descended from populations that had very &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt; urbanization and density in 1500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/fig_ccp_urb.png&quot; alt=&quot;Adjusted relationship for urbanization&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What CCP do is thus adjust each country’s urbanization and density in 1500 to account for this, and compare to the original AJR result. The figure here with the label “Panel A” is from their paper. On the left it shows the original AJR relationship of log GDP per capita in 1995 with the urbanization rate in 1500, and the negative slope - the reversal - is clear. But on the right, you have the CCP ancestry-adjusted measure of urbanization along the x-axis. This has a clear &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; slope. In other words, countries that contain a large number of people descended from places with high urbanization rates are still rich today. In that sense there was persistence in development over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/fig_ccp_dens.png&quot; alt=&quot;Adjusted relationship for density&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do the same adjustment with the density data, as in the figure with label “Panel B” from the CCP paper. Again, the AJR result is on the left, and the CCP result is on the right. And again, there is a clear flip from a negative relationship and reversal to a positive relationship and persistence. Countries today that have populations descended from dense places are relatively rich today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives us some evidence that population-based differences in living standards are persistent over very long periods of time. And the fact that these comparisons are only over former colonies removes some concern that we’re comparing apples (colonizers) to oranges (colonized). But there clearly remain some open issues here. The nature of colonization was not identical across these countries. The ancestry-adjusted population of Argentina is heavily European because colonization led, through disease or warfare, to an almost total annihilation of the original population. On the other hand, Nigeria’s population has very little European descent because the disease environment favored Nigerians and (perhaps because of this) Europeans never wanted to, or never could, undertake migrations like those into Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the CCP results confirm that there is &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; persistent in development levels of populations. So if we want to understand why some of those populations were able to achieve the take-off to sustained growth, and some not, we want to keep digging backwards in time to see how they differed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-we-do-with-this-evidence&quot;&gt;What do we do with this evidence?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before going forward, it may be worth thinking about what we’re up against in trying to explain current development patterns as a function of past development patterns. I think of it in two steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we have to identify characteristics of &lt;em&gt;populations&lt;/em&gt; today that differ by the level of development. We cannot just identify them, we need some causal evidence that these characteristics have a real effect on development. In addition, we’ll need some theoretical understanding, which need not involve any kind of fancy math, of what creates that causal link. To give you an example of what I mean here, think of trust in strangers. There is evidence that the amount of trust people have in strangers differs significantly between populations, with many rich populations displaying higher levels of trust than poor populations. There is some plausible evidence that trust in fact causes more economic activity, and the theory is that trust with strangers allows one access to a much wider possible set of transactions than limiting oneself to transactions with kin-group members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second step, which is where the deep roots literature specializes, is in trying to identify the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; of the variation in that characteristic. Why would some populations be prone to trust strangers more than other populations? The data presented here are indirect evidence that this variation extends way back in time, and hence the source may extend way back in time as well. It could be specific historical events, such as evidence that trust within Africa was affected by the degree to which populations were exposed to the slave trade. Or perhaps there are environmental features that lead to variation, as perhaps different types of farming require different amounts of cooperation or work with possible strangers? Maybe it involves some combination of institutional and cultural shifts, perhaps related to marriage patterns? Regardless, we’re after &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; these characteristics, like trust, vary by populations, not just in identifying that they vary in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need both steps. The first step, by itself, can be interesting, but without the second step can deteriorate into “just-so” stories about why certain populations are “of course” better suited to development. The second step, by itself, can be interesting, but without the first can deteriorate into what amounts to overly complicated magazine articles without any relevance for current development. Which isn’t to say that every single paper has to tackle both steps, although some do. Our overall understanding has to involve both.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The deep roots of development - Part 1</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Deep-Roots-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Deep-Roots-1/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This coming semester I’m teaching a new version of my graduate course in growth and development. I’ve always taught a course that looks at long-run growth, but in the past that has involved at times a lot of theory (e.g. unified growth models) along with a close look at the literature on institutions as the origin of the take-off embedded in that theory. Some of the most popular posts I’ve every done on this blog were the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/the-skeptics-guide-to-institutions-part-1/&quot;&gt;“Skeptics Guide to Institutions”&lt;/a&gt;, which were in part lecture notes for that course. I also folded in material on the transition out of agriculture, something that I find an important part of this transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that version of the course was always a little muddled in focus, and so for this semester my aim is to step back and start over. The plan is to take a more coherent look at the literature on “deep roots” or “comparative development”, which I’ll define in more detail below. As part of that, my plan is to offer a few lectures during the semester that give an overview of areas within that literature, and a bit of their intellectual history, to frame the specific papers that I’m going to have students dig into and the data work I’m going to have them do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is meant to be a rough draft of the first of those overview lectures, introducing the field and the major ideas and themes we’ll be covering. The title of the post includes “Part 1”, which is intended as a commitment device. Part 2 should (no, will!) be about the evidence of persistence in economic outcomes over history, and the spatial pattern of development. Part 3 will be about institutions and colonization, Part 4 on culture and family structure, Part 5 on agricultural conditions, and Part 6 on cultural and genetic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timing-wise, those posts are likely to dribble out over the next few months, ideally well ahead of the scheduled date in class, but more realistically in some panicked burst of activity the day before. Once I get the final syllabus worked up, I’ll post that as well, in case people are interested in the bibliography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-the-deep-roots-or-comparative-development-literature&quot;&gt;What is the deep roots or comparative development literature?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any literature, there is no crystal clear definition. But I’d say that one characteristic common to any paper in this literature is that the underlying question is “Why are some places rich and some places poor?”. A second characteristic is that the answer involves deep-rooted characteristics of populations, rather than things like trade policy, macroeconomic stability, research subsidies, or social safety nets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be more concrete, I think there are several key stylized facts or concepts that this line of research has either established or takes as given. Most people in working in this area would agree with most of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Differences in development are about differences in &lt;em&gt;populations&lt;/em&gt;, not countries. It is not that France, Germany, and the U.S. are rich, it is that places with people descended from ancient European populations tend to be rich. Conversely, places populated with descendants of ancient African populations tend to be poor. Note that this is not a statement about genetics. It is a statement about where the ancestors of current populations lived in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These populations differ substantially in not just the proximate sources of development (e.g. capital stocks and productivity levels) but in more fundamental characteristics like culture and institutions. Attitudes towards trust, patience, importance of family, and the like all show significant variation across populations. The assumption is that these characteristics drive the proximate sources of development, and some evidence is available to back this up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Differences in the cultural and institutional characteristics of population arose early. By early, I mean well before industrialization, conceivably back to the origins of settled agriculture in 10,000 BCE, and perhaps even before that. This does not necessarily mean that these cultural and institutional differences created differences in living standards in the past; the effect on development may have been latent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are differences in the geographic, biological, agricultural, and climatic conditions of the ancestors of current populations. Furthermore, cultural and institutional characteristics are correlated with these conditions (things like variability in rainfall, the presence of frost, the durability of stored food, the disease environment, access to the ocean, and so on). Whether those environmental conditions &lt;em&gt;caused&lt;/em&gt; (some of) the differences in culture and institutions is not as clear, but evidence is accumulating that they did.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Things like culture and institutions are incredibly &lt;em&gt;persistent&lt;/em&gt;. Even once the underlying source of differences in those things disappears (e.g. immigrants with different ancestral environmental histories come to the same country) their cultural and institutional differences remain, at least for several generations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While characteristics are persistent, specific historical events (e.g. the slave trade) appear capable of changing them demonstrably. Therefore these events can change the development possibilities of populations. Which events rise to this significance is an empirical question, but colonization is a common origin.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work I’ll cover in this course can usually be framed as speaking to one or more of these points. But taking them together, we can stitch together a rough story of why some places are rich and some are poor. First, we should rephrase that as “Why are European-descended populations so rich relative to the rest of the world?”. Second, we could answer it this way. They are rich because the environment they originated in favored the spread of cultural and institutional characteristics (e.g. trust in strangers, patience) that were conducive to economic growth. Given that advantage, they were able to avoid (and instead impose) significant negative historical shocks on the rest of the world that arrested or rolled back their development, giving rise to the observed difference in living standards today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;institutions-versus-geography&quot;&gt;Institutions versus geography?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The words “institutions” and “geography” both show up in the points I just laid out. And that recalls a long-running debate on the relative importance of each. That debate, I think, has played itself out. Not because one side won and another lost, but because we appreciated that it was a stupid debate in the first place. There is nothing mutually exclusive about institutions and geography (and culture, for that matter) as determinants of development. Rather, both matter and interact with one another to create persistence differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me illustrate what I mean by comparing two excellent papers in this field. The first is Melissa Dell’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/ecm/emetrp/v78y2010i6p1863-1903.html&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on the mining &lt;em&gt;mita&lt;/em&gt; in Peru. The &lt;em&gt;mita&lt;/em&gt; was a forced labor institution that required natives within a specific area to provide work in the Potosi silver mine for Spain. Dell established in her paper that areas today that were once inside the &lt;em&gt;mita&lt;/em&gt; have lower development levels (on several measures) than places that were once outside the &lt;em&gt;mita&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second paper is Marcella Alsan’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v105y2015i1p382-410.html&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on the effect of the TseTse fly on African development. She builds a measure of the natural geographic range of the TseTse fly, based on temperature and rainfall. As the TseTse feed mainly on cattle, areas with the fly are less likely to use cattle in agriculture. Alsan shows that across ethnic groups, places exposed to TseTse flies did use fewer cattle, had less of a role for women in agriculture, and were less dense, among other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the surface, Dell’s paper shows the importance of an institution, while Alsan’s shows the importance of geography. And it would be ridiculous to think that one somehow invalidates the findings of the other. Both, though, show that aspects of development are persistently affected by deep roots, in a broad sense. In Dell’s case, there is a specific historical event - the &lt;em&gt;mita&lt;/em&gt; - that continues to cast a shadow on development within Peru. Note, however, that her finding is not on the effect of that institution, per se, as the mita ceased to exist centuries ago. Rather, she shows that historical shocks have persistent effects. Further, you can easily read Dell’s paper as proof that geography matters, because the location of the &lt;em&gt;mita&lt;/em&gt; was driven by the location of the Potosi mine. Those places are poor because geographically they happened to be close to a major silver lode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Alsan, the deep root is the range of the TseTse fly, which affected how ethnic groups within Africa subsisted, with effects on the role of women and type of agriculture. Again, underlying conditions had persistent effects. Further, she shows that the TseTse itself has no direct effect on development (measured by night lights) once you control for ethnic group centralization prior to colonization. One possibility is that the TseTse - through changing density and other characteristics - influenced centralization, and hence influenced development indirectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that in neither case is there a bright line between institutions and geography (or culture). Both papers show the deep-rooted elements - in one case a historical institution, in another the geographic range of a pest - have detectable effects on development that can persist up until the present day. Both papers provided evidence that helped build the concepts in points 1-6 above, but neither invalidates the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;empirical-methodology-and-data&quot;&gt;Empirical methodology and data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the concepts I listed, perhaps the other defining characteristic of this deep roots literature is the methodology used. It is an almost entirely empirical literature. Theory, when it is used, is illustrative rather than structural. Yes, it is easy to see the deep roots literature as an outgrowth of unified growth theory (UGT), which was much more theory-based. Oded Galor, the originator of UGT, is a central figure in the deep roots literature. But to my point, the theory embedded in his papers today is far more used to frame some simple hypotheses than to model history. If you want to think about how this deep roots literature fits with UGT, think of it as trying to figure out the specific conditions that determine why some places hit the take-off point, and when, rather than figuring out the specific mechanics of how a take-off works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Methodologically, the deep roots literature has ingested much of the logic of the causal revolution in economics, and combined that with two novel sources. The first source is extenseive GIS data, including night lights as well as datasets on inherent agricultural characteristics. This has meant the ability to do sub-country level empirical work at the district or pixel level, massively increasing the power of studies and allowing for better identification by being able to use fixed effects for larger political units and/or doing spatial regression discontinuities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second source(s) are bringing what I’ll call cultural datasets into the literature. One prominent one you’ll see is the Ethnographic Atlas, a compendium of anthropological information that was compiled from ethnic-group level studies, and coded into a common set of indicators for different cultural characteristics. For example, Alsan’s paper uses this to look at which groups within Africa relied mainly on cattle, and which had a significant role for women in agriculture, for example. Another is the World Values Survey (among others) that takes contemporary measures of cultural attitudes on things like trust, family, and the like. In both cases, further work has been done to link these cultural measures to maps, so that one can combine the geographic data with the cultural data, often at a sub-country level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond these, researchers in this area have brought data in on genetic diversity of populations, language relationships across groups, historical city populations, and so on, in order to make their case. One of the prominent features of this literature is an explosion in datasets being brought to bear on relevant questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While welcome, there are potential issues with this expansion of data. The origins of the data are not always well understood, as one might expect within the field of economic history, for example. The Ethnographic Atlas, for example, is taken as given. It was coded mainly by a single anthropologist working from studies taken from over about eighty years. One can easily imagine that you could teach an entire class on a single one of the 1200-odd ethinc groups in the dataset, and debate the nuances of the family structure, gender roles, and taboos of that group. The idea of coding that nuance into, say, a five point scale for whether a group is “patriarchal” probably makes most anthropologists break out into hives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The geographic datasets utilized also tend to be black boxes. A common source is something called the Global Agro-ecological Zones (GAEZ) project. This provides a pixel-level map of the world with numbers of the potential yield of that pixel for oats, for example. How do they arrive at that potential yield? Well, that depends on estimates of rainfall, sunlight, and soil type in that pixel, combined with plant-level parameters for needed water, length of growing period, and the like. What assumptions about how the plant is cultivated are built into the program the GAEZ uses to make that estimate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should remain skeptical - in the academic sense - of the work built on these kinds of datasets. I don’t think we have a good feel for how sensitive the existing results are to plausible variation in these sources. That is, one could easily come up with an alternative Ethnographic Atlas based on a new set of anthropologists coding the same source material, or come up with a new GAEZ based on a different set of assumptions from agronomists. Do those line up closely with the existing versions? If so, great. That might give us some assurance that the results we review are robust. But if not, things are very murky. The deep roots results could well fall apart with a slightly different version of the Atlas or GAEZ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;determinism&quot;&gt;Determinism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving aside the questions about data quality, this literature seems to imply some strong versions of determinism. That is, were the places that are poor today doomed to be poor because of some historic event 500 years ago, or because of geographic conditions present 10,000 years ago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I think it helps to think statistically, rather than in absolutes. And here I do not mean thinking about the uncertainty associated with point estimates of effect sizes, but rather the fact that in no case will any study show you an R-squared of one, meaning perfect prediction. To use a more concrete example, it is plausible that ethnic groups in areas where there were large returns to long-run investment in agricultural production may end up more patient in the long-run as well (as more patient people were selected for). There is a significant relationship of productivity with patience in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a significant relationship, but the R-squared is about 10%. That means that within the existing data, it is quite plausible to find pairs of ethnic groups that have different patience levels today even though they had similar productivity levels, or pairs with the same patience, but with different productivity. That’s all consistent with a statistically significant result and an R-squared of 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to the point on determinism, the results don’t mean that ethnic group A with higher productivity &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to have higher patience than group B with lower productivity. Imagine bootstrapping world history 10,000 times, starting over at like 100,000 BCE every time. The significant relationship of productivity and patience means that we’d expect patience to be higher in A than in B in more than half of those runs, but the R-squared of 10% it wouldn’t happen in all of them. It might be only that in 550,000 of the run does A have more patience than B, meaning B is more patient in 450,000 alternative histories. And yes, the positive relationship of productivity and patience could still be true even in those 450,000 histories because the patience of groups C, D, E, etc.. are all changing each time as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that the explanatory variable here, agricultual productivity, is taken to be plausibly exogenous to the patience of the groups is immaterial. Lots of other things affect the patience of an ethnic group over and above the productivity level, and hence lots of things could have changed over the course of history to explain patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acknowledging that geography (or biology, or agro-climatic characteristics) are significant for some cultural trait, institution, or level of development does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; imply a deterministic relationship exists, and that history is locked in no matter what. R-squares are not 100%!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings in this literature do not mean it is impossible to change the development level of countries or groups today. But the deep-rooted nature of development may mean we have to find &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; policy levers to push, as we cannot go back in time and roll back colonization, or change inherent agricultural productivity, and so forth. This isn’t that different than what you’d find in an applied micro course on, say, education. There you might study the effects of a program to raise graduation rates, and see whether it is effective or not. But note that graduation rates in some schools were not low to begin with because of the lack of this program, they were low because of (probably) poor socio-economic backgrounds, a lack of resources, poor teachers, etc. Even in these worlds we spend a lot of time pushing &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; policy levers than the ones that created the situation in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-forward&quot;&gt;Going forward&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike a lot of courses, this material will at times be breathtaking in the questions it asks and answers it proposes. It will seem presumptuous to explain cross-cultural patience as a function of agricultural productivity around the time of the Neolithic Revolution. And I think that researchers within this field do have a tendency to take big swings at big questions, and at times the prose in the papers will reflect that. Don’t let that put you off. The question still remains whether there is a valid empirical link established, and whether that link can be interpreted causally or just as a correlation. I think you’ll see that there is an accumulation of papers establishing strong links between deep roots and current development, and that this is not just a few odd results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, what I’m hoping to do from here forward (on the blog) is post subsequent parts with material on persistence, institutions and colonization, culture and families, agricultural productivity, and diversity. In the class itself, we’ll be covering specific papers within each section, and I’ll be trying to get my students up to speed on using R’s spatial packages to bring in some of the datasets used and replicating some basic results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/topic-deep/&quot;&gt;topic page&lt;/a&gt; up on my site already with all the existing posts I’ve classified as related to “deep roots”, so if you’re into this material feel free to have a poke around that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New evidence on convergence</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Convergence/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Convergence/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dev Patel, Justin Sandefur, and Arvind Subramanian &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cgdev.org/blog/everything-you-know-about-cross-country-convergence-now-wrong&quot;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; the other day some new evidence on cross-country convergence. They showed that there is statisticaly significant evidence for unconditional convergence in GDP per capita across countries. I’ll get to more details below, but in short they find that poor countries grow faster than rich ones, on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They set this up as a counter-point to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jel.20181207&amp;amp;&amp;amp;from=f&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; coming out in the Journal of Economic Literature by Paul Johnson and Chris Papageorgiou that says cross-country convergence doesn’t occur. The difference in the PSS post and the JP paper is that PSS look at relatively recent windows of data. For example, PSS look at whether countries that were poor in 1990 grew faster than rich countries in 1990 from 1990 to 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In constrast, JP appear to look at longer time frames. They find that there isn’t much evidence countries that were poor in 1960 grew faster than rich countries in 1960. This isn’t a contradiction with PSS. Both can be true at once. All PSS have done is indicated that around twenty-five years ago poor countries did start growing faster than rich countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implication of that finding is that poor countries are &lt;em&gt;converging&lt;/em&gt; to rich country GDP per capita. And while that statement is defensible, it does need a host of qualifications, because it doesn’t mean you should expect that developing countries are soon going to look like Western Europe. This post is meant to pick through those qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flavors-of-convergence&quot;&gt;Flavors of convergence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with a better definition of convergence. There are two kinds. Within economics, they acquired particular names, and I’ll use those to be consistent with the literature. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence: this kind of convergence occurs if the growth rate of GDP per capita is negatively related to the initial level of GDP per capita. That is, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence is defined by poor countries growing faster than rich countries.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence: this kind of convergence occurs if the variance (or any measure of dispersion, really) of GDP per capita &lt;em&gt;across&lt;/em&gt; countries shrinks. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence means the gap in GDP per capita from rich to poor gets smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence should imply &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence. And in some cases it does. Rather than GDP per capita, think about the height of the people in my house. If you plotted the growth rate of height from 2005-2018 against height in 2005 for all four of us, you’d get a negative coefficient. My two daughters were really short in 2005, but grew very fast over the next 13 years. My wife and I were both relatively tall in 2005, but neither of us grew at all. That’s &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence. In this case, if you looked at the variance of heights in 2005, that would be much larger than the variance of heights in 2018, and hence there was also &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence in my house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For height, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence implies &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence because there is not any additional noise or variance in height to worry about. I don’t wake up every day and randomly find myself 6 inches taller or shorter than I was the day before. That ensures that as my daughters grow, they really do catch up in height. I don’t get randomly taller, and they don’t get randomly shorter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of economic growth, there are random shocks to GDP per capita. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence says that poor countries, &lt;em&gt;on average&lt;/em&gt;, grow faster than rich countries. But there will be instances where poor countries have really slow, or negative, growth sometimes. Think of currency crises or political upheavals. There will be some instances where rich countries experience rapid growth. With both of these things going on, it’s entirely possible that poor countries keep falling farther behind in terms of GDP per capita, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-&lt;em&gt;divergence&lt;/em&gt;, even though the poorer they get the faster they grow on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an analogy that could help. Imagine somone one juggling bowling pins. Gravity is like&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence. If the bowling pin is up in the air, then gravity is making it fall. But every time it reaches the juggler, she throws it back up in the air. This means there is always the same amount of dispersion in the location of the pins; some are up and some are down. In other words, there is a constant amount of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence, even though the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence caused by gravity is always at work. If the juggler throws the pins up with a little less force each time, then the dispersion will decrease. If the juggler throws the pins up with more force each time, the dispersion will &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt;. Nevertheless, gravity - &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence - is still working the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic shocks act a little like the juggler, except that it isn’t just the rich countries (the ones the juggler catches) that experience shocks (the toss in the air). But the principle is similar, which is that with sufficiently large shocks, the dispersion in GDP per capita may not fall, and could even rise, over time. This is true even though &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence, like gravity, operates on countries the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of cross-country comparisons, we’re mainly interested in &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence: is the gap between poor and rich countries shrinking over time? Observing &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence in the data does not tell us whether that is true. Now, some sort of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence to occur. At some point, a poor country has to grow faster than a rich country in order to catch up. But &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence isn’t sufficient for &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence. The PSS result doesn’t mean that the dispersion of GDP per capita across countries got smaller, or will get smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;convergence-speed&quot;&gt;Convergence speed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s leave aside whether &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence implies &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence for the moment. Let’s assume that the shocks are small enough that in fact, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence is implied. The next question is &lt;em&gt;how long&lt;/em&gt; it will take a poor country to close the gap with a rich country, and the actual coefficient that PSS estimate can tell us about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make sense of this, I need a little math. The convergence relationship that PSS estimate looks like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\ln y_{t} - \ln y_0}{t} = \alpha + \beta \ln y_0.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the left is the growth rate of GDP per capita, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y\inline&quot;/&gt;, from some initial year 0 to year &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;. This is related to the initial level of GDP per capita, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_0\inline&quot;/&gt;, on the right-hand side. The strength of that relationship is measured by the coefficient &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence means that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, or that the growth rate gets smaller as the initial level of income gets higher. How large (in absolute value) &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is determines how strong that effect is. The extra parameter &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt; is a baseline growth rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little re-arrangment of this gives us&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\ln y_t = \alpha t + (1 + \beta t) \ln y_0&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is the level of GDP per capita at time &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;, given initial GDP per capita at time 0. That multiplicative term &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta t\inline&quot;/&gt; is the effect of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this, here’s a question we could ask. Given a poor country has &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_0^{Poor}\inline&quot;/&gt; that is only 10% of the value in a rich country, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_0^{Rich}\inline&quot;/&gt;, how long will it take (i.e. how big does &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt; have to be) before &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_t^{Poor}\inline&quot;/&gt; is 90% of the value in the rich country, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_t^{Rich}\inline&quot;/&gt;? Given the set-up, this &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; happen at some point. I didn’t add any of the shocks mentioned above that could keep spreading these two countries apart. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence will eventually win out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this hypothetical time &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;, we want that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_t^{Poor}/y_t^{Rich} = .9\inline&quot;/&gt;, which if you take logs and plug in from the above equation, gives us&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\ln .9 = \alpha t + (1 + \beta t) \ln y_0^{Poor} - \alpha t - (1 + \beta t) \ln y_0^{Rich}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and we can simplify this to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\ln .9 = (1 + \beta t) (\ln y_0^{Poor} - \ln y_0^{Rich}).&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also said that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_0^{Poor}/y_0^{Rich} = .1\inline&quot;/&gt;, so taking logs of that, we can plug in and get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\ln .9 = (1 + \beta t) \ln .1&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and now re-arrange to solve for time &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;t = \frac{\frac{\ln .9}{\ln .1} - 1}{\beta}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how long it will take the poor country to go from 10% of rich country GDP per capita to 90% per capita. And you could plug in other numbers in the obvious spots here to think about the time to go from 20% to 99%, or whatever you wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is that the absolute size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; matters. The smaller is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; in absolute value, the more time it takes to converge. Now, what PSS show is that in samples that only run through 2000, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; was about 0, which means that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt; is essentially infinity. With no &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence, there isn’t a way for the poor country to ever catch up, because it doesn’t grow faster than the rich country. But with later samples, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, so they can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their biggest estimate value is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta = -.005\inline&quot;/&gt;, not very big. Plugging that into the above equation implies that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t = 190\inline&quot;/&gt;, or it will take about 190 years for a country to go from 10% of rich-country GDP per capita to 90%. That’s a loooong time. So even in the case where we assume that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence leads to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence (i.e. the ratio goes from 10% to 90%), and ignore the possibility that shocks keep spreading things out, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence may not imply much noticeable &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sigma\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence over the next few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;absolute-and-conditional-convergence&quot;&gt;Absolute and conditional convergence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSS result of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta = -.005\inline&quot;/&gt; is small. At the same time, you will see references that the convergence coefficient is more like &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta = -0.02\inline&quot;/&gt; in the literature. Probably the most famous of these papers are from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/oup/qjecon/v106y1991i2p407-443..html&quot;&gt;Barro&lt;/a&gt; in 1991 and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/ucp/jpolec/v100y1992i2p223-51.html&quot;&gt;Barro and Sala-i-Martin&lt;/a&gt; in 1992. There are a host of other papers offering more estimates of this parameter, but I think it is fair to say that -0.02 is a good eyeball average of those results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we have to be a little careful here in these older results to PSS. PSS estimate &lt;em&gt;unconditional&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence, meaning they just making raw comparisons of growth in GDP per capita against initial GDP per capita across countries. Their result implies that poorer countries grow (a little bit) faster than rich countries, and that this doesn’t depend (is unconditional) on characteristics of those countries. It says that if you are poor, no matter &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you are poor, you grow a little faster than rich countries, no matter &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they are rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original convergence literature did the same kind of unconditional analysis, and found nothing. That is the point, in some sense, of the PSS note. But that original literature did find evidence for &lt;em&gt;conditional&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence. This means that if you look only at groups of countries that have similar characteristics (e.g. savings rate, human capital levels, etc..) then you find &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence in those groups - the poorer ones grow faster than the rich ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;across&lt;/em&gt; groups, there was no tendency for &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence. For example, if you looked only at the OECD countries, you’d see pretty strong evidence of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence, with an estimate of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta = -0.02\inline&quot;/&gt;, roughly. And if you looked only at the set of Sub-Saharan African countries, you’d see similar evidence of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence. But, there was no tendency for SSA countries as a group to grow faster than OECD countries. It was only that &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the group of SSA countries, poorer ones grew faster, and &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the group of OECD countries, poorer ones grew faster. You can find this notion of conditional - or “club” - convergence in blog-favorite William Baumol’s 1986 &lt;a href=&quot;http://piketty.pse.ens.fr/files/Baumol1986.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that was one of the first to think about this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different way of looking at conditional convergence was to use data on states or prefectures within a single country. They would all have roughly similar characteristics relative to countries (e.g. Texas and Florida differ, but that difference pales in comparison to the difference between Texas and Nigeria). And within countries, the evidence seems was clear that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence happens. Again, these coefficients were usually around &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta = -0.02\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta = -0.02\inline&quot;/&gt; number implies much faster convergence. If you think of a poor state that had 10% GDP per capita relative to a rich state, then it would only take about 48 years for it to reach 90% of GDP per capita of the rich state. That’s, not surprisingly, one-fourth the time it takes a poor country to catch up to a rich one. It’s also one way of thinking about why we don’t see U.S. states with only 10% the GDP per capita of rich ones. Any time a gap opens up, it tends to dissipate. Although I need to note that there is some recent research saying that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence across U.S. states no longer occurs. Let’s leave that aside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which number is right, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta=-0.005\inline&quot;/&gt; or &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta = -0.02\inline&quot;/&gt;? Neither. They don’t measure the same thing. The former is for unconditional cross-country convergence in the last 25 years, the latter is appropriate for conditional convergence or within-country convergence. Both can be true in their individual setting. Individual provinces within Kenya might converge very quickly, even though Kenya as a whole isn’t converging very quickly to U.S. GDP per capita.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-does-convergence-tell-us&quot;&gt;What does convergence tell us?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of convergence results depends on what you’re after. The &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; value that PSS report, similar to every other estimated &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; value, tells you whether &lt;em&gt;on average&lt;/em&gt; poor countries grow faster than rich ones. But that doesn’t make it very informative about any particular country. It certainly won’t tell you whether to expect some kind of growth miracle or disaster to occur in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I mean. I took the Penn World Tables, one of the datasets used by PSS, and plotted the data used to estimate &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. You’ve got the average growth rate of GDP per capita from 1990 to 2014 on the y-axis, against the (log) of GDP per capita in 1990 on the x-axis. The downward-sloped dashed line is the best fit to this data, and the slope of that line is about -.005, the PSS estimate of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_convergence.png&quot; alt=&quot;Convergence&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can see that this hides a lot of variation. I labelled a few countries for reference. The USA and Japan (JPN), out on the right, can be the stand-in for the “Rich” countries. You can also see China (CHN) and India (IND), both of which had growth rates well above the estimated relationship, and hence they converged much faster towards rich-country GDP per capita. This would set them apart from the Central African Republic (CAF) and Zimbabwe (ZWE), who both started out relatively poor, but &lt;em&gt;shrank&lt;/em&gt; in terms of GDP per capita, and fell even further behind the USA and JPN. I also threw South Korea (KOR) in there, as an example of a country that closed almost the entire gap with JPN from 1990 to 2014, although many other countries with a similar level of GDP per capita in 1990 did not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crude way of seeing how useful the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence result is comes from looking at the R-squared of the regression that was used to estimate &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. It’s 0.0462. In other words, 95.38% of the variation in growth rates from 1990 to 2014 is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; explained by how poor a country was in 1990. Yes, there is evidence here for unconditional convergence &lt;em&gt;on average&lt;/em&gt;. But plenty of countries grew slower than necessary to converge to rich country levels of GDP per capita.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is probably best not to think of unconditional &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence as representing some kind of structural truth about economic growth. If it were, you’d expect it to show up regardless of the exact time frame looked at, and PSS show that’s not the case. It’s better to think of it as a summary statistic of the general experience of poor countries in a given time frame. The PSS results tell us that &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; changed around 1990 such that many poor countries grew faster than rich countries, relative to the period from 1960 to 1990. But it doesn’t tell us what or why it changed, or if it will persist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t make the PSS estimate spurious. It’s a nice descriptive result that tells us we should think a little more about what might have changed around those years, even if the implication of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;-convergence from that period is not that strong.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Involution and growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Involution/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Involution/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a long-promised, long-simmering, longer-than-necessary post on the concept of involution. This term comes up often in discussions of Asian and/or Chinese development, or the lack thereof relative to western Europe. You can find several definitions, which is one of the problems with the concept. Perhaps the best way to give you a sense of what it means is that the Platonic use of the term would be “Rather than developing like western Europe, the Yangzi Delta involuted.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the term arose because scholars were searching for some shorthand for what happened in Asian historical development (it is almost always used with respect to Asia) to set it apart from what happened in Europe. But just saying Asia was different than Europe is of no help; of course it is. So is there anything to the concept of involution that is useful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;geertz-and-the-subtleties-of-involution&quot;&gt;Geertz and the subtleties of involution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classic reference for the term involution in the study of economic development comes from Clifford Geertz’ &lt;em&gt;Agricultural Involution: The processes of ecological change in Indonesia&lt;/em&gt;. Geertz borrowed the term from an anthropologist, Alexander Goldenweiser, who used it to describe a situation in which the crafts or art of a society stuck with the same fundamental patterns, only making them more an more intricate over time. Think of mosaic tiles, as an example. The patterns you create in a mosaic may get more complex, or the individual tiles may get smaller, or you may find a way to create new color. But in the end you are still doing mosaics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geertz adopted the word as a description of how village society in Indonesia, in particular in the sawah (i.e. paddy rice growing) heartland of Java, had adapted to the growth in population,  colonization by the Dutch, and the introduction of sugar as an export crop. His concept was that the villages did not change in a fundamental way during all this, even as they incorporated sugar production alongside paddy rice, but simply refined their existing social structures to further support small scale intense labor use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those social structures included how land and labor was rented, hired, and shared across families. Geertz’ idea of involution meant that this became more particular over time. Perhaps people went from renting “about half” of another families rice paddy to renting “the part of the field on the west side of a line drawn from between these precise property markers”. In a situation of high population density, it would matter whether a specific rice plant was on my side or your side of the line. The basic concept of renting in land to feed your family wasn’t different, the details of it were. This is why I think the mosaic analogy is nice. You can imagine the management of land being done at smaller scales - by the plant - rather than larger scales - by the paddy. Labor would have faced a similar process, going from generic obligations to hyper-specific exchanges of tasks and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; come along with all this refinement in agricultural relationships was growth in output per worker. That refinement allowed output per worker to tread water, given increases in population, and that was it. Involution, in Geertz’ original conception, was a situation where technological changes (i.e. sugar and rubber) as well as market changes (i.e. exposure to the Dutch trading network) occurred but there were no real changes in social structure or living standards. The village life in Indonesia did not become more market-oriented or commercialize in a way that one familiar with western European or English economic history might have expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geertz identified a few particular characteristics of Indonesia in the colonial period that were associated with involution. First, there was paddy rice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Wet-rice cultivation, with its extraordinary ability to maintain levels of marginal labor productivity by always managing to work one more man in without a serious fall in per-capita income, soaked up almost the whole of the additional population that Western intrusion created, at least indirectly. It is this ultimately self-defeating process that I have proposed to call “agricultural involution”. (Geertz, p. 80)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see some of the importance of the reaction of the marginal product of labor in rice by comparing the involution that occurred in the sawah areas of Indonesia with the areas that used swidden agriculture, which involves a slash-and-burn approach. In those swidden areas, which often became centers for rubber production, he finds some real changes in commercialization and market orientation after they are linked into the trading network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second important characteristic for involution was the relationship with the Dutch, and the idea that Indonesia was an effective agricultural hinterland for Amsterdam. Thus money and goods flowed back and forth, but there was almost no flow of &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;. For Geertz, the importance of this showed up in a comparison of Java and Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… where Japanese peasant agriculture came to be complementarily related to an expanding manufacturing system in indigenous hands, Javanese peasant agriculture came to be complementarily related to an expanding agro-industrial structure under foreign management. … in Java most of the invigorating effect of the flourishing agro-industrial sector was exercised upon Holland, and its impact upon the peasant sector was … enervating. (Geertz, p. 135)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hang on to those distinct characteristics for a moment, because I’ll come back to both in a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-crude-conception-of-involution&quot;&gt;The crude conception of involution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following Geertz, the term involution has been applied in a number of different contexts to describe development, or its lack. But relative to Geertz, the actual content of the term “involution” devolved from subtlety to something more crude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not the only example of this, one particular example I’ll use is Philip Huang’s work on Chinese development, both in his 1985 book on &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2CKh7lf&quot;&gt;Northern China&lt;/a&gt;, and in his 1990 book on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2ChnJGB&quot;&gt;Yangzi Delta&lt;/a&gt;. The 1990 book defines three types of agrarian economic change. First is development, where output expands faster than labor input, so output per worker grows. Second is intensification, where output expands at the same rate as labor, so that output per worker stays the same. Finally is involution, which is when output expands but at a slower rate than labor, so that output per worker falls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implicit in Huang’s conception is again the idea that there were technological and market changes taking place in the Chinese economy, but what differed by region within China, or differed between China and Europe, was the response to that. For much of China, and in particular the Yangzi delta, Huang identifies the outcome as involution, by his crude definition. He identifies changes in the type of crops produced (e.g. cotton, tobacco, maize, silk) and in family work relationships (e.g. an expansion of women’s role in producing goods for sale), but does not explore, like Geertz, the refinement or hyper-specialization of agrarian relationships within these areas. Here’s a sense of what Huang has in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is not to say that there was no modernization at all in crop production and rural industry in the Yangzi Delta. The example of the first three decades of postrevolutionary rural China, during which income per farm person stagnated side by side with vigorous agricultural modernization (tractor plowing, electrified pumping, chemical fertilizers, scientific seed selection, and the like) and urban development, should alert us to the fact that neither is precluded by involutionary growth. (Huang, 1990, p. 129)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the concept of involution is really about how per-worker or per-capita outcomes could stagnate or fall despite expansions in absolute output, and at the same time as significant technological and commercial changes. This observation of involution is argued to run back through Chinese history to at least 1350, the scope of Huang’s book. That isn’t to say that Huang ignores social changes, quite the contrary. Most of his work is about changes in social structures that took place in adapting to the technological and commercial changes that occurred. But that social change was not involutionary in the sense that Geertz proposed originally, as it was not necessarily a refinement of existing social or agrarian structures, but rather involved significant changes in those structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a side debate to be had on whether output per worker in fact &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; stagnate, and even if it did, whether that level of output per worker was similar to those seen in Northwest Europe, or below. Huang’s argument is that it did stagnate, and stagnate at a low level, as opposed to the California School types like &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2pRsKOQ&quot;&gt;Ken Pomeranz&lt;/a&gt; who argue that the Yangzi, at least, was equivalent in living standards to Northwest Europe just prior to the Industrial Revolution. You can see the May 2002 issue of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-asian-studies/issue/3222A2F9ADD9F71283E271C62C080486&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Asian Studies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which contains several articles dedicated to this debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;involution-as-a-malthusian-outcome&quot;&gt;Involution as a Malthusian outcome&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave aside the debate on the exact level of living standards in the Yangzi. Let’s assume that in fact they were stagnant, and stagnant at a low level. Is the term involution useful as an analytical concept for understanding why this occurred? No, as far as I’m concerned. At least involution in the crude sense of the word. It is just a word that describes what happened, but doesn’t contain any explanatory power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t know why we need that extra word when we’ve got a reasonable analytical model - Malthus - that allows one to think about the relationship of output per worker, population density, and the effect of changes in technology. It has the advantage of being clear on how those things are related, while also highlighting that the response of family formation and fertility to changes in output per worker is central to the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malthus, however, does not appear in either Geertz or in Huang’s work, not even in passing. For Geertz, this is particularly odd, because he absolutely nails the logic and implications of a Malthusian model. Here he is talking about how the sawah system adapted to new crops (e.g. sugar) and what it implied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… the maintenance of the marginal productivity at some low but nearly constant (or perhaps gradually declining) figure. It merely gave the multiplying Javanese a bigger pool in which more of them could tread water. (Geertz, p. 94)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always wondered if Malthus was so &lt;em&gt;obvious&lt;/em&gt; to Geertz that he didn’t seem worth mentioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Huang’s work - and in similar pieces - the absence of Malthus is more problematic. The goal was to explain the historical development of China, or perhaps another area in south or southeast Asia. In particular, explain why that historical development differed from Europe, given that many similar forces were at work in the sense of technological change, commercial changes, and expansion of markets. Because the outcomes differed, the presumption was that Asian development must have operated on different principles than European development, and hence involution became a necessary concept to set it apart from whatever it is that happened in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that the Malthusian setting can make sense of the both outcomes. Which is not to say that Europe and Asia were identical outside of some lucky shock, or that the particular institutional details are not important or interesting, but just that we don’t need a new concept like involution to think through the two settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard Malthusian model has two key elements. A negative relationship of the size of population and living standards (thanks to a fixed or nearly fixed resource base), and a positive relationship of population growth and living standards. Put those two together, and you will find that no matter where you start, the economy is pushed towards a stagnant level of output per worker. When times are good, more people are born/survive, the population grows, and this drives down living standards. When times are bad, few people born/survive, and the population shrinks, and this drives up living standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And stated that way, the logic of the Malthusian model doesn’t seem to apply. Because what we see is that the population in China, or Indonesia, or any other setting that involution was applied to, &lt;em&gt;grew&lt;/em&gt; over time, almost without fail. It would seem that the Malthusian model can get the stagnation right, but cannot fit with the rising population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that it can, without too much trouble, once you allow for persistent growth in technology/productivity. The implication of this in the Malthusian model is one thing that is not very intuitive. If there is productivity growth, then there should be growth in living standards, right? Kind of. As long as population growth is still positively related to living standards, then productivity growth means growth in living standards, which increases population growth, which puts a drag on growth in living standards, as per the basic version of the Malthusian model. At some point, the positive effect of productivity growth will be offset by the negative drag of population growth, and output per worker will become stagnant again, even though productivity growth continues. And even more important, at that stagnant equilibrium in living standards, population growth remains &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you can see where I’m going here. It is entirely within the scope of a Malthusian economy to have (1) positive productivity changes such as increased commercialization and market access, (2) positive population growth, and (3) stagnant output per worker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the idea that output per worker was &lt;em&gt;falling&lt;/em&gt; over time, as Huang argues? That is still understandable within the context of the Malthusian setup. If the economy is not right at the equilibrium point, but has living standards slightly above that equilibrium for whatever reason, then those living standards fall over time towards the stagnant level. And that transition can take a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time. Nippe Lagerlof has a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nippelagerlof.com/research/happening/Waves_April_2018_post.pdf&quot;&gt;recent paper&lt;/a&gt; working out that given realistic demographics, it can take &lt;em&gt;centuries&lt;/em&gt; for a Malthusian economy to slide towards its equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess you could call all this involution if you felt like it, but I’m not sure why I need a special name for a particular outcome of the model. I’d reserve the term involution for Geertz’ specific idea that - as part of a Malthusian outcome - the agrarian or social relationships within an economy may evolve to a more refined or hyper-specialized version of themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing that the Malthusian model suggests we should be concerned with are the particulars of fertility rates and family formation. To the extent that fertility is more, or less, sensitive to living standards, this will change the speed at which a Malthusian economy reaches equilibrium, and determine the level of living standards in that equilibrium. You can see this, and all of the nuances of the Malthusian setting, in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0Bw0xeVVYEG5XOURQR1Y1NnFKVlk/edit&quot;&gt;Ashraf and Galor&lt;/a&gt; paper, which has a very nice simple description of the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, work on involution does not delve into the particulars of fertility and family formation. Huang’s two books, for instance, contain only a few passing asides to fertility rates and why they may have been insensitive to living standards (which would have led to low equilibrium living standards and slow transitions). Using the concept of involution, as opposed to a Malthusian setting, buries the importance of these fertility/family differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-made-asia-different&quot;&gt;What made Asia different?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fine. Let’s say that crude involution is just one kind of Malthusian outcome, and a more sophisticated take on involution looks like Geertz’ definition. Why did crude involution appear to occur in Asia relative to Europe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the first answer to that is that crude involution &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; take place in many places in Europe, for a lot of Europe’s history. Despite &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Leisure/&quot;&gt;some evidence&lt;/a&gt; that specific places within Europe - like England - may have been experiencing growth in output per worker earlier than we thought, most of Europe up until the late 1800s could still be explained within the context of a Malthusian model with modest gains in productivity over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there were places within Europe that saw commercial and market development which did lead to growth in living standards, urbanization, and ultimately sustained growth earlier than this occurred in most of Asia. Why or how did they accomplish that, if they were stuck inside the same Malthusian framework?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a partial answer - since this is essentially one of the all-time big questions in historical development - let me reach back to those two specifics that Geertz talked about with respect to Indonesia. They were, to remind you, the use of paddy or wet rice cultivation, and the absence of an urban outlet within Indonesia itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of an urban outlet comes about because it offers an alternative sink for population growth and economic activity. This tweaks the original Malthusian setting. Now, rather than saying that living standards in general have a negative relationship to population size, we would say that agricultural output per worker has a negative relationship to agricultural population size. If there is an urban area that absorbs some population growth, then the growth rate of &lt;em&gt;agricultural&lt;/em&gt; population is not as large. If the flow to urban areas is large enough, it could be that the technological change in agricultural outweighs the drag from agricultural population growth, and output per worker in agriculture could go &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall the comparison of Japan and Java that Geertz made. Beyond the lack of a sink for population growth, urban areas offered another avenue for productivity growth, due to agglomeration effects and/or gains from specialization. Hence Japan could benefit from textile production as it developed, whereas Indonesia could not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese experience included urban areas, so it was not a “pure” Malthusian economy like Indonesia, in that sense. Despite that, it still ended up in a Malthusian situation of stagnant or falling output per worker, and the urbanization rate did not appear to change much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I think the second factor identified by Geertz, the nature of paddy rice production, played a role, at least for the development of the Yangzi (North China relies on different kinds of crops). As Geertz noted, and other sources corroborate, the marginal product of labor in rice production does not fall by much as additional labor is applied.  That means output per worker in those agricultural areas is insensitive to growth in the number of workers. This turns out to be both good and bad for those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the good side of the ledger, this means that living standards in agricultural areas can handle population growth without too much trouble. The drag from population growth in a Malthusian setting is more muted in areas with paddy rice production. On the bad side of the ledger is that this means population continues to grow. In the end, what you get is that the speed at which the economy approaches the Malthusian equilibrium is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; slow. That’s good in the sense that output per worker stays about the stagnant equilibrium level for a long time, bad in the sense that output per worker is falling for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another aspect of this effect of rice production. Remember, with an urban outlet, this can slow down population growth in the agricultural area, and thus output per worker in agriculture faces less of a drag on its growth. But this doesn’t seem to have helped in China. Here’s Huang:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The involuted peasant economy was able to support very large and complex cities, and, by extension, also a highly advanced elite and urban culture, even if the surplus above subsistence produced by the average cultivator shrank from the diminished marginal returns that came with involution. The paradox is poorly understood. Large cities and advanced urban cultures are commonly associated with rural prosperity, but I would like to suggest that the opposite was actually the case in much of Chinese history. (Huang, 1990, p. 332)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll contend that the nature of rice production resolves the paradox. With rice production, rural output per worker is insensitive to rural population growth. Even if there is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of rural-to-urban migration, there is little effect on rural output per worker. The benefits of having urban outlets in China - at least the Yangzi - were not very big in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this compare to Europe, and why does it explain the lack of crude involution? In European agriculture, there are reasons to think that the marginal product of labor is very &lt;em&gt;sensitive&lt;/em&gt; to the amount of labor used. This is both bad and good. It is bad, because any population growth in agriculture leads to significant loss of output per worker. But that means population growth slows down quickly, and hence the transition to the Malthusian stagnant equilibrium is very fast. So one reason Europe may not have looked like it “involuted” is that it did not have long, drawn-out, transitions towards the Malthusian equilibrium, as in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with respect to urban outlets, which Europe had as well, the nature of agricultural production is helpful. When population growth in rural areas slows down thanks to urbanization, this has a very big effect on output per worker, because agricultural output is so sensitive to the amount of labor. Thus, relative to rice-growing areas of China, Europe had an advantage in that any urbanization it generated created this follow-on effect of improving rural output per worker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular story about the difference in the sensitivity of output to labor in different types of crop systems is something I’ve done a lot of work on - see &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/assets/eber_voll_2016.pdf}&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dvollrath/Crops/blob/master/Drafts/Constraint-Master.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/assets/JOEG_basis.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In many ways, it was thinking about involution that got me there. Another incredible source of information on this topic is Francesca Bray’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2CHXFpb&quot;&gt;The Rice Economies&lt;/a&gt;, which remains one of the very best books I’ve ever read on comparative development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I haven’t even touched on differences in family formation and fertility patterns, which would add a whole other layer on top of this. But as I’ve reached well over 3000 words at this point, we’re going to leave that aside for the time being. Suffice it to say that they were different (perhaps endogenously) and would have contributed to the different outcomes in a Malthusian setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-involution&quot;&gt;What about involution?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where does that leave me with respect to involution as a concept? It is crucial to distinguish Geertz’ notion of the refinement of agrarian practices from the cruder notion of stagnant or falling agricultural output per worker. Geertz’ definition of involution is useful in thinking about how the specific agrarian institutions we observe today came about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the crude definition of involution is just a synonym for “Malthusian equilibrium allowing for technological change”. It isn’t a problem to use a single term to stand in for a more complex phenomena. It can save you some time typing. But I think using the concept of involution without its Malthusian context leads one to do a lot more analytical work than necessary. The Malthusian setting gives you clear guidance on what the proximate determinants of living standards are. And in the Asia/China setting, the experience with respect to commercial and technological changes are not necessasrily paradoxes or mysteries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The inverse relationship of farm size and productivity</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/IFSP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/IFSP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I am an intellectual raccoon, it was not a surprise that when &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GarettJones&quot;&gt;Garett Jones&lt;/a&gt; dangled a shiny object called “the inverse farm-size productivity relationship” in front of me on Twitter, I grabbed hold with my dirty little paws and would not let go. The inverse farm-size productivity (IFSP) relationship is something I’ve been interested in since grad school, and my very first published paper has a strong link to the subject. But from Garett’s tweet, and the responses it gathered, I realized I was a bit behind on the state of this literature. And so here we are, with a blog post that is something of a literature review and something of a critical analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-origin-of-the-ifsp-fact&quot;&gt;The origin of the IFSP “fact”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by laying out what precisely the IFSP is, and some of the implications of it. Note that by the end of this post you’re going to see that the “standard” IFSP I’m going to define here is probably wrong. Still, I think it is worth seeing what it is, where it came from, and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we now think it is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IFSP is the stylized fact that small farms have higher yields per acre than large farms. In other words, output per hectare is decreasing with the number of hectares, and hence there is an &lt;em&gt;inverse&lt;/em&gt; relationship of farm size (hectares) and productivity (output per hectare).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ur-text of the IFSP literature is &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Sen_1962.pdf&quot;&gt;Sen&lt;/a&gt; (1962). Yes, I know &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/alexander_chayanov_the_theory_of_peasant_economy.pdf&quot;&gt;Chayanov&lt;/a&gt; (1926) talked about it as well in the context of Russia, but Sen’s work managed to kick off a few &lt;em&gt;decades&lt;/em&gt; worth of research, whereas Chayanov’s observation just kind of sat there for years without much response (at least within economics). Sen’s original 1962 paper does not provide any direct evidence of the IFSP. He simply mentions this (his Observation III) as something that is found to be generally valid in Indian agriculture. This conclusion is based on a series of Farm Management Surveys done in the 1950’s for several Indian states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dig back through a lot of the papers that follow Sen, they take this relationship for granted, or also appeal to the Farm Management Surveys (FMS). One of the first papers I know of that actually documents the IFSP in the FMS data is from &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Saini_1971.pdf&quot;&gt;Saini&lt;/a&gt; (1971). He looks, using the farm level data, at the elasticity of total output with respect to operational area of a farm. If that elasticity is less than one, it means that if farm size increases by 1%, output increases by &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; than 1%, and hence the yield falls. This constitutes the standard method for establishing the &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; evidence that the IFSP exists. Here’s the original table from Saini,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_saini_tab1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Saini Table 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the column labelled &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;, which is the estimated elasticity. You can see that all but three are less than one. And if you look at the second to last column, at the t-values, you see that in all but six we can reject the hypothesis that the elasticity is equal to one. On this basis, Saini says that the stylized fact of the IFSP used by Sen and others is a robust statistical relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at this point (roughly) forward, the notion that the IFSP exists in some manner becomes an established fact. Note that this is based on Indian data alone, and it will remain the case throughout this literature that the IFSP is centered around a discussion of Indian agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t until a book by &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books/about/Agrarian_Structure_and_Productivity_in_D.html?id=i_4DAAAAMAAJ&quot;&gt;Berry and Cline&lt;/a&gt; (1979) that we get some evidence for the IFSP in different contexts. The strength of the book at the time was pulling in farm-level data from different countries, and exploring the existence of the IFSP directly in each. The book, in addition, documents a number of other facts related to farm-size distributions. Which is the reason that the U of Houston library copy has lived in my office for the last 13 years (and, uh, sorry about all the margin notes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quickly, Berry and Cline examine the farm-level data and find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brazil: a regression shows a negative relationship of yield (output per area or &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?output per\inline&quot;/&gt; value of land) and the number of hectares on a farm, including controls for regions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colombia: summary data shows that yield (gross or net farm income per hectare) falls as you look at groups of larger and larger farms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Philippines: regression shows a negative relationship of yield (value-added per hectare or just value-added from crops per hectare) and the area (total hectares or cultivated hectares) across farms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pakistan: regression shows a negative relationship of yield (gross farm income per acre) with area of farms (in acres), including controls for regions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Malaysia: summary data shows that yield (value-added per hectare) falls as you look at groups of larger and larger farms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berry and Cline also confirm the findings for India. So between that original work on India, and the Berry and Cline evidence from different settings, the IFSP appears to be an established fact by the early 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unleash-the-theorists&quot;&gt;Unleash the theorists!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could not let a good stylized fact go to waste, so the economics profession quickly got to work theorizing about &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the IFSP existed. And that theorizing invariably started with an observation that the IFSP &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; exist given standard assumptions about how markets work. In this, the IFSP literature echoed the literature on share-cropping, the existence of which had bothered economists all the way back to Marshall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If people can buy, sell, or rent land at will, and if people can work for wages, hire workers for wages, and work on their own farm, and if people are attempting to maximize the profits they earn using their land (if they hold some), &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; there should be no IFSP. Let’s say you have a large farm and a small farm , but the yield on the large farm is lower than on the small farm. The large farmer should offer to rent the small farmer some land. This will reduce the large farm size, but raise its yield. The small farmer would get larger, and their yield would fall. It will make sense to keep renting land to the small(er) farmer until the yield is identical on the two farms. This will maximize the total output across the two farms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also get to this idea if we think of the labor market. The large farmer should offer to hire the small farmer for some hours of work. This would lower the yield on the small farm (less work is getting done) but raise the yield on the large farm (more work is getting done). For a similar argument, the large farmer should keep hiring more hours of the small farmer’s time until the yield across all hectares is identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, the yield on every hectare of land should be identical, no matter the actual ownership structure of the land to begin with. The fact that the yield is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; identical means we are sacrificing some output. And that didn’t make sense. It’s seems like leaving dollar bills on the sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But simply assuming that developing country farmers had some inability to see, or desire to take advantage of, these kinds of gains, was a no go. T.W. Schultz had just published in 1964 &lt;em&gt;Transforming Traditional Agriculture&lt;/em&gt;, which argued that you had to see farmers in these situations as keen optimizers (given their poverty, probably even more concious of maximizing their output than someone with a more secure lifestyle). So the game was to see under what conditions it would be that the IFSP was the result of many farmers pursuing an optimizing strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Sen_1966.pdf&quot;&gt;Sen&lt;/a&gt; (1966) laid the groundwork for one common explanation, which was that the labor employed on small farms was effectively &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; than hired workers. Because of a surplus labor situation (a la Lewis), or a low opportunity cost for family labor, or a monitoring cost for hired workers, the effective wage of family workers is lower than hired workers. For a small family farm, they “hire” more of their own labor given the relatively low effective wage, raising the labor used per hectare and raising yields. For large farms, which must hire in workers, the effective wage is higher, and as such the large farmer employs fewer workers per hectare, resulting in lower yields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That makes &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; sense, and you can get into the weeds on what exactly creates the monitoring costs or lowers the opportunity cost for family members. But regardless of the explanation, a paper by &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Feder_1985.pdf&quot;&gt;Feder&lt;/a&gt; (1985) established that a single market failure like this (i.e. a wedge in the effective wage of otherwise similar workers) cannot, by itself, account for the IFSP. The basic argument is that if only one market has a wedge or friction, the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; markets can all adjust such that the IFSP doesn’t hold. To see this, imagine that our large farmer and small farmer exist as before, and that the large farmer hires some of the small farmers time (or hires some of the small farmers family members) to work on their farm along with the large farmers own family. You could still raise output by having the large farmer rent some land to the small farmer. You would do this until the two farms were just of the size that both were being worked by only family workers. Thus output would be higher, and the work effort (and yield), would be identical across the two farms. What Feder showed was that it took &lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; market failures to deliver the IFSP. We need &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; an implicit difference in wages between family and hired labor, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; an inability to rent in/out land, for the IFSP to persist. So in that sense, the presence of the IFSP implied multiple failed or missing markets within developing countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there was another line of reasoning that attempted to explain the IFSP, based on risk. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Srinivasan_1972.pdf&quot;&gt;Srinivasan&lt;/a&gt; (1972) and &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Barrett_1996.pdf&quot;&gt;Barrett&lt;/a&gt; (1996) both considered that production risk could induce small farmers to work more intensely on their farms. A simple way to see this is to imagine that each farmer has a fixed minimum absolute amount of output that they &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to produce to survive, and that there is some uncertainty in how much their land will yield in a given year. For a small farmer, they raise the expected yield of their land to a very high level so that they eliminate (or make insignificant) the risk that a bad year leaves them without enough to eat, and hence they achieve high yields on average. For the large farmer, the absolute amount of output they get from their land is large even in a bad year, so they do not need to jack up their expected yield. Hence their observed average yield is low. (As an aside, Barrett’s paper is really about price risk for output, not risk in the actual output itself, but the same ideas apply.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A last theoretical possibilty, one that tended to get dismissed for the most part, is that farm production is decreasing returns to scale. That kind of assumes the answer, but still left open the question of why the large farmer didn’t split up or rent out their land to smaller farmers. You still needed some kind of missing market to make this one work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;implications-for-redistribution&quot;&gt;Implications for redistribution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of the IFSP in practice is that it makes a case for redistribution of land. Regardless of the underlying source of the IFSP, its presence implies that one could &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; a break up of large farms into small farms, and have higher output overall. You might imagine that one can use the extra output to compensate the large farmers, or perhaps you don’t care. Regardless, the implication of the IFSP is that an unequal distribution is &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; related to lower output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/vollrath_fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vollrath 2007 Figure 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, by they way, was what my first &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/assets/ajae_2007.pdf&quot;&gt;published paper&lt;/a&gt; was about. I looked at the relationship of country-level measures of land inequality and the output per hectare from agriculture. I found a negative relationship, and you can see the raw version of this in the figure, and it holds up once you control for all sorts of other things that you’d expect affect yields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This negative relationship is consistent with the presence of the IFSP within countries. In fact, it &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; makes sense if there is an IFSP to begin with. If you dare to believe my results were causal - and you’d want to be very, very hesitant to do that - then it supports that idea that redistributing land (lowering inequality) would be associated with higher yields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the IFSP provides one justification for land redistribution, including a relatively recent (2009) &lt;a href=&quot;http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTARD/Resources/Ag_Land_Redistribution.pdf&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; from the World Bank on the prospects for land reform. See Chapter 1, page 11. When you combine this IFSP with the historical origins of land inequality in many locations (i.e. elites controlling vast amounts of land) then the rationale for land redistribution comes from both notions of fairness and from notions of efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trying-to-explain-it-away&quot;&gt;Trying to explain it away&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the fairness motive for redistribution can exist independently of the IFSP, the efficiency argument cannot. And starting not long after the IFSP became a stylized fact, people have asking whether the IFSP represents a real efficiency loss, or just a spurious correlation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main argument for a spurious correlation is that the IFSP ignores differences in land quality. If small farmers simply have better quality land, then the higher yields make perfect sense, and there is no mystery about missing markets or effective wages. More important, if land quality differences explain the difference in yields between small and large farms, there is &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; efficiency argument for redistribution. No matter who farms a given plot of land, we’d get the same yield, so the distribution is unimportant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Carter_1984.pdf&quot;&gt;Carter&lt;/a&gt; (1984) looked at the IFSP within India, and compared farms within given villages, on the assumption that land quality was similar within a village. He found the IFSP was slightly weaker, but still existed. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Bhalla_Roy_1988.pdf&quot;&gt;Bhalla and Roy&lt;/a&gt; (1988) went back to the Indian data as well, and incorporated information on soil quality directly, finding that the IFSP weakened substantially when you control for this. Implicitly, when they controlled for soil quality, they were comparing small farms to large farms that have the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; quality of soil. And when they did that, the IFSP disappeared in most settings. They concluded that the evidence for the IFSP was weak. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Benjamin_1995.pdf&quot;&gt;Benjamin&lt;/a&gt; (1995) used Indonesian data, and came at the question indirectly. Without getting into the weeds on this, he finds that unobservable characteristics (e.g. land quality) likely explain the IFSP in the raw data, but didn’t have direct data on land quality. So there is/was some evidence that the IFSP could be accounted for by land quality, but hang onto that result for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different line of research tried to assess the source of the IFSP by looking at &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt;-household variation in yields by plots. There are a few papers that did this, but let me use &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Assuncao_Braido_2007.pdf&quot;&gt;Assuncao and Braido&lt;/a&gt; (2007) as the example here. These authors used Indian data, and were able to look not only at each farmer, but at each &lt;em&gt;plot&lt;/em&gt; used by each farmer. What they found was that there was an IFSP that held across each individual farmers plots. That is, the same farmer achieves higher yields on smaller plots than on larger plots. This suggests that household-specific explanations are not to blame for the IFSP. That is, it cannot just be that some farms use family labor and some farms have to hire in workers, and that they face different implicit prices for labor (or for other inputs). These are the same farmers, and they can adjust the labor they do use however they want across plots. Assuncao and Braido suggested instead that perhaps their result reflects unmeasured differences in land quality across the plots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a 2010 paper by &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Barrett_etal_2010.pdf&quot;&gt;Barrett, Bellemare, and Hou&lt;/a&gt; did a similar study, but with very detailed soil quality measurements done on each specific plot a farmer uses (the data is from Madagascar). What they find is that the land quality differences explain &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; of the differential yields across plot sizes, and that thus the IFSP is not due to land quality differences. What remains is possible &lt;em&gt;intra&lt;/em&gt;-household inefficiency in allocations of labor across plots, or perhaps the IFSP just reflects errors in how we measure the size of farms and/or plots. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Lamb_2003.pdf&quot;&gt;Lamb&lt;/a&gt; (2003) was one of the first to suggest the IFSP was due to some measurement error in the area of farms, but a recent paper by &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Carletto_etal_2013.pdf&quot;&gt;Carletto, Savastano, and Zezza&lt;/a&gt; (2013) using data from Uganda that uses GPS tracking claims that accurate measurement of plots actually &lt;em&gt;reinforces&lt;/em&gt; the IFSP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means we might be down to just intra-household explanations. And at that point I’m not sure what to tell you, because then it becomes closer to saying that farmers are leaving dollar bills on the sidewalk (or that there is some additional unmeasured difference in land quality we just cannot capture).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-u-shaped-relationship&quot;&gt;The U-shaped relationship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before we leave the IFSP behind, we have to check in with another recent paper from &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/papers/Foster_Rosenzweig_2017.pdf&quot;&gt;Foster and Rosenzweig&lt;/a&gt; (2017) that tells us that the stylized facts behind the IFSP are in fact incorrect, and that what we should be looking at is the U-shaped relationship of yields and farm size. While among relatively small farms in developing countries we see the IFSP, this does not capture what is seen in more developed economies, where yields &lt;em&gt;rise&lt;/em&gt; as farm size increases. By itself, that might not be very interesting, as it may be a little like comparing apples and oranges. But what the authors show is that using more recent data from India there is a clear U-shaped relationship of farm size and yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fr_fig6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Foster and Rosenzweig Figure 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure shows the raw data they use to make this claim, and the U-shape is obvious. Above 10 acres, yields rise with size. Now, you can subject this to similar types of analysis to what I explained in the prior section, such as controlling for soil quality and looking only at plots run by a single given farmer. In each case, they find that the U-shape persists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fr_fig8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Foster and Rosenzweig Figure 8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second figure shows the yields after controlling for these things. The blue line shows the case when they looked across farmers plots, and controlled for soil quality. The squiggly nature of the estimated line comes from the fact that they are allowing for a flexible estimation, and so small variations in yields are going to show up in the line. Nevertheless, the U-shape still appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is really interesting is that this is essentially the same analysis that was done in Assuncao and Braido. But those authors used Indian data from 1975-1984, while Foster and Rosenzweig are using Indian data from 2009-2014. It is possible that the IFSP held as expected in the earlier period, and it is only with subsequent development (e.g. the availability of new types of capital goods) that the upward slope among large farms appeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FR work out a theory that can help explain the U-shape, and it really is a nesting of two explanations. First, they assume that there are some labor market issues as the classic IFSP explanations use. First, labor gets more expensive as farms get larger (when farms are small). Second, capital goods require a minimum scale of farm or plot to use, but these capital goods are really productive. Hence you see yields fall from very small to medium-sized farms due to the effect of rising labor costs, and then somewhere around 10 hectares (in this data) it starts to make sense to use capital goods, which starts to raise yields as you get bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that one of the implications of the IFSP could be that land redistribution would increase output. This is no longer so clear with the FR results. If you took all the land and redistributed it out in 10-hectare parcels, so that there was no inequality in land holdings, you’d get the &lt;em&gt;lowest&lt;/em&gt; possible yield from the land. Your best bet, given their data, is to redistribute such that you &lt;em&gt;maximized&lt;/em&gt; inequality, with a bunch of very small farms (high yields due to low labor costs) and very large farms (big enough to use capital).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FR results bring back in some notions of earlier ag and development economists suggesting that fostering agricultural consolidation, and encouraging large farms that could leverage modern capital and techniques, was the best way to raise agricultural output. That strategy faced the problem of explaining what exactly the now-landless small farmers were supposed to do, but from the IFSP facts that suggested it would not actually raise yields. Does the calculus change if you know yields would actually rise given a consolidation of land into large farms? Would it allow you enough resources to compensate the small holders who lost land - assuming that you could figure out a way to actually make that compensation happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of its relevance for thinking about the aggregate level of production in agriculture, and the possible effects of land redistribution, the IFSP and/or U-shaped relationship remains a relevant topic for development economics. What I think remains the really key question is why the IFSP part of the relationship appears to hold &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; households, where the farmers should face fewer frictions to allocating resources. Quick gut reactions are that it might have to do with distance (e.g. large plots tend to be located far away?) or some kind of limited stock of management ability/attention that can be allocated by a farmer to different plots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you go, Garett. Now I’m done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Detecting changes in trend growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-Again/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-Again/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick aside before I start the main part of the post. My blogging has been sparse in the last few months, or even year. This was in large part a reaction to working on a book about the growth slowdown, and time that would have gone into posts got poured into that book. Topics that I would have addressed in posts here got folded into the text of that book. As a few days ago, I’ve got a contract to publish that with the U. of Chicago Press, and it should come out in 2019. There is still some revising to do, but at this point I should get back to some more regular blogging, as I’m out of the weeds on getting the book drafted. Famous last words, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to actual posting. One of the very early posts on this blog, back in 2014, asked “&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/is-robert-gordon-right-about-u-s-growth/&quot;&gt;Is Robert Gordon right about U.S. growth?&lt;/a&gt;”. Gordon had written a few pieces explaining that, as of 2007, the trend growth rate of GDP per capita in the U.S. was 0.9%. That is just under half of the trend growth rate that held through most of the 20th century and up to 2007, roughly 2% per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I did in that post was point out that it would take several years to accumulate enough evidence to reject the hypothesis (in a statistical sense) that the growth rate was still 2%. The issue is that there are fluctuations in GDP per capita around trend (e.g. recessions, booms), and thus it was possible that GDP per capita could still have a 2% trend growth rate, yet GDP per capita could grow quite slowly for a few years due to the effects of the financial crisis or other fluctuations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I came up with in that post was that it would be 2018 before we could make some concrete statements about whether the trend growth rate had fallen below 2%. I really should wait until next year when the data from 2018 are available, but nevertheless it seemed interesting to revisit this question now that we’ve got more evidence on GDP per capita from the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in evaluating whether trend growth has dropped below 2% it turns out to be important to distinguish between changes in the growth rate and changes in the level of GDP per capita. The distinction of the level and growth rate is similar to the distinction between the lane you are in on a highway, and your forward speed. Your forward speed could be identical in either lane in the long run, but if you change lanes (i.e. there is a level shift) your &lt;em&gt;forward&lt;/em&gt; speed (i.e. the growth rate) will drop for a few moments as you transfer some of that into moving sideways. And we don’t want to use the temporary drop in forward speed from changing lanes to make an inference about your long-run forward speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this setting, we could think of two versions of Gordon’s hypothesis. The first is that the growth rate changed in 2007, but there was no level shift. That is like saying that you stayed in the same lane, but the car slowed down. The second is that there was a level shift in 2007 - you changed lanes - &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; that the car slowed down once you got into the new lane. It will be much easier to detect the change in speed in the first situation than in the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I’m calling this “Gordon’s hypothesis”, but the general idea that the trend growth rate has dropped is not a unique prediction of his, and is probably the default hypothesis for most people who pay attention to the economy. He just put a specific number on the drop, so it makes his prediction more tangible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-simple-drop-in-the-growth-rate&quot;&gt;A simple drop in the growth rate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the first version of Gordon’s argument, that the growth rate dropped in 2007, but there was no level shift. Taking that as the alternative, I did some very crude calculations in the original post asking when it might be plausible to reject the hypothesis that trend growth was still 2%. The intuition of those calculations was that if trend growth was in fact 0.9% - if we had slowed down - then eventually GDP per capita would fall so far below the 2% trend that we’d have to reject that growth was still 2%. At some point in time it wouldn’t be plausible anymore that all we were seeing were some fluctuation that took us below trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_gordon_trend.png&quot; alt=&quot;Trends&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure tries to give you some visual for this situation. The solid black line represents the old trend line, estimated using data from 1950 to 2007 (the actual growth rate of this is about 2.1%). The gray lines above and below that 2% trend line are the error bands, meaning that if GDP per capita were in that range, we couldn’t reject that 2% trend growth was accurate. What you also see is the dashed black line representing 0.9% growth starting in 2007, Gordon’s hypothesis. And again, there are gray error bands around this showing where we might expect GDP per capita to be if 0.9% growth was true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can see the thick black line tracking actual GDP per capita. The financial crisis in 2009 drops the economy below all the error bands, which just represents how dramatic the crisis was relative to the normal fluctuations we might expect in GDP per capita. Since 2009, GDP per capita continued to track upward, but not very rapidly. What seems to be clear from this figure is that GDP per capita is well outside of the 2% error bands, and has been for several years. From this we should reject 2% trend growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that mean Gordon is right? In favor of the 0.9% hypothesis is that GDP per capita falls within the error bands of that trend. Which means we &lt;em&gt;cannot reject&lt;/em&gt; 0.9% growth. But that is different than saying 0.9% is &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;. We also cannot reject 1% growth, or 0.7% growth. Nevertheless, whether we want to buy Gordon’s precise 0.9% alternative, it would appear that the old trend line no longer applies. We’re just too far out of range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;separating-trend-growth-and-trend-level&quot;&gt;Separating trend growth and trend level&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before we dispense with 2% trend growth, we need to think about the distinction of the growth rate and the level. It is quite possible that the financial crisis shifted the &lt;em&gt;level&lt;/em&gt; of GDP per capita down, but that the growth rate of GDP per capita remained around 2% on trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_gordon_shift.png&quot; alt=&quot;Level shift&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see what I mean, take a look at this next figure. Here, what I’ve done is show what a simple level shift - a lane change - looks like for the economy that keeps the 2% trend growth rate. I eyeballed the level shift so that the financial crisis set the new level. But given that new lower level, the growth rate stays the same, and so the dashed lines show the trend and error bands we could expect for GDP per capita after the shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, it is less obvious that we can reject a trend 2% growth rate. The actual path of GDP per capita is still within the error bands of 2% growth &lt;em&gt;given the new level&lt;/em&gt;. We are just about to scrape outside of those error bands, so within the next year or so, barring an economic miracle, you’d probably reject 2% growth even if you believed there was a level shift after the financial crisis. But we’re not quite there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, even if next year we decide that we can reject a trend 2% growth rate, that is different from accepting that growth is 0.9%. All we’ll know is that it &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt; 2%. It might be 1.7%, or 1.5%, or something else. But even if we can’t say that Gordon’s prediction is &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; precisely, we could certainly say that he is right that the trend growth rate is &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; than it was prior to 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;long-run-implications&quot;&gt;Long run implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction I’m making here between the two situations may seem overblown. Regardless of the scenario, we definitely seem to be below the old trend line. True, but the implications of the two scenarios for the future are very different. If we really are going to experience 0.9 or 1% growth for the indefinite future, that is far &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; than experiencing a level shift in GDP per capita followed by continued 2% growth (or something like 1.5% growth). Compounding always wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go back to 2007, and start there. Now extrapolate out different scenarios to 2040. On the old trend line, GDP per capita in 2040 would be almost exactly 2 times (98%) higher than in 2007. If starting in 2007 the trend growth rate dropped to 0.9%, then GDP per capita in 2040 would be only 35% higher than in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there was a level shift after 2007 that lowered the trend line by 9% (what I drew in the figure), but the growth rate remained at 2%, then in 2040 GDP per capita would be 81% higher than in 2007. That’s much better than in the situation with the lower growth rate. And even if there is a level shift &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the growth rate drops to 1.5%, we’d still have GDP per capita in 2040 48% higher than in 2007. Still better off than if the growth rate dropped to 0.9% per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that you don’t want to confuse the scenarios with growth changes and level shifts. These have very distinct implications for the future. And the available evidence on GDP per capita doesn’t tell us which of these scenarios is right, and which is wrong. All we know is that we can reject the old 2% trend line, but we’ll need more evidence before we can figure out whether we saw a drop to a lower growth rate only, or a level shift and possible drop int he growth rate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What determines value?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Value-Everything/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Value-Everything/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2z9NWXJ&quot;&gt;The Value of Everything&lt;/a&gt;, by Mariana Mazzucato, a few weeks ago, and have finally gotten around to writing up something of a review. This book made me think, so I count that as a positive recommendation. Sometimes I was thinking things like, “This is ridiculous, you cannot refuse to acknowledge the difference in stocks and flows!”, but in between those there were some genuine moments where Mazzucato got me to see things from a different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mazzucato makes the point - obvious in retrospect but easy to forget - that the value of economic activity involves a choice. A choice of what “counts” as having value, and what does not. In exploring this, she works through the systems that past writers have used, and compares that to ideas that underlay our current thinking. This is not just a question of “what gets counted in GDP?”, but intended to be broader. Her question is something like, “by using GDP what implicit decisions have we made about what has economic value?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The threads of her answer come a little undone by later in the book. After setting up the contingent nature of measuring economic value, she moves into questioning why finance is assigned too much value, while government is assigned too little. I think she intends all this to be radical, but I think the book fails to provide the real kill shot on this. A radical book would outline a new means of assigning value, even in vague terms, but I didn’t get that here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, as I said the book did get me thinking on several points. What follows then is far less in the way of review, and more speculative response. Caveat emptor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-counts-as-valuable&quot;&gt;What counts as valuable?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What became apparent to me in reading Mazzucato’s history was that in most cases, the notion of what counted as valuable in the economy had less to do with &lt;em&gt;output&lt;/em&gt;, and more to do with the &lt;em&gt;inputs&lt;/em&gt;. The Physiocrats, for example, explained that economic value came from agriculture alone. If something was produced using the land, and some sturdy peasants and perhaps some draft animals, then that something had economic value. Any other transactions that took place, like people moving or trading grain, didn’t add value. They shuffled value around between the movers or traders, but didn’t create value. You could increase value only by adding land, peasants, or animals. I’d guess that if you pressed the Physiocrat line, you could allow for technological change in agriculture to raise value, but regardless, value was assigned only to output coming from a specific set of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not a big leap from here to Marx, where value was located in the labor effort that went into a product. Marx dropped the focus on land or agriculture, per se, but retained the concept that what determined whether output had value was whether it used labor. You could have a hypothetical factory that ran on complete automation, and used no labor. That output could only have value from digging back into the labor used in producing the factory, etc.., but the point is similar to the Physiocrats. It took the “right” inputs to create value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to snort at the ideas of the Physiocrats and Marx regarding this kind of thinking. But I’d argue that the most peoples intuitive sense of “economic value” still comes back to their sense of which inputs were used. Much like Marx, most people will attribute value to output based on the perceived labor effort that went into producing it. Like the Physiocrats, production that involves extracting or processing raw materials is considered to have value. Again, it takes the “right” inputs to create value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see examples of this all over the place. To demonstrate the Physiocrat/Marxist attitude, I give you Commerce Secretary Wilbur Ross, whose Senate testimony on Trump’s tariffs is quated in this article from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/2018/06/20/wilbur-ross-canada-steel_a_23463975/&quot;&gt;Huffington Post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We don’t have a trade deficit of note (on steel),” Ross replied. “We have a surplus in dollars; we do not have a surplus in physical value.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could do a whole class unpacking the incoherence of that statement. But let’s focus on the fact that what ultimately matters to Ross is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the notion of dollars, but rather the “physical value”. Steel is built from “real” inputs, so it has a real value beyond anything that we can measure with dollars. I think you can get some traction in thinking about the motives behind tariffs (and support for them) if you consider this notion of value. We can be “losing” at trade because we import things of value (based on their input content) from abroad, even if the associated money flows don’t look so bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a different context, when people argue for a minimum wage, or a “living wage”, they often appeal to the idea that a hard days work (e.g. the input) grants the work value different from and beyond the dollar value that work earns on the open market. Support for family farms has a similar language of value based on fact that it employs physical labor and - Physiocratic-style - land. It is seen as unfair if this labor and land does not generate a large monetary value, because we assign inherent value to those inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see something of this in the original sets of national accounts, where far more attention was paid to counting up manufacturing output (based on real inputs like labor and coal and iron) that to service output (which presumably used less inherently valuable labor, and, &lt;em&gt;gasp&lt;/em&gt;, no iron ore at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sense that finance doesn’t “count” works in a similar way. The inputs that go into finance work - people sitting at desks being clever - aren’t assigned value by themselves. The notion of “bullshit” jobs is another example of judging value based on the nature of the input - presumably sitting at a desk and stapling. No one considers farming or mining or manufacturing a “bullshit” job, why? Because they involve “real” labor input, physical work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mazzucato engages in this type of argument, although she doesn’t phrase it this way. Her argument that a number of financial activities do not have value is because they involves &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; inputs. Well, a little bit of clever accounting, perhaps, but for all intents and purposes the only “input” they are using is market power. Because the output produced by finance doesn’t rely on real inputs, it cannot have real value. The opposite holds for government and public sector work. This involves real labor (e.g. police officers) and other real inputs (e.g. highways) so it has real value, even if we have trouble putting a clear number on it because of a lack of a profit and loss statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me say that there is nothing inherently wrong with Mazzucatos position, as in there being some kind of logical inconsistency. She, and everyone, is welcome to value inputs and hence the output of different sectors in any way they want. The question becomes why standard measures of economic activity, like GDP, have diverged so much from Mazzucatos notion of value, and whether there is some way to bring them back together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gdp-and-the-value-of-output&quot;&gt;GDP and the value of output&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did we get to the point where finance is valued “too much”, while government is valued “too little”? Let’s go back and think about how we would add up the value of economic activity if we did appeal to our notions of which inputs matter, or are “real” enough to count. How do you compare the value of one product to another? How do you compare the labor used in one product to another? Just time? Or does skill matter? How do you add up the value of a bushel of corn with a ton of steel? Do those values change over time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may want to value economic output based on your opinion of the inputs involved, and that’s fine. But I’m not sure you can do that, for all the reasons that Hayek laid out long ago. It’s an information problem. There are too many products, with too much heterogeneity, and too many inputs, for you to come up with a &lt;em&gt;complete&lt;/em&gt; set of rules to value output. And no, general principles don’t solve this, because you need to make particular decisions. The general principles of national income accounting are simple, but the details of how and what we count run to hundreds of pages. And what if I disagree with your opinion, how do we reconcile this? I guess we could each have our own individual measure of economic activity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you want a single measure then you need a consistent way of measuring the value of output from different activities relative to one another, so that you can add them up. The only practical way to do this we’ve come up with so far is to use relative prices. This is how GDP is calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue for Mazzucato is that by using relative prices, it breaks the link to the inherent value of inputs. Products that have high prices count for a lot, even if those high prices are due to markups from market power, rather than some “true” value of the inputs used. Hence finance, where the markups seem to represent market power to Mazzucato (e.g. net interest margin) gets a heavy weight. Government, where we don’t even have a clear measure of the true price of the output because it isn’t bought and sold like a normal good, ends up downweighted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that Mazzucatos argument about the problems with using relative prices is very compelling, for the reasons I laid out above about information. There does not seem to be a plausible way to add up economic activity without using prices. I guess to my point much earlier, if this was a radical book it would have proposed some kind of structure to add up activity that does not involve these prices. But I didn’t see that radical idea. In a lot of ways, Mazzucato’s point is just that relative prices are a poor approximation of &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; utilities, even if they are good approximations of &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt; utilities. Note, by the way, that even if there is market power and markups that relative prices are still a good indicator of marginal utilities. See my post on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox-2/&quot;&gt;paradox of markups&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, while I’d leave aside this particular criticism of using relative prices, I still think there was a lot of value (yes, that was deliberate) in the book for thinking about how inputs inform our opinions on inherent value. There is a coherent argument to make about how we could or should value certain economic activities more, in the sense of supporting or encouraging them, even if they do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; lead to higher measured GDP, but because they involve the use of some inherently valuable inputs. For example, you could argue that a jobs guarantee is valuable even if it led to GDP being lower than it would otherwise (of course, it might be higher, but that’s a different argument). That would be the case of valuing things based on the nature of the input (e.g. full time work for adults) rather than on the value of output. But using relative prices to value GDP is neither an argument for, nor against, your position.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sustained growth and the increase in work hours</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Leisure/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Leisure/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in March, I &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/When-Growth/&quot;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; a summary of some &lt;a href=&quot;https://jacobweisdorf.files.wordpress.com/2017/12/unreal-wages_humphries-and-weisdorf_dec-2017_wp1.pdf&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; by Jane Humphries and Jacob Weisdorf on the onset of economic growth. Their paper documented &lt;em&gt;annual&lt;/em&gt; labor contract terms in England over several centuries, and compared those to the typical &lt;em&gt;day&lt;/em&gt; labor rates that have been used in economic history to study the onset of growth and the effects of the Industrial Revolution. The short version of that paper is that the annual labor contracts starting seeing sustained growth in their value around 1650 or so, far sooner than the day wages indicated. This pushes back the origin of economic growth to well before the actual technological IR, and this also matches the data on GDP per capita developed by Broadberry, Campbell, Klein, Overton, and van Leeuwen in &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2GnD1Nm&quot;&gt;British Economic Growth, 1270-1870&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that I didn’t address in my post, but which came up in a few replies I saw, was whether the data on annual contracts (and on GDP per capita) indicate a rise in &lt;em&gt;living standards&lt;/em&gt;. Let’s take the day wage data as factually correct, and those day wages remained roughly constant from 1650-ish to 1850-ish. This has several implications. First, people that did work for day wages in this period would only see their annual income rise by working more days or hours per day. Second, if the value of annual contracts were tied in some way to the day wage, then annual contracts rose in value also due to rising work effort in days/hours. For both types of workers this doesn’t seem to indicate that they are better off, just working more hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what little evidence we do have on actual hours worked does seem to indicate that they increased a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; in the period around the actual Industrial Revolution. Hans-Joachim Voth, in two papers from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/cup/jechis/v58y1998i01p29-58_01.html&quot;&gt;1998&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/cup/jechis/v61y2001i04p1065-1082_04.html&quot;&gt;2001&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a book &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2JxpQLl&quot;&gt;Time and Work During the Industrial Revolution&lt;/a&gt;, provided estimates of work hours based on court records. Around 1760, annual hours were about 2500, while in 1800 and 1830 annual hours were about 3300, before dropping back to about 2700 in 1870. In the period of the actual (technological) Industrial Revolution, it would appear that work hours did rise substantially. We know the day wages did not rise until around 1850-ish. But with the rise in hours worked, the annual income of a worker would have risen during the early 1800’s. We might assume that those workers on annual contracts, if they were part of the same labor market, would also have seen their hours rise, and hence their annual income growth was due to more work time as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t settle anything, however. The HW data indicate that the value of annual contracts began to grow in the middle of the 1600’s, well before the rise in hours documented by Voth. If annual hours were consistent at 2500 from 1650 to 1750, then that means the rise in annual contracts represented growth in the implicit income per hour for those workers as well. On the other hand, you could argue that even the growth that HW document was driven by hours. In the 100 years from 1650 to 1750, HW estimate annual contracts grew in value by 67%-ish. If that was driven entirely by an increase in hours worked, then hours worked had to grow by about 67% as well. That would mean that in 1650 annual hours worked on these contracts were around 1,500. Is that reasonable? I don’t know that there is an obvious answer to that question. There is plenty of evidence for long idle periods in agricultural work, and so 1,500 hours in a year might have been the normal amount expected in 1650. On the other hand, that seems like a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; increase in hours worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s assume that even the rise in annual contract value was driven entirely by an increase in hours worked. And let’s stretch this argument out so that while annual contracts (as well as GDP per capita) started growing in 1650, it wasn’t until 1850 that this was because day/hour rates rose. Does this mean that the growth in annual contracts and GDP per capita did not represent a rise in &lt;em&gt;living standards&lt;/em&gt; until 1850?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to that depends on the reason for the rise in work hours. If they were physically coerced, then for sure you’d say that the growth in per worker annual contracts or GDP didn’t represent a rise in living standards. But on the assumption that the extra hours were not coerced, then we need to think hard about the labor supply decision of workers. Mark Koyama has a nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://mason.gmu.edu/~mkoyama2/About_files/Koyama12a.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that lays out a simple theoretical model for thinking about this, and the particular feature of this model that matters is the possibility of a backward-bending labor supply curve. When wages are very low, people provide very little labor to the market. Why bother? But as wages rise, people provide more labor to the market, because it is worth their time to work, as the wage they earn allows them to consume more goods. But on the assumption that people do enjoy non-work time, at some point the wage gets high enough that people start providing &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; labor. If you can earn enough to buy everything you want in 30 hours a week, why work 40 hours? This is the backward bending part of the labor supply curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Mark does is then work through various ways in which work hours might rise, the implication for living standards, and how these relate to different stories about economic growth. We can see which might make sense in the English case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;immiserating-growth-or-involution&quot;&gt;Immiserating growth or involution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first case is one where the wage starts (say in 1650) high enough that we are “on” the backward bending part of the labor supply curve. At this point, a negative productivity shock (e.g. a bad harvest) pushes down the wage, and because we are on the backward bending part of the supply curve, this &lt;em&gt;raises&lt;/em&gt; the amount of labor done. More hours at a lower wage would imply workers are worse off. Yet, if the elasticity of labor supply with respect to wage is &lt;em&gt;large&lt;/em&gt; enough, then the overall effect on earnings is &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt;. A large shift in L, even with a decline in w, can mean that wL (total earnings) increase. We could thus interpret the onset of annual contract growth in the HW data as an example of immiserating growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One issue with this story is that while we do not see growth in daily wages in the data, we also do not see a substantial &lt;em&gt;decline&lt;/em&gt; in wages. Yes, wages appear to decline from about 1450 to 1650, after the Black Death when population is rising, but after 1650 the wage data shows, if anything, a very small positive trend. Without clear evidence of a drop in the wage, and with the need for what seems like an unreasonably large labor supply elasticity, this story doesn’t seem to fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;involution&quot;&gt;Involution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a second theoretical case that can be used to generate more hours without rising living standards. This could occur because of an increase in the price of a necessity or subsistence good, like food. Because people have to consume a certain amount of this necessity, if it gets more expensive, they have to either work more hours, or decrease their consumption of all other goods. Under the assumption that people enjoy both leisure and consuming other things, they’ll decrease both by a little. The drop in leisure means an increase in work time, and hence we’ve got a rise in hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t require us to assume that workers are already on backward-bending part of the labor supply curve. The rise of the price of the necessity shifts down the whole labor supply curve down, and so people work more hours regardless of where they were to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether this results in an increase in measured earnings (wL) depends on the effect of the rise in the price of the necessity on the equilibrium wage, and how much the labor supply curve shifts. You can wrestle the model into giving you an increase in wL, while people are still worse off. This kind of effect has been called “involution” before, a concept that at some point in my life I’ll write a much longer post about. But for the present post, the problem is that there is no obvious rise in food prices in England starting in 1650.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;industrious-revolution&quot;&gt;Industrious revolution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leaves us with the last case that delivers an increase in work hours and living standards, which captures the intuition of Jan de Vries “Industrious Revolution”, which you can read about &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2l1dSuL&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, in one of the more enjoyable books on economic history you’ll come across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story here is that there are different kinds of consumption. Some consumption is time-intense (e.g. Netflix) in that it requires a little of your money, but a lot of your time to consume it. Some consumption is good-intense (e.g. clothes) which requires a lot of your money, but very little of your time. And no, don’t get too picky on that distinction. Yes, you might wear a shirt for 12 hours, but once it is on you don’t have to spend any time or attention to keep wearing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If time-intense consumption is cheap, then you’ll tend to buy lots of it, and that means you’ll work very little. You don’t need much money to buy these consumption items (so you don’t need to work much), and you do need time to enjoy them. The argument here would be that England prior to 1650 was a world in which time-intense consumption was cheap. Workers had little need to work more hours, because why bother? What were you going to purchase with that extra income? It made sense to buy the time-intense consumption good, leisure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But around the middle of the 17th century, in line with de Vries’ argument, new good-intense consumption goods became available, like sugar and tea. So people shifted their consumption towards these things, which did not require much time to enjoy, but did require you to purchase something. So putting more labor into the market made sense. Similarly, the price of textiles was falling at this time (yes, prior to the IR). People shifted from the time-intense activity  of making ones own clothes, towards the good-intense purchase of ready-made clothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decline in the price of these good-intense consumption items “straightens out” the labor supply curve, making the transition to backward-bending occur at a higher level. And hence for any given wage, the labor supplied is higher. In this setting, living standards are &lt;em&gt;rising&lt;/em&gt; with the increase in work time, as this is an optimal response to a drop in the price of one of the available consumption items. The drop in the price of good-intense items shifted time spent at home (and out of the labor market) into time spent in the labor market. Unlike the prior two explanations, the data work here. The prices of things like tea and sugar and clothing did fall in the period starting from the mid-1600’s, at the same time hours were rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-is-it-all-about-trade&quot;&gt;So is it all about trade?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, let’s say that we buy the story of the industrious revolution, and buy that the onset of growth in annual labor contracts and GDP per capita starting in 1650 represented a real gain in living standards. One interesting implication of this is that the origin of sustained growth was associated, in large part, with the expansion of trade in England. Rather than a series of clear technological breakthroughs (e.g. the spinning jenny, etc.) it was the “technology” of trade, by inducing a change in the available basket of consumption goods, that kick-started sustained growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a fascinating question is how important trade was in &lt;em&gt;sustaining&lt;/em&gt; sustained growth. That is, the availability of cheap trade goods could have created a period of rapid growth in the late 17th century, perhaps running through the late 18th century. But without the continued expansion of trade to bring in new goods, or finding cheaper sources of those goods, could growth have continued? Even if you could find new and cheaper imports, at some point wouldn’t people reach a limit on how much additional time they wanted to work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence you could argue that the technological Industrial Revolution of the late 1700’s and early 1800’s was necessary to keep sustained growth going after trade got things started, and that technological innovation is still necessary for growth to continue indefinitely. But you could also argue that without trade creating growth to begin with, there never would have been an incentive to make those technological changes in the first place. I’m well beyond my brainpower capacity to answer this. But the HW data, along with the Broadberry et al data on GDP per capita, by pushing back the date of sustained growth to 1650, makes the link between trade and the Industrial Revolution more salient. Did the Industrious Revolution trigger the Industrial Revolution?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the answer to that, I think it is a good working hypothesis that the growth documented by HW and Broadberry et al starting in the 1650’s was associated with real gains in living standards, as the increase in hours worked is consistent with a switch to goods-intense consumption items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-complete-aside&quot;&gt;A complete aside&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has absolutely nothing to do with the onset of sustained growth. But the logic of the industrious revolution I presented above can be used in reverse to think about changes in economic growth in the recent past. You could argue that recent innovations have made time-intense consumption items (e.g. Netflix or video games) cheaper. And in a mirror image response to the 1600’s, people are substituting more time-intense consumption for goods-intense consumption. This means that they willingly withdraw labor from the market in order to enjoy those time-intense activities, as in the proverbial 20-something male living in his parents basement playing Halo all day. Nothing terribly insightful here, I just thought I was interesting to think about this as the flip of the industrious revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The paradox of markups, part 2</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I told you I wouldn’t leave you waiting on the next post concerning markups and the paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/content_link/JCsTqiauR0JBboj3vsNFRhyw9MrxV3B0j7L3f4fURJnfAUAxSXJXASiRl8OFiU2F/file&quot;&gt;David Baqaee and Emmanuel Fahri&lt;/a&gt;, so here you go. In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I described the (at times) paradoxical nature of markups. When there is &lt;em&gt;dispersion&lt;/em&gt; in markups, output is lower than it could otherwise be, given technology. But when there is dispersion in markups, there are circumstances - like increasing markups in low-markup producers or shifting resources towards high-markup producers - where raising the average markup in the economy will be associated with higher output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that is in the BF paper, but it is not the main purpose of it. One of the main contributions of the paper is to show that you can generalize these effects of markups to almost any arbitrary model of the economy. The paradox is not just the result of making some particular assumptions about production functions or preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One application they pursue (among many) is decomposing productivity growth into terms involving technology and terms involving allocative efficiency. If you read this blog at all, you know that productivity is a big bucket of different things going on in the economy. In that bucket are true technology effects, the ability to physically produce more widgets given some set of physical inputs. But also in that bucket are things like the allocation of those inputs across firms that produce different kinds of widgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decomposing-productivity-growth&quot;&gt;Decomposing productivity growth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the economy were perfectly efficient, meaning that the inputs we use were allocated across different firms such that we were at the maximum possible output level, then productivity would measure &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; true technological improvements. Yes, inputs might move between different firms in response to technological changes, but the &lt;em&gt;efficiency&lt;/em&gt; of the economy is being held constant, and so those changes in input use have zero effect on productivity to a first approximation. The problem with using productivity to measure technology is not that inputs move around, per se, it is that the movement of inputs may not represent a move from one efficient equilibrium to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give you an example to illustrate what I mean. Let’s say that in 2004, all the inputs (e.g. labor) in the economy were allocated in an efficient manner, and output was as high as it could possibly be given the specific physical technologies available in that year. We look at this allocation and say, clearly this is the best way to allocate inputs, so let’s pass a law to freeze the allocations at the 2004 shares. If 4% of all people worked at the Gap in 2004, then 4% of all people would always be required to work at the Gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005, though, there are changes in the specific physical technologies used by different firms. Some may have better technology, some worse. Perhaps the Gap discovers a better way to fold shirts. Who knows. Because the technologies changed, there &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be changes in the allocation of inputs. In an efficient economy, there &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; be changes in the allocations. But we have this dumb law that says the allocations cannot be changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a productivity perspective, the growth in productivity - which remember is the output we can produce given a set of inputs - is affected by two things. First, there are the specific technological changes that occurred. By themselves, those should &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; productivity (remember the cool new folding technique at the Gap). Second, there are now all the distortions introduced by the law. More than 4% of the labor force should work at the Gap now, but it is confined to only employing 4%. Thus we are getting less output than we could, and hence productivity is &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Productivity growth is thus a combination of the positive technological effect, and a negative effect of the allocation law. What we’d like to do is separate out those two effects. And that is what BF propose to do, in a setting that allows for any kind of arbitrary structure in terms of production functions, links between firms acting as suppliers to one another, and preferences. The contribution of their work is not to identify this issue in measuring productivity - we’ve known about that for a while - but to develop a way to manage that issue in almost any conceivable setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do they do? Intuitively, they say you have to calculate the &lt;em&gt;efficient&lt;/em&gt; outcome in 2005 given the changes in technology. Then you compare the productivity of this hypothetical efficient 2005 economy with the efficient 2004 economy, and in that case the productivity you measure is getting the “pure” effect of technology, &lt;em&gt;holding constant the efficiency of the economy&lt;/em&gt;. In theory that is possible to do, but in practice it is hard (impossible) because you don’t know how much the true physical productivity of each firm improved over time. Hold on to that problem for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve calculated this pure technological effect, you are left with changes in productivity that are due to changes in allocative efficiency. Here, the idea is that you are comparing the &lt;em&gt;efficiency&lt;/em&gt; of the economy in 2004 to the &lt;em&gt;efficiency&lt;/em&gt; of the economy in 2005, without asking about the technological changes. What BF show is that given some readily available data on markups and factor income shares (e.g. wages as a fraction of output) you can calculate this allocative efficiency effect without too much trouble, and this is true no matter how complex the underlying economy may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall productivity growth is thus a combination of the pure technology effect and the allocative efficiency effect. The simple math is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta Prod = \% \Delta Tech + \% \Delta AE.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BF have data on productivity growth (this is just the normal thing we calculate from data on output and inputs), and they show how to calculate &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\% \Delta AE\inline&quot;/&gt;. So in the end they don’t need to measure the precise technological changes of each firm, they can just back out the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\% \Delta Tech\inline&quot;/&gt; term from the above equation. You can infer the pure technological change in the economy once you measure the allocative efficiency change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To implement this, BF need some way of measuring allocative efficiency, and they use the data on markups charged by firms. They draw this data from a paper from Gutierrez and Philippon that I talked about &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Investment/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you recall from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, markups push the economy away from the efficient allocation, and so BF can use changes in markups to measure the change in how far away from that efficient allocation the economy moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_BF_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sources of productivity growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of all this are in the figure. The blue line, labelled the Solow residual, shows how productivity itself grows over time. This is what they are trying to decompose. The allocative efficiency line (orange dashes) is the contribution to productivity from changes in how close to the efficient allocation the economy got. Notice that this term is &lt;em&gt;rising&lt;/em&gt; over time, meaning that according to their calculations the economy was more efficient in 2015 than in 1996. We’ll get back to that in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By definition, the difference between the blue line (productivity) and the orange dashed line (allocative efficiency) has to be the effect of pure technology. The purple line captures this, and you can see that this is also growing over time. But note that overall productivity grew faster than technology because of the allocative efficiency improvement. BF suggest that the each account for about 50% of the growth in productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You can also see one last source of growth in productivity, factor undercounting. I ignored this in my little analysis up above. This is capturing the fact that in the presence of markups the measure of inputs that we can calculate is not quite equal to the true level of input use. This effect can get very large - BF find it matters more using other data on markups that are larger than the Gutierrez and Philippon markups - but for the time being, lets set that effect aside.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wait-efficiency-was-going-up&quot;&gt;Wait, efficiency was going up?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that BF find allocative efficiency was &lt;em&gt;improving&lt;/em&gt; over time is perhaps surprising. To see why this was occurring, we can turn to a further decomposition that BF provide. To understand this, it helps to think of the allocative efficiency term as being determined by something like a weighted average of the markups across firms. As a weighted average, it can change over time for two reasons. The markups themselves could change, or the weights could change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next figure, BF have separated out these two effects. The blue line is the same total allocative efficiency term from the first figure. The “markup effect” in orange dashes is measuring changes just the change in markups charged by firms, effectively holding the weights constant. The general increase in the “markup effect” comes from the fact that most markups were &lt;em&gt;falling&lt;/em&gt; according to the Gutierrez and Philippon data. If you want to refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, this is telling us that all the markups in the economy were collapsing towards one (meaning no markup), and that the economy was getting closer to the point where the ratio of marginal utilites was equal to the ratio of marginal costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_BF_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sources of allocative efficiency&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we have what BF call the “cross-entropy” effect. That is not terribly informative. It refers to the fact that the &lt;em&gt;weights&lt;/em&gt; in the weighted average of markups change over time. Recall that holding markups constant, if you push more resources into high-markup firms, this &lt;em&gt;raises&lt;/em&gt; productivity because the output of those firms is very valuable. The yellow line shows that productivity was rising over time due to this effect, and that in turn implies that more and more resources were getting pushed into high markup firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shift towards higher markup firms is consistent with the rise in profit share at the aggregate level. But that shift didn’t mean that productivity was falling. There &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; situations in which the rising profit share would be associated with lower productivity; if firm-specific markups were rising this would detract from productivity while raising profits. But what appears to have happened here is that profits rose due to changes in the composition of spending towards high-markup firms, and that is associated with higher productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;revisiting-harbergers-triangle&quot;&gt;Revisiting Harberger’s triangle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The productivity accounting that BF do relates to changes in allocative efficiency, but only in a local sense. It tells us whether we are getting closer or farther from the efficient equilibrium, but it doesn’t tell us how far away the efficient equilibrium is to begin with. How much higher would output be if there were no markups?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BF use their setting to answer this question. The exact numbers depend on the precise set of markups they use, and some assumptions about the structure of the economy, but the answer is that output would be about 40% higher without markups. This is much, &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt;, higher than the traditional answer, usually attributed to Harberger, who said the losses from monopoly were around 0.1%. Harberger’s number was always a bad estimate, as it was based on looking across sectors (not firms) only within manufacturing. It was an other example of assuming that what occurs within manufacturing is the only thing that matters. But even so, the scale of the effect that BF find is significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question is whether this substantial departure from the efficient equilibrium is worth it. We believe that markups are &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to induce economic growth, as they provide the reward to those who innovate. Is operating 40% below the efficient outcome worth it, in the sense that the markups pushing us down there are in turn generating rapid growth? I have no idea what the answer to that question is. You’d need to build some more structure on top of the BF model to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another interesting thing about their calculations, and it is an aspect of the paradox of markups. The 40% number BF calculate is for 2014. For 1997, they find that the loss associated with markups is only 4.5%. The loss associated with markups rose from 1997 to 2014, and yet allocative efficiency improved from 1997 to 2014, which is what the productivity calculations showed. How can those two things both be true?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BF’s productivity calculations show that the economy was moving &lt;em&gt;towards&lt;/em&gt; the efficient equilibrium over time, and hence this contributed to productivity growth. But at the same time, the efficient equilibrium was moving farther and farther away. Think of me running a 100 meter race against Usain Bolt. He’s much faster, but I am running in the same direction, at least. My allocative efficiency improves, in the sense that I’m headed in the right direction. But my absolute efficiency declines, in the sense that Bolt gets farther and farther ahead of me every moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, without some more information, you can’t say whether falling further behind the efficient equilibrium is good or bad, but it is an interesting piece of information to throw into the mental wood chipper. It may be worth it to be further behind if that is associated with greater incentives to innovate. Or perhaps it is a correlate of the lack of dynamism in business formation and employment turnover that has been documented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not even begun to scratch the surface of the interesting applications of the BF paper. I focused on the productivity accounting just because it is something I find to be of particular interest. The power of the paper is, to repeat, that these findings hold without having to make any strong assumptions about what production functions look like or how firms fit together into an input/output matrix. The only annoying thing about the paper is that it is forcing me to see how limited my understanding of the role of markups was in the economy. But it is well worth the effort to read it (so much notation!) if you’re into this kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The paradox of markups</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Paradox/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten the lag time between posts down from 6 months to six weeks. Progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topic that comes up often here is the effect of markups on aggregate productivity. And there is a recent-ish paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/content_link/JCsTqiauR0JBboj3vsNFRhyw9MrxV3B0j7L3f4fURJnfAUAxSXJXASiRl8OFiU2F/file&quot;&gt;David Baqaee and Emmanuel Fahri&lt;/a&gt; that has approached the relationship of markups (and distortions in general) with aggregate productivity from a very general perspective. By that I mean they show how to assess the impact of markups in an economy that may have some arbitrarily complex input-output structure for production, and in which it may be impossible to write down a coherent aggregate production function. In other words, they can assess the effect of markups on something approaching an actual economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intention was to walk through some of their main theoretical results on how to track the effect of markups, and show you what they come up with when they use those results to quantify the effect of rising markups over time. And I’m going to get to that in a future post, which I promise will arrive in fewer than six weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in working on that post, I started to write up a short section to lay out how markups affect real GDP in the first place. This post is that section, and as you’ll see I failed completely on the “short” thing. It’s well over 2000 words and at some point involved a python program to draw the figure you’ll see below. So this review of the effect of markups is getting put up as its own post, and then I’ll use this to jump off into a more complete discussion of the BF results in the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key things that comes up in studying the role of markups is an apparent paradox. The presence of markups can mean the value of aggregate output is lower than it otherwise would be, as it leads to a misallocation of inputs. But at the same time, it is possible that raising the &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; markup in the economy will increase the value of aggregate output. It would appear as if markups can be both bad and good for output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice the hedges in those statements - “can mean” and “it is possible”. That is because these are not universal truths, but rather hold in specific circumstances. Once you understand how markups work in general, the circumstances under which this paradox arises will be more clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In explaining all this, I’m going to pursue exact opposite strategy of the BF paper, and show you how markups work in one very particular setup with only 2 goods and no interesting input-output structures between them. Keep in mind that BF establish how the intuition behind my simple example extends to more complex situations, and everything I’m doing here would still hold in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bad-effect-of-markups&quot;&gt;The bad effect of markups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we’ve got an economy where there are two goods, 1 and 2. People want to consume both goods, but have diminishing marginal utility in consuming more of either one. Producers can make either good by using some input, and call it labor to be concrete. The technology to produce either good is simple. There is a constant marginal cost in terms of labor for producing one additional unit of a good, but that marginal cost might be different for the two goods. For example, if &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC_1 = 3\inline&quot;/&gt;, then it takes 3 units of labor to produce one more unit of good 1. Note that if we flip this over, then &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/MC_1 = 1/3\inline&quot;/&gt; is additional output of good 1 we get from using 1 more unit of labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having now dealt with preliminaries, what is the efficient outcome for this economy? And by efficient, I mean the outcome where the economy achieves the highest level of utility possible given the technology available and the stock of labor available. That outcome will be the point - the amount consumed of goods 1 and 2 - where the trade-off in utility between the two goods (the ratio of their marginal utilities) is exactly equal to the technological trade-off between the two goods (the ratio of their marginal costs). If you took intermediate economics, you might be familiar with this as the condition where the marginal rate of substitution equals the marginal rate of transformation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{MU_1}{MU_2} = \frac{MC_1}{MC_2}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is helpful to rearrange this to see what is going on. So write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;MU_1 \left(1/MC_1\right) = MU_2 \left(1/MC_2\right).&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the left, this is the additional utility you would get if you put one more unit of labor to work producing good 1. You’d get, as mentioned, an additional &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/MC_1\inline&quot;/&gt; units of good 1 from that extra labor. Multiplying those units of good 1 by &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MU_1\inline&quot;/&gt; tells us how valuable they are in terms of utility. If you did use one more unit of labor on good 1, though, you’d have to take that labor away from producing good 2. How much would you lose? You’d lose &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/MC_2\inline&quot;/&gt; units of good 2, and multiplying that by &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MU_2\inline&quot;/&gt; would tell you how much utility you just sacrificed. When the utility gained from extra good 1 just equals the utility lost from less of good 2, then you haven’t improved your situation at all. And once we’re at the point where you can’t improve your situation at all, we’re at the efficient outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig-markup-A.png&quot; alt=&quot;Markup equilibrium&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a lot of words. It is so much easier to see in a figure. What you can see labeled as the point “Efficient” is just the point at which the slope of the indifference curve (which is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?-MU_1/MU_2\inline&quot;/&gt;) is equal to the slope of the production possibilities frontier (which is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?-MC_1/MC_2\inline&quot;/&gt;). There is no feasible point we can produce (which is what the PPF captures) that gives us a higher level of utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible for the economy to reach that efficient outcome if no one is forcing it to reach that point? Sure, under some very specific conditions that boil down to the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{MU_1}{MU_2} = \frac{P_1}{P_2} = \frac{MC_1}{MC_2}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have that consumers take the prices of the goods as given, then they will buy goods until the ratio of their marginal utilities are equal to the ratio of prices. This is the point where their trade-off in utility is equal to the &lt;em&gt;market&lt;/em&gt; trade-off between the two goods. On the other side, we need that for producers, the prices they charge are equal to the ratio of their marginal costs, or the technological trade-off is also equal to the &lt;em&gt;market&lt;/em&gt; trade-off. In my figure, you can think of these conditions as saying that the budget constraint facing consumers (which tells consumers the ratio of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_1\inline&quot;/&gt; to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_2\inline&quot;/&gt;) has the same slope as the PPF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what happens when firms are charging markups? By definition, a markup of price over marginal cost, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt;, means that the price charged is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_1 = \mu_1 MC_1\inline&quot;/&gt; for good 1, with a similar expression for good 2. If there are markups, then we’ve got&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{MU_1}{MU_2} = \frac{P_1}{P_2} = \frac{\mu_1 MC_1}{\mu_2 MC_2}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, you can see that even though consumers are doing their thing setting the ratio of marginal utilities equal to the ratio of prices, that ratio of prices is not necessarily equal to the ratio of marginal costs. And if the ratio of marginal utilities is not equal to the ratio of marginal costs, the economy cannot be at the efficient point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look back at the figure, you an see what is happening. What I’ve done there is assume that there is a markup on good 1 relative to good 2. This means that the ratio of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_1\inline&quot;/&gt; to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_2\inline&quot;/&gt; is &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; than the ratio of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC_1\inline&quot;/&gt; to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC_2\inline&quot;/&gt;. For consumers, the budget constraint they face is steeper than the PPF, and so they naturally make the choice to consume less of good 1 and more of good 2. In the figure, I’ve shown the pure substitution effect of this change in prices with the point labeled “Hicks”. This holds their utility constant, but shows how choices shift when good 1 is pricier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the “Hicks” point is that it is not feasible to produce. It lies outside of the PPF. We have to slide the budget constraint facing consumers backwards until their choices of what to consume given the marked up price for good 1 are possible to produce. That point is labeled “Markups”, and is where the economy ends up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few important notes on this “Markups” outcome. First, the economy is still &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; the PPF (the thick gray line). The problem with markups is not that they make the economy less &lt;em&gt;technologically&lt;/em&gt; productive, or that they somehow push us inside the PPF (which would imply that we aren’t using all of our labor), but that they skew where along the PPF that we produce. Hence “misallocation” is the right way to characterize the effect of markups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it is not the existence of markups that creates a misallocation, it is &lt;em&gt;dispersion&lt;/em&gt; in markups that creates a misallocation. To see this, go back to the last equation I showed. What would happen if &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; goods charged the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; markup? Then &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1 = \mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt;, and we are back to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MU_1/MU_2 = MC_1/MC_2\inline&quot;/&gt;. The economy would operate at the efficient outcome. Markups would imply that producer surplus had been increased at the expense of consumer surplus - there would be distributional consequences - but the economy would not be inefficient. Markups lower aggregate output when they &lt;em&gt;differ&lt;/em&gt; across producers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, note that I did not mention anything about &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; markups exist, or what kind of market power or market structure might allow them to exist. What the BF paper helped give me some clarity on was that, from the perspective of aggregate output, it is neither relevant nor necessary to know why markups exist, it is sufficient to know that they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A real quick aside here before I jump into the paradox of higher markups. I bounced back and forth a little above in talking about how markups lower the “value of output” or lower “utility”. Those are precise synonyms here. Measuring the value of output, as we try to do with real GDP, is measuring utility. We can argue about whether the BEA gets the calculations exactly right for the aggregate economy, but the principle still holds. So when I say that markups lower the value of output or utility in my little model here, that implies that measured real GDP would be lower as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-higher-average-markups-are-associated-with-higher-output&quot;&gt;Why higher average markups are associated with higher output&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the situation I just described, how is it that higher average markups are associated with higher output? There are two ways this could work. To see the logic behind both, let me first define what I mean by &lt;em&gt;average markup&lt;/em&gt;. This is the weighted average of the markups for the two goods, where the weights are their share in total spending. This would be something like &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_1 \mu_1 + s_2 \mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt;, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_1\inline&quot;/&gt; is expenditures on good 1 relative to total expenditures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(In practice, and to be consistent with BF, what we really want is the weighted harmonic mean of the markups. This is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(s_1/\mu_1 + s_2/\mu_2)^{-1}\inline&quot;/&gt;. But while this is the technically accurate way of doing things, all the intuition you need to understand the paradox flows from the simple weighted average I started with.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the situation I set up in the figure, I said that the markup on good 1 was higher than on good 2, so &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1 &amp;gt; \mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt;, and that dispersion in markups lowered output. So we could raise output by &lt;em&gt;raising&lt;/em&gt; the markup on good 2. If we got to the point where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_2 = \mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt; again, then as I mentioned above, this would restore us to the efficient outcome. Raising &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt; up to the size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt; would obviously raise the average markup in the economy as well. Hence we have one example of the paradox of how higher average markups could be associated with higher output, even though “markups” (really, their dispersion) are associated with lower output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second possibility is that we leave the size of the markups themselves alone, but increase the expenditure share on good 1 with the high markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_1\inline&quot;/&gt;. This will raise the average markup in the economy, which should be obvious. But at the same time, this will act to raise total output, and hence give us the paradox again. How does this work? Remember, because of the fact that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1 &amp;gt; \mu_2\inline&quot;/&gt;, it is the case that the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MU_1 (1/MC_1) &amp;gt; MU_2 (1/MC_2)\inline&quot;/&gt;. In other words, we can gain utility by taking one unit of labor away from producing good 2 and switching it to producing good 1. In the figure above, the market didn’t make this move happen because as far as consumers are concerned the (marked up) prices of the goods are such that there is no gain to their utility from moving expenditure away from good 2 towards good 1. So anything that can induce a shift of expenditure away from 2 and towards 1 would raise the value of output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What might induce such a change in expenditure? One thing would be if the productivity of producing good 1 increased, and hence &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC_1\inline&quot;/&gt; fell. This would make good 1 cheaper (the PPF and budget lines in the figure would become flatter), and people would buy more of good 1 than before, raising its expenditure share. The average markup would rise, and output would go up. You can see some of this logic by running the mental experiment out to an extreme. Let’s say that the marginal cost of producing good 1 fell towards zero, so that everyone consumed &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; good 1. Then we’re at a case where the economy is efficient - consumers want to consume only good 1, and the producers only make good 1 - but the average markup in the economy is exactly &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt;. That situation might mean that producers are capturing most of the surplus, but as I said above, all we’re talking about here is the relationship of markups and the value of output, not its distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are thinking through the possibilities, you’ll see that there is still a case where raising the average markup would &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; the value of output. If the dispersion of markups gets &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu_1\inline&quot;/&gt; gets even higher, then the average markup would rise, and the economy would end up at a point with lower utility. You can see this if you think of making the budget line facing consumers in the figure steeper. Hence all the qualifications I made in the beginning of this post about the nature of the paradox of markups. There are circumstances in which higher average markups can hurt the economy, and circumstances in which it can help the economy (in terms of the value of output).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology-productivity-and-markups&quot;&gt;Technology, productivity and markups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last thing I want to make clear is the distinction between productivity and technology, which I’ve been beating on for a while. Productivity is defined as the value of output divided by some measure of input use. Hence for my little toy economy, it is just utility divided by the units of labor used in production. Because the “Markups” point produces less utility than the “Efficient” point, but they use the same amount of labor, productivity in the “Markups” case is necessarily going to be lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt; in use at the “Markups” point is &lt;em&gt;identical&lt;/em&gt; to the technology used at the “Efficient” point. The PPF did not move anywhere or change its slope because of the markups, and hence technology is the same at “Markups” and at “Efficient”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think instead in terms of changes, or growth, then this intuition shows that productivity could grow (or not grow) for two reasons. First, technology could grow, meaning that the PPF shifts out, and then regardless of the markups we’d achieve higher utility. Second, the markups could change, and we could move &lt;em&gt;along&lt;/em&gt; the current PPF, which would also change utility, and hence measured productivity. BF provide a way of breaking down changes in measured productivity into that contribution of the PPF itself versus the contribution of changes in markups, similar but not identical work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/eecrev/v46y2002i6p963-991.html&quot;&gt;Basu and Fernald&lt;/a&gt; from 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll get to all of that - and more! - in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>When did sustained growth start?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/When-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/When-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You know how when you get older, time seems to move faster? Well, imagine how that feels, and now pretend that you write a blog. It’s been about six months since I last posted something, and that was not a conscious decision, but just something that kind of happened as I kept putting it off while I worked on classes or research. If I want to blame something in particular, I have been helping to coach my kids lacrosse team for the last few months, and you’d be shocked at how much mental real estate U-12 lacrosse eats up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the reason, I’m back. And it was a working paper that I finally got around to reading that prompted me to get back on the wagon. Jane Humphries and Jacob Weisdorf have put out “Unreal wages? Real income and economic growth in England, 1260-1850”, which you can find an ungated version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jacobweisdorf.files.wordpress.com/2017/12/unreal-wages_humphries-and-weisdorf_dec-2017_wp1.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As they set it out, there is a disparity in the data sources we use to think about the timing and evolution of sustained economic growth. The basic problem can be see in their figure, reproduced below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/HWfig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;GDP per capita and wages&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using aggregated data, Broadberry, Campbell, Klein, Overton, and van Leeuwen in &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2GnD1Nm&quot;&gt;British Economic Growth, 1270-1870&lt;/a&gt; come up with a series for GDP per capita, plotted in the open circles in the figure. This shows a take-off to growth around 1650. However, the standard data used to establish the path of living standards has been wage data, and here a paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/bla/ehsrev/v60y2007i1p97-135.html&quot;&gt;Clark&lt;/a&gt; from 2007 is their source. As you can see, the wage data indicate no take-off in the 1600’s, and even by 1850 there is little to indicate that wages are experiencing sustained growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two data series tell very different stories about the origin of economic growth. And it seems as if one of them must be wrong. What Humphries and Weisdorf (HW) suggest, in short, is that the wage data are incorrect. The underlying issue is that the most of the discussion about living standards for workers over this period is based on observations of &lt;em&gt;day&lt;/em&gt; wages drawn from various sources, which are then multiplied through by some estimate of the number of working days in a year - typically 250 - to get an implied annual income. But this of course has all sorts of issues. How many days of work was truly typical, and did it vary significantly over time? Even if the day wages recorded in the data are accurate, should we believe that any worker could earn that wage for as many days as they wish during a year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What HW do is dig back into the data and pull out evidence on actual &lt;em&gt;annual&lt;/em&gt; labor contracts. Many farm workers had annual, or permanent contracts, and the farm owner padded out that work force with day laborers as necessary. But annual contracts existed outside of agriculture as well. These annual contracts are, in theory, a much better way of measuring labor’s living standard. However, they have the issue that these contracts often included not just a monetary payment, but payments in-kind, in terms of housing and food allowances. The big issue that HW have is trying to value those in-kind payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, they make the assumption that all annual workers received in-kind payments that had a monetary value equal to a “respectability” basket of goods. This set of goods (and services in the form of rent) was defined by Bob Allen, and you can find the details of it in the HW paper. It consists of a a certain amount of specific foods (e.g. 234 kg of bread), as well as things like soap, linen, lamp oil, fuel, and rent. The monetary value of this basket is added to the actual observed money wages in the annual contracts, and that forms the annual earnings of a worker for HW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the element of the paper you should be most concerned with. HW check the value of this respectability basket of goods against the few contracts they have that are more specific about the in-kind benefits that a worker receives, and for those cases Allen’s basket doesn’t look too far off. But that’s not the same as saying that all workers received exactly this same kind of basket, and more important for HW, that’s not the same thing as saying that all workers received this basket &lt;em&gt;over time&lt;/em&gt;. If the in-kind payments were declining over time, then they are overstating the growth in the value of annual earnings. If the in-kind payments were increasing, then they are understating the growth in annual earnings. I don’t know enough about the historical sources to make an educated criticism here; I’ll leave that to the economic historians. What HW do given the lack of data is reasonable, but that doesn’t make it accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this post, let’s assume that this issue is not significant issue, and see what their numbers tell us. The punch line of the paper is really the following figure. The dark line is the annual wage series developed by HW, and the other two lines are identical to the first figure. You can see that the annual wages track the GDP per capita data very well. And as HW point out, there are two significant things to draw from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/HWfig2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Annual earnings, GDP per capita, and wages&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the reaction of wages to the Black Death (around 1350-1450) is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; smaller in terms of annual wages compared to day wages. We (and by we, I mean me in most of my classes) have used the day wage data for years to illustrate the Malthusian reaction of living standards to population shocks. As the Black Death killed off between one-quarter and one-third of the population, wages shot up, but as the population recovered after that (in the 1500s) wages dropped back to their roughly stagnant level. The HW annual earnings data show that the reaction was more muted. It still existed (look at 1350 to 1400 in particular), but was not as dramatic. In fact, it does not look like annual wages &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; fell back to the pre-Black Death level. This doesn’t mean that the Malthusian model is wrong; there are a lot of other changes going on in the economy over the 200 years following the Black Death. But it isn’t the neat illustration of the mechanism it once was. A different way of looking at this is as follows; assuming that the Malthusian model is &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt;, then the annual earnings data tell us that there must have been &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kind of significant change in the English economy in that period, otherwise the earnings should have dropped back to the 50-75 range in the figure by 1650.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, and probably most noticeable, is the onset of sustained growth in annual earnings &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; earlier than the actual Industrial Revolution. Both the GDP per capita and the annual earnings series being to accelerate around 1650. The Broadberry et al series of GDP per capita does not just reflect an increase in land rents or payments to capital, but appears to also represent an increase in the real living standards of workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That increase predates even the most aggressive dating of the industrial revolution in terms of specific technologies (e.g. Newcomen’s engine in 1712), and is well before dates in the 1760’s based on the spinning jenny or water frame. Steam power was invented in the 1700’s, but it wasn’t really until the early 1800’s that it became a significant source of motive energy for industry in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What HW’s data does, in its strongest interpretation, is firmly sever the connection of the Industrial Revolution - a technological event - from the onset of sustained growth - an economic event. I’ve made this case &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/unified-growth-theory-is-not-the-enemy/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, and the HW findings only reinforce it. The day wage data had already sawed through most of that connection, because day wages had lagged technological change by so many decades. But notice that the HW data suggest the disconnect is not that earnings &lt;em&gt;lagged&lt;/em&gt; the technological change, it is that they &lt;em&gt;predated&lt;/em&gt; the technological change. This is consistent with the GDP per capita data, and that has a very different set of implications for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One story that would need a rethink is human capital as the origin of sustained growth. The idea here has been that it was not until the industrial processes of England, in the mid 1800’s, started to require more human capital that the quantity/quality trade-off for families tilted towards quality, allowing for sustained growth. But if sustained growth began in 1650, then it cannot be that the change in industrial demands for human capital of the mid-1800’s led to sustained growth. Now, you could rescue this by saying that &lt;em&gt;whatever&lt;/em&gt; was going on in 1650 was human-capital intense, and that while the timing of the story was wrong, the theory itself if right. But now we’ve got to establish what was going on with the nature of human capital in 1650 to cause this. At the same time, you need to account for the fact that population growth in England did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; slow down starting in 1650, and on the basis of much data, accelerated not long afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second story that needs some rethinking is the institutions hypothesis. Here’s what you don’t want to do. Don’t look at the HW data and decide that it must have been the murder of Charles I in 1649, or the ascendancy of Oliver Cromwell that “caused” the acceleration to sustained growth. One, the HW data in the figure look precise, but you need to imagine some kind of errors bars around their earnings series, so the take-off to growth is probably safely situated somewhere between 1600 and 1700. Two, that’s not how causal inference works. That said, I probably need to update my prior on the plausibility of the institutional changes associated with the Glorious Revolution of 1689 having an important effect on growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another story that comes to mind with respect to origins of sustained growth is the role of discoveries or early colonization. By pushing back sustained growth into the 1600’s, the timing fits as a reaction to the growing colonization of the Americas. The Pilgrims were in 1620, and Massachusetts Bay Colony was organized around 1630. So one could take more seriously that the Americas were an important feature of sustained growth. At the same time, it seems hard to believe that the scale of migration and trade between the Americas and England was so big that it could show up in an appreciable change in English wages even by the late 1600’s. But like the institutional hypothesis, let’s say that I would update my prior on the importance of the colonies. I’m still not sold, but I’m a little less skeptical than I was a few days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A last story that seems to benefit from this kind of data is Bob Allen’s theory about wage pressures and industrial technology. In thinking about why England &lt;em&gt;adopted&lt;/em&gt; certain technologies in the late 1700’s and early 1800’s, and many continental countries did not, Allen cites the relatively high wages in England (compared to relatively low energy prices). The annual earnings data are consistent with his hypothesis, conditional on those technologies (e.g. the jennies and water frames and steam engines) having been invented when they were. There is still a different story to tell about why those inventions were made in the first place, but that probably will stray off too far into the weeds for this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the HW data shakes up the stylized facts about the take-off to sustained growth enough that it should change our ideas of what caused it. It at least got me to start thinking hard about this again. We should separate the notion of sustained growth (i.e growth in annual earnings) from the notion of industrial revolution (i.e. the invention or adoption of specific technologies). Yes, we think growth depends on technological changes, but no, it does not mean it &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to be the technologies involved in cotton production that led to sustained growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really big question, though, is whether I can get out the next post in under six months. Stay tuned. But not too closely, because you might waste a few months waiting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Where did all the investment go?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Investment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Investment/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The fact that economic growth has slowed in the last few decades is not news, at least not on this blog. And I’ve been through a series of possible explanations over the course of the last few years. One bit of data that I played around with a few years ago was the decline in the growth rate of capital per worker. In this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/describing-the-decline-of-capital-per-worker/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; I looked at some figures using BLS data that showed the amount of capital per worker was &lt;em&gt;declining&lt;/em&gt; in 2010-2013. That was unprecedented, as even during recessions in the past it was the case that capital per worker kept growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new working paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/2_gutierrezphilippon.pdf&quot;&gt;German Gutierrez and Thomas Philippon&lt;/a&gt; (GP) has taken on this same topic, only in much more detail, and with a lot of effort put into understanding &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; investment has been low recently. Moreover, they document that investment by firms has been falling over a longer period of time, coincident in large part with the productivity slowdown of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;investment-is-lower-than-youd-expect-given-profits&quot;&gt;Investment is lower than you’d expect given profits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GP start by documenting that firms remain profitable over time, but that their investments are declining over time. This first figure shows the net operating return on capital for non-financial firms (which do the bulk of non-residential investment). “Business” here is the umbrella covering both corporate and non-corporate firms. What is apaprent from GP’s first figure is that the net operating return on capital has remained constant, or grown, over time. For corporations, it is about 10% throughout this period, while for non-corporate firms it has gone up from about 20% to almost 30%. So the decline in investment by firms is not because they are unprofitable. Even the financial crisis in 2009 only produces a slight dip in the net operating returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net operating return on capital&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second figure shows the crux of the story in GP. Net investment (investment spending minus deprecation) relative to net operating surplus appears to have shifted down after 2000. Prior to that, net investment averaged roughly 20% of net operating surplus, while afterwards it averaged only about 10%. I’m not sure how hard to think about the spike in this ratio in the 1990’s - this may be a temporary thing driven by the same technology surge that appears to have driven productivity growth - but you might be able to argue that the average net investment rate got down to 10% as early as 1990. Regardless, it is clear that the investment rate out of operating surplus fell, and stayed low, in the 2000’s. This, derived from more finely-grained data, is the equivalent of what I was talking about in my post from a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net investment relative to net operating surplus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as GP point out, it is not the case that we should expect this ratio of net investment to net operating surplus to be constant over time. Firms are (presumably) optimizing their investment behavior to maximize profits, and based on changing conditions it might make sense to invest more or less of their net operating surplus. What GP work through is a standard model of firm behavior, and link net investment to Tobin’s Q. This metric is, roughly, the market value of a firm relative to the replacement cost of its capital. If Q is more than 1, then the firm should be investing enough to &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; its capital stock, because market value they get from having capital is more than what it costs to install it. If Q is less than one, the firm should let its capital stock run down (allow depreciation to outweigh investment) as the they are not generating as much market value with their capital as they would pay to replace it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two measures of Q&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation, then, for the decline in net investment relative to net operating surplus is just that Tobin’s Q fell. And Tobin’s Q would fall if people expected particularly low future earnings (and hence gave firms lower market values) or if the replacement cost of capital was rising. But as GP show, Q wasn’t falling. It was &lt;em&gt;rising&lt;/em&gt;, at least for corporate firms. The two measures of Q differ by how exactly GP calculate it, as it isn’t obvious how to treat a set of miscellaneous assets and liabilities at firms in order to come up with the market value part of the Q ratio. Regardless, however Q is measured, it is now relatively high compared to the 1980’s, and only lags the very high values seen in the late 1990’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net investment versus Q ratio&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GP then use the data on investment rates and Q from 1990 to 2001 to get a baseline relationship of the two. Given that relationship, they look at what the net investment rate &lt;em&gt;would have been&lt;/em&gt; given the Q values we had in the 2000’s, if investment had continued to follow that 1990-2001 relationship. In the above figure, this is plotted as the orange dashed line. Compared to that is the solid green line, which is the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; net investment rate. You can see that starting in 2000 the observed investment rate is always &lt;em&gt;below&lt;/em&gt; the predicted investment rate, and sometimes by substantial amounts. Based on this, GP conclude that firms are under-investing compared to how they used to. This, despite the fact that they are profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blame-it-on-concentration-and-institutional-ownership&quot;&gt;Blame it on concentration and institutional ownership&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; are firms investing less given their Q ratio and profitability? GP go through an extensive list of possible explanations, which I will not repeat here. Let me jump ahead to the two explanations that hold up across all of their analysis: concentration and institutional ownership. Before I get on to that, let me say that their analysis consists of regressions of net investment rates at either aggregate, industry, or firm level on various sets of control variables. In each case, they control for Q itself, to capture the natural fluctuations in net investment rates. The other control variables are there to see if they are significantly &lt;em&gt;correlated&lt;/em&gt; with net investment rates. GP have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www8.gsb.columbia.edu/faculty-research/sites/faculty-research/files/finance/Macro%20Lunch/IK_Comp_v1.pdf&quot;&gt;companion paper&lt;/a&gt; which does more work trying to see if those significant correlations are in fact causal. For the time being, let’s just hang in there with the correlations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across all these regressions, what keeps showing up is a significant correlation between net investment rates and measures of concentration and measures of institutional ownership, while other possible correlations are insignificant or disappear once you control for other variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For concentration, what GP mean is fewer firms within small sub-industries, implying that each remaining firm has possibly more market power. At the aggregate level, the following figure shows that the rate of firm entry and exit has declined over time, consistent with all the evidence that the John Haltiwanger-led posse of researchers has been banging on for several years. Less entry means fewer new competitors entering, and less exit means fewer firms are being forced out of business. This is consistent with higher concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Establishment exit and entry rates&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would concentration limit investment? The simple intuition is that if you don’t have to worry about competing with anyone, why bother to blow any money investing in a better product? Think of a cable company (&lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt; Comcast &lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt;) which has a monopoly in a local market. What incentive do they have to either upgrade their technology to make it more reliable or faster, and what incentive do they have to invest in, say, more repair vans and extra technicians? None, because they know you can’t go anywhere. Be careful to not run too far in the other direction, however. If firms have &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt; market power, they also will have no incentive to invest, because any advantage they get will be immediately competed away. Somewhere in there is some kind of market power/concentration level that maximizes firms incentives to invest (and innovate, by the way). GP’s results suggest we are on the “back side” of the curve, and increasing concentration is leading to less investment (i.e. more Comcasts) rather than creating incentives for firms to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second significant correlation GP find is with institutional ownership of firms, which can include mutual funds and pension funds. Since 1980, these institutional investors have taken on larger and larger stakes in corporations, to the point that the average firm has about 60% ownership by institutions as opposed to individuals. I’ll admit to not being quite clear on what a “transient” institution means, but the “quasi-indexers” are things like actual index funds as well as widely-diversified mutual funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp10b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Institutional ownership&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the share of quasi-indexers rises, GP find, the rate of net investment falls. Now, you can tell yourself a lot of stories about this, both good and bad. The bad is that quasi-indexers are pushing firms to think only about short-term ((e.g. quarterly) results, and as such firms are loath to spend on long-term investments. The good is that quasi-indexers are pushing management to be more thoughtful about exactly what they invest in, which would imply that the high rates of net investment before were probably &lt;em&gt;too high&lt;/em&gt;. It isn’t obvious which one of those interpretations is correct, on the face of it. The prima facie evidence would be that the growth rate of GDP has fallen in the same period in which the net investment rate has fallen, suggesting the bad interpretation is correct. But there could be other forces at work that kept the growth rate high in the 1980’s, even though the net investment rate was too high. So don’t pull out the torches and pitchforks just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Buybacks and payouts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the intepretation of the institutional ownership, what GP do document is that share buybacks have climbed over this period. Mechanically, spending more on doing share buybacks means less money left over for net investment. It appears that firms, since the early 1980’s, have been using more of their net operating surplus to buy back existing shares (driving up the market value for existing owners) and less on investment. The total payouts/assets in this last figure include buybacks and dividends, and after 1982 you can see that the trend upward in total payouts/assets is driven by an increase in buybacks. GP note in the figure 1982 as an important point because this is when the SEC passed a rule (10b-18) allowing companies to repurchase their own shares on the open market without any regulatory limit. Prior to that, there were restrictions on how much they could repurchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a major shareholder of a firm, you can think of two major ways of making money off your holding. First, you could pursue long-term investments to grow the business and/or expand your market. This would raise the value of your shares by increasing the assets of the firm. Second, you could get the firm to buy back existing shares, driving up their price, and the value of your shares would increase proportionately. This second strategy is faster (you don’t need to wait to install the capital) and arguably less risky, because you don’t have to make a commitment to a new plant or location that may or may not prove to be profitable. Of course, you could go back and argue again that firms were over-investing in the past, and that the buybacks allow those shareholder who were bought out to reinvest their money in higher-return projects. Again, the prima facie evidence is working against you here, but that doesn’t mean you’re wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note here is that GP look separately at the effect of concentration and institutional ownership on capital expenditures (e.g. physical equipment) and R&amp;amp;D spending. Higher concentration and more institutional ownership are correlated with lower rates of spending on both. The decline in investment they document is not just for physical equipment (which perhaps one could argue is becoming less relevant for production) but also for R&amp;amp;D (which one could not argue is becoming less relevant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-it-really-matter-for-growth&quot;&gt;Does it really matter for growth?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last section of GP covers the implications of this for growth. I’m not going to go through their work in detail, as they are trying to line it up with some work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/fernaldtextsp17bpea.pdf&quot;&gt;Fernald, Hall, Stock, and Watson&lt;/a&gt;, and that gets more complicated than I want to cover in a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But GP do sneak in an interesting point in their discussion about the importance of falling investment for growth. If we think that the underlying growth rate of productivity has fallen, which is what appears in the data regarding productivity growth, then this implies that the long-run capital/output ratio should &lt;em&gt;rise&lt;/em&gt;. For those of you who grok the Solow model, the capital/output ratio is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K/Y = s/(n+\delta+g)\inline&quot;/&gt; in steady state. Lower g, higher K/Y ratio. Except that we do not see a higher K/Y ratio over time. It has remained relatively constant, even as the trend growth rate of productivity has fallen. So something else must be going on, and one possibility is that “s” has fallen. In the Solow model, that “s” is the share of output that is turned into investment goods (“saved”) every period. Consistent with the GP story, if s has fallen at the same time g has fallen, then the K/Y ratio will remain roughly constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that the growth rate of GDP gets pulled down even more than it would be through just the decline in g. If s stayed constant, then the drop in g would lower the growth rate of GDP, but the increase in the K/Y ratio would offset that by a little. With the coincident drop in s, we don’t get that offset, and so the effect of the drop in g is particularly pronounced. GP speculate that increased market power of firms can explain why s dropped at the same time as g. That story is consistent with the data that is accumulating, for sure. I have not worked through their companion paper on causality in detail yet, so I can’t offer any opinion on whether increased concentration or market power appears to &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; the decline in s. For now, let’s leave it out there as a very plausible story for what has occurred. Whatever the causality, their initial evidence is clear that there has been a decline in net investment, and that warrants attention if we’re trying to account for why the growth rate of GDP has fallen over the last few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why don't tax cuts boost growth?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxing-GDP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxing-GDP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Relative to current events, this probably seems less important at the moment, and a week or so too late, but the tax cut proposed by th Trump administration is still kicking around. There have been any number of responses to it, and responses in particular to the claim that it will “supercharge” economic growth, and ultimately pay for itself. In short, it won’t do either of those things, which is the conclusion you come to after reviewing all the evidence available. I did so here, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxes-Growth/&quot;&gt;prior post&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/posteverything/wp/2017/09/28/i-helped-create-the-gop-tax-myth-trump-is-wrong-tax-cuts-dont-equal-growth/&quot;&gt;Bruce Bartlett&lt;/a&gt; just posted an article where he also comes to that conclusion, and recants his earlier stand in the 1980’s pushing the whole “tax cuts increase growth” line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is not to rehash the arguments and evidence showing that tax cuts do not increase growth. Rather, I want to think a little about &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they do not increase growth. Because the claim that they do &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; right, but fails in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with some basics. If you want to raise economic growth - meaning an increase in real GDP - then you need to increase the amount of capital, labor, and/or productivity. Whether that is pulling new capital, labor, or innovations into the economy, or putting idle capital, labor, and innovations back to work is irrelevant. You want to increase the inputs to increase GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of economics is that people respond to incentives. In the case of inputs, the incentives to provide them are the returns they earn, like wages, dividends or interest, or profits. If you tax those returns, that lowers the returns, and people will provide less labor, capital, or innovations. So if you lower that tax, the idea is that people will provide &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; labor, capital, or innovation. Nothing here is rocket science. Why does it not work the way we think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;small-elasticities&quot;&gt;Small elasticities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think that if you lower the tax rate, and hence raise the returns to inputs, we should get more of them. But to “supercharge” growth in GDP, or to have any appreciable effect on GDP at all, you need that the elasticity of that input supply with respect to those returns is really big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For labor, there appears to be good evidence that this elasticity is in fact &lt;em&gt;small&lt;/em&gt;. There is not some pent-up store of workers and human capital out there that is just a 35% tax bracket away from getting off their ass and going to work. This labor supply elasticity is found to be essentially zero in almost every case, with the exception of married women. You can see some citations on this in the review paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/jeclit/v50y2012i1p3-50.html&quot;&gt;Saez, Slemrod, and Giertz&lt;/a&gt; (SSG).  With an elasticity close to zero, no matter how much you lower the tax rate, and raise the return to labor (i.e. the wage), you can’t induce a substantial increase in labor supply. And without a substantial increase in labor supply, you don’t get a big increase in GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the capital side, this is tougher to estimate because while it is easy to assert that reported wages are payments for real labor, it is much harder to say what part of reported business income is a payment to “capital”. Dividends are probably one of the cleanest things to look at, as they are direct payments to stockholders. But when &lt;a href=&quot;https://eml.berkeley.edu/~yagan/DividendTax.pdf&quot;&gt;Yagan&lt;/a&gt; looked at the 2003 dividend tax cut, he found there was no effect on corporate investment (i.e. real capital inputs). In other words, the elasticity of real capital inputs to the tax rate was zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For innovation, there is some better evidence of an effect of taxation on R&amp;amp;D activity (although we have to be careful to distinguish between R&amp;amp;D activity and innovation itself). &lt;a href=&quot;http://economics.mit.edu/files/12817&quot;&gt;Dechezlepretre, Einio, Martin, Nguyen, and Van Reenan&lt;/a&gt; have a working paper that uses a change in the threshold for qualifying for an R&amp;amp;D tax credit in the UK on both R&amp;amp;D spending &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; patenting, meaning they are trying to see an effect on actual innovation. They find significant effects of R&amp;amp;D tax incentives on R&amp;amp;D and patenting. Now, tax incentives (like an actual tax credit or allowing firms to write off R&amp;amp;D spending) are not exactly the same as tax rates. And the current tax proposal, so far as I can tell, does not include a specific change to R&amp;amp;D incentives. Changing the marginal tax rate on individual income or corporate income is not the same as providing R&amp;amp;D tax incentives. But, if you are looking for an avenue for tax policy to spur growth, then creating incentives for R&amp;amp;D and innovation appears more plausible than lowering tax rates on labor and capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-tax-financial-flows-not-inputs&quot;&gt;We tax financial flows, not inputs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing reducing the impact of tax cuts on GDP is that taxes are not levied on only the transactions that are part of GDP, they are levied on all kinds of transactions. Think of the fact that every year there are billions (and maybe trillions) of individual transactions that take place in the economy. &lt;em&gt;Some&lt;/em&gt; of those transactions involve payment for a real input like labor or capital, which means they are part of GDP. But &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of those transactions are purely financial, and so are not. But the tax code does not make this distinction; you are not taxed only on your transactions that contribute to GDP, you are taxed on all (okay, most) of your transactions where you receive some money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break this down to four different kinds of transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taxed, and income is from providing a real input. Your paycheck is an example. You provide a real input (labor) to your employer, and hence this income is part of GDP. The income you earn is also subject to taxation. So if you lower the tax rate on this income, you presumably will supply more labor, which will raise GDP. As we saw above, this response would be small for both labor and capital, so GDP would not go up by much. Lower taxes on R&amp;amp;D or innovation might have a more tangible effect.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Untaxed, and income does not come from providing a real input. Think of a small gift of cash, under the IRS threshold, from your grandparents to you. This is income, in the sense that you have an inflow of money, but it is not in return for a real input. It is untaxed because it happens to be small in size.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Untaxed, and income is from providing a real input. You could think of small scale payments for work that fall below IRS reporting thresholds, like babysitting or some home services. Now, because they do not have to be reported to the IRS, they are untaxed, but its also likely they don’t get picked up and &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; as part of GDP. But technically, because they involve someone providing a real input like labor, this income &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be measured as part of GDP. Regardless, because they are untaxed, lowering tax rates would do nothing to change the real inputs people provide here; your babysitter is not going to offer to do a 2nd night a week if the marginal tax rate falls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taxed, and income does not come from providing a real input. Here we’ve got a whole world of financial transactions. If you buy shares of stock for cash, there is no real input provided, so this transaction does not add to GDP. But, this transaction is taxed, in the sense that the capital gain to the seller is subject to tax. If you lower tax rates, then you will get more of these financial transactions, but that will not add anything to GDP. [A side note is that the &lt;em&gt;commissions&lt;/em&gt; on this trade &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; get counted as part of GDP, because they are made for providing a real service.]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big reason that tax cuts do not boost growth in GDP is that tax cuts apply to transactions of type 4, as well as type 1. Lowering the tax rate should increase transactions of both types In practice, the elasticities involved in type 1 transactions are small, so there is little change in &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; inputs provided by tax cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But tax cuts may have a big effect on those type 4, financial, transactions. Those type 4 transactions may boost &lt;em&gt;taxable incomes&lt;/em&gt; by making the transactions more attractive, but have no impact on the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; provision of inputs which would go into raising GDP. SSG use the example of the 1986 tax reform to demonstrate this. In response to this, there was a surge in reported S-corp income (i.e. “pass-through” income), which implies a legal shift from corporations to S-corp’s, but this had no practical effect on the supply of inputs to the economy. It is just reshuffling the paper ownership of companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, you &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; make the argument that if you want to raise GDP it would be ideal to raise taxes on financial transactions (a la the Tobin tax) to reduce the incentives to do those type 4 transactions, but lower taxes on type 1 transactions dealing with the provision of real inputs, and definitely provide incentives to R&amp;amp;D spending and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to convince me that these financial transactions of type 4 &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have an important effect on real GDP growth, then you’d have to talk me into believing that facilitating the exchange of ownership leads to a more efficient allocation of management ability, or something like that. For that to be true, it would have to be that there are a lot of exchanges of ownership that are not currently taking place because they are not worth it due to high taxes. But the prima facie evidence works against you, because you’d want to show me that there has been some kind of decline, or stagnation in financial transactions like this over time, and that is just not the case. But that’s your in, if you are looking for one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That aside, I think it’s key to reiterate that claiming tax cuts will not have an effect on growth is not a denial of the basic theory. Rather, the claim is based on the low elasticities, which mean that the responses are small, and a disconnect between the returns that are &lt;em&gt;taxed&lt;/em&gt; and the returns that are paid to real inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Harvey</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Harvey/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Harvey/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You may or may not realize that the global headquarters of Growthecon.com is in Houston. So it’s been an interesting few days, to say the least. This post has nothing to do with economics. It’s just things that keep running through my head as we clean up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live a charmed life, for so many reasons. But most recently, it’s the fact that we made it out of the storm with a dry house (barely) and with everyone safe. Lots of our neighbors are not so lucky, so we’ve been doing what we can to help. It doesn’t feel like much. I hope it makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this post is me documenting things I don’t want to forget, which includes a lot of raw emotions in response to some amazing events. So farther down you are going to find me taking some shots that maybe one day I’ll regret. Maybe. But right now I don’t think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-is-what-lucky-looks-like&quot;&gt;This is what lucky looks like&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday night, the 26th, is when the rain started hard in the Houston area. We didn’t sleep. We just watched the rain come down, and ran outside during breaks to clear debris away from the storm drain in front of our house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Houston Flood Control district has an online system recording rain totals around the bayous in the city. If you watched the news, you know the bayous are a series of artificially widened creeks that drain the city into the Gulf. Here’s the time series of rainfall totals from the Braes Bayou near Stella Link road, the closest gauge to our house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_rain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rainfall totals&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already had 1.32 inches during the morning of the 26th, and then before midnight we added another 3.56 inches. For some sense of scale, 4.88 inches is right around the typical &lt;em&gt;monthly&lt;/em&gt; total for August in Houston. And that was before the heavy stuff came. Between midnight and noon on Sunday, the 27th, we took 9.92 inches, most of that between midnight and 3am. I cannot describe for you how fast and how hard the rain came down in the first few hours of Sunday. And our area wasn’t the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a break Sunday morning, and this was the view out of our front door. That front areas of bricks was under an inch of water that you can’t quite make out in the picture. Under the street light, on the left, is the storm drain. When I waded out there to check it for blockages, the water was at my waist. Across the street from the light is supposed to be a fire hydrant. It was under water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_worst.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flooding&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That water rose not just because it rained hard, but because the bayou overflowed, and there was no place for it to go. The flood district also provides plots of the level of each bayou at certain stations, and here’s the time series of Braes Bayou. You can see the essentially vertical rise right around midnight of the 26th, into the 27th. At that point the rains continued, and the bayou, thanks to our rain, rain upstream flowing down, and rain downstream backing it up, stayed above flood level into Monday the 28th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_bayou.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bayou level&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you flip back to the rain chart, you’ll see that we still got 3.2, 2.28, and 6.24 inches of rain in the 36 hours &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the heavy stuff. Believe it or not, this is where we got lucky. That let-up of 3.2 and 2.28 inches allowed the bayou to recede, just a little. It bought us a few inches to spare, so when the 6.24 came, our house was able to survive. When I wandered downstairs at about 1:30am on Monday morning, the water had at retreated about one foot from our house, and it wouldn’t come closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its height, we came within 1-3 inches of flooding, depending where exactly around the house you looked. Over the rest of the morning of the 28th, Monday, the water retreated further, and we (personally) were out of trouble. Some tense moments occurred on Tuesday as we took more rain, but never enough to flood the bayou near us again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said, this is a story of amazing luck. Through all that, we didn’t flood. We didn’t even lose power throughout the storm. We didn’t do anything special, it just turns out that our house is one or two inches higher than a few others on our street. People just a few doors down our street are now ripping out carpet and drywall. I don’t know the exact number of people we know who flooded, but it’s more than I can count up quickly in my head. We’ve tried to help people out, but it feels like very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;people-really-are-amazing&quot;&gt;People really are amazing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just about a week ago, I was still reading stories about alt-right neo-Nazi shitheads with brittle egos and tiki torches. And right as Harvey was hitting land the first time, known terrorist Joe Arpaio was getting pardoned for taking a dump on the Constitution. But for each and every one of those people, I saw over the last week hundreds and thousands of decent human beings put everything they had on the line to help perfect strangers. Hundreds and thousands. Remember that when the news gets back to publicizing the worst among us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a few of the best:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everyone with a boat. They came from Houston itself, from the rest of Texas, from Louisiana, from Kentucky, from Michigan, and hundreds of places I missed. Brave, selfless, and inexhaustible. These people drove &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; the shitstorm that was Harvey and got to work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jeff Lindner and everyone at the Houston Flood Control District. Step by step, Lindner came on TV or radio and talked everyone through the situation with the bayous and rivers. Never flustered, never hyperbolic, never flippant, he is part of the reason this didn’t turn out more chaotic than it already was.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;City of Houston and Harris County emergency response teams. I hope you all can go home and sleep for six months. I hope &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; families and &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; homes are safe and dry. And yes, that includes Mayor Turner and Judge Emmett (the county administrator). Those two somehow kept it together the whole time. I’m sure you can find some mistake they made along the way, but anyone who wants to nitpick their decisions should be invited to kiss both of their asses.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eric and Matt at &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacecityweather.com&quot;&gt;Space City Weather&lt;/a&gt;. Those two were a beacon of sanity and reality throughout the weekend. The TV weather guys were not over the top, but were often just struggling to keep up with the constant series of tornado and flood warnings. Eric and Matt were able to put out clear and concise summaries, about every 3-4 hours, of what was coming.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The National Weather Service. Without the information provided by these people, this and every hurricane (not to mention most tornadoes) are mass casualty events. Keep this in mind when you start getting antsy to cut funding at federal agencies to support a tax cut. Weather information doesn’t “trickle down”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I haven’t mentioned all the people that are out right now volunteering their time to clean out their neighbor’s houses, or cook them food, or help evacuees fill out FEMA forms, or … everything else they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every editor of every newpaper, magazine, and website out there, here’s the deal. Go out and find every single one of these magnificent people. Go find them and tell their story. Until you do that, I don’t want to see or hear another piece that involves the term “real America”, or how some unnamed official is “distressed” at something happening in the White House, or provides a profile of some shitbag neo-Nazi with a self-esteem issue. And until you find all these people, I don’t want to read any Vox or Atlantic columns on “What Harvey says about …”. It’s a catastrophe, not a fucking metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you wondering why the whole city didn’t evacuate, do you really think that the city was shocked to discover it could be hit by a massive hurricane? Sheltering in place was not some shoot-from-the-hip wild guess of a strategy. It’s the best of bunch of crappy options. If you want to have a discussion, say a month from now after the worst of this is all over, about whether there are ways to effect an evacuation during the next Harvey-like event, great. Let’s do it. In the meantime, your homework is to devise a plan to evacuate the &lt;em&gt;entire state of Massachusetts&lt;/em&gt; subject to the following constraints. (A) you have 48 hours, (B) you can’t use Rhode Island, Connecticut, or New York, and (C) everyone needs shelter for up to 10 days. Go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read this far, thanks. It was a self-indulgent brain dump from someone with exactly zero problems right now. I should be outside finding a better way to help than generating a blog post. If you have a mind to help, one charity that my wife has been involved with, and does a great job locally, is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.houstonfoodbank.org&quot;&gt;Houston Food Bank&lt;/a&gt;. Go there, give them money. Let them feed people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rising Markups and Falling Productivity</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/DE-Markups/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/DE-Markups/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In between checking weather updates here in Houston, I finally got around to reading the new working paper by Jan De Loecker and Jan Eeckhout (DE), on “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.janeeckhout.com/wp-content/uploads/RMP.pdf&quot;&gt;The Rise of Market Power and the Macroeconomic Implications&lt;/a&gt;”. The authors find that the markup of price over marginal cost charged by public US firms has been rising steadily since 1960, and in particular after 1980. It has generated a lot of commentary already, as in this &lt;a href=&quot;http://noahpinionblog.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by Noah Smith, this &lt;a href=&quot;https://niskanencenter.org/blog/markups-market-power/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by Karl Smith, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2017/08/rise-market-power.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; from Tyler Cowen. A lot of the discussion so far has been about how to interpret their results, and whether it indicates a rise in “market power”, and that devolved somewhat into a discussion of how to define “market power” in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to jump in with some of my own thoughts on the paper, but I’m going to avoid getting into this “market power” interpretation thing. I’m more interested in what DE’s results have to say about the productivity slowdown. Let’s start with how DE get these numbers in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;estimating-markups&quot;&gt;Estimating markups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing; you can’t observe these markups. While the price of a specific good might be knowable, the marginal cost of that good is not. The average cost of producing that good - total costs divided by number of goods sold - is not the same thing as the marginal cost. I’d be willing to bet that a lot of firms would be hard-pressed themselves to tell you the marginal cost of an additional good. And that doesn’t even get into the issue with multi-product firms, where their aggregated financials cannot tell you about the specific prices and costs associated with specific products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when DE are talking about estimating markups, they are extracting the markup of a firms “price” over the firms “marginal cost”, where the price is some agglomeration of the prices of their various products, and the cost is some agglomeration of the cost of their various inputs. That’s not a knock on the approach, but it should be kept in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you extract this markup if you don’t have the exact costs, or even prices? DE assume that firms are cost-minimizers, a less forceful assumption than strict profit maximization. Whether firms are pricing their goods to maximize profits or not is immaterial to DE, but they assume that firms are trying to produce their goods or services using the lowest-cost combination of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the logic involved in the firm’s decision pretty easily. If a firm’s markup is the price relative to marginal cost, then for the marginal good it produces, it should be that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Rev = Markup \times MC \times Inputs&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Rev\inline&quot;/&gt; is the revenue from that marginal good, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Markup\inline&quot;/&gt; is the … markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC\inline&quot;/&gt; is the cost of an additional bundle of inputs, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Inputs\inline&quot;/&gt; are the bundles of inputs it takes to produce that marginal good. Simply rearrange this to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Markup = \frac{Rev}{MC \times Inputs}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you’ve got it. DE have data on firm-level revenues, and they have data on firm-level costs for inputs. There is an extra step, which is that this kind of condition should hold for each separate input (i.e. labor and capital) as opposed to “Inputs” the way I’ve described it. All this does is insert a parameter into this expression that weights revenues by how important that specific input is to production. If we were working with labor, for instance, we might say that the revenue &lt;em&gt;attributable to labor&lt;/em&gt; is only 60% of total revenues, and so divide 0.6 times revenues by the cost of labor to arrive at the markup. For the purposes of this post, though, I think you can easily stick with the idea that markups are obtained from ratios of revenues to costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DE do this for all the public firms they have data for, for all the years running from 1960 to recently. The figure below is the central result, which is that markups rose steadily from 1960’s - when they were about 1.18 on average - to today, when they are about 1.67 on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DE_2017_Fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Evolution of Markups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those papers where it shocks you that no one has done this before. This paper takes some relatively off-the-shelf techniques, and uses them to generate an incredibly interesting set of estimates. Granted, the authors are some of the people who put those techniques up on the shelf in the first place, but the innovation in this paper is the application to the long panel of US public firms, not the techniques. The results in this figure are what have generated a lot of commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the big empirical caveats. If you want to disbelieve DE’s results, then you’d have to think hard about the effect of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sample is only public firms. Probably the biggest question mark. The average markup charged by &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; firms in the economy may not have changed much over time, but if there was a distinct change in the choice to either go public, or stay public, starting around 1980, and that change was related to markup sizes, then this could just be sample selection. For example, you could argue that as investors became laser-focused on quarterly earnings, this meant that the only firms willing to go public or stay public were those with large markups that could generate the expected earnings growth. All the low markup firms are private, and so don’t show up in the DE dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Industry production functions are assumed to be identical for all firms and over time. I mentioned above that DE actually use specific inputs in the calculation, and for that they need these weights (like the 60% for labor I mentioned). To get those, they estimate production functions for each industry using their data. And that estimation assumes that the weights are identical for all firms in an industry (i.e. American and United each have a weight of 44% on labor) and over time (i.e. United’s weight on labor is 44% every year from 1960 forward). DE have an appendix where they relax this assumption, and show that the growth in markups over time (but not their level) is unchanged, so this is unlikely to be driving the results.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cost minimization may not hold. This doesn’t seem like a strong assumption, and it is certainly weaker than assuming full profit maximization. But it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an assumption. If the firms in the DE dataset are not operating to minimize costs (perhaps they just care about maximizing market share or executive compensation?) then the first order condition DE use would be picking up something other than the true markup. I don’t have a great sense of how the bias would work here, or a great sense of whether this could be a big or a small problem. But it could be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to take the DE results as indicative of what is happening in the US as a whole, then the second half of their paper is for you. Here, they break down several secular trends in the economy (e.g. declining labor shares, declining productivity growth) and show how the rise in markups can account for them. As the association of markups with productivity is something I’ve been banging around on for a few years - you could start with this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Cake/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; and work backwards - let me focus on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;productivity-accounting&quot;&gt;Productivity Accounting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presence of markups - and changes in markups - have implications for measured productivity growth. And DE corroborate that, while offering the data to be more precise about the effects. But they do it using a slightly different line of attack than I have in the past, so let me digress for a moment to try and link this all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways we could describe aggregate output. The first is using a production function, like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = T X&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T\inline&quot;/&gt; is &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X\inline&quot;/&gt; is an index of &lt;em&gt;inputs&lt;/em&gt;. Technology, T, is the for-realisies measure of how good we are at transforming inputs into useful output. It is what we really would like to measure. Based on this production function, we could back out technology as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = \frac{Y}{X}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave that aside for the moment, we’ll come back to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also describe aggregate output using incomes, meaning we can write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = \Pi + wX&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\Pi\inline&quot;/&gt; are economic profits, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w\inline&quot;/&gt; is the “wage” of inputs. For those wages, think of something like a weighted average of actual wages (to labor) and payments to capital and/or natural resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are profits? Well, let’s assume that there is a markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu\inline&quot;/&gt;, which recall measures the ratio of price to marginal cost. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu = 1.5\inline&quot;/&gt;, then firms are charging 50% over cost. So profits are equal to 50% of costs. Another way of saying this is that profits are &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu - 1\inline&quot;/&gt; times costs,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = (\mu - 1)wX + wX = \mu w X&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or total output can be expressed as the markup times the wage times the inputs used. We’re still the world of pure accounting, by the way. No behavioral assumptions have been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, go back and compare the original production function version of output, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = T X\inline&quot;/&gt;, to this markup version, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = \mu w X\inline&quot;/&gt;. From these, it shows us that we could write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = \mu w.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or technology is equivalent to the markup times the wage. I like to think of this expression this way: technology (or an increase in technology) can be used for one of two things (a) raising the markup or (b) raising the wage paid to inputs. One quibble with DE is that they say something along the line of “if markups go up, this raises technology”, which should more accurately be phrased “if markups go up, this implies that tecnology was higher”, which eliminates the implicit causal statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve got two ways of backing out technology, T, from the data. Either use &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T = Y/X\inline&quot;/&gt;, or use &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T = \mu w\inline&quot;/&gt;. In terms of growth rates, the first says that the growth rate of technology (using little hats to denote growth rates) is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{T} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X}\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the second says that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{T} = \hat{\mu} + \hat{w}\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s great, but when we go to the data is it quite plausible that we make mistakes. That is, we go to the data and calculate residual &lt;em&gt;productivity&lt;/em&gt;, P. And unless we are exactly right about how the world works, our measure of P may not be equal to T. Here’s what I mean. Take the production function version of things, which I’ve talked about a lot before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{P} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X}^{wrong} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X} + (\hat{X} - \hat{X}^{wrong}) = \hat{T} + (\hat{X} - \hat{X}^{wrong})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of productivity is the growth rate of output minus the growth rate of &lt;em&gt;a possibly mismeasured index of input use&lt;/em&gt;. This mismeasurement may be because we really don’t know how to count units of capital or human capital correctly, or because we are weighting those counts incorrectly. The point I’ve made in a few posts in the past is that by ignoring markups, you could may be making a weighting mistake, and this would lead to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{X}^{wrong} &amp;gt; \hat{X}\inline&quot;/&gt;, so productivity growth understates technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you instead were going to try and measure productivity growth using the real wage, then you could get something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{P} = \hat{\mu}^{wrong} + \hat{w} = (\hat{\mu}^{wrong} - \hat{\mu}) + \hat{\mu} +  \hat{w} = \hat{T} + (\hat{\mu}^{wrong} - \hat{\mu})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where you might be making an error about how fast markups are growing. If you do, and in particular if you assume &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{\mu}^{wrong} &amp;lt; \hat{\mu}\inline&quot;/&gt;, which you might do if you assumed markups were unchanging over time, then your productivity growth term understates technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what DE essentially do in the very last part of the paper. They say that by falsely assuming markups are constant, productivity growth measured using changes in real wages is understating true technological growth. When they make an adjustment to allow for the real growth in markups they observe, they find that true technological growth was around 3-4% per year over the last few year, as opposed to almost 0% growth in measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a massive difference, and suggests that (a) technological progress is clipping along very nicely, thank you, and (b) that almost all of the gains from this are being leveraged into higher markups rather than higher real wages to inputs like labor. Entirely consistent with stories of increased market power and concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t a glaring issue with the analysis that DE do here, but they could go further with it. The papers that establish the discrepancies between growth in productivity, P, and technology, T, point out that much of the problem stems from trying to do this at the aggregate level alone. If you had individual firm-level (or plant-level) data on technological growth, then you could add those up directly (suitably weighted by their size), to arrive at &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T\inline&quot;/&gt; directly. No need to back it out from aggregate information on inputs used, or wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And DE have all the data to do this. When they estimate the production functions that allow them to recover the markups, they also recover an estimate of technology for each firm. It would be straightforward to find technological growth from the “bottom-up”, and compare it to what we get using aggregate methods. This would give us (a) a true(r) measure of technological growth and (b) help identify what precisely we are doing wrong with the aggregate measures of productivity growth. I’ll let DE add that to the near-infinite list of things that people have suggested they do with this data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-are-markups-higher&quot;&gt;Why are markups higher?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of productivity, and for most of the other secular trends DE talk about, the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; of the markup is irrelevant. Arguing about whether markups represent market power or not, or whether monopolistic competition is equivalent to market power, adds nothing to the discussion of the implications. They would matter if we were talking about how to change markups. But at this stage DE are simply documenting the growth in markups and showing that these can be associated with a number of phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much of the discussion about the markups has circled around market power, let me point out two additional possible sources of markups, and growth in markups. First, scale. If there are increasing returns to scale, then the markup will be above one. Think of a firm with big fixed costs. They have to charge above marginal cost in order to recover those fixed costs. You could imagine that what has changed over time is that the firms in the DE dataset invested in some fixed costs that gave them increasing returns to scale, and the markups are covering those costs. The problem with this explanation is that you wouldn’t expect labor’s and capital’s share of output to be declining over time in this case, which they are. So perhaps it doesn’t matter much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it could be us. That is, the markup could be rising because consumers are getting more particular about their bundle of purchases. Whether these firms are true monopolists, or involved in monopolistic competition, or compete in some kind of strategic game with one another, the more inelastic our demand gets for their product, the bigger the markups they can charge. I think of this as a caveat of structural change. As our basic material needs get met more easily over time, we get pickier about the goods and services we consume, making our demand more inelastic. This could explain some of the rise in markups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take seriously the DE findings, then decomposing this rise in markups into different sources is the natural next step. The other step is to find ways to confirm that this rise in markups is robust to non-public, and possibly non-US, firms. Tracking similar changes across countries would help eliminate or confirm some explanations (US-specific anti-trust policies). Nevertheless, I found the DE paper an intriguing (and very large) step forwards.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
