<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Growth Economics Blog</title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description>Dietrich Vollrath Economic Growth Blog</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 09:05:26 -0500</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technology versus the Distribution of Workers in Aggregate Productivity</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Decomposition/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Decomposition/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There was a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://artir.wordpress.com/2016/04/25/no-great-technological-stagnation/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by an engineer rebutting Robert Gordon’s (and others) thesis that technological change was slowing down. The evidence cited is a series of plots and figures showing how specific technologies (battery storage, energy efficiency, computer speed, etc..) are advancing just as fast as they have for decades, if not faster. And there were a number of responses along the lines of “See, Gordon is wrong!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mistake here is that this doesn’t constitute evidence that Gordon is wrong. But the mistake is partly forgivable because Gordon himself indulges in these kinds of anecdotal arguments to advance his thesis, and so it seems as if you could refute his conclusions by offereing alternative anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the important part of Gordon’s argument is not that specific technologies are or are not advancing. It is that &lt;em&gt;aggregate productivity growth&lt;/em&gt; is slowing down. And aggregate productivity growth depends not only on individual technologies, but crucially on the distribution of workers using those technologies. Arguing about only those individual technologies is like using an increase in the price of milk to argue that inflation must be high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggregate productivity growth depends on what we can call “within-sector” growth, which is going to be tied closely to those individual technologies. But it also depends on “across-sector” growth, which is tied to the movement of workers from one sector (or job) to another. If workers are shifting from high- to low-productivity sectors or jobs, then aggregate productivity growth may fall even though nothing happened to actual technological change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll make this more clear below, but here’s a quick summary of what I’ll try to establish. Gordon’s critics could well be right about their individual technologies, and yet wrong about this having anything to do with aggregate growth, because those sectors may not employ many people. And Gordon can be right about aggregate growth, but wrong about individual technologies stagnating, because the movement of workers to low-productivity sectors may be dragging down growth. In short, you cannot talk about aggregate productivity growth without talking about both technology &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the distribution of workers across sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gruesome-detail&quot;&gt;Gruesome Detail&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, there is math. Gordon’s argument is about the growth rate of total factor productivity (TFP). But sector and industry level data on TFP isn’t available for the time frames I want, so I’m going to look instead at value-added per hour, a measure of labor productivity. TFP and value-added per hour are going to be highly correlated, but not perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value-added per hour, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y\inline&quot;/&gt;, is the summation across all &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?J\inline&quot;/&gt; sectors of the economy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;y = \sum_{j=1}^J s_j y_j&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_j\inline&quot;/&gt; is the share of total hours worked in sector &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?j\inline&quot;/&gt;, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_j\inline&quot;/&gt; is the value-added per hour in sector &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?j\inline&quot;/&gt;. With that definition, the &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; in value-added per hour from time 0 to time &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt; can be written as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta y_t = \sum_{j=1}^J s_{jt} y_{jt} - \sum_{j=1}^J s_{j0} y_{j0}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t very informative by itself, but by rearranging the terms in those two summations, adding and subtracting some other common terms, and a little algebra, we can get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta y_t = \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} s_{j0} + \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta s_{jt} y_{j0} + \sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} \Delta s_{jt}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of notes on this equation. First, this is the absolute change in value-added per hour. This isn’t the growth rate. You could divide by sides by &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_0\inline&quot;/&gt; to get a growth rate, but as written the equation looks simpler. Second, I’ve made precisely zero assumptions about behavior to get this. This is pure accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three separate summations on the right-hand side can be nicely interpreted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Within-sector growth&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} s_{j0}\inline&quot;/&gt; holds constant the allocation of hours seen at time zero. This is the growth we’d get if all that happened was that each sector got more productive, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\Delta y_{jt}\inline&quot;/&gt;, but we did not allow anyone to change jobs. The idea is to measure just improvements in labor productivity within sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Across-sector growth&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_{j=1}^J \Delta s_{jt} y_{j0}\inline&quot;/&gt; holds constant the value-added per hour seen at time zero. This is the growth we’d get if all that happened was that workers (and their hours of work) moved between jobs. Note that this will be positive if people move from low- to high-productivity jobs, or negative if they move from high- to low-.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Covariance&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_{j=1}^J \Delta y_{jt} \Delta s_{jt}\inline&quot;/&gt; captures the fact that not only do sectors vary in their time-zero level of productivity, but differ in their productivity growth. This term captures whether or not people are moving into sectors where productivity is &lt;em&gt;growing&lt;/em&gt;, which would show up as a positive value. A negative means that workers are moving to sectors where productivity is shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the role of these three effects, I pulled down sector-level data from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rug.nl/research/ggdc/data/10-sector-database&quot;&gt;Groningen 10-sector database&lt;/a&gt; for the U.S., from 1950-2010. The 10 sectors are broad - agriculture, manufacturing, construction, etc. - but have the advantage of spanning a long time frame. I can pull data from the BLS at a much finer industry level at the cost of only going back to 1987. From what I found, the BLS data confirm the story I’ll tell with the Groningen data, so let’s stick with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each year, I calculated the three terms in the above equation, looking backward 10 years each time. So I have the rolling 10-year growth in value-added per hour (VAPH), as well as how it breaks down into within, across, and covariance terms. What I’ve plotted below is the total growth rate, not an annualized rate, so that everything still adds up exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_us_decomp_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;US Decomposition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is pretty clear is that within-sector growth is the dominant force in VAPH. And you can see the early high reported rates of growth of within-sector growth in the 1960’s (which capture growth from the 50’s into the 60’s). There is a clear slowdown in within sector growth from about 1975 to 1990, consistent with all the other evidence, and then things recover not quite back to the 1960’s level. The dip in 2009 and 2010 indicates that growth in VAPH from about 1999/2000 to 2009/2010 has been relatively slow, again consistent with our priors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now look at the contributions of across-sector growth and the covariance term. Across-sector growth is consistently positive throughout most of this period, but starts declining significantly around 1990, so that over the last ten years across-sector growth is &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; for overall growth in VAPH. That means between 2000 and 2010 workers were moving out of sectors with high productivity (in 2000), and into sectors with low productivity (in 2000). Without any slowdown in actual productivity growth, &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; aggregate productivity growth is going to be lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negative contribution of the covariance term tells a similar story of negative effects, although this appears to be a consistent issue. Workers are not only moving into low productivity sectors to begin with, but into sectors with low productivity &lt;em&gt;growth&lt;/em&gt;. This also drags down measured aggregate productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10-year growth rate, starting in the 1990’s (which means the effects started in the early 80’s), no longer lies &lt;em&gt;above&lt;/em&gt; the within-sector growth rate. In other words, starting in the 80’s, we see the across-sector and covariance effects of structural change producing a negligible or even negative effect on VAPH growth. This is most apparent in those final few years of the graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Gordon’s critics, they can be right that individual technologies are still growing quickly, but what they do not account for is that labor may be moving &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; of those sectors and hence aggregrate growth could still be low. If we could get finer and finer levels of industry data, it is quite possible that what looks like a decline in within-sector growth in 2009/2010 is really just negative across-industry growth at those finer levels of industry. Gordon being wrong about whether specific technologies are improving does not make him wrong about aggregate growth declining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the fact that aggregate growth was high in the 40’s and 50’s doesn’t necessarily mean that individual technologies were improving faster than they are today.I don’t have the data, but I’d be fascinated to know what this figure looks like going backwards in the 1950’s and 1940’s, during Gordon’s golden age of productivity growth. Were those decades really a time of amazing “true” technological growth - which might be proxied by the within-sector effect - or did they benefit as much from strong across-sector and covariance terms?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One plausible reason for strong across-sector and covariance terms is the hump-shaped nature of demand for manufactured goods. In the 40’s and 50’s and 60’s, there was within-sector productivity growth in durable goods - refrigerators, TVs, cars - for sure. But this also generated large movements of people &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; those sectors, which would have produced big positive across-sector and covariance terms. Why? Because Americans didn’t own lots of refrigerators, cars, and TVs. Higher within-sector productivity would have lowered prices, and a high elasticity of demand would have meant those sectors pulled labor into those sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But by the 70’s and later, higher within-sector productivity growth in durables and other manufatures may not have generated the same across-sector and covariance effects. Why? Because there are limits to durable good demand. Once everyone has a refrigerator, they tend to want to buy other things, and not &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; refrigerator. I know that’s not totally true; I have a 2nd fridge in my garage that serves as a strategic beer reserve. But in general, demand for durable goods becomes less elastic as we get richer. Which means that within-sector productivity gains don’t pull workers into manufacturing employment, it actively pushes them &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt;. And because the sectors that labor is moving into are relatively low productivity, and have low productivity growth, we get negative across-sector and covariance terms. By the way, there is nothing here that William Baumol couldn’t have told you thirty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A comparison with South Korea is interesting, because they are several decades behind the US in this transformation. In the figure below I plotted the same rolling 10-year growth rates as for the US. It shows the big across-sector contribution to growth in South Korea in the 80’s and 90’s, as they were industrializing heavily and the elasticity of demand for those kinds of durable goods was still large. Compare the figures, and you’ll see that while the US may have had 8% total growth in VAPH due to across-sector effects at the maximum, in South Korea this maximum is closer to 40%. As South Korea got richer, this across-sector contribution has been falling, but is still adding about 6% to total growth in VAPH. The example of South Korea is why I think that part of the explanation for the rapid productivity growth in the US during the 40’s and 50’s could be across-sector effects, and not just a higher rate of innovation or technological change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_kor_decomp_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;SK Decomposition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has now gotten so long that I need to wrap it up. Let me try to do that by essentially repeating my summary from above. You cannot talk about aggregate productivity growth without talking about both technology &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the distribution of workers across sectors. Anecdotes - positive or negative - about individual technologies are not informative about the aggregate level of productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Concentration and Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Comp-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Comp-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A whole raft of posts and articles (&lt;a href=&quot;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2612047&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://promarket.org/are-we-all-rent-seeking-investors/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://equitablegrowth.org/what-are-the-factors-behind-high-economic-rents/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2015/12/17/robert-reich-challenging-oligarchy/#fnr-5&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) has shown up recently regarding “rent-seeking”. This is kind of a catch-all for increased concentration within industries, more lenient anti-trust enforcement, and the increasing share of corporate profits in output. This is then tied to the slowdown in wages over the last few decades, increasing inequality, and even to slower aggregate growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments made by those &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; the concentrating and profit-making is that they are promoting efficiency, productivity, and hence growth. Do we know whether concentration or rent-seeking would be good or bad?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to draw a lot on one of my professors in grad school, Peter Howitt, who along with Philippe Aghion is really one of the godfathers of studying competition and growth. They have a really nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nber.org/papers/w18824.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; with Ufuk Akcigit regarding their “Schumpeterian theory” and how it connects to the data. Schumpeterian theory, for the uninitiated, is growth theory that explicitly deals with firms replacing each other by innovating. This “creative destruction” is what gives the theory its moniker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/aah1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Competition and innovation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AAH paper provides a few sets of empirical results culled from various work done by the authors. One of the most interesting is in the figure posted above, using British industry data, which plots patent activity by firms against the level of competition in their industry. Competition is measured by the ratio of marginal costs to price; the inverse of the markup a firm can charge. A higher ratio means MC and P are very close together in the industry, and hence it is very competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you can see is that patent activity, a proxy for innovation, has this inverted U-shape with respect to competition. That is, increasing competition doesn’t necessary mean more innovation. Why? Because at some point it isn’t worth it to the firms. If you have little market power, what incentive do you have to innovate? In contrast, if you have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of market*, then you also are less inclined to innovate, because why bother? You already control market share, and R&amp;amp;D is just a cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “neck-and-neck” industries are just those in which the leading firms are very close in productivity level. They have an additional incentive to innovate (which shows up as their curve being shifted up) because these firms want to try and shed their main competitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, what this figure implies for concentration and growth is that it depends. Concentration and consolidation mean that industries are moving to the &lt;em&gt;left&lt;/em&gt; along the x-axis, with less competition. Now, if that industry were already very competitive (close to 1, say), the consolidation may actually increase innovation. But if the industry is already consolidated to some degree, then decreasing competition is going to lower innovation and growth. I have in my head the difference between Marriott consolidating hotel chains around the country in the 70s and 80s, reaping some economies of scale, and investing in improved hotel quality, and Marriott in 2016, buying Starwood. Marriott will probably want to argue that they will still innovate more, but the worry is that they are on the “wrong side of the curve” in AAH’s diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/aah2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Entry and Growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second result AAH focus on deals with frontier versus backward firms. Here, they again look at British firms, but along the x-axis is the degree of competition measured by the entry of foreign firms into their industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For “frontier” firms, meaning those who have productivity levels close to the maximum in the industry, increased competition leads to &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; productivity growth. These firms respond to the foreign competition by getting better. But for “non-frontier” firms, the increased entry means they innovate &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt;. Their productivity growth rate actually falls. They don’t try as hard to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question with this result is what it implies for concentration. If concentration means less competition (going left on the x-axis) then this implies frontier firms will innovate &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt;, while non-frontier firms will innovate &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;. But of course concentration implies that firms are buying up one another (or forcing one another out of business). It seems likely that it is the frontier firms pushing the non-frontier firms out of business with concentration. Hence the lower competition would lower the growth rate of productivity in the frontier, and now larger, firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very nice, specific, example of the effect of competition on productivity is in one of my favorite &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.stanford.edu/~klenow/Schmitz.pdf&quot;&gt;papers&lt;/a&gt;, by James Schmitz. He studies the reaction of the US and Canadian iron ore industries to competition from Brazilian suppliers. They responded by massively upgrading productivity relative to its level in the prior decades. His figure shows the jump in labor productivity in the US industry around the early 1980’s, when Brazil came online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/schmitz.png&quot; alt=&quot;Iron Ore Productivity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting about this paper is that Schmitz documents how nearly all of the improvement in productivity came through work practices. There was not any massive technical innovation at play here. The competition changed behavior at the producers of iron ore, and essentially got capital utilization rates (i.e. hours of use per day of machines) way up over prior levels. Productivity improvements are not necessarily a function of R&amp;amp;D, these firms could have made those improvements for decades before Brazil entered. But they had a dominant market position, and didn’t need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, yes, the increasing concentration of industry and rent-seeking, may well be having a demonstrable drag on productivity growth. If this concentration has reduced the need to innovate to stay ahead, because no one can compete with you any more, then this is a negative for growth. Industries, like the iron ore industry prior to the 80’s, that have concentrated market structures with little competition, may not implement even obvious productivity improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there has been a long-run increase in concentration, decline in entry, and consolidation of market power, then this could be part of the productivity slow-down of the late 20th century/early 21st. Ryan Decker, John Haltiwanger, Javier Miranda, and Ron Jarmin, have been banging on the subject of declining “dynamism” for a while. Ryan’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rdecker.net/research&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; is probably the easiest place to find this research all centralized. While I expressed &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/economic-dynamism-and-productivity-growth/&quot;&gt;caution&lt;/a&gt; that declining new business formation is, by itself, necessarily a sign of slower innovation, the whole body of evidence they have about slower gross flows of workers between firms and firms into/out of existence suggests something is quite different over the last few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, and this is my impression, not some kind of established fact, concentration likely lowers innovative activity. Put it this way, the null hypothesis should probably be that concentration lowers innovation. An individual industry needs to provide evidence they are on the “right side of the curve” in the first AAH figure to believe concentration would be good for productivity growth in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Productivity versus Technology in American Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-TFP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-TFP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I just &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-Review/&quot;&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; Bob Gordon’s book on the rise and fall of American growth. A quick recap of Gordon’s thesis is that we experienced an anomalous burst of technological progress during the 1930’s and 1940’s, bleeding a little into the 1950’s and 60’s. Prior to that period, and since that period, technological progress was relatively slow, and Gordon expects that slow technological progress to be the norm for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thesis is based in large part on evidence of differences in TFP growth decade-by-decade. Gordon’s Figure 16-5 is probably the key graph in his book, as it shows TFP growth of 3.5% per year during the 1940’s, well above the norm for other decades. Even without the 1940’s, TFP growth around 1.5% per year in the 30’s, 50’s, and 60’s. In contrast, TFP growth was below 1% per year in the 1900’s, 10’s, and 20’s, as well as the 1980’s, 90’s, and 2000’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But TFP growth is measured as a residual, and is not necessarily equal to a measure of technology. I’ve made this point &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/labors-share-profits-and-the-productivity-slowdown/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; on this blog, but it is worth revisiting in light of Gordon’s book. In short, do Gordon’s TFP growth rates really indicate significant differences in &lt;em&gt;technological&lt;/em&gt; growth by decade?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;residuals-and-technology&quot;&gt;Residuals and Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, we have to establish how TFP and technology are related. The residual measure of TFP that Gordon uses is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R = \frac{Y}{K^{1-s_L}L^{s_L}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is a completely standard way of doing this. The &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L\inline&quot;/&gt; is labor’s share of revenues (GDP). As is typical, Gordon assumes there are constant returns to scale so that capital’s share is mechanically &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-s_L\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Output is actually defined by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = A K^{\alpha} L^{\beta},&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where I’ve left open the possibility that the elasticities on capital and labor add up to something other than one. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha+\beta&amp;gt;1\inline&quot;/&gt;, then you have increasing returns to scale. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha+\beta=1\inline&quot;/&gt;, you have constant returns. The term &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?A\inline&quot;/&gt; is the actual measure of technology. The residual measure Gordon uses is thus capturing the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R = A \frac{K^{\alpha - s_K}}{L^{\beta - s_L}}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is pretty clear that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?R\inline&quot;/&gt; need not necessarily be equal to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?A\inline&quot;/&gt;. In terms of growth rates, which is what Gordon is focused on, we can write this as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{R}}{R} = \frac{\dot{A}}{A} + (\alpha - 1 + s_L)\frac{\dot{K}}{K} + (\beta-s_L) \frac{\dot{L}}{L},&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the growth rate of the residual is not necessarily equal to the growth rate of technology. It all depends on whether the revenue shares, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-s_L\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L\inline&quot;/&gt;, are in fact equal to the elasticities, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get some structure to understand why they might differ, we can make the minimal assumption that firms are cost-minimizers. In that case it will be true that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\alpha + \beta = \mu(1-s_{\pi}).&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation says that the returns to scale, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha + \beta\inline&quot;/&gt;, are equal to the markup of prices over marginal cost, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu \geq 1\inline&quot;/&gt;, times the share of revenues that are paid to factors of production. That share is one minus the share of revenues paid out as profits, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi}\inline&quot;/&gt;. Note that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi} &amp;gt; 0\inline&quot;/&gt; means that the shares of output paid to capital and labor need not add up to one - but in Gordon’s calculation they have to add up to one. Gordon’s assumption is very typical, but it is one way of the things that will generate a possible divergence between the measure of productivity and the measure of technology. If you’re interested at all in how to derive all this, the ideas come from &lt;a href=&quot;#hall1988&quot;&gt;(Hall 1988; Hall 1989; Basu &amp;amp; Fernald 2002)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings us back to the residual measure. If you plug in the scale, markup, profit relationship into the growth rate of the residual, and rearrange, you can come up with the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{R}}{R} = \frac{\dot{A}}{A} + (\mu(1-s_{\pi}) -1)\frac{\dot{K}}{K} + s_L(\mu-1)\left[\frac{\dot{L}}{L} - \frac{\dot{K}}{K}\right].&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the only way to write this, as you can manipulate the equation into different forms. But I think this is a useful way to look at things. This says that there is a difference between the growth rate of TFP, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{R}/R\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the growth rate of technology, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{A}/A\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of this difference is the term involving &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi}\inline&quot;/&gt;, and this is picking up any effects of increasing returns to scale. If there are IRS, then this term will be non-zero. The increase in scale associated with a larger capital stock generates higher measured productivity growth, even if technology isn’t growing any faster than normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part of this difference is the last term involving &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L(\mu-1)\inline&quot;/&gt;. This captures the fact that assuming capital’s share in output is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-s_L\inline&quot;/&gt; may be wrong. If it is wrong, which would show up as &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu&amp;gt;1\inline&quot;/&gt; in some way, then the growth rate of TFP isn’t going to be equal to the growth rate of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-these-adjustments-matter&quot;&gt;Do these adjustments matter?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Gordon is relying on is that the residual TFP measure is in fact a good gauge of technological growth. In other words, that the two adjustments I outlined above are close to zero. That will be true if we have constant returns to scale, so &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha+\beta = 1\inline&quot;/&gt;, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; firms have no market power so that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu=1\inline&quot;/&gt;. These assumptions are commonly made, so it isn’t like Gordon is doing anything sneaky. Even if he is wrong about those precise values, if firms had a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; market power, so that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu=1.02\inline&quot;/&gt;, or there were mild IRS, so &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha+\beta=1.01\inline&quot;/&gt;, then the adjustments would be insignificant. Gordon’s measures of TFP growth are good measures of technological growth if we think that production is constant returns and markups are sufficiently close to one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if they are not, though? The period of time that has the biggest spike in TFP growth is the 1940’s, which seems to have a number of odd features that make me wary of the assumption about markups and returns being close to one. First, there were guaranteed markups given to firms producing defense goods (which Gordon mentions himself on page 553). Second, there were clearly some massive economies of scale in production during this decade. The U.S. didn’t build B-24 bombers at a bunch of mom-and-pop bomber assembly shops. They were built in a single location, Willow Run, at a peak rate of 432 &lt;em&gt;per month&lt;/em&gt; in 1944. It seems hard to believe that there weren’t economies of scale at work in the economy of the 1940’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does that have a meaningful quantitative impact on the measurement of technology growth? I’m eyeballing numbers here from Gordon’s graphs, so this is fuzzy, but I think it can give an idea of what was going on. First, we need a measure of capital growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{K}/K\inline&quot;/&gt;, and labor growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{L}/L\inline&quot;/&gt;. For capital growth, I used Gordon’s table A-2, which shows his adjusted capital stock data for several select years, including 1941 and 1950. Using those, it looks like capital grew at 1.7% per year in the 1940’s. That feels low, given the war, but isn’t really any different than the growth rate reported by the BEA. I have no real reasons to question the rate. For labor, I did go back to an NBER publication by &lt;a href=&quot;http://papers.nber.org/books/kend61-1&quot;&gt;Kendrick&lt;/a&gt; that Gordon uses, and tried to dig up the growth in hours he uses. Combining that with the adjustment for labor quality growth that Gordon pulled from &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/zanran_storage/www.hup.harvard.edu/ContentPages/50365105.pdf&quot;&gt;Goldin and Katz&lt;/a&gt;, Table 1.3, I get a total growth rate of labor of 1.8% per year for the 1940’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With those, I need a markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu\inline&quot;/&gt;. For the moment, let’s try to see how big of an effect I can have, and choose &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu=1.5\inline&quot;/&gt;. That’s big, with 50% markups over marginal cost. But if there really were massive economies of scale, then this kind of markup may not be that implausible. The last things to plug in are the share of revenues for labor, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L\inline&quot;/&gt;, and profits, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi}\inline&quot;/&gt;. For &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_L\inline&quot;/&gt;, I use Gordon’s number, 0.7. For profits? I don’t know. It is quite plausible that firms in the 40’s charged markups, but that those were to cover fixed costs. So perhaps true economic profits are zero? Again, I’m trying to see how big of an effect these adjustments might have, so let’s set &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\pi} =0\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, from Gordon’s figure 16-5 we know that measured TFP growth in the 1940’s was about 3.3% per year. So put this all together and we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;0.033 = \frac{\dot{A}}{A} + (1.5(1-0)-1)0.017 + 0.7(1.5-1)(0.018-0.017) = \frac{\dot{A}}{A} + 0.00885.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the residual growth rate &lt;em&gt;overstates&lt;/em&gt; technological growth by about 0.85 percentage points per year. Technological growth was 0.033 - 0.00885 = 0.02415, or 2.42% per year, not 3.3% per year. That is a pretty sizable adjustment. But it is still very high compared to all other decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we’d have to make this adjustment to all those other decades as well. Would that lower their implied technology growth as well? That depends on (a) the growth rate of inputs in those decades, and (b) what you assume about the markup in those years. I think you could make the case that the adjustment would be much smaller in other decades. First, the growth rate of inputs is slower. The labor measure Gordon uses combines hours worked with an adjustment for growth in quality of labor. Labor quality (i.e. schooling) is growing more slowly now, and labor hours are not rising as fast due to both demographics and shorter work weeks. So it could easily be that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{K}/K &amp;gt; \dot{L}/L\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the growth rate of TFP &lt;em&gt;understates&lt;/em&gt; technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, maybe IRS was something unique to the 40’s (or other mid-century decades), which would eliminate the first adjustment due to scale. The transition towards services would certainly be one reason to believe that we do not have as much possibility of IRS in aggregate production. The 40’s may have been unique in having a large fraction of output produced by IRS industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played around with several other decades, with the idea of seeing if any adjustments are even &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; that could eliminate the gap in technological growth from the 1940’s. But there is no plausible way I see to make adjustments to their productivity growth that deliver “real” technological growth close to 2.42% per year. The adjustments are not big enough to change Gordon’s main thesis. The 1940’s appear to be an outlier(s) in terms of technology growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, some of the observed productivity growth in the 1940’s is probably not technology growth, per se, but rather reaping the benefits of increasing returns to scale. One way of interpreting Gordon’s thesis is that the WWII era was special because it incorporated IRS production into the economy, and that really was a one-time thing. But now that we’ve added those industries - and because there is ultimately limited demand for their output - we no longer reap the benefits of those IRS. If you pushed this far enough, then I think you would be worried less about Gordon’s “headwinds”. It isn’t that we are somehow failing to match the technological growth of an earlier period, it’s that we simply outgrew the stage at which IRS boosted measured productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;basufernald&quot;&gt;Basu, S. &amp;amp; Fernald, J., 2002. Aggregate Productivity and Aggregate Technology. &lt;i&gt;European Economic Review&lt;/i&gt;, 46, pp.963–991.&lt;/span&gt;  

&lt;div id=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style: none;&quot;&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;Abstract&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Aggregate productivity and aggregate technology are meaningful but distinct concepts. We show that a slightly-modified Solow productivity residual measures changes in economic welfare, even when productivity and technology differ because of distortions such as imperfect competition. We then present a general accounting framework that identifies several new non-technological gaps between productivity and technology, gaps reflecting imperfections and frictions in output and factor markets. Empirically, we find that these gaps are important, even though we abstract from variations in factor utilization and estimate only small average sectoral markups. Compared with productivity growth, our measured technology shocks are significantly less correlated with output, and are essentially uncorrelated with inputs. Our results imply that calibrating dynamic general equilibrium models as if Solow residuals were technology shocks confuses impulses and propagation mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;BibTeX&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;pre&gt;@article{basufernald,
  author = {Basu, Susanto and Fernald, John},
  date-added = {2013-04-20 00:29:41 +0000},
  date-modified = {2016-04-06 20:40:58 +0000},
  journal = {European Economic Review},
  keywords = {alloc},
  pages = {963-991},
  title = {Aggregate Productivity and Aggregate Technology},
  volume = {46},
  year = {2002}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hall1988&quot;&gt;Hall, R.E., 1988. The Relation between Price and Marginal Cost in U.S. Industry. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Political Economy&lt;/i&gt;, 96(5), pp.921–47. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/ucp/jpolec/v96y1988i5p921-47.html&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;  

&lt;div id=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style: none;&quot;&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;Abstract&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;p&gt; An examination of data on output and labor input reveals that some U.S. industries have marginal cost well below price. The conclusion rests on the finding that cyclical variations in labor input are small compared with variations in output. In booms, firms produce substantially more output and sell it for a price that exceeds the costs of the added inputs. This paper documents the disparity between price and marginal cost, where marginal cost is estimated from annual variations in cost. It considers a variety of explanations of the findings that are consistent with competition, but none is found to be completely plausible. Copyright 1988 by University of Chicago Press.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;BibTeX&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;pre&gt;@article{hall1988,
  author = {Hall, Robert E},
  date-added = {2016-04-06 20:43:33 +0000},
  date-modified = {2016-04-06 20:45:58 +0000},
  journal = {Journal of Political Economy},
  keywords = {account,alloc},
  month = oct,
  number = {5},
  pages = {921-47},
  title = {{The Relation between Price and Marginal Cost in U.S. Industry}},
  url = {https://ideas.repec.org/a/ucp/jpolec/v96y1988i5p921-47.html},
  volume = {96},
  year = {1988},
  bdsk-url-1 = {https://ideas.repec.org/a/ucp/jpolec/v96y1988i5p921-47.html}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hall1989&quot;&gt;Hall, R.E., 1989. &lt;i&gt;Invariance Properties of Solow’s Productivity Residual&lt;/i&gt;, National Bureau of Economic Research. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nber.org/papers/w3034&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;  

&lt;div id=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style: none;&quot;&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;Abstract&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;In 1957, Robert Solow published a paper that provided the theoretical foundation for almost all subsequent work on productivity measurement. Although most applications of Solow’s method have measured trends over fairly long time periods, the method also has important uses at higher frequencies. Under constant returns to scale and competition, the Solow residual measures the pure shift of the production function. Shifts in product demand and factor supplies should have no effect on the residual. Tests of this invariance property show that it fails in a great many industries. Though other explanations may deserve some weight, it appears that the leading cause of the failure of invariance is increasing returns and market power. The empirical findings give some support to the theory of monopolistic competition.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;details&gt;
		&lt;summary&gt;BibTeX&lt;/summary&gt;
		&lt;pre&gt;@techreport{hall1989,
  author = {Hall, Robert E.},
  date-added = {2016-04-06 20:45:30 +0000},
  date-modified = {2016-04-06 20:47:29 +0000},
  doi = {10.3386/w3034},
  institution = {National Bureau of Economic Research},
  keywords = {alloc, account},
  month = jul,
  number = {3034},
  series = {Working Paper Series},
  title = {Invariance Properties of Solow&#39;s Productivity Residual},
  type = {Working Paper},
  url = {http://www.nber.org/papers/w3034},
  year = {1989},
  bdsk-url-1 = {http://www.nber.org/papers/w3034},
  bdsk-url-2 = {http://dx.doi.org/10.3386/w3034}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
		&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savings, Savings, and More Savings</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings-Redux/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings-Redux/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is about savings. It is also a plea with Nick Rowe to slow the &lt;em&gt;)#&lt;/em&gt;#@ down in posting things that get stuck in my head. I’m still working on this savings thing, and now he’s got a &lt;a href=&quot;http://worthwhile.typepad.com/worthwhile_canadian_initi/2014/05/mrscc1r1mpkmrtcidmrtcidt.html&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; up about capital that I’m chewing over too. I have a life, Nick, for God’s sake - pump the brakes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, this is just a wrap-up of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about “What happens to GDP if I save 100 dollars”? And the point there was that this is an ill-formed question. Or at least it is ill-formed because we economists have screwed up by using the word “savings” for lots of different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of an individual, they earn income in dollars. That income in dollars is divided across several different uses, several of which could be called “savings”. So let’s be a little more exact. Write &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Inc_t = C_{t,now} + C_{t,later} + I_t + Bank_t&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This says that income can be spent in four ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C_{t,now}\inline&quot;/&gt; is spending on consumption goods (or services) that are consumed in period &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;. For example, I bought a Diet Coke this afternoon, and just drank it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C_{t,later}\inline&quot;/&gt; is spending on consumption goods that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; consumed in period &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;. For example, I bought a case of Diet Coke today, and it is sitting in my office. I will not consume all of those Diet Cokes before the close of 2016Q1. The purchase, though, gets added to 2016Q1 GDP, even though I don’t consume all of them that quarter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I_t\inline&quot;/&gt; is spending on investment goods. Which, to be clear, is simply an arbitrary definition based on an assumption about what the goods will be used for. An example here would be if I bought a bulldozer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Bank_t\inline&quot;/&gt; is the net change in my bank account in period &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;. This could be positive (I saved!) or negative (I borrowed!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In plain English, numbers (2)-(4) all could conceivably be called “savings”. For the purposes of thinking about macroeconomics, though, the distinction between (4) and (1)-(3) is crucial. (1)-(3), whatever you call them, all involve actually &lt;em&gt;spending&lt;/em&gt; money. Whether you spend that money on goods that you then put in the pantry, or store underground, or use to produce more goods next period is irrelevant. You spent the money. “What happens to GDP if I save 100 dollars?” is, I’m sure, a question about what happens if I increase (4) by 100 dollars and decrease (1)-(3) in combination by 100 dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I said in the last post was that this &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have an effect on GDP. It certainly lowers the velocity of money, so nominal GDP would fall. If prices are sticky, then real GDP would fall as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have in mind a different concept of “save 100 dollars” then the effect on GDP could be different. If you mean that you raise (2) or (3) by 100 dollars while lowering (4) by 100 dollars, then this could &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; GDP. You are now spending 100 dollars that you otherwise would not have. You have raised velocity, so nominal GDP goes up, and if prices are sticky, real GDP goes up too. Even though you are “saving” 100 dollars of goods by buying a bulldozer or putting your Diet Coke cans in the garage fridge for later, you still spent 100 dollars on goods - and that is all GDP cares about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, perhaps by “save 100 dollars” you mean that you lowered (1) or (2) by 100 and raised (3) by 100. That is, you “saved” by switching from buying consumption goods to buying investment goods. What effect does that have on GDP in period &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t\inline&quot;/&gt;? None (okay, maybe a 2nd order effect if investment good producers have a different propensity to spend their income than you do). You still spent the 100 dollars. In the future, this may effect GDP because the bulldozer may let you produce more output. In growth models, like the Solow model, “savings” mean spending money on (3). And the more you save, the higher will be GDP in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the original question is best phrased as “What happens to GDP in this period if I put 100 dollars of my money in the bank this period rather than spending it on any kind of good or service?” And that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; lower GDP today. If you mean a different kind of “savings”, then you have to be specific. Or, as economists we have to teach you to be more specific. Or, as economists we have to push back and force you to be more specific. Because the answers are different depending on what you mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beware-what-follows&quot;&gt;Beware what follows&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last bit is all wild-ass speculation. If each person has an budget constraint of the form I gave above, we could add up across all individuals like this
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum_i Inc_t = \sum_i C_{t,now} + \sum_i C_{t,later} + \sum_i I_t + \sum_i Bank_t.&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say that total spending on goods and services (the two C terms plus the I term) are equal to some multiple, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?c\inline&quot;/&gt;, of income. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?c\inline&quot;/&gt; could be greater than one (so people are net borrowing) or less than (people are net saving). Then I have
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1-c) \sum_i Inc_t = \sum_i Bank_t.&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sum of income flowing to individuals has to add up to nominal GDP by the national income product accounts, so call &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_i Inc_t = PY\inline&quot;/&gt;. Then plugging this in and rearranging I have
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;PY = \frac{\sum_i Bank_t}{1-c}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(1-c)&amp;gt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, then this means people do not spend all their income, so it makes sense that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_i Bank_t &amp;gt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;. In other words, savings are accumulating in aggregate. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(1-c)&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, then it makes sense that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_i Bank_t&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, or savings are de-cumulating in aggregate. Either way, the ratio on the right is positive, and equal to nominal GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this some kind of bastard quantity theory? I ask because I honestly don’t know. I don’t even know what to make of this, or if I made some kind of dumb mistake in here somewhere. Should I take this seriously? Could I think of the terms in the ratio becoming unlinked? That is, could we think that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?c\inline&quot;/&gt; stays constant, but &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\sum_i Bank_t\inline&quot;/&gt; goes up in absolute value, so nominal GDP goes up? What would it mean for the total flow of money into banks to go up, but for people’s propensity to consume from their income to stay the same?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reviewing the Rise and Fall of American Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-Review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Gordon-Review/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I finished reading Robert Gordon’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1Sb860J&quot;&gt;The Rise and Fall of American Growth&lt;/a&gt; a while ago, but finally found the time to write down an extended review. I’m way behind the curve. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foreignaffairs.com/reviews/review-essay/2016-02-15/innovation-over&quot;&gt;Tyler Cowen&lt;/a&gt; has an excellent review, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/UpdatedPriors&quot;&gt;Ryan Decker&lt;/a&gt; sort of live-tweeted his way through the book recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin, a comparison. A few months ago I praised Garrett Jones for the sleek nature of &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1UQCXV6&quot;&gt;Hive Mind&lt;/a&gt;. The Rise and Fall of American Growth is, um .. not sleek. It starts out with a 531-page description of the diffusion of major innovations within the U.S. over the last 140 years, then transitions to a 104-page presentation of Gordon’s thesis about what generated differences in productivity growth in that period, and finishes with a 12-page postscript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on what you’re after, this is either a bug or a feature. As a statement of Gordon’s thesis regarding productivity growth, it’s a bug. You can read Gordon’s thesis in two (free) working papers (&lt;a href=&quot;http://economics.weinberg.northwestern.edu/robert-gordon/Is%20US%20Economic%20Growth%20Over.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://economics.weinberg.northwestern.edu/robert-gordon/NBER%20P383F%20Sequel_140126.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The 531 pages of anecdotes about technology diffusion are ancillary to making this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the 531 pages are a feature if you want to understand just how amazing the transition in living standards has been over the last 140 years. For that purpose, the unending onslaught of facts, stories, and comparisons is necessary to make the case. Gordon takes the reader through the transition from the disconnected, unhealthy, underfed, dark lifestyle facing workers in 1880 to a world of lights, abundant food, communication, travel, and health. And that’s just by 1940. The core networks of modern life - electricity, sewers, roads, broadcasting - were in place by the end of the Great Depression. Despite these massive changes in welfare, what Gordon documents is that measured productivity growth up through the 1930’s was actually quite low. Growth in GDP per capita systematically understates growth in welfare; this is not something that has arisen recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1950’s, and spilling into the 60’s and early 1970’s, productivity growth jumped appreciably. For Gordon, this is partly a feature of those core networks being extended out into the whole country. Diffusion, more than innovation, is what fundamentally explains the spike in measured productivity growth in the immediate post-war period. Since the 1970’s, productivity growth has retreated back to pre-WWII levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I don’t understand about the book is the insistence that the &lt;em&gt;welfare&lt;/em&gt; gains of growth after the mid-century are necessarily smaller. Maybe they are, maybe they aren’t. Fundamentally it is a book about economic growth, not welfare growth. Yet all I kept hearing in my head while reading the second half of the 531-page narrative was “you darn kids and your Facebook”. This may just be a problem of tone, but it also pushes Gordon close to a real problem. He veers close to using the assumption that the welfare gains of current innovation are small to conclude that the rate of economic growth in the future must be small as well. That does not follow. It is quite possible that productivity growth could spike to 3.5% per year again in the 2020’s, and yet the welfare gains of this could be trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But will growth spike to 3.5% again? Gordon says no. For him, the innovations in the early 20th century were unique. In networking everyone together, they had a one-time boost to productivity that the computing/internet revolution of the last twenty years cannot match, and more importantly &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; not match. The productivity growth facts are what they are, productivity has grown much slower 1995-2015 than 1950-1970. But that doesn’t mean productivity growth will stay low. We just don’t know. Tyler Cowen’s review does a great job of laying out the fundamental problem; future technology is unforecastable. And while Gordon makes a passing effort at claiming it is, his anecdotal example of a &lt;em&gt;Ladies Home Journal&lt;/em&gt; from 1900 predicting air conditioning does not constitute evidence. We just don’t know what new innovations will bring, or what effect they will have on economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, there is a very powerful idea running along underneath Gordon’s book, and I don’t know that he draws enough attention to it. Gordon’s narrative shares a feature of Piketty’s &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt;; it questions aspects of the Kaldor Facts that have formed the basis for most work on economic growth. Those facts were based on observations made in the 1950’s-70’s. Piketty showed that the idea of a constant labor share is not a universal feature of growth, but an anomaly of immediate post-war period. Gordon shows that rapid, sustained productivity growth was &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; an anomaly of the immediate post-war period (see his Figure 16-5). Together, these two authors tell us that the stylized facts that generations of growth models have tried to match are probably wrong. So whatever the other merits of Gordon’s book, it is valuable for making this point vividly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve built generations of growth models on the idea that they have to deliver “balanced growth paths” because those match up to the Kaldor Facts. But if those facts do not hold, then this opens up a much wider set of possible growth models. Growth could run out of steam, growth could accelerate, growth could follow a random walk, etc. etc.. In that sense, Gordon’s book is worth reading, in that it forces you to reconsider - or at least defend - the assumptions underlying our explanations for economic growth. You could probably have gotten there in under 647 pages, but nevertheless it is a good point.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You Saved What?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Savings/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nick Rowe just had a &lt;a href=&quot;http://worthwhile.typepad.com/worthwhile_canadian_initi/2016/02/does-saving-count-towards-gdp.html#more&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about the effect of savings on GDP. I’m paraphrasing, but a student asks him whether “saving an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100” raises GDP (or not), because the national income product accounts can be written as\inline&quot;/&gt;Y = C + S + T&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?. I think Nick nails the issue, which is that you &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; specify “instead of what?” when you say you “save an extra\inline&quot;/&gt;100”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve run into the same question before, and I’ve gone back and forth on how best to explain the answer (which, strictly speaking, is “it depends”). This also gives me a chance to rant a little about my pet peeve of measuring GDP in dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem we have is that “save an extra $100” means “keep 100 slips of green paper in my wallet rather than spending them” to any normal human being. This is a statement about how you use the medium of exchange. It’s a statement inherently related to the turnover of that medium of exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the word “savings” and the symbol “S” are also used as a concept in national income product accounts to stand for “the value of goods and services that are neither consumed nor handed over to the government as taxes”. Because you typically measure the value of good and services using dollars, this creates confusion. But “&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 of S” is a statement that uses dollars as a unit of account, and has nothing to do with\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of the medium of exchange. “&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 of S” means that you purchased\inline&quot;/&gt;100 worth of goods and services, &lt;em&gt;and then saved those goods and services&lt;/em&gt;. It does not mean you kept 100 slips of green paper in your wallet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question from Nick’s student isn’t easy to answer, and it should be easier. He wants to know the effect on GDP if he “saves an extra $100”, and right now the answer gets confusing because of this confusion in medium of exchange and unit of account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be clearer if we didn’t insist on measuring GDP (and its components like S) in units of dollars. Yes, we tell everyone they are “2005 dollars” or something like that, but we all hear “dollars!” in our head and think of little slips of green paper. I really think a better way to do this would be to just measure GDP as physical units of output. You can do this in a crude (but effective) way by just measuring GDP as the equivalent number of cans of Diet Cokes (e.g. divide nominal GDP by $0.85, the price in our department vending machine). Or if you insist on being more accurate, divide nominal GDP by the actual dollar value of the CPI basket, and you’ll get “number of CPI baskets produced”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, if GDP is in real terms - Diet Cokes or CPI baskets - then we no longer have this confusion of the medium of exchange (dollars) and the unit of account (DC or CPI baskets). When you say you “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100”, I think it now becomes obvious that you &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; complete that statement with “…instead of buying\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Cokes or CPI baskets”. It is clear what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re not totally out of the woods. GDP is a flow concept, not a stock. So it’s impossible to specify the effect of “saving an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 instead of buying\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Coke” without saying precisely &lt;em&gt;how long&lt;/em&gt; you plan to save that money for. It is March 6th. If you “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100” today by not spending it, and don’t spend it until April 13th, then &lt;em&gt;first quarter GDP&lt;/em&gt; goes down by at least\inline&quot;/&gt;100. At least. You not spending that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 means someone else didn’t earn that\inline&quot;/&gt;100, and they cannot spend the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100, and so there may be a whole chain of transactions that don’t occur because you saved an extra\inline&quot;/&gt;100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100” on March 6th, but then spend that\inline&quot;/&gt;100 on March 8th, first quarter GDP might not got down at all. You still spent the $100 in the first quarter, and all the subsequent transactions that might be keyed off of your spending still have time to occur. Maybe the 2 day delay means that someone 15 transactions down the line doesn’t get a chance to buy a Snickers bar until April 1st, and now that transaction is not counted in first quarter GDP any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t solve our problem, because we didn’t account for the fact that maybe the producers will respond to our lack of spending by changing prices. If you “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100 instead of buying\inline&quot;/&gt;100 of Diet Coke” on March 6th, then the DC distributor might notice that 117.67 cans of DC are still on the shelf on March 7th that they expected to be gone. They figure this represents lower demand, so to clear their inventory they lower the price. By March 31st, even though &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; didn’t spend $100 on Diet Cokes, somebody bought those cheaper Diet Cokes and hence real GDP (the number of Diet Cokes sold) is the same as if you hadn’t saved that money at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that there is a simple way to teach this stuff. I think you could probably spend a whole semester just going over (and over and over) the difference between GDP and the money supply. Let me take a crack at a relatively simple way of accomodating a question about what happens when you “save an extra $100”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key here is the Quantity Theory of Money. It is an identity that tells us how to determine nominal GDP. You know the formula, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MV = PY\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone says “save an extra $100”, they mean “lower velocity” by some amount. They are turning over their actual dollars more slowly (e.g. waiting until April 13th to spend them). How much velocity goes down is a question of (a) how long they wait to spend the money and (b) how crucial that spending is for everyone else’s spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, because V has gone down, it must be that either M goes up, or PY has gone down. If we assume that M stays constant, then it has to be that PY goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens to &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; GDP - cans of Diet Coke - Y? That depends on how flexible you think prices are. If P can adjust easily (the DC distributor notices quickly and lowers prices), then Y may be unaffected by your decision to “save an extra &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?100”. But if prices are sticky, then your decision to save\inline&quot;/&gt;100 has to lower Y by an amount proportional to how much velocity goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about that whole NIPA accounting equation &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = C + S + T\inline&quot;/&gt;? Well, what about it? S is a classification of real GDP. S is the number of Diet Cokes that you &lt;em&gt;buy&lt;/em&gt;, but do not actually &lt;em&gt;drink&lt;/em&gt;. S is “GDP that is neither consumed nor given to the government”. Yes, the BEA calls that “savings”, but that is a crappy term that just causes confusion. If we measured GDP in real units, and stopped using the term “savings” both for “dollars not spent” and “goods and services not consumed”, we wouldn’t have to keep rehashing these questions again and again every year with a new set of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I might have read Nick’s post wrong, and maybe the student was asking about spending 100 gold pieces to raise his &lt;em&gt;saving throw&lt;/em&gt; from a 17 to an 18. Easy mistake to make.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growth References</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/New-References/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/New-References/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A very quick post just to alert you that I’ve added a new page of &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/references/&quot;&gt;references&lt;/a&gt; to the site. It is essentially a dump of my own BibTeX file, broken down by topic area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s incomplete, but as I clean up and add to the references over time, they’ll populate to that page. Of course, I’ll probably be in my 70’s before I get around to it, but maybe announcing it publicly will act as a commitment device. It can’t make me go any &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; at fixing up my BibTeX file, that’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Accelerate Growth Rates</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Accelerate-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Accelerate-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A good amount of discussion takes place about how to accelerate growth, with a lot of prominent examples coming from the US presidential primaries. Jeb! promised to get the growth rate of GDP to 4%. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dollarsandsense.org/What-would-Sanders-do-013016.pdf&quot;&gt;Gerald Friedman&lt;/a&gt; said that Sanders’ plans would raise growth to 5.3%, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ineteconomics.org/uploads/general/romer-and-romer-evaluation-of-friedman1.pdf&quot;&gt;Romer’s&lt;/a&gt; have published a rebuttal saying that is almost impossible to achieve. &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/kocherlakota009/home/policy/thoughts-on-policy/2-23-16&quot;&gt;Narayana Kocherlakota&lt;/a&gt;, on the other hand, says that we can adopt policies that can achieve 5-6% growth over the next four years. I know I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/insert-policy-here-wont-boost-growth-rates/&quot;&gt;said before&lt;/a&gt; that whatever your favorite policy is, it won’t boost growth rates by maybe more than 1 percentage point, so maybe you could hit 3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what gives? Is it possible, or not, to materially boost growth rates through policy? The answer, which lets you distinguish between the links given above, is that it depends on the kind of policy. To be crude, divide policies into either aggregate supply (AS) policies or aggregate demand (AD) policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big difference between them, at least for understanding their impact on growth rates in the short run, is in whether they involve spending money &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. AS policies - reform the tax code, reduce occupational licensing, cut back regulation, etc. - are about changing incentives for people to invest in new capital (human or physical) or to reallocate that capital to higher productivity uses. AD policies - monetary policy, direct transfers - differ in that they directly involve moving money from one person or institution to another. Some policies, infrastructure spending, for example, have elements of both. The infrastructure changes incentives for investments by private business (AS), but also involves a direct transfer of money to pay for it (AD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be a little more concrete about my distinction of AD and AS policies, think of the difference between a change to tax law that lowers the tax rate on small businesses (an AS policy) and a $500 tax refund sent to every person in the US (an AD policy). The change in tax rates will presumably induce more small businesses to start or expand (arguing about the size of this effect is something for a different post, roll with it) over time, but this will take time. Nothing material is going to happen to GDP growth this quarter because of that policy change, even though over time it might result in significantly more GDP. In constrast, the tax refund is going to put money in people’s pockets &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, and so there will be a more immediate effect on GDP, although it will fade away relatively quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try and illustrate the difference, let me try some diagrams that should be familiar to anyone who has taken intermediate macro. These are basic AS/AD diagrams, but with an additional feature that comes from growth economics. Rather than one long-run AS curve (LRAS), we have two. The first is the current LRAS, and the second is the potential LRAS curve. In terms of the Solow model, the current LRAS is based on our current capital stock and productivity, while the potential LRAS is the steady state LRAS (To be really true to growth models, we’d say that the potential LRAS curve is slowly moving to the right due to trend growth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Basic AS/AD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y is the current level of GDP, determined by the intersection of the AD curve with the &lt;em&gt;short-run&lt;/em&gt; AS curve, SRAS. I’ve drawn the diagram such that we are in a situation where GDP is below current potential. I did this to be clear. Being below steady state in a growth model (Current LRAS &amp;lt; Potential LRAS) is a different thing than having “slack” in the economy (Y &amp;lt; Current LRAS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this I can think through the differences in policies that attempt to accelerate growth, meaning that Y starts to “move to the right” quickly in my diagram. Start with AS policies. These push the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; LRAS curve to the right, but have little immediate effect on the current LRAS or the current SRAS. Over time, the current LRAS will converge to the potential LRAS, but as I’ve talked about before that takes a long time to occur. Note that the fact that the current and potential LRAS are far apart in my diagram to start with is irrelevant. The policies will shift the potential LRAS curve, and we’ll still have to wait for the current LRAS curve to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas2.png&quot; alt=&quot;LRAS Shift&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because AS policies don’t shift the current LRAS and SRAS curves by much, the increase in Y is small, and hence there is only a small effect on the growth rate. In the long run, these policies can have a massive effect on living standards, but it can take decades for that to manifest itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constrast that with AD policies. These shift the AD curve directly, and close to immediately. I’m perfectly willing to concede that there is some kind of lag in when the AD curve shifts out, but that’s measured in quarters, not decades. Because this AD shift happens immediately, and because the SRAS curve slopes upwards, there is a big effect on GDP from Y to Y’. Note that this depends crucially on the assumption that the SRAS curve is upward sloping. Without that, the AD shift would have no effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/adas1.png&quot; alt=&quot;AD Shift&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the AD policy has no effect on either potential or current LRAS. And while I’ve drawn the SRAS curve as a line, it probably becomes vertical at some point when GDP is high enough, so you cannot just use AD policies to push up GDP arbitrarily. But if you want to boost growth &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, then the AD policies are more effective. A last point is that the size of the effect depends on how far away Y is from the current LRAS curve. Part of the Romer’s critique of Friedman is that he overstates that gap, which thus overstats the power of AD policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large part of the argument about whether you can influence growth in the short run depends on whether we are talking about AD or AS policies. Kocherlakota, for example, explicitly talks about AD policies - monetary policy - as part of his argument for being able to boost growth to 5%. Sanders’ plan is a mix of AS and AD, but I think Friedman got caught up treating all of them as AD plans, which overstated their possible effects in the short run. When I dismissed the ability of various reform plans to boost growth in the short run, it was because they are AS reforms. They will have effects over the long-run, but not in the short run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are probably few policies that are purely AS or AD policies. Monetary policy is probably - unless you don’t buy the classical dichotomy - a purely AD policy. Fiscal policy, on the other hand, seems muddier. It depends on the nature of it. Direct transfers are AD policies (although they might have incentive effects that affect the AS side). Policies that change regulations or the tax code, though, are not really fiscal policy, so much as they are AS policies. Another example might help. Changing education policy to allow teachers to be hired/fired more easily - AS policy. Hiring 1,000 teachers to start teaching this fall - AD policy. A major education reform bill, then, might be both AS and AD at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the attractions of infrastructure spending, by the way. It provides both AS and AD effects. Spend money now to repair bridges, ports, and roads, and immediately boost GDP growth. But at the same time, you are investing in public capital that can incent private business to invest as well, and you are pushing out the potential LRAS curve, which ultimately is the only one that matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What all this means is that you cannot just look at the projected growth rate of a plan to assess it. Friedman isn’t wrong because he projects 5% growth, but he’s probably wrong because he is assuming AS policies are going to have big current effects. Kocherlakota isn’t wrong because he projects 5% growth either, but his plan is more plausible because it is based in large part on AD policies. Jeb! wasn’t wrong because he proposed 4% growth, he was wrong because of how he proposed to get there. You can accelerate growth in the short run, but you have to use AD policies to do that. AS policies deliver higher living standards in the long run, but it takes them a long time to ramp up to that higher level.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Absolute Changes in Living Standards</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Absolute-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Absolute-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This may or may not be interesting, I’m not entirely sure myself. But I got a question from an undergrad in my economic growth course, and it was one of those questions that kind of catches you off guard because you hadn’t really thought about it. The question was - paraphrasing - “Why do we look at growth rates rather than how much GDP per capita actually changed?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Duh, it’s a course on growth” is what I did &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; say. But it did take me a moment to shake that feeling. In his defense, the answer isn’t obvious. Why do we focus on growth rates - percentage changes - as opposed to absolute changes in GDP per capita? Growth rates maks major differences in the absolute change in GDP per capita. For example, a growth rate of 2% implies an absolute change of 1000 in an economy with a GDP per capita of 50,000, and only a change of 200 in an economy with GDP per capita of 10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what does the distribution of aboslute changes in GDP per capita even look like? I had no idea. So I calculated the absolute growth in real GDP per capita per year for each country in the PWT. Then I plotted the kernel densities of these absolute changes for several countries. You can see the results below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_abs_growth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Densities for Absolute Growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kernel densities are basically smoothed histograms, so the height of the density curve indicates how often absolute growth in GDP per capita of a given amount occurred. As you can see, for India (the black dashed line) absolute growth tended to be very small. On average, from 1950 to 2011, GDP per capita rose by 51 dollars per year in India. The median was 42 dollars. Despite these small absolute changes, the percentage growth rate in could actually be quite high because GDP per capita is very low to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare that to the United States, where the density is much flatter and covers much larger values (both positive and negative). For the US, average absolute growth in GDP per capita was 482 dollars, with a median of 617 dollars. Of course, those large changes in GDP per capita reflect very small percentage growth rates in the US, because GDP per capita is already so large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of growth rates, the US isn’t growing very quickly compared to India, at least over the last 25 years. But in absolute terms, the increase in living standards in the US is about 10 times higher than in India in a given year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we care about these absolute changes? The answer hinges on your view on how GDP per capita translates to welfare, the utility function. It is really common to assume “log utility”, or welfare is the log of GDP per capita (or consumption per capita, or something else proportional to GDP per capita). Log utility has the very particular property that the same &lt;em&gt;growth rate&lt;/em&gt; of GDP per capita yields the same &lt;em&gt;absolute&lt;/em&gt; change in welfare. If India and the US both have growth rates of 3%, then welfare in both countries rises by 3%, even though the absolute change in GDP per capita in the US is much larger. The figure above doesn’t have any information about welfare gains, in other words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is simply diminishing marginal utility. But log utility specifies that the diminishing happens in such a way that growth rates translate directly to absolute changes in welfare. Now what if utility is “more curved” than log? That is, what if marginal utility falls very quickly as GDP per capita goes up? Then even if two countries have the same growth rate, they do not have the same absolute change in welfare. In fact, the richer country would have a &lt;em&gt;smaller&lt;/em&gt; change in welfare than the poorer country. So 3% growth in India generates &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; welfare than 3% growth in the US, even though the absolute change in GDP per capita is much smaller in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we could go the other direction, and look at utility that is “less curved” than log, or where marginal utility diminishes very slowly. Now, if there are two countries with identical growth rates, the richer country has a higher gain in welfare. The limit case here is linear utility, where marginal utility doesn’t decline at all as you get richer. Then the absolute change in GDP per capita is all that matters, and the US has (on average) much larger gains in welfare every year than India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An argument for thinking of utility as “more curved” than log is subsistence constraints. That is, let’s say that you only get utility from GDP per capita over and above a minimum level; GDP per capita at that minimum level is what we call subsistence, and it doesn’t provide any welfare, it just keeps you alive. If you have subsistence constraints, then marginal utility is incredibly high close to this constraint, and marginal utility falls very quickly as you move away from it. So India experiences much bigger gains in welfare - despite their small absolute gains in GDP per capita - because those extra 51 dollars get you farther away from that subsistence constraint. The US gets relatively little utility from its 482 dollar change, because we’re already so far above that subsistence constraint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, habit formation would be a force pushing towards “less curved” utility. In short, imagine that the subsistence constraint itself is rising as we get richer. The “minimum level” of GDP per capita that people need to meet is higher in the US than in India. If you believe that, then it is quite possible that the higher absolute growth of GDP per capita in the US is delivering bigger gains in absolute welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, then, I think the answer to the students question is that we think there is diminishing marginal utility, and so growth rate rates make sense because they tell us something about absolute changes in welfare. But…who said utility of GDP per capita has to be as curved as log? What if there are significant habit effects? Maybe the gap in welfare between places like the US and India is actually &lt;em&gt;growing&lt;/em&gt; over time, even though India’s GDP per capita is catching up slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not a “Duh” question after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Inferences about Tropics, Germs, and Crops</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/oid-test/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/oid-test/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the long-running arguments in growth is “geography versus institutions”. A lot of ink and a tiny amount of computing power was thrown at this question. The early stages of this involved a lot of cross-country regressions that attempted to figure out empirically whether measures of institutions or geography had explanatory power for GDP per capita. (By the way, I’m talking here just about the economic growth literature’s take on this. The general question goes back centuries.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tweet by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GarettJones&quot;&gt;Garett Jones&lt;/a&gt; recently reminded me of one of the entries in this literature, Bill Easterly and Ross Levine’s “&lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/moneco/v50y2003i1p3-39.html&quot;&gt;Tropics, Germs, and Crops&lt;/a&gt;” paper. EL want to assess the role of geography in explaining cross-country incomes per capita. Their main questions are summed up nicely in the abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Does economic development depend on geographic endowments like temperate instead of tropical location, the ecological conditions shaping diseases, or an environment good for grains or certain cash crops? Or do these endowments of tropics, germs, and crops affect economic development only through institutions or policies?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their conclusion is that geography has no effect, other than through its relationship to institutions. This conclusion, though, doesn’t follow from the empirical tests they run. Let’s run through the empirics on these questions, and see how to answer them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to do this with precisely the dataset that EL use. I don’t recall when or where I picked up the data, but I believe it was from Easterly’s old website, where he had a nice set of links to datasets. Regardless, it’s the right dataset because I can perfectly replicate their results. You can download my version &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/east_levine_2003.dta&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and play around with it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-geography-even-related-to-gdp-per-capita&quot;&gt;Is geography even related to GDP per capita?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we have to establish that geography has a relationship to income per capita in the first place. If it doesn’t, the answers are clear. EL’s three primary measures of geography: (log) settler mortality, latitude, and a dummy for being landlocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these are questionable as measures of “geography”, and they are certainly incomplete. But for the purposes of this exercise, we’ll stick with them. Settler mortality is from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v91y2001i5p1369-1401.html&quot;&gt;Acemoglu, et al&lt;/a&gt;, and is intended to capture the nature of the disease environment (of Europeans, at least). Latitude is supposed to capture whether the country is tropical or not, and landlocked is there to account roughly for access to shipping. The “Crops” of the title of the paper could be added by including a series of dummies for producing different crops, but including those doesn’t really change the point of this post, so I’m going to skip them for brevity’s sake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regress log income per capita on the three geography measures. You get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;------------------------------------
                              .   
Dep var: GDP p.c.            b/se   
------------------------------------
Log Settler Mortality      -0.610***
                          (0.111)   
Landlocked                 -0.711   
                          (0.359)   
Absolute Latitutde          2.377*  
                          (1.027)   
Constant                    9.695***
                          (0.612)   
------------------------------------
R-squared                   0.509   
N                              72   
------------------------------------
* p&amp;lt;0.05, ** p&amp;lt;0.01, *** p&amp;lt;0.001
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick apology that the results aren’t formatted better. That aside, in case you aren’t familiar, the first number listed for each variable is the estimated effect (e.g. -0.610 for settler mortality), and the number in parentheses is the standard error of that estimate. The stars show you whether the estimated effect is statistically significant. So settler mortality is significant at less than 1/10th of 1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we see a clear effect of two measures of geography: settler mortality and latitude. The R-squared for this regression is 50.9%, meaning half of the variation in GDP per capita is associated with variation in “geography”. At a minimum, it suggests that geography &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; explain varation in incomes. But of course we don’t know if this acts only through institutions, or is a direct of geography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-there-an-indepdent-effect-of-geography-outside-of-institutions&quot;&gt;Is there an indepdent effect of geography outside of institutions?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s our second question. This has a clear empirical set-up. Regress GDP per capita on geography &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a measure of institutions. Look at the estimated effect of geography. Is it significant, even with institutions in the regression?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is entirely straightforward. The whole point of regressions is to do this kind of thing: separate out the effect of one variable from another. I ran that regression, using the EL measure of institutions, which is pulled from &lt;a href=&quot;http://info.worldbank.org/governance/wgi/pdf/govind.pdf&quot;&gt;Kaufman, Kraay, and Zoido-Lobaton&lt;/a&gt;. This is an averaged index of 6 different measures of “institutions”. I’ve made my views on the silliness of these indices &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/the-skeptics-guide-to-institutions-part-1/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, so I won’t belabor the point here. We’ll just accept it as is for this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;------------------------------------
                            .   
Dep var: GDP p.c.            b/se   
------------------------------------
Log Settler Mortal~y       -0.302** 
                      (0.102)   
Landlocked                 -0.530   
                      (0.291)   
Absolute Latitutde          0.698   
                      (0.870)   
Institutions                1.163***
                      (0.189)   
Constant                    8.639***
                      (0.521)   
------------------------------------
R-squared                   0.682   
N                              72   
------------------------------------
* p&amp;lt;0.05, ** p&amp;lt;0.01, *** p&amp;lt;0.001
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that institutions are indeed significant (three stars!!). But so is settler mortality (at 1%), and landlocked is actually significant at 10% (but no stars for you!). “Geography matters” here, even after you control for institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect size of geography is definitely smaller than before. Look at the coefficient on settler mortality, which dropped from -0.610 to -0.302. This is showing that some of the effect of mortality on GDP per capita in my first regression was actually just picking up the effect of institutions (and by implication, mortality and institutions are negatively related, as AJR would suggest). But what the regression also shows is that the remaining effect of mortality is still statistically significant. Yes, there is an independent effect of geography on GDP per capita, even controlling for geography’s correlation with institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether the estimate of “Institutions” here is in fact a causal estimate is a different question. We might be concerned that institutions are endogenous, either because GDP per capita improves institutions, or because we’ve left out some other control variable that institutions is picking up on (culture, etc..). And if the estimate of institutions is wrong, then the conclusion about the geography variables could be wrong too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So…..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;does-geography-still-matter-even-if-institutions-are-instrumented&quot;&gt;Does geography still matter even if institutions are instrumented?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this concern about institutions being endogenous, we’d like to find some pure exogenous variation in institutions to use in our empirical analysis. In other words, we’d like to find another variable that both (a) (imperfectly) predicts the level of institutions and (b) is unrelated to the problematic unobserved variation in GDP per capita. We want an instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we had such an instrument (IV), the process here is clear. We’d regress institutions on that IV and get the fitted values, which would represent variation in institutions that is &lt;em&gt;by assumption&lt;/em&gt; unrelated to the problematic unobserved variation in GDP per capita. Regress GDP per capita on this fitted value of institutions, and &lt;em&gt;et voila&lt;/em&gt;, we’ve got a true estimate of the effect of institutions. We could run the regression with the geography variables included as well, and see if geography matters for GDP per capita once we control for &lt;em&gt;instrumented&lt;/em&gt; institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is we need an instrument, and this is where EL run into a problem. The instrument for institutions that they propose to use is exactly the measures of geography: settler mortality, landlocked, and latitude. Which means they &lt;strong&gt;assume&lt;/strong&gt; that these three measures have no relationship to GDP per capita outside of their influence on institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They answered their question by assuming the answer was no. There is no getting around the fact that condition (b) above is an assumption. There is literally &lt;strong&gt;nothing&lt;/strong&gt; you can do to test if it is true or not. To use settler mortality, landlocked, and latitude as IV’s, you are, without fail, assuming they have no independent effect on GDP per capita.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about this over-identification (OID) test that EL use? Isn’t that evidence that their assumption is correct, and in fact geography has no effect on GDP per capita outside of institutions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why. The OID test has the following null hypothesis: settler mortality, landlocked, and latitude are &lt;em&gt;jointly&lt;/em&gt; unrelated to unobserved variation in GDP per capita. If you find enough evidence to reject this null, then you have evidence that one or more of your instruments are related to the unobserved variation in GDP per capita. In other words, your assumption is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But EL do not reject the null. EL report that they fail to reject the null.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeat after me. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true. Failure to reject the null does not mean the null is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not evidence that geography does not matter. It’s not. It’s not even kinda-sorta evidence, and well, you know, it probably means that geography doesn’t matter. That’s not how statistics work. There is no evidence, so there is &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt; conclusion to draw. A failure to reject is an absence of information, so you cannot infer anything from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-geography-totally-matters-right&quot;&gt;So geography totally matters, right?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe. We don’t know. We haven’t solved the problem we had in the 2nd regression I ran. Our estimated effect of institutions might be biased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is true is that &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt; the true effect of institutions were larger (say a coefficient of 2.22 versus 1.16), then the estimated effects of geography would end up statistically insignificant. How do I know that? Because I can run a regression where I force the coefficient on institutions to be 2.22, and see what happens to the geography variables. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;------------------------------------
                                .   
Dep var: GDP p.c.            b/se   
------------------------------------
Institutions                2.220   
                              (.)   
Log Settler Mortal~y       -0.022   
                          (0.107)   
Landlocked                 -0.366   
                          (0.348)   
Absolute Latitutde         -0.828   
                          (0.994)   
Constant                    7.681***
                          (0.592)   
------------------------------------
R-squared                           
N                              72   
------------------------------------
* p&amp;lt;0.05, ** p&amp;lt;0.01, *** p&amp;lt;0.001
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that all the geography variables are not statistically significant (no stars!). Why does this happen? Because institutions are now explaining so much, there really isn’t anything “left over” for geography to explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.22 is the value that EL actually find for the effect of institutions. But how do they get that? By running an IV regression that assumes geography has not effect. It’s circular. If they assume that geography doesn’t matter, then they find a big effect of institutions. And then they use this big effect of institutions to conclude that geography doesn’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the hypothesis: “Geography does not matter outside of its influence on institutions.”” I can’t prove that hypothesis wrong, certainly not with this data. But using the OID test from the El regressions doesn’t prove that this statement is right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Isn&#39;t the Whole World Developed?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Clark-Cotton/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Clark-Cotton/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;That’s the title of Greg Clark’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/cup/jechis/v47y1987i01p141-173_04.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; from 1987 on cotton production in the early 20th century. Clark uses that specific industry to study the sources of variation across countries in real wages. I revisited it recently because I want to use it in my graduate course, and because I think it lays out a clear case for what could be loosely called a “cultural” explanation for differences in development. In short, the paper is going to come to the conclusion that poor countries are poor because of some unknown cultural source that supports a norm of low efficiency of labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to the paper is that Clark can compare outcomes across different countries that are using essentially identical technology. The spinning machines and looms being used by cotton manufacturers in essentially all countries at this time were designed, built, and commonly installed by English engineers. If anything, because they were relatively young industries, other countries in the early 20th century had &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; machines than their English peers. So Clark is able to compare the performance of different countries in producing cotton using an identical technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, Clark works comes at the problem from a slightly different direction than the typical macro/growth paper would. Take a look at Clark’s Table 1, which contains most of the information we need to talk about the story here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/clark_tab1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clark Table 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with Clark’s method, and then below I’m going to compare that to the macro/growth approach. He asks two questions, one kind of obvious and one not so obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What rate of return on capital (“implied profit rate”) would an English cotton factory earn if it faced the same input prices in country X?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What price could a factory in country X charge for cotton cloth and still earn an 8% return on capital (“manufacturing cost”)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 1:&lt;/strong&gt; To answer the first, it is crucial to realize that Clark is assuming that the English factory is going to use the exact same proportions of workers, capital, and coal no matter the input cost. They are going to produce the exact same amount of output, sell it for the exact same price, and earn the exact same revenue. In other words, this technology is Leontief in this experiment. The only difference is going to be in how much they pay for inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other nit-picky point is that the column in Table 1 called “Plant and Machinery” is the cost of capital in the sense of paying for depreciation costs. It is not the amount of capital used (which is listed in Clark’s Table 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final row of Table 1 gives you the cost shares for an English firm, and we need this to back out the implied cost shares for other countries. For example, in England 61.8% of revenues get paid to labor. But in China, because wages are 0.54/5.0 = 0.108 of English wages, the share of revenues being paid to labor is only 0.108 x 0.618 = 0.067. Using a similar calculation, the share of revenues paid out for capital depreciation is 0.159 in China, and the share for coal is 0.044. In total, 0.067 + 0.159 + 0.044 = 0.270 of revenue is paid to inputs, meaning that 0.73 of revenue is paid to owners of capital. In comparison, only 0.224 of revenues are paid to owners of capital in England, mainly because wages are so high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Clark’s Table 2 (not shown), the actual capital used in China is 17.76, while in England it is 15.06. Since 0.224 of revenue in England is assumed to provide an 8% return on 15.06 units of capital, revenues must be 0.08x15.06/0.224 = 5.379. This number is meaningless, except that it allows us to calculate the return on capital in China, which is 0.73x5.379/17.76 = 0.221. Hence the 22.1% implied profit rate for China in Clark’s Table 1. Lather, rinse, and repeat for the other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did firms in China actually earn 22.1% on their capital? No! That’s the whole point of the paper. They didn’t. If they did, we’d expect to have seen a massive shift of cotton cloth production towards China, or Japan, or any of the many other places earning higher profits than England or the US. But we did not, so there must be something that kept the majority of cotton cloth production in England. In short, they must not have been able to produce as much given those same inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 2:&lt;/strong&gt; What I’ve called Clark’s second question is not something he says explicitly in the paper. But I find it a better way to understand what is going on in his “manufacturing cost” column. Very simply, set the English price of cotton to 1.0. What price would a given country have to charge to earn exactly 8% on their capital?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, for China to earn 8% on their capital, only 17.76x0.08/5.379 = 0.264 of their revenues would need to be paid to capital owners. Their inputs are taking up only 0.270 of revenues. So Chinese firms need to only generate 0.264+0.270 = 0.534 of the revenues of an English firm to create an 8% return on capital. In other words, they could cut revenues to 53% of an English firm (perhaps by lowering the price to 53% of English prices) and still match the 8% return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Clark means by “manufacturing cost”. It’s the cost of producing an 8% return to capital, matching his assumed norm for English firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, it is clear that Chinese, and most other countries, were relatively low cost and/or could have offered lower prices &lt;em&gt;if they in fact could produce as much as English firms&lt;/em&gt;. But they cannot, and the whole rest of Clark’s paper is exploring reasons for why they could not produce as much as English firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with two things that do not explain the differences across countries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technology. Like I said above, the beauty of this paper is that Clark can establish quite clearly that the firms in all countries used essentially identical machines. For all intents and purposes, they were operating with identical technology and capital. So this doesn’t explain the difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capital utilization. Perhaps China or other countries worked fewer hours, and we’ve incorrectly assumed that they worked as many hours as English workers. But Clark shows in his Table 2 that most other countries worked for &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; hours than England. The mystery is in fact even deeper. With high hours in China, it should have made them even more profitable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we get to the heart of Clark’s explanation, worker efficiency. He shows, in his Table 3 copied below, that the amount of capital per worker was very different across countries. His original question assumed it was identical (Leontief).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/clark_tab3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clark Table 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that English (and US/Canada) used far more machines per worker than China or India or other countries. So the labor cost for China was in fact very different than England. Paying a Chinese laborer 0.54 didn’t get you the same amount of work as paying an English laborer 5.0. In England, to operate 2.04 machines, you hired one worker. In China, to operate 2.04 machines you had to hire 2.04/0.48 = 4.25 workers. And so the true labor cost in China was 4.25*0.54 = 2.3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This changes the implied profit and cost calculations in the final two columns. Note that the vast majority of the countries now are &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; cost than England, and earn a much &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; implied profit rate. In the US, this is because labor is expensive. In China and others, it is because workers don’t operate as much capital as in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now Clark asks why machines per worker are so low in some places. Or if you like, why there are so many workers operating each machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Substitution of labor for capital? In this case, not only is production not Leontief, but there is a high degree of substitution allowed. Perhaps India/China used lots of labor in place of capital, and hence could achieve high output per unit of capital, even though output per unit of labor was low. Except, no. Clark shows evidence that they did not produce more per unit of capital. It really is a low efficiency of labor used.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Differences in cotton quality? No, it doesn’t appear that India/China used extra labor because they were using higher quality cotton that required more attention.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worker experience? No, this doesn’t appear to make sense. Average years of experience were higher in England, but not by much, and not universally compared to the other countries. Moreover, Clark provides some evidence that the returns to experience within mills was relatively low, as evidenced by some places relying almost exclusively on young women who only worked for a few years before they got married.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worker quality? No, interestingly enough. Clark’s evidence here is that immigrants to the US from these other countries earned just as much as their peers. French immigrants (who in France were only 54% as efficient as English workers) earned essentially an identical wage to English immigrants in the US. Simliar for Mexican, Russian, Italian, and Japanese workers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last point is telling. The workers in other countries are entirely capable of working at the efficiency of an English or US worker, but for some reason they do not. (You might worry about selection of immigrants; Clark argues that the selection effect would have to be ridiculously large to account for this data.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are left with what Clark calls “local effects”. Workers in China or India, for example, are just as inherently skilled as anywhere else, but the norm in China or India is that they do not work as efficiently. Clark has a quote (from India) referring to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The operatives in this mill refuse to attend to more machinery. I watched two ring frames for three minutes; there was not a single end down, yet the workpeople would not look after more than one side. They said they were satisfied with the present wage, and that there were too many men who want work and cannot get it that it would be unfair if they were to attend to more machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this “culture”, as Clark later alludes to? If you think this is something particularly “Indian”, then I guess so. But I’m not sure that the attitude expressed here necessarily varies by culture. It is entirely plausible that India, with a dearth of capital, saw workers expressing an attitude that any country with a dearth of capital would express. The explanation may still be a feature of low capital stocks, not something cultural. If there is something Leontief about cotton technology, then the limit on cotton employment is the stock of machinery, which is something that conforms with the quote. And we could certainly imagine that if English workers faced the same dearth of capital, they could take the same attitude towards work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there is something about the “local effects” to be explained. Why did the cotton industry persist so long in Britain, despite the drag of high wages. Surely at some point it had to make sense to try and relocate capital to low-cost countries? Could it be an institutional friction - risk of expropriation - that prevented people from taking advantage of the high implied returns in other countries? If it is cultural, then this culture doesn’t apparently travel with natives, otherwise the immigrants to the US wouldn’t have been as productive. This is different than what most modern research on culture would suggest; it tends to find that cultural traits travel with migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big story of the Clark paper is that technology is not sufficient to explain massive differences in outcomes. And this sets it up as an alternative story to the one from &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/&quot;&gt;Comin, Easterly, and Gong&lt;/a&gt; that I recently posted about. For CEG, technology itself differs, and this difference persists. If you extrapolate Clark’s work, technology is similar, but the local effect of culture varies, and that is what presumably creates persistence in outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-comparison-to-growthmacro&quot;&gt;A Comparison to Growth/Macro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick aside about how a modern macro/growth paper would approach this. In short, you’d be doing a variance decomposition on the real wage in Clark’s data. More precisely, you’d be doing a variance decomposition of the log of real wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variance of log real wages in Clark’s data is 0.645, a number that means nothing by itself. The question is what fraction of the variance could be explained by variation in capital per worker or coal per worker. The remaining fraction is then attributed to the residual. To calculate this, you need the weighted variance of log capital per worker and log coal per worker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “weighted” part of this is the importance of capital or coal in production. How do you find these weights? You look at the cost shares. And here is the crucial difference between what a macro/growth paper would do and what Clark did. Macro/growth is going to take the English cost shares and assume that these are the same for all countries. In other words, we’d assume Cobb-Douglas production functions, as opposed to Clark’s implicit Leontief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Aside: We don’t know the actual amount of coal used, but to get around that we might assume that the coal/capital ratio is the same across countries. If we can’t, then I don’t know how to proceed, so bear with me. This simply means that the variance of log coal per worker is identical to the variance of log capital per worker.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the weighted variance of log capital and log coal per worker is either 0.0188 (if you use Clark’s index of capital) or 0.0381 (if you use Clark’s data on looms equivalents). Either way, this is only 2.92% or 5.90%, respecitively, of the total variance in real wages. A tiny fraction of variation in real wages is driven by differences in capital per worker, and the rest must be explained by technology, human capital, or something else. Clark has disposed of technology as an explanation, so it could be human capital. Clark eliminates big human capital differnces (at least in terms of age structure or experience), so it has to be “something else”. That something else is either local effects or culture, depending on your choice of terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this a better method? No. Clark’s initial assumption of Leontief technology may be more appropriate here. Or it may not. We don’t actually know. Both Clark and the macro/growth literature are making assumptions about production functions that partly drive their results. In either case, we get that differences in the stocks of capital per worker are not entirely sufficient to explain why some places are rich and some are poor.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Site Upgrades</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Site-Upgrades/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Site-Upgrades/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Cavs/Spurs game turning into a snorer, I distracted myself by fixing up a few things on the new site. Rocking Saturday night, I know. I’m old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SSL&lt;/strong&gt;: The site is now using SSL, which means you’ll see “https” in the web address. You don’t need to do anything, the site automatically redirects you to the https link. If you want to save yourself a millisecond, change your link to the site to say “https” explicitly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSS Equations&lt;/strong&gt;: One thing that came up in the transition was that the RSS feed was not rendering equations. You’d see markup code in your RSS reader, not a nicely formatted equation. This is fixed….I think. In fact, here’s a little test. If you can see &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y = x^2\inline&quot;/&gt; in your RSS feed as a nicely formatted equation, then apparently things are working well. If not, then I know what I’m doing next Saturday night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, thanks for reading, and thanks for the patience with the tweaks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Persistence of Technology</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the papers I use to introduce several ideas into my graduate growth and development course is by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aejmac/v2y2010i3p65-97.html&quot;&gt;Diego Comin, Bill Easterly, and Erick Gong&lt;/a&gt;, titled “Was the Wealth of Nations Determined in 1000BC?”. If we were being strict about things, the answer is no. But the longer answer is “Well, not really 1000BC. But there is a surprising amount of explanatory power in technology measures from 1500AD”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What CEG document is that technology levels are incredibly persistent, and that technology levels reaching back centuries retain some predictive power for explaining variation in income per capita in 2002. I’ll hit back below on this idea of predictive power, and how that differs from “causal explanation”. For the moment, focus on that word “persistent” and think about what it means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to think about two kinds of persistence. What I’ll call “time-series persistence” is the idea that for a given country or economy, their technology level in the past is highly predictive of their technology level today. This is different than “cross-sectional persistence”, which is the idea that gaps between countries persist over time. You could have time-series persistence without cross-sectional persistence (e.g. slow convergence to a common technology level) or cross-sectional without time-series (e.g. fixed level differences in technology).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CEG are going to, in the end, provide some evidence of both kinds of persistence. Let’s start with the cross-sectional persistence, which is the main theme of their paper. Here let’s stop to describe exactly how they measure “technology”. CEG use several sources, including the Murdock Ethnographic Atlas, to pull out binary measures of technological use for different ethnic/cultural groups. Did your group use wheeled wagons in 1500? Yes? You get a 1. Did you use paper? No? You get a zero. Did you produce steel? No? You get a zero. Average these 0/1 measures across the different measures of technology, and you get an overall score that lies between 0/1 based on how many of these technologies you had. There is no intensive measure here (i.e. how widespread the use of the technology was within your group), only a coding for whether you used it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/ceg_figure1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Figure 2 gives you essentially the whole thrust of the paper. They use the ethnic group technology measures, assign each country a technology level based on the highest scoring ethnic group in their country, and then adjust the country level scores based on the fact that country populations are different in 2002 from in 1500 (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/bro/econwp/2008-15.html&quot;&gt;Putterman and Weil, 2002&lt;/a&gt;. Thus they have “migration-adjusted technology in 1500AD” on the x-axis, and log income per capita in 2002 on the y-axis. There is a strong positive relationship. The higher the technology in 1500AD, the higher the expected level of income per capita in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few open questions I have is whether this is robust to (a) using the minimum, average, or median ethnic group technology level for a country, rather than the maximum, (b) using all the ethnic group technology data, and run that through the Putterman/Weil matrix to find a country’s technology level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their empirical results are in the following table. When they regress 2002 current income per capita on technology levels in past years, they find significant effects. This holds for technology in 1000BC, 0AD, and 1500AD. Note that the coefficients rise as the time span becomes shorter. This isn’t surprising, as technology levels are imperfectly persistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/ceg_table8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table 8A&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of the effect is surprising. Take the 1500AD result in column (3). The coefficient is 3.261, which means that if the technology index goes from 0 (no technologies) to 1 (all the original technologies), log income per capita goes up by 3.261 log points, or by a factor of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?exp(3.261) = 26\inline&quot;/&gt; times. Technology doesn’t vary between 0 and 1 in their index, but this gives you a sense of how strong the effect is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also notice the R-squared, which is 50% for the 1500AD results. That’s a big number. Half the variation in income per capita in 2002 is associated with variation in technology in 1500AD. It is worth stopping here to say something about what CEG are saying empirically. This is not a “policy experiment” paper, and I don’t think it is appropriate to evaluate it as such. This is a paper about forecasting, basically. What their result says is that if you tell me the level of technology in 1500AD, I can predict with a good amount of accuracy your income per capita in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s different than saying that if one could increase technology in 1500AD by “1 unit”, you could raise income per capita today by a factor of 26. First, as is obvious, there is no way to actually do that. Second, this isn’t the interesting research question here. CEG are trying to establish that old technology levels have predictive power for current income per capita. They are not looking for explanatory power, or forecasting power, and not a strict causal effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Should&lt;/em&gt; they be looking for a strict causal impact? That’s a fair question, but one without an obvious answer. Ultimately, you might want to argue that we want strict causal explanations for why some countries are rich in 2002. But an explanatory paper like this is valuable to that search. Knowing that &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; in 1500AD has strong predictive power for incomes today is informative. It tells us that we have to look back to 1500AD for at least some of those causal forces. Even if it turns out that technology in 1500AD is just a proxy for institutions, or geography, or culture, or whatever, this is a time period we should be looking at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that CEG have evidence of cross-sectional persistence. Gaps in technology in 1500AD appear to persist for centuries. This doesn’t mean the gaps are perfectly persistent (i.e. will last forever), just that they take a loooooong time to dissipate. Is this surprising? Perhaps not, if you think that there is a lot of &lt;em&gt;time-series&lt;/em&gt; persistence in technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And CEG provide some evidence of that time-series persistence. Not just in their baseline results from the table I showed, but in a secondary analysis that uses the fact that they have multiple categories of technology. With multiple categories, they have multiple observations on each country in each year. Which means they can look at technology-level regressions while pulling out country-time effects (i.e. England in 1500 and England in 2000 just happened to both be lucky) and technology-country effects (i.e. England is just really good at transport technologies). Here, I need to be clear that their measure of technology in 2000 is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same as their measure in 1500AD. The measure in 2000 comes from other work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/hbs/wpaper/10-035.html&quot;&gt;Comin and Bart Hobijn&lt;/a&gt; that is richer in measuring how many modern technologies a country has adopted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, they show that if a country-technology level is high in 1500AD, then it also tends to be high in 2000. Given the fixed effects included, that is saying that if a technology in England in 1500 was slightly about the average tech level in England in 1500, then it also tends to be above average in 2000. This is a little stronger evidence of time-series persistence, because they are not actually comparing one country to another any more, but one country to itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All well and good. But like I said above, time-series persistence doesn’t imply cross-sectional persistence. Why do we see so much cross-sectional persistence. CEG provide a list of theories of time-series persistence, but I don’t know that this is really adapted to the job of explaining the cross-sectional persistence. Many of the theories they document posit no limits on the flow of ideas (spillovers, complementarities, recombinations, etc..) between sectors, people, or technologies. And this makes sense in explaining time-series persistence. But if the ideas can flow, then why not over borders?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For cross-sectional persistence, you need something that actually limits the flow of ideas to different populations/countries. For cross-sectional persistence, it seems unlikely that it really is an inability to invent or copy new technologies; they are out there, easy to see. You need some friction that lies outside of a narrow view of technology. And I think that this pushes you towards theories that are based on culture and institutions (both loosely defined). It seems there must be non-technological factors that prevent adoption of technologies, perhaps because of norms (“we refuse to use things invented by infidels”) or entrenched interests (“we refuse to use things that threaten our monopoly power”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that sense, it isn’t the technology in 1500AD &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt; that matters in the CEG regressions, this is an indicator of some kind of variation in culture or institutions (or something else?) that matters. To return to the earlier discussion, it seems likely that their results won’t ultimately turn out to be causal, but the predictive power is telling us to something about how powerful those cultural/institutional factors are.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to GrowthEcon</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Welcome/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is both a welcome message to my new site - &lt;a href=&quot;http://growthecon.com&quot;&gt;growthecon.com&lt;/a&gt; - as well as a test that everything is working out alright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth Economics Blog is now located here, but the old &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Wordpress site&lt;/a&gt; will linger on for a while. I know people have links set up to old posts that they may use in classes. I’ll provide some warning of when those links will die. And they may never die, because I will probably forget to ever close down the old Wordpress site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, if you are still along for the ride, I appreciate it. In terms of following the new site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email&lt;/strong&gt;. I’ve set up a new mailing service for all the existing subscribers. You should have to do nothing. If you would like to subscribe via email, there is a link at the bottom of the home page to do that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSS&lt;/strong&gt;. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://growthecon.com/feed.xml&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the new feed, or copy and paste the link into your favorite reader.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt;. New posts will continue to get pushed to Twitter, so follow me at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DietzVollrath&quot;&gt;@DietzVollrath&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments are enabled here, and the old comments have all been imported. You may have to create a new login for the new commenting service. I apologize for that, but I didn’t have any way around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Declining Marginal Product of Capital</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/the-declining-marginal-product-of-capital/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/the-declining-marginal-product-of-capital/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.wordpress.com/2015/11/24/describing-the-decline-of-capital-per-worker/&quot;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about the recent decline in capital per worker in the U.S. The short summary is that from 2009-2013 capital per worker has been &lt;i&gt;shrinking&lt;/i&gt;, and this is at odds with most of historical experience. This shrinking capital per worker contributes to higher measured productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The illustrious &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bus.lsu.edu/achanda/&quot;&gt;Areendam Chanda&lt;/a&gt; asked, in response, what the marginal product of capital looked like given the decline in capital per worker in this series. This is straightforward to calculate given the BLS data, and it shows what I think is an interesting pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I calculate the MPK as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MPK = \alpha \frac{Y}{K}&quot; alt=&quot;MPK = \alpha \frac{Y}{K}&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\alpha}\inline&quot;/&gt; is capital&#39;s share of output. If the world is roughly Cobb-Douglas, this should describe for us the extra amount of output we could get from one additional unit of capital. This is an aggregate concept, and doesn&#39;t necessarily map to any specific use of capital (e.g. the marginal product of a laptop can be different than the marginal product of a shovel). This is the marginal product of dumping an extra unit of homogenous ``capital&#39;&#39; into the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the figure showing the time path from 1960 to 2013:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_MPK_1960.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marginal Product of Capital&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of the recent decline in capital per worker, the uptick in the actual series (black line) from 2000-2013 makes some sense. Declining capital per worker should be associated with a higher return on capital. But what appears to be true is that the recent uptick in MPK is driven by a change in capital&#39;s share in output. I plotted in gray an alternative MPK that assumes capital&#39;s share is constant at 0.31 (a rough long-run average), and as you can see this continues the downward trend of the prior decades. The uptick is due almost entirely to the increase in capital&#39;s share of output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What seems far more interesting in this figure is the general drift downward in the MPK since 1960. I can come up with two different interpretations of this, which depend a lot on the time frame you consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Secular shift in MPK:&lt;/b&gt; Essentially, interpret this as evidence of some kind of sustained, secular change in the US economy. The drift down in the MPK isn&#39;t consistent with the US being on a balanced growth path (BGP). As a quick reminder, traditionally a BGP is a situation where GDP per worker is growing at a roughly constant rate, the return on capital (MPK) is constant over time, and the share of output going to capital is constant over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we almost always presume that the US is on a BGP. I will be telling my undergrads this in a week or so, I&#39;m sure. Almost every growth model is written so that it delivers a BGP eventually, because people feel that this represents what we see in the data. And when they say ``BGP&#39;&#39; in their model, they almost always mean that the MPK is constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a standard Solow model, the steady state is a BGP, and the model tells us what determines the MPK on that BGP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MPK = \alpha\frac{n + g + \delta}{s}&quot; alt=&quot;MPK = \alpha\frac{n + g + \delta}{s}&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\alpha}\inline&quot;/&gt; is capital&#39;s share of output, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{n}\inline&quot;/&gt; is population growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt; is productivity growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\delta}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the depreciation rate, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the savings rate. Note, this equation is for the MPK in steady state, not necessarily at any given point in time, but it is useful for thinking about what might drive the decline in MPK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steady decline in the MPK over time is consistent with declining &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{n}\inline&quot;/&gt; (because capital&#39;s marginal product is lower when there are fewer people around), declining &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt; (slower productivity growth), and higher &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; (more savings). In this story we are transitioning from the immediate post-war era of relatively rapid population and technological change, to a new era of relatively low population and technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth remembering here that the MPK is calculated using the BLS data, which excludes the government sector and the residential housing stock. So this represents a decline in the non-residential-housing MPK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Return of MPK to Long-run trend:&lt;/b&gt; But from a long, long-term perspective, maybe the decline in MPK since 1960 is just a reversion to a steady state value? The MPK should be roughly a proxy for the return on capital. One other rough proxy for that is the earnings yield on the S&amp;amp;P 500, which represents how much you get in earnings for buying a ``unit&#39;&#39; of capital by purchasing a basket of stocks. The figure below, which I grabbed from Brad DeLong&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bradford-delong.com/2015/02/i-understand-where-martin-feldstein-starts-i-do-not-understand-where-he-ends-up-focus.html&quot;&gt;site&lt;/a&gt;, plots this earnings yield from 1880 until today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_yield.png&quot; alt=&quot;SP Earnings Yield&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this it seems to me that the earnings yield has a ``normal&#39;&#39; level of about 6%, and that while there are sustained deviations from this value, it always appears to head back to 6%. The first figure shows that MPK has been declining from 1960 until now, matching the decline in the earnings yield from rouhgly 1970 until today. Was the MPK just on walkabout, and is coming back to its long-run BGP level? And no, I&#39;m not terribly worried about the fact that the MPK is always higher than the earnings yield. They are both proxies, so the fact they don&#39;t agree on levels isn&#39;t terribly meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earnings yields suggests that what is abnormal about the figure for MPK is the high values in the 60&#39;s and 70&#39;s, not the low values now. The S&amp;amp;P evidence is consistent with that, although the match-up is imperfect. Why was the MPK so high in the 1960&#39;s, while the earnings yield didn&#39;t rise until the 1970&#39;s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, in this interpretation, the steady state MPK has stayed roughly the same, but for some reason we deviated in the 60&#39;s and 70&#39;s to having a high MPK. Perhaps it was atypical shocks to productivity (over and above the regular trend growth rate &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt;), or atypical shocks to population growth (Baby Boomers?), and we&#39;re now coming back down to normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The caveat here is that the S&amp;amp;P earnings yield might be a bad comparison for the MPK. But given that the MPK is ex-residential-housing-capital and ex-government, perhaps not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know that there is a way to distinguish between the two stories, not without doing more research that I don&#39;t have time to do right now. Without taking a firm stand on this, one important point here is that the explanation depends crucially on what you take to be ``normal&#39;&#39;. And that depends in part on how far back you graph the data. The S&amp;amp;P data suggests a different story than the MPK series (and the MPK series doesn&#39;t go back any further because the BLS doesn&#39;t have the requisite data any further back). I guess it is a caution that the starting point of your data series is not necessarily the same thing as the ``starting point&#39;&#39; of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 21:17:16 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
