<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Growth Economics Blog</title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description>Dietrich Vollrath Economic Growth Blog</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 22:35:15 -0600</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Persistence of Technology</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Persistence-Technology/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the papers I use to introduce several ideas into my graduate growth and development course is by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aejmac/v2y2010i3p65-97.html&quot;&gt;Diego Comin, Bill Easterly, and Erick Gong&lt;/a&gt;, titled &amp;quot;Was the Wealth of Nations Determined in 1000BC?&amp;quot;. If we were being strict about things, the answer is no. But the longer answer is &amp;quot;Well, not really 1000BC. But there is a surprising amount of explanatory power in technology measures from 1500AD&amp;quot;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What CEG document is that technology levels are incredibly persistent, and that technology levels reaching back centuries retain some predictive power for explaining variation in income per capita in 2002. I&amp;#39;ll hit back below on this idea of predictive power, and how that differs from &amp;quot;causal explanation&amp;quot;. For the moment, focus on that word &amp;quot;persistent&amp;quot; and think about what it means. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to think about two kinds of persistence. What I&amp;#39;ll call &amp;quot;time-series persistence&amp;quot; is the idea that for a given country or economy, their technology level in the past is highly predictive of their technology level today. This is different than &amp;quot;cross-sectional persistence&amp;quot;, which is the idea that gaps between countries persist over time. You could have time-series persistence without cross-sectional persistence (e.g. slow convergence to a common technology level) or cross-sectional without time-series (e.g. fixed level differences in technology). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CEG are going to, in the end, provide some evidence of both kinds of persistence. Let&amp;#39;s start with the cross-sectional persistence, which is the main theme of their paper. Here let&amp;#39;s stop to describe exactly how they measure &amp;quot;technology&amp;quot;. CEG use several sources, including the Murdock Ethnographic Atlas, to pull out binary measures of technological use for different ethnic/cultural groups. Did your group use wheeled wagons in 1500? Yes? You get a 1. Did you use paper? No? You get a zero. Did you produce steel? No? You get a zero. Average these 0/1 measures across the different measures of technology, and you get an overall score that lies between 0/1 based on how many of these technologies you had. There is no intensive measure here (i.e. how widespread the use of the technology was within your group), only a coding for whether you used it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/ceg_figure1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 2&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Figure 2 gives you essentially the whole thrust of the paper. They use the ethnic group technology measures, assign each country a technology level based on the highest scoring ethnic group in their country, and then adjust the country level scores based on the fact that country populations are different in 2002 from in 1500 (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/bro/econwp/2008-15.html&quot;&gt;Putterman and Weil, 2002&lt;/a&gt;. Thus they have &amp;quot;migration-adjusted technology in 1500AD&amp;quot; on the x-axis, and log income per capita in 2002 on the y-axis. There is a strong positive relationship. The higher the technology in 1500AD, the higher the expected level of income per capita in 2002. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few open questions I have is whether this is robust to (a) using the minimum, average, or median ethnic group technology level for a country, rather than the maximum, (b) using all the ethnic group technology data, and run that through the Putterman/Weil matrix to find a country&amp;#39;s technology level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their empirical results are in the following table. When they regress 2002 current income per capita on technology levels in past years, they find significant effects. This holds for technology in 1000BC, 0AD, and 1500AD. Note that the coefficients rise as the time span becomes shorter. This isn&amp;#39;t surprising, as technology levels are imperfectly persistent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/ceg_table8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table 8A&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of the effect is surprising. Take the 1500AD result in column (3). The coefficient is 3.261, which means that if the technology index goes from 0 (no technologies) to 1 (all the original technologies), log income per capita goes up by 3.261 log points, or by a factor of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?exp(3.261) = 26\inline&quot;/&gt; times. Technology doesn&amp;#39;t vary between 0 and 1 in their index, but this gives you a sense of how strong the effect is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also notice the R-squared, which is 50% for the 1500AD results. That&amp;#39;s a big number. Half the variation in income per capita in 2002 is associated with variation in technology in 1500AD. It is worth stopping here to say something about what CEG are saying empirically. This is not a &amp;quot;policy experiment&amp;quot; paper, and I don&amp;#39;t think it is appropriate to evaluate it as such. This is a paper about forecasting, basically. What their result says is that if you tell me the level of technology in 1500AD, I can predict with a good amount of accuracy your income per capita in 2002. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s different than saying that if one could increase technology in 1500AD by &amp;quot;1 unit&amp;quot;, you could raise income per capita today by a factor of 26. First, as is obvious, there is no way to actually do that. Second, this isn&amp;#39;t the interesting research question here. CEG are trying to establish that old technology levels have predictive power for current income per capita. They are not looking for explanatory power, or forecasting power, and not a strict causal effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Should&lt;/em&gt; they be looking for a strict causal impact? That&amp;#39;s a fair question, but one without an obvious answer. Ultimately, you might want to argue that we want strict causal explanations for why some countries are rich in 2002. But an explanatory paper like this is valuable to that search. Knowing that &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; in 1500AD has strong predictive power for incomes today is informative. It tells us that we have to look back to 1500AD for at least some of those causal forces. Even if it turns out that technology in 1500AD is just a proxy for institutions, or geography, or culture, or whatever, this is a time period we should be looking at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that CEG have evidence of cross-sectional persistence. Gaps in technology in 1500AD appear to persist for centuries. This doesn&amp;#39;t mean the gaps are perfectly persistent (i.e. will last forever), just that they take a loooooong time to dissipate. Is this surprising? Perhaps not, if you think that there is a lot of &lt;em&gt;time-series&lt;/em&gt; persistence in technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And CEG provide some evidence of that time-series persistence. Not just in their baseline results from the table I showed, but in a secondary analysis that uses the fact that they have multiple categories of technology. With multiple categories, they have multiple observations on each country in each year. Which means they can look at technology-level regressions while pulling out country-time effects (i.e. England in 1500 and England in 2000 just happened to both be lucky) and technology-country effects (i.e. England is just really good at transport technologies). Here, I need to be clear that their measure of technology in 2000 is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same as their measure in 1500AD. The measure in 2000 comes from other work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/hbs/wpaper/10-035.html&quot;&gt;Comin and Bart Hobijn&lt;/a&gt; that is richer in measuring how many modern technologies a country has adopted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, they show that if a country-technology level is high in 1500AD, then it also tends to be high in 2000. Given the fixed effects included, that is saying that if a technology in England in 1500 was slightly about the average tech level in England in 1500, then it also tends to be above average in 2000. This is a little stronger evidence of time-series persistence, because they are not actually comparing one country to another any more, but one country to itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All well and good. But like I said above, time-series persistence doesn&amp;#39;t imply cross-sectional persistence. Why do we see so much cross-sectional persistence. CEG provide a list of theories of time-series persistence, but I don&amp;#39;t know that this is really adapted to the job of explaining the cross-sectional persistence. Many of the theories they document posit no limits on the flow of ideas (spillovers, complementarities, recombinations, etc..) between sectors, people, or technologies. And this makes sense in explaining time-series persistence. But if the ideas can flow, then why not over borders?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For cross-sectional persistence, you need something that actually limits the flow of ideas to different populations/countries. For cross-sectional persistence, it seems unlikely that it really is an inability to invent or copy new technologies; they are out there, easy to see. You need some friction that lies outside of a narrow view of technology. And I think that this pushes you towards theories that are based on culture and institutions (both loosely defined). It seems there must be non-technological factors that prevent adoption of technologies, perhaps because of norms (&amp;quot;we refuse to use things invented by infidels&amp;quot;) or entrenched interests (&amp;quot;we refuse to use things that threaten our monopoly power&amp;quot;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that sense, it isn&amp;#39;t the technology in 1500AD &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt; that matters in the CEG regressions, this is an indicator of some kind of variation in culture or institutions (or something else?) that matters. To return to the earlier discussion, it seems likely that their results won&amp;#39;t ultimately turn out to be causal, but the predictive power is telling us to something about how powerful those cultural/institutional factors are.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to GrowthEcon</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Welcome/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is both a welcome message to my new site - &lt;a href=&quot;http://growthecon.com&quot;&gt;growthecon.com&lt;/a&gt; - as well as a test that everything is working out alright. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth Economics Blog is now located here, but the old &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Wordpress site&lt;/a&gt; will linger on for a while. I know people have links set up to old posts that they may use in classes. I&amp;#39;ll provide some warning of when those links will die. And they may never die, because I will probably forget to ever close down the old Wordpress site. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, if you are still along for the ride, I appreciate it. In terms of following the new site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email&lt;/strong&gt;. I&amp;#39;ve set up a new mailing service for all the existing subscribers. You should have to do nothing. If you would like to subscribe via email, there is a link at the bottom of the home page to do that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSS&lt;/strong&gt;. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://growthecon.com/feed.xml&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the new feed, or copy and paste the link into your favorite reader.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt;. New posts will continue to get pushed to Twitter, so follow me at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DietzVollrath&quot;&gt;@DietzVollrath&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments are enabled here, and the old comments have all been imported. You may have to create a new login for the new commenting service. I apologize for that, but I didn&amp;#39;t have any way around it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Declining Marginal Product of Capital</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/the-declining-marginal-product-of-capital/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/the-declining-marginal-product-of-capital/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.wordpress.com/2015/11/24/describing-the-decline-of-capital-per-worker/&quot;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about the recent decline in capital per worker in the U.S. The short summary is that from 2009-2013 capital per worker has been &lt;i&gt;shrinking&lt;/i&gt;, and this is at odds with most of historical experience. This shrinking capital per worker contributes to higher measured productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The illustrious &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bus.lsu.edu/achanda/&quot;&gt;Areendam Chanda&lt;/a&gt; asked, in response, what the marginal product of capital looked like given the decline in capital per worker in this series. This is straightforward to calculate given the BLS data, and it shows what I think is an interesting pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I calculate the MPK as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MPK = \alpha \frac{Y}{K}&quot; alt=&quot;MPK = \alpha \frac{Y}{K}&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\alpha}\inline&quot;/&gt; is capital&#39;s share of output. If the world is roughly Cobb-Douglas, this should describe for us the extra amount of output we could get from one additional unit of capital. This is an aggregate concept, and doesn&#39;t necessarily map to any specific use of capital (e.g. the marginal product of a laptop can be different than the marginal product of a shovel). This is the marginal product of dumping an extra unit of homogenous ``capital&#39;&#39; into the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the figure showing the time path from 1960 to 2013:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_MPK_1960.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marginal Product of Capital&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of the recent decline in capital per worker, the uptick in the actual series (black line) from 2000-2013 makes some sense. Declining capital per worker should be associated with a higher return on capital. But what appears to be true is that the recent uptick in MPK is driven by a change in capital&#39;s share in output. I plotted in gray an alternative MPK that assumes capital&#39;s share is constant at 0.31 (a rough long-run average), and as you can see this continues the downward trend of the prior decades. The uptick is due almost entirely to the increase in capital&#39;s share of output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What seems far more interesting in this figure is the general drift downward in the MPK since 1960. I can come up with two different interpretations of this, which depend a lot on the time frame you consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Secular shift in MPK:&lt;/b&gt; Essentially, interpret this as evidence of some kind of sustained, secular change in the US economy. The drift down in the MPK isn&#39;t consistent with the US being on a balanced growth path (BGP). As a quick reminder, traditionally a BGP is a situation where GDP per worker is growing at a roughly constant rate, the return on capital (MPK) is constant over time, and the share of output going to capital is constant over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we almost always presume that the US is on a BGP. I will be telling my undergrads this in a week or so, I&#39;m sure. Almost every growth model is written so that it delivers a BGP eventually, because people feel that this represents what we see in the data. And when they say ``BGP&#39;&#39; in their model, they almost always mean that the MPK is constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a standard Solow model, the steady state is a BGP, and the model tells us what determines the MPK on that BGP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;\[MPK = \alpha\frac{n + g + \delta}{s}\]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\alpha}\inline&quot;/&gt; is capital&#39;s share of output, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{n}\inline&quot;/&gt; is population growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt; is productivity growth, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{\delta}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the depreciation rate, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the savings rate. Note, this equation is for the MPK in steady state, not necessarily at any given point in time, but it is useful for thinking about what might drive the decline in MPK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steady decline in the MPK over time is consistent with declining &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{n}\inline&quot;/&gt; (because capital&#39;s marginal product is lower when there are fewer people around), declining &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt; (slower productivity growth), and higher &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; (more savings). In this story we are transitioning from the immediate post-war era of relatively rapid population and technological change, to a new era of relatively low population and technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth remembering here that the MPK is calculated using the BLS data, which excludes the government sector and the residential housing stock. So this represents a decline in the non-residential-housing MPK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Return of MPK to Long-run trend:&lt;/b&gt; But from a long, long-term perspective, maybe the decline in MPK since 1960 is just a reversion to a steady state value? The MPK should be roughly a proxy for the return on capital. One other rough proxy for that is the earnings yield on the S&amp;amp;P 500, which represents how much you get in earnings for buying a ``unit&#39;&#39; of capital by purchasing a basket of stocks. The figure below, which I grabbed from Brad DeLong&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bradford-delong.com/2015/02/i-understand-where-martin-feldstein-starts-i-do-not-understand-where-he-ends-up-focus.html&quot;&gt;site&lt;/a&gt;, plots this earnings yield from 1880 until today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_yield.png&quot; alt=&quot;SP Earnings Yield&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this it seems to me that the earnings yield has a ``normal&#39;&#39; level of about 6%, and that while there are sustained deviations from this value, it always appears to head back to 6%. The first figure shows that MPK has been declining from 1960 until now, matching the decline in the earnings yield from rouhgly 1970 until today. Was the MPK just on walkabout, and is coming back to its long-run BGP level? And no, I&#39;m not terribly worried about the fact that the MPK is always higher than the earnings yield. They are both proxies, so the fact they don&#39;t agree on levels isn&#39;t terribly meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earnings yields suggests that what is abnormal about the figure for MPK is the high values in the 60&#39;s and 70&#39;s, not the low values now. The S&amp;amp;P evidence is consistent with that, although the match-up is imperfect. Why was the MPK so high in the 1960&#39;s, while the earnings yield didn&#39;t rise until the 1970&#39;s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, in this interpretation, the steady state MPK has stayed roughly the same, but for some reason we deviated in the 60&#39;s and 70&#39;s to having a high MPK. Perhaps it was atypical shocks to productivity (over and above the regular trend growth rate &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?{g}\inline&quot;/&gt;), or atypical shocks to population growth (Baby Boomers?), and we&#39;re now coming back down to normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The caveat here is that the S&amp;amp;P earnings yield might be a bad comparison for the MPK. But given that the MPK is ex-residential-housing-capital and ex-government, perhaps not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know that there is a way to distinguish between the two stories, not without doing more research that I don&#39;t have time to do right now. Without taking a firm stand on this, one important point here is that the explanation depends crucially on what you take to be ``normal&#39;&#39;. And that depends in part on how far back you graph the data. The S&amp;amp;P data suggests a different story than the MPK series (and the MPK series doesn&#39;t go back any further because the BLS doesn&#39;t have the requisite data any further back). I guess it is a caution that the starting point of your data series is not necessarily the same thing as the ``starting point&#39;&#39; of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 21:17:16 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Do You Need More Money for Economic Growth to Occur?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/do-you-need-more-money-for-economic-growth-to-occur/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/do-you-need-more-money-for-economic-growth-to-occur/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR version: No.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another entry to file under &quot;notes for undergrads&quot; and/or &quot;explaining things to your neighbor&quot;. A very common question I get about growth is: how does growth occur if there is not any &quot;more money&quot; in the economy. Another common question I get is: how is it economic growth if spending on one product just replaces spending on another?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions come, I think, from continued confusion about (a) nominal versus real GDP, (b) nominal GDP versus the stock of money, and (c) absolute versus relative prices. In short, things an economist might call money illusion. In the defense of students and my neighbors, it isn&#39;t terribly easy to think in relative prices and real terms when every single transaction you undertake involves absolute dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s start with an economy that produces exactly 10 cans of Budweiser, and nothing else, in a year. They each sell for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1, meaning that nominal GDP in this economy is \\inline&quot;/&gt;10 for the year. What is real GDP? Well, we already really know the answer - it&#39;s 10 cans of Budweiser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real GDP is measured in &quot;real units&quot;. That&#39;s obvious in this example, because the real units are obvious - cans of Bud. To do this more formally, we find real GDP by dividing nominal GDP by a price index. In this case, the price index is easy to figure out. It&#39;s \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 per can of Bud. So real GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;10/\$1 per can of Bud = 10 cans of Bud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One confusion with real GDP is that the BEA and economic textbooks insist on talking about it in terms of dollars. That is because the price index they use is not something like &quot;\&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 per can&quot;, but is something like &quot;\\inline&quot;/&gt;1.37 per \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 of output in 2005&quot;. So real GDP is\inline&quot;/&gt;10/&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1.37 per 2005 dollar = 7.3 units of 2005 dollars, which would be reported as &quot;\\inline&quot;/&gt;7.3 (2005 dollars).&quot; But despite being reported in terms of dollars, real GDP has nothing to do with money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sometimes think that we should save our effort at coming up with good price indices, and just use something like the price of a can of Bud, or a pair of Levi 501 jeans, as the price deflator in national accounts. Because then real GDP would be reported in real, tangible units, and would save us from confusing it with a nominal number. For example, if the price of a can of Bud was \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.50, then real GDP in the US for 2014 would be \\inline&quot;/&gt;17,615 billion/ &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.50 per can on Bud = 35,230 cans of Bud. Nominal GDP through Q3 2015 is \\inline&quot;/&gt;18,060, so that&#39;s real GDP of 36,120 cans of Bud, a 2.5% increase in real GDP from 2014. I&#39;m laboring this point because when it comes to explaining how growth works, this confusion between nominal and real concepts becomes a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s go back to our simple 10-can economy, with a price per can of \$1, and see how growth works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Growth through expanding production of existing products:&lt;/b&gt; This is the easiest to explain. Something happens at Anheuser-Busch that lets them produce even more cans of Bud with their given inputs. Perhaps they water it down even more than it already is. Whatever the reason, the economy produces 12 cans of Bud this year. We &lt;i&gt;know&lt;/i&gt; that real GDP went up, from 10 cans to 12 cans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&#39;s walk through how to do this calculation using nominal GDP and a price index. Think of two possibilities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nominal GDP stays constant.&lt;/b&gt; That is, nominal GDP is still \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10. Then it &lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt; be that the price of a Bud fell to \\inline&quot;/&gt;0.83. The supply curve of Bud shifted out, and hence the quantity of Bud went up and the price of Bud went down. Real GDP is \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10/\\inline&quot;/&gt;0.83 per can = 12 cans of Bud. For the given flow of money through the economy - &lt;i&gt;which does not have any necessary relationship to real GDP&lt;/i&gt; - the price of a can of Bud must adjust to make supply equal demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The price of Bud stays constant.&lt;/b&gt; Let each can still be \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1. The it &lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt; be that nominal GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;12, and real GDP is \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?12/\\inline&quot;/&gt;1 per can = 12 cans of Bud. Here, the supply curve of Bud has shifted out, but apparently the demand curve shifted out as well, leaving the price unchanged and the quantity higher. Why would this happen? Who knows, and who cares. It&#39;s possible. For a given flow of money through the economy, the price of a can of Bud must adjust to make supply equal to demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it is irrelevant whether nominal GDP goes up or stays constant (it could even fall). Whether nominal GDP rises or not is &lt;i&gt;completely irrelevant&lt;/i&gt; to whether real GDP goes up. If we could observe the real quantity of cans consumed, we wouldn&#39;t need nominal GDP at all. But we don&#39;t actually observe the number of cans of Bud consumed. All we observe is nominal GDP and the price of a can of Bud. So when the BEA reports a nominal GDP of \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10, and a price of \\inline&quot;/&gt;0.83 per can, we divide and infer that real GDP is 12 cans of Bud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your question now is where people get the &quot;extra money&quot; to afford 12 cans of Bud when their price stays at \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1, take a moment to meditate on the equation\inline&quot;/&gt;MV = PY$. We&#39;ll come back to that in a few paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Growth through addition of new products:&lt;/b&gt; This one will stretch the mind a little more, but the same principles are going to hold. Rather than Bud watering down their beer even further, we&#39;re going to introduce a new beer into the market. Someone - and God bless them - invents &lt;a href=&quot;https://realalebrewing.com/beers/coffee-porter/?age-verified=a3ffaebbbf&quot;&gt;Real Ale Coffee Porter&lt;/a&gt;. In response, people with functioning taste buds buy 5 cans of Coffee Porter, and everyone else still buys 5 cans of Bud. So we&#39;ve still only got 10 cans of beer being sold. Is this economic growth, meaning that real GDP is higher?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It depends on relative prices. If those cans of Coffee Porter are more expensive than cans of Bud, then this represents real economic growth. Why? Because if the relative price of Coffee Porter is higher than that of Bud, then the relative marginal utility of Coffee Porter is higher than that of Bud. Assuming that utility for both has typical properties (declining MU), then we know the MU of the 5th can of Bud is higher than the 10th can. And since Coffee Porter has a higher MU than that, it follows that we are better off in utility terms. More intuitively, if we &lt;i&gt;weren&#39;t&lt;/i&gt; better off, then why were we willing to substitute away from Bud even though Coffee Porter costs more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which suggests that if Coffee Porter and Bud sold for the same amount, then we aren&#39;t any better off. In this case it&#39;s a perfect substitute, and the choice of 5 of each is just random. It&#39;s the difference in relative prices that a new product introduces that defines it&#39;s contribution of real growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So eocnomic growth is just about things getting more expensive? No. Note that I didn&#39;t say anything about the absolute price of Bud or Coffee Porter - because that is irrelevant for real GDP. So long as Coffee Porter is more expensive &lt;i&gt;than Bud&lt;/i&gt;, we&#39;ve experienced real growth. That holds if Porter costs \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?2 to Bud&#39;s \\inline&quot;/&gt;1, or \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?20 to Bud&#39;s \\inline&quot;/&gt;10, or \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.02 to Bud&#39;s \\inline&quot;/&gt;0.01.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we&#39;ve established that there is a relative price difference, then the same questions about nominal GDP from before come up. Let&#39;s say that we observe that Coffee Porter costs twice as much as Bud. How do we calculate real GDP?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nominal GDP stays constant.&lt;/b&gt; It must be that Bud costs \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.67, and the porter is \\inline&quot;/&gt;1.33, so nominal GDP is \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10 (multiply it out and you can see it). What is real GDP in this case? Sticking with our standard of using the price of Bud, real GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;10/\$0.67 per can of Bud = 15 cans of Bud. It is &lt;i&gt;as if&lt;/i&gt; our economy produced 15 cans of Bud, where before it only produced 10. There is real GDP growth due to the introduction of Coffee Porter - even though all Coffee Porter does is replace consumption of Bud and total beer drinking stays constant at 10 cans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The price of Bud stays constant.&lt;/b&gt; If Bud still costs \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1, then the porter is \\inline&quot;/&gt;2. So nominal GDP is \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?15 (again, just multiply it out). What is real GDP? \\inline&quot;/&gt;15/\$1 per can of Bud = 15 cans of Bud. Real GDP has gone up. It is irrelevant what the nominal price of Bud is, we observe real GDP growth because the introduction of Coffee Porter introduced a relative price difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that if all the BEA reports to me is nominal GDP and the price of Bud, I can infer real GDP regardless of what exactly happens. Our  &quot;Bud-based&quot; measure of real GDP goes up to 15. I don&#39;t actually have to observe the number of cans purchased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example of adding a new product brings up one issue with price indices, which is product replacement. If - as would be logical if people tasted them - the introduction of Coffee Porter completely eliminated Bud from the market, then we cannot calculate real GDP. There will be no price of Bud to divide nominal GDP by. And we can&#39;t just use the price of Coffee Porter, because yesterday all we had was Bud, and there was no price for Coffee Porter. One of the reasons we use more sophisticated price indices (that combine the price of Bud and Coffee Porter in some way) is so that we always have a price index to use. But that sophisticated price index, by putting things in &quot;2005 dollars&quot; or something like that, creates confusion between real GDP and nominal GDP. Always think of real GDP as being &quot;cans of Bud&quot;, rather than in dollar terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, If you are still wondering where people get the &quot;extra money&quot; to buy the Coffee Porter in this example, then the next section is for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Where does the extra money come from?&lt;/b&gt; Nowhere. There is no extra money. Nominal GDP is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; a measure of &quot;how much money we have&quot;. Nominal GDP is the flow of dollars through the economy. The stock of money is, well, a stock. In all the examples above, what is the stock of money? You can&#39;t answer that question, because I never said anything about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s say that this economy has a stock of 4 one-dollar bills. Here&#39;s the transactions flow in this economy in the initial stage, with only 10 can of Bud consumed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person A starts with the \$4. (Nominal GDP is zero)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person A buys 4 Buds for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person B. (Nominal GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person B buys 4 Buds for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person C. (Nominal GDP is now \\inline&quot;/&gt;8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person C buys 2 Buds for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?2 from person D. (Nominal GDP is now \\inline&quot;/&gt;10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person D ends up with \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?2 and person C with\inline&quot;/&gt;2. (Final nominal GDP is \$10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then next period we start again, only now C and D hold the money stock. The money stock is always \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4, and it gets turned over and over, resulting in \\inline&quot;/&gt;10 of nominal transactions, or GDP. (No, it doesn&#39;t matter that the circle isn&#39;t closed here, with different people ending up with the actual dollars.) Real GDP is 10 cans of Bud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we have the case where Coffee Porter gets introduced, things look like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person A starts with the \$4. (Nominal GDP is zero)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person A buys 2 Porters for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person B. (Nominal GDP is \\inline&quot;/&gt;4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person B buys 4 Buds for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person C. (Nominal GDP is now \\inline&quot;/&gt;8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person C buys 2 Porters for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 from person D. (Nominal GDP is now \\inline&quot;/&gt;12)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person D buys 1 Bud for \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 and 1 porter for \\inline&quot;/&gt;2 from person E. (Nominal GDP is now \$15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Person D ends up with \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 and person E with \\inline&quot;/&gt;3. (Final nominal GDP is \$15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No &quot;new money&quot; is necessary. Real GDP is 15 cans of Bud. The same \&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4 gets recycled over and over again, this time used to purchase both Buds and Porters. Different people end up with money stock at the end. We could easily write out an example where the growth occurred because of just an increase in the number of Buds. And if you prefer that nominal GDP not increase, you can easily go back and work out the same set of transactions, lower the absolute prices, and get nominal GDP to come out to exactly \\inline&quot;/&gt;10. And yes, I made up these examples. But I just need to show you that it is possible to get economic growth even though there is no new money in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic growth occurs either because we produce more of existing things, or because we introduce new things that that are more valuable than the old things we produced - which shows up in &lt;i&gt;relative&lt;/i&gt; price differences. The level of absolute prices is irrelevant. The level of nominal spending is irrelevant. The stock of money is irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any modern economy, it is effectively impossible for there to be &quot;not enough money&quot; to let growth occur. The economy as a whole can always turn over the money stock faster to allow for the extra transactions if necessary. Whether that turnover involves &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt;, and means that &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt; can afford to buy some Coffee Porter, is a different question, and involves your own productivity and/or ownership of a Bud- or Coffee Porter-producing machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 20:06:18 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
