<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Growth Economics Blog</title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description>Dietrich Vollrath Economic Growth Blog</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 12:47:58 -0600</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>The returns to societal capital</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Society-Dividend/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Society-Dividend/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Brad DeLong had a &lt;a href=&quot;http://equitablegrowth.org/equitablog/regional-policy-and-distributional-policy-in-a-world-where-people-want-to-ignore-the-value-and-contribution-of-knowledge-and-network-based-increasing-returns/&quot;&gt;recent post&lt;/a&gt; that contained a number of ideas regarding how we view redistribution in a market economy. I picked up on some comments he made towards the end of that post, in which he points out that much of our prosperity comes from a stock of societal capital that we unknowingly rely on every day. And because that societal capital is unseen and uncompensated, we are all in some way overpaid for what we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he says societal capital, I think of it in two broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt;: I think this is much of what DeLong has in mind. We are lucky to be in the “trust” or “cooperate” equilibrium in our repeated game of exhanging goods and services. If you like, call it the “stag hunt” equilibrium &lt;a href=&quot;http://worthwhile.typepad.com/worthwhile_canadian_initi/2016/12/staghunt-and-the-irs.html&quot;&gt;Nick Rowe&lt;/a&gt; talks about. Regardless, we benefit from the decisions of our ancestors to play this equilibrium, so that it is the default. If you want to say this is due to some institutions, or culture, or pure luck, it doesn’t matter. We’ve found our way to the trust equilibrium, and benfit from that immensely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scale&lt;/strong&gt;: He doesn’t mention this explicitly, but I think it is as relevant as trust. Scale influences the potential profits from innovations, and so is crucial to growth. Bigger market, more profits, more incentives to innovate. But scale is not the same thing as trust, or institutions, or culture. If you doubt that, ask yourself why no firm is spending millions to get into New Zealand, paragon of free market institutions, but they are falling all over themselves to do business in China. Living in the US, or EU, or China, is to reap the benefits of living with scale.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heart of DeLong’s point is that neither trust nor scale are things that are owned by any firm or individual. You could say that we inherited them from our ancestors, or you could say these are emergent properties, or you could say that they are designed by the institutions we choose for ourselves. Regardless, trust and scale are “ideas” in the broadest sense, and are inputs into the production process in that trust and scale mean our set of rival inputs (labor, capital) can produce more with them than without.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is it that scale and trust mean we are overpaid? Here I’ll borrow an idea from DeLong, and “hoist one from the archives” of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/what-assumptions-matter-for-growth-theory/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just to refresh, a production function tells us that output is determined by some combination of non-rival inputs and rival inputs. Non-rival inputs are things like ideas that can be used by many firms or people at once without limiting the use by others. Think of blueprints. Rival inputs are things that can only be used by one person or firm at a time. Think of nails. The income earned by both rival and non-rival inputs has to add up to total output. Okay, given all that setup, here are three statements that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Output is constant returns to scale in &lt;em&gt;rival&lt;/em&gt; inputs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Non-rival inputs receive some portion of output&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Rival inputs receive output equal to their marginal product&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pick two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas of trust and scale are non-rival inputs to production. If we assume that output is constant returns to scale in rival inputs (point 1), then we have to pick wither 2 or 3. As neither trust nor scale receive payments, we have essentially chosen 3. And in that sense DeLong means that rival inputs (our labor and our capital) are overpaid. We are not compensating anyone for the trust and scale that we inherited or created as a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first aside is that in my set-up choosing 3 implies that rival inputs earn their marginal products, and DeLong is saying that our labor is earning &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than its marginal product. I don’t think this is actually a meaningful difference. DeLong is saying that labor is overpaid because it earns returns that could be going to ideas like trust and scale. Whether we say that what it earns is the marginal product or not is irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second aside is that it isn’t really as stark as saying we chose option 3. Some ideas - the patent for an iPhone, the trademark on Coca-Cola - are protected and receive compensation. All I’m saying here is that scale and trust are ideas that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; receiving compensation, and in that sense rival inputs like labor are overpaid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third aside is you may be wondering how the increasing returns to scale that DeLong mentions fits in here. Note that point 1 only says production is constant returns to scale in rival inputs (labor and capital). In terms of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; inputs (labor, capital, and ideas) production is increasing returns to scale. If I doubled all of them, output would more than double.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the main story. What DeLong does with this is to provide what I found to be a unique justification for the public sector. That is, taxes are a way of collecting the royalties on trust and scale that we inherited and/or create ourselves. Taxes are the rents to idea of playing “cooperate” or having scale. And the proper use of those rents, if I am reading him correctly, is in ensuring that those endowments are perpetuated and handed off to our own children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to perpetuate trust and scale? Part of it, I think, is in providing the insurance against the fluctuations that are the necessary corrollary of the markets we create with trust and scale. Those fluctuations play havoc with local communities and ways of life, a la Polyani. Hence individuals or communities may be tempted to defect from the cooperate/trust equilibria, or hive themselves off on their own and reduce the scale of the economy. If we spend the rents of trust and scale supporting those communities, we can incent them to stay in the good equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue with this, as DeLong spends most of his post working out, is that simply handing out those rents to people creates issues for everyone involved. Those paying taxes feel that they are being taken as suckers. Those receiving the rents - the members of disrupted communities - feel like deadbeats. No one wants to be in either of those positions. We have built-in preferences that make deviation from trust and scale look attractive. Which is why being in the good equilibrium is such a delicate thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How then, do you justify the collection of the rents that, arguably, rightfully belong to all of us, and ensure that we pass on the trust and scale necessary for prosperity to the next generation? And do so in a way that is palatable to all parties?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea is that you can use the idea of rents or royalties as a positive justifcation of taxation. We are collecting on the royalties due to us as a citizenry for our trust and scale, the same way that Apple collects royalties due to them as a designer of useful touchscreen emoji delivery machines. In this concept, taxation is not theft, or a necessary evil, but rather the enforcement of our intellectual property rights over trust and scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other end, the distribution of those rents is perhaps more palatable when seen not as a handout (which makes people feel like a deadbeat) but as something like a dividend on shared ownership of an asset. I feel like this would be one way to think of how a universal basic income could be framed - everyone is getting their share of the collective dividend payment due to the owners of the “ideas” of trust and scale. It is a sign of ownership, not dependence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Can you do historical counter-factuals?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Causality/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Causality/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warning: rank speculation lies ahead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I fell hopelessly behind in an on-going Twitter-storm surrounding history and economics, and how the two fields think of causality and counterfactuals. The culprits filling up my notifications page included &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pseudoerasmus&quot;&gt;Pseudoerasmus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/leah_boustan&quot;&gt;Leah Platt Boustan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RichardALJones&quot;&gt;Richard Jones&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kevinhorourke&quot;&gt;Kevin O’Rourke&lt;/a&gt;. This is my uber-Tweet response, and I’m going to leave the 140 character limit in the dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The origin of the Twittering was an article in the Chronicle of Higher Education by Marc Parry that on a battle between economists and historians. He speaks with historian Eric Foner, and says “Foner considers counterfactuals absurd. A historian’s job is not to speculate about alternative universes, he says. It’s to figure out what happened and why.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the record, the context of the article is about the debate between economists and historians on the role of slavery in supporting capitalism, with (some) historians implying capitalism was impossible without slavery and (some) economists responding that capitalism would have proceeded just fine without it. You can see a little summary in the Economist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/blogs/freeexchange/2016/12/pain-past&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What appeared to get people going on Twitter was the idea that Foner “considers counterfactuals absurd”. The response to this is best summarized by the immortal Inigo Montoya: “I do not think that word means what you think it means.” The criticism is that &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; historians do counterfactuals when they suggest that factor X (e.g. slavery) caused Y (e.g. capitalism). By saying X caused Y, you are saying that if X failed to exist/happen - which would be counter to the facts of history - Y would not have existing/happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are the economists (many of them) so comfortable with, and happy to think about, counterfactuals? And why are historians (some of them) not happy with the concept? My proposal here is that the economists approach these questions from the perspective of a standard empirical setting with lots of observations, and they extend that to thinking about history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of a big cross-sectional dataset on individuals, let’s say with information on wages, education, and the like. It also has a dummy variable for gender: 0 for males, 1 for females. You could run a regression of (log) wages on years of education, age, lots of other control variables, and the gender dummy variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An economist trained in empirics will look at this and say that the gender dummy variable indicates the counter-factual effect of gender on wages. That is, if you could take a man, and counter-factually make them a woman while holding everything else about them the same, how much would their wage fall? Or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this is of course ridiculous as an actual policy change. You cannot simply flip someone’s gender, and even if you could, the other variables related to this person would likely change as well. If you could go back and change the gender of a person at birth, they would have almost certainly have had different education experiences, different job experiences, different health outcomes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with a large cross-sectional dataset, we could page through the data and find a woman with the same, or very similar characteristics, to the man we started looking at. And then we could just compare the man to the woman with similar characteristics, and look at their wage difference. That is plausible in an intuitive way. And when economists think of doing a counter-factual, this plausible comparison is what they often have in mind. Or at least, this is what empirical training has embedded in their brains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we take that kind of counter-factual to historical studies, where the plausible intuitive way doesn’t make sense. Studying slavery and capitalism, for example, we do not have thousands of different societies or cultures to page through to find one that looks &lt;em&gt;almost exactly&lt;/em&gt; like the Anglo-American industrializing societies, but doesn’t have slavery. We cannot compare like to like, and do the plausible counter-factual comparison like we did with gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only have the more dramatic counter-factual. What if we took the observed Anglo-American industrializing societies and somehow “switched off” slavery, just like taking the man in the wage data and “switching” his gender to female. The experience and implications of slavery are entwined with every other aspect of the industrializing societies, and pulling it out would entail massive shocks to all these other aspects. “Doing the counterfactual” looks like a big mess, and perhaps this is what Foner is objecting to because it sounds like writing some sort of alternative history novel. And it would be pure speculation to write such a novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would, but this is a second point at which concepts drawn from large dataset empirics make economists more comfortable with counter-factuals. We don’t have to think about writing down an alternative history novel. We need to think about lots and lots of possible novels in which slavery did not exist, and lots and lots in which it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And based on those thousands of alternative history novels, is it true that when slavery remains present into the 1800’s, that capitalism develops? And is it true that when slavery fails to persist (or maybe never really exists?) that capitalism fails to develop? We wouldn’t even have to be strict about the relationship between one and the other, we could ask if - statistically speaking - alternative histories without slavery tended to be without capitalism, and alternative histories with slavery tended to have capitalism. When economists are talking about historical counterfactuals, I think this is what they have in mind. At least, it is what I have in mind to make sense of claims like “slavery was necessary for capitalism”, or any claim that “X was necessary for Y”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The claim that slavery was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; necessary for capitalism is not meant to be an iron-clad statement of truth. At least I hope that those who make the claim do not mean it this way, because that would be wrong. What it does mean is that of all the alternative histories we could have gotten, the ones without slavery most likely would still have gotten capitalism anyway. And the proposed explanations for that - Indian and Egyptian supply responses, alternative labor arrangements in the US South - are arguments about the probability of capitalism occurring in those thousands of alternative histories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see why this can be frustrating to those coming at this from the history side of things. This seems to reduce historical work, which is in part the patient documentation of the particular, to a sideline. How could you possibly conceive of thousands of different alternative histories, when we as yet know so little about this one? The economist’s approach appears dismissive. Much the same way that telling someone who failed to find a good job after college, and is getting by working part-time at Pizza Hut, that their wages are approximately 50% higher in expectation because of their degree. Guess your particular error term draw just sucked. ¯_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, one advantage of thinking explicitly about this in terms of many-alternative-histories is that you can avoid falling into arguements about mono-causality. If you say that slavery is necessary for capitalism, and then say that in a counterfactual history without slavery capitalism would not have existed, you a careening perilously close to saying that slavery was the &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; cause of capitalism. You might try to swerve to avoid this by saying that speculating about that counterfactuals is silly in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you think about many alternative histories, it is much easier to avoid making mono-causal statements. Saying, “If we compared histories with slavery and without slavery, I believe that a statistically significant difference would exist between them in the appearance of capitalism” is wishy-washy, poor writing, and not exactly attention-getting. But it is clear that slavery is not the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; possible cause of capitalism, because you are allowing for the idea that some non-slave histories could have found their way to capitalism anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot get my head around asking “why”, as Foner does, without being able to undertake any kind of counter-factual exercise, whether in the data or in my head. But perhaps the concept of thinking in terms of many-alternative-histories, rather than feeling you must commit to a single one, is a way of making the idea of counterfactuals more palatable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growth links of interest</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Links-1612/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Links-1612/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick post to vent some of the pressure from my reading list before it explodes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Greg Ip has an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/the-economys-hidden-problem-were-out-of-big-ideas-1481042066&quot;&gt;extensive piece&lt;/a&gt; in the WSJ on being “out of big ideas”. One quality of this article is that it gives some plausible ideas for &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the pace of innovation may have slowed down in some areas. We may be plowing resources into things like medical research that have apparently small returns in terms of years of life saved. But, given our relative wealth, this may be entirely optimal. Adding a week to a cancer victims life may be worth more than inventing a better dishwasher. One quibble. Ip states early on that despite historically high number of scientists and engineers, “None of this has translated into meaningful advances in Americans’ standard of living.” We don’t know that. It may not appear to have generated advances in the growth rate of GDP per capita, GDP per capita need not be the same thing as meaningful advances in standards of living.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the benefits of Twitter (yes, they exist) is following very smart people as they argue a point. I fell behind during an on-going discussion of Robert Allen’s concept of a “high-wage economy” in England driving the adoption of machines leading to the industrial revolution. &lt;a href=&quot;https://notesonliberty.com/2016/12/07/the-high-wage-economy-hypothesis/&quot;&gt;Vincent Geloso&lt;/a&gt; did the Lord’s work in providing a fair summary of Allen’s position and some of the associated Twitter-commentary, and then catches you up on the possible holes in Allen’s argument. As a place to start reading about Allen’s hypothesis, this is quite nice, and provides many links to research questioning the assumptions behind Allen’s ideas. Then follow it up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://pseudoerasmus.com/2016/12/01/allen/&quot;&gt;Pseudoerasmus’&lt;/a&gt; post on the same subject, and with a similar, honest, approach.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT is starting a “micro-masters” &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.mit.edu/2016/mitx-micromasters-program-development-economics-masters-degree-1205&quot;&gt;program in development&lt;/a&gt;. Low-cost enrollment on-line for students in developing countries, with the possibility for exceptional students being offered physical positions at MIT. As a means of expanding the availability of education, this is great. As a way of tightening the net that excellent students may slip through, it is even better. I do admissions for the PhD program at UH, and I am sure that I have let slip students who would be incredible economists. But their applications just cannot show that. Giving students a low-cost way of signalling their quality ahead of time is the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Piketty, Saez, Zucman machine rolls on, with their &lt;a href=&quot;http://equitablegrowth.org/research-analysis/economic-growth-in-the-united-states-a-tale-of-two-countries/&quot;&gt;new paper&lt;/a&gt; trying to reconcile national income accounts (GDP, etc..) with individual wealth/income distribution data. If you are reading this blog, you likely already have perused the paper or summaries based on it. It’s stark in how the fortunes of various percentiles of the income distribution have fared over time. What I also would like to applaud these authors for is writing papers that are about simple accounting. This the kind of economic research that you could explain to your neighbor in about 20 minutes, and that should be seen as a feature, not a bug.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://voxeu.org/article/production-fragmentation-and-global-trade-slowdown&quot;&gt;Timmer, Los, Stehrer, De Vries&lt;/a&gt; have a nice post of their current research regarding the change in trade over the last 15 years. In short, if I’m getting this right, the surge in trade from 2000-2008 was in large part due to the increasing fragmentation of production in goods - lots of parts coming from lots of different countries - and then this trend stopped after the crisis in 2008. Trade growth is slowing down because production is not increasing the number of sources for parts any more, to again over-simplify. Some of this slowdown in fragmenting of production appears due to demand effects, as countries (incl. China) shift demand towards goods (or services) that use fewer differentiated parts as inputs. Baumol strikes again?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Useless, but fun. Selected &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freepatentsonline.com/crazy.html&quot;&gt;stupid patents&lt;/a&gt; that have actually been granted.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href=&quot;http://voxeu.org/article/piketty-s-housing-capital-results-new-us-facts&quot;&gt;piece of evidence&lt;/a&gt; that much of the increase in capital’s share of income over time is due to housing. Gianni La Cava narrows it down further to an increase in the share of income going to owner-occupied housing. Now, this income is imputed from the value of housing, so La Cava is finding that the run-up in the value of the housing stock is creating a noticeable shift in the distribution of income towards capital. Here’s a good question, then, which I may try to tackle at some point. What is the capital/labor split of income &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; housing - or any other imputed value - included? Is the labor share shrinking as well?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A nice &lt;a href=&quot;https://timeline.com/robots-have-been-about-to-take-all-the-jobs-for-more-than-200-years-5c9c08a2f41d#.6kz8o2jlp&quot;&gt;timeline&lt;/a&gt; of various reporting on the possibility that machines will steal all the jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Would you pay to save a job?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Trade/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Trade/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mike Konczal has a nice &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@rortybomb/learning-from-trump-in-retrospect-dce431b23ed0#.70zws6ugy&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about how important it is to distinguish “jobs” from “the economy”, and how Trump used that to his advantage. Noah Smith had a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-12-02/a-job-is-more-than-a-paycheck&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt; of the idea that a job is “more than a paycheck”. In my head, this is a complement to the arguments that Dani Rodrik has been making for years, as in his 1997 book &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2gzJqH4&quot;&gt;Has Globalization Gone too Far?&lt;/a&gt;. In economist terms, the easiest way to say this is that having a job actually enters the utility function separately from the real wage it generates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have one idea to add to this, which is that even the “winners” of trade (or technological shocks) are unhappy about other people losing their jobs. If you like, the job status of others has an effect on the utility function of those &lt;em&gt;with jobs&lt;/em&gt;. And it means they are willing to trade off some other source of utility (real wages) in order to give those people jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’m not sure I’m explaining this terribly well, let me give you an example of a choice I posed to a number of “regular people” in my neighborhood, and during the after-game-beer-drinking phase of my hockey league. I’ve been doing this for a year or two, but recent events have made the responses more salient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not claiming that I had some sort of insight a few years ago. This all started because of a random conversation with Kenny, one of the guys in my hockey league, which led to him saying that he’d “absolutely” pay $100 more for a TV if it meant more American workers didn’t have to go on welfare. After that, I started posing the same kind of question to others in an ad hoc manner. I realize that this all has a very David Brooks-ish bullshit man-on-the-street vibe. Feel free to discount accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the essence of the choice I posed to people regarding a hypothetical trade deal (I typically didn’t use such precise numbers, but this gives you a concrete idea of what I was asking):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option A&lt;/strong&gt;. With the trade deal, let’s say that the income of a winner - people who stay employed - is 1000. The price index with trade is 0.8. Let’s say there are four winners for every loser - the ones who lose jobs - but we organize a redistribution of the gains from trade to make sure the losers are compensated. We tax every winner 200, and use that to give every loser 800. The winners, after their tax of 200, are also making 800. With an price index of 0.8, every person - winners and losers - has a real wage of 800/0.8 = 1000.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option B&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t do the trade deal. Everyone is still employed, but their income is 700, which is lower than what a winner makes under the trade deal, and means that in aggregate, total income is lower than with the trade deal. Also, the price index is higher without trade, because we don’t get cheap imports. So let the price index be 1, and every person has a real wage of 700/1 = 700.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which option would you choose? The pure economist answer is A, because obviously everyone is better off in terms of real consumption, with a real wage of 1000 versus 700. Noah’s post was about how job losers would probably prefer B. Most people would rather take the lower real wage of 700 with an actual job, versus a transfer with a real value of 1000. If you want to call this a form of money illusion, fine, but that doesn’t make it wrong. It is easy to say that their utility function puts more weight on income that is received from working versus income received as a hand out. It is not a stretch to get your head around this. I have spent years trying to instill this &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; preference set into my kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was more interesting in posing this question to various people I knew was the response of “winners”. Most of the time, I told people that they should imagine that they would be a “winner” under the deal. And for the most part, the people I was talking to were already winners with respect to trade, or were professionals relatively immune from the effects (e.g. doctors or lawyers). Regardless, &lt;em&gt;even winners preferred B&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would potential winners prefer B? Anecdotally, they don’t like the idea of having to hand over some of their own wages to subsidize people who are &lt;em&gt;not working&lt;/em&gt;. They know these people lost their jobs due to the trade deal or technological change, and a number of people I spoke with said they would be in favor of some kind of subsidy for the losers, but only for a very limited time. But it doesn’t seem fair to them that the job losers don’t have to do &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;, even if it wasn’t the job losers fault in the first place. People care about the job status of others. This is, I would venture, some of the reason that individuals care about their &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; job status in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hypothetical winners also tend to express a sort of endowment effect. Once you pay them 1000, it is much more tangible to them that they are giving up some of “their” money to subsidize job losers. On the other hand, under plan B they pay the subsidy implicitly through higher prices and lower nominal wages, and there is no endowment effect for them. And the people I asked this question are completely aware, like Kenny, of the fact that they are paying a subsidy through higher prices. The winners are for redistribution, but they care a lot about how that redistibution takes place. Again, this sounds like money illusion, but that doesn’t make it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the answers I got are in line with what Konczal, Smith, and Rodrik (and others) have said before about the value of jobs versus GDP. I’d suggest that even those with secure employment have preferences that would lead them to support jobs &lt;em&gt;for others&lt;/em&gt; at the cost of some GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean we should scrap every trade deal? No. The implication of my little study is that people are willing to trade off &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of the gains from trade to keep more people employed. That doesn’t mean they are willing to trade off &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the gains from trade. If Option B were to scrap all trade deals and lower the real wage of everyone to 200, rather than 700, you would probably get a different answer from both potential winners and losers. And given the embedded nature of imports in supply chains, you could well make the case that the losses would be astronomical, and thus not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other policies relating to job creation would face the same questions. Noah brought up the idea of incentives for long-term contracts, and noted the worry that you can take this too far. If you incentivize long-term contracts, do you gum up the labor market so much that new firms cannot afford to get stated or grow, and old ones cannot afford to shut down? Or do you end up getting the same issues we have now with trade; a class of “winners” that get long-term contracts and a class of “losers” that do not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of doing economics, I’m not sold that building the concept of this job preference into models would amount to much more than slapping some math around. I think our job is a little more humble. Be really clear about the economic costs and benefits of Options A and B on things like real wages and GDP that we have some hope of actually quantifying, and then let people decide if they are willing to pay those costs to save jobs or not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Employment Going South. Literally.</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Jobs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Jobs/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From 1990 to 2015, the US economy as a whole increased employment by about 30 million (30,056,664 according to the BLS). Employment in 1990 was 118,900,000, so that meant that there was a roughly 25% increase in employment over that 25 year period, with a little more than 1 million jobs added per year, on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to surprise anyone by saying that these 30 million jobs were not spread equally across the entire US. What I didn’t have a good sense of, personally, was how disparate the change in employment was across the US. This post is just some documentation about the absolute size of the change in job distribution across the US. I don’t know that I have a broader point, but I don’t really internalize the information until I play with it, so this is me trying to internalize the information on shifts in jobs within the US over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BLS provides county-level employment totals for 1990-2015, hence the time frame I’m looking at. And I can calculate the change in total employment in that 25 year period for each county. I could use the size of the labor force instead (employed plus unemployed) but the patterns I’m going to show you here don’t change appreciably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/county_loss.png&quot; alt=&quot;Binary job gain loss&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, of the 3,133 counties for which I have data, 909 of them &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; jobs in absolute terms from 1990 to 2015. The map highlights those 909 counties in pink. The location of these counties are not terribly surprising, although I don’t think I realized how much upstate New York’s employment numbers had dropped over time. You can see the smudge of pink in coal country of West Virginia and Kentucky, along with a big set of job-losing counties in the deep, deep south of Mississippi, northern Louisiana, and southern Arkansas. Downstate Illinois and a swath across the Great Plains also saw absolute declines in the number of employees over 25 years. In total, those counties saw employment fall by 1,471,436 jobs in this period, from a base of about 19.5 million jobs to just over 18 million jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the 909 counties that lost jobs in absolute terms, a number of counties lost jobs in relative terms. What I mean by relative loss is as follows. Total employment in the US grew by 25% from 1990 to 2015. If the distribution of jobs across counties stayed fixed at the 1990 distribution, then all counties should have seen job growth of 25% as well. A county that had job growth below 25% then saw a relative decline in employment compared to the rest of the country, and one with job growth above 25% saw a relative increase in emploment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 2,188 counties that saw a &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; decline in employment over this period, or roughly two-thirds of the counties in the US, and includes the 909 counties with absolute losses. Those counties started with roughly 73 million jobs, and finished with 78.4 million in 2015, an increase of about 5.4 million jobs, or about 7.4%. If those counties had instead grown at 25%, like the US as a whole, they would have had about 91 million jobs, an increase of 18 million jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 2,188 counties fell about 13 million jobs “short” of what we’d expect given the 1990 distribution of jobs. Which means that jobs moved out of those 2,188 counties, and moved into the other 944 counties that gained in &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those 944 counties started with 45.5 million jobs in 1990, and ended in 2015 with 70.5 million jobs, for a gain of about 25 million jobs, which is a percent gain of 55%. The 944 counties that gained in relative terms over this period gained 13 million &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; jobs than we would expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/county_scale.png&quot; alt=&quot;Relative job bins&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map here plots the relative job change, in number of jobs, for each county in the US over this period. I didn’t include the legend because it got too busy, and shrinking it down made it unreadable. The darker green the county, the more jobs, in relative terms, that it gained over this period. The darker the pink/red the county, the more jobs, in relative terms, that it lost over this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harris county (Houston), where I live, is a dark green smudge down on the Gulf Coast of Texas. It gained 663,757 jobs over 1990-2015. That is 291,540 more jobs than you would have guessed based on the 1990 distribution of employment, the relative job change. Other counties with big relative gains include Maricopa County, AZ (Phoenix) with 566,974 extra jobs, Clark County, NV (Vegas) with 477,942 extra jobs, and Riverside County, CA (greater LA) with 341,434 extra jobs. You’ll also see dark green counties in North Carolina (Charlotte and Raleigh), Texas (Dallas, San Antonia, Austin), Colorado (Denver), and Florida (basically everything but the panhandle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest relative losers in job terms are generally older cities. LA County came in 628,796 jobs under what you would have thought - it gained only 441,710 jobs but we would have guessed it should have gained over 1 million based on the distribution in 1990. Cook County, IL (Chicago) lost 558,190 jobs in relative terms. Wayne County, MI (Detroit) lost 378,043 jobs in relative terms. Cuyahoga County, OH (Cleveland) lost 225,300 in relative terms. Other big relative losses happened in Philadelphia, Milwaukee, Pittsburgh, St. Louis, Baltimore, Hartford, and big swaths of upstate New York (Buffalo and Rochester, mainly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These big losses are dominated by big cities because they start with big populations. We can look instead at scaled relative change of jobs. That is, take the relative change in jobs (e.g. -225,300 relative jobs lost in Cuyahoga County) and divide by the initial level of jobs in that county in 1990 (e.g. 642,367 in Cuyahoga County) for a scaled loss (e.g. -0.35 for Cuyahoga).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/county_perc.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scaled changes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map shows these scaled changes, and the message is similar to before. It was relative loss in the Upper Midwest, Northeast, and some core parts of the South and relative gains in very concentrated urban areas that generally lie in the Sunbelt, plus Denver. So it is not only&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I’m not claiming that this is some kind of revelation here. The movement of population, and hence jobs, from the Northeast/Midwest to the Sunbelt is well known. What I found interesting was putting some tangible numbers of the shift. The little counter-factual I’m doing here is not very rigorous; there is no particular reason to believe that the 1990 distribution is the “right” distribution of jobs to compare against. But the 1990 distribution does have the feature of being prior to NAFTA and prior to China’s accession to the WTO, both of which are at times cited as sources of manufacturing job losses in the upper Midwest and Northeast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of the relative job changes, though, indicates that more of the losses have to do with free trade &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the US than free trade &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; of the US. The areas with relative decline lost 13 million jobs compared to the 1990 distribution of jobs. In total the US shed 6 million manufacturing jobs from 1990 to 2015 (18 million to 12 million, roughly). So this relative decline cannot possibly be a function only of manufacturing and international trade in manufactured goods. There is just too much relative movement out of the declining counties to attribute to this. This is a sloppy way of thinking about how this would work counter-factually (I’m ignoring spillovers entirely), but if you magically added 6 million extra jobs to those counties in relative decline, &lt;em&gt;they would still be in relative decline&lt;/em&gt; compared to the Sunbelt in terms of jobs. They’d have 84.4 million jobs (as opposed to 78.4 million), but you’d expect them to have 95.6 million based on the 1990 distribution, so they would still be 11.2 million jobs off the pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breadth of relative loss, though, seems striking, and is the one thing I did not appreciate prior to looking at this data. 909 counties &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; jobs in absolute terms, which is 29% of all counties. Another 1,279 counties, 41% of all counties, gained jobs in absolute terms buy lost in relative terms. 944 counties, 30%, gained in relative terms. Just as many counties gained in relative terms as lost in absolute terms. The winning locations - Houston, Dallas, Atlanta, Miami, Phoenix, Denver, Vegas - won big, but the losing was spread across a wide area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More jobs in 2015 are still located in places in relative decline (78.4 million) than are in places in relative ascent (70.5 million). Of those 78.4 million, 18 million (or about 12% of jobs) are in counties that experienced absolute job losses over the last 25 years. &lt;em&gt;Most&lt;/em&gt; jobs are still in places that look to be losing out to Sunbelt cities over time. To the extent that your local economy plays a role in forming your opinions, this seems relevant, although I am going to stop now before I try to do any amateur political science or sociology.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ethnic fractionalization and growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Ethnic/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Ethnic/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is not a post about Donald Trump or the election, except tangentially. I have thoughts on Trump - so, so many thoughts - but most of them have been said, meaning I will provide little value added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garett Jones did a &lt;a href=&quot;http://economicsdetective.com/2016/07/costs-ethnic-diversity-garett-jones/&quot;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; with The Economics Detective recently on the costs of ethnic diversity. It is particularly worth listening to given that racial identity has re-emerged as a salient element of politics. A quick summary - and the link above includes a nice write-up of relevant sources - would be that diversity within workplaces does not appear to improve outcomes (however those outcomes are measured).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, there is a parallel literature, touched on in the podcast, about ethnic diversity (or fractionalization, as it is termed in that literature) and economic growth. But one has to be careful drawing a bright line between the two literatures. It does not follow that the results for workplace diversity imply the results regarding economic growth. And this is because the growth results, to the extent that you believe they are robust, all operate through political systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here let me walk through some of the core empirical relationships that have been found regarding ethnic fractionalization and economic growth, and then talk about why you need to take care with over-interpreting them. This is not a thorough literature review, and I realize there are other papers in the same vein. What I’m after is characterizing the essential results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baseline-empirics&quot;&gt;Baseline empirics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hks.harvard.edu/fs/pnorris/Acrobat/stm103%20articles/Easterley_Levine_Ethnic_Divisions.pdf&quot;&gt;Easterly and Levine&lt;/a&gt; did one of the first studies of fractionalization and its relationship to economic growth, with a focus on Africa. To measure fractionalization they used a simple index that has become the de facto norm for measuring this kind of thing going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Frac = 1 - \sum_i s_i^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_i\inline&quot;/&gt; is the share of group i in the population of a given area. You can interpret the fractionalization measure as the probability that two random people in an area belong to different groups. If there is only one group, then the summation term is 1, so Frac is zero. If every single person is in a unique group, so there are N groups, then the summation term approaches 1/N, and Frac approaches 1. EL constructed indices like this for a set of countries using data that originally came from Soviet ethnographers. As I’ll mention in more detail below, their index thus depends on choices made by those ethnographers about what constitutes and ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EL then looked at basic growth regressions. That is, they looked at the relationship between the average growth rate of GDP over a long period of time and how that correlated with their measure of fractionalization. In doing this, they controlled for initial GDP per capita and several other characteristics of countries. What they found was that higher fractionalization was associated with lower growth when only basic controls were included. To take the extreme, going from 0 fractionalization to total fractionalization was associated with a growth rate 2 percentage points lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a quick aside, note that this doesn’t mean a permanently lower growth rate. EL are working with a standard growth regression, controlling for initital income. What they are finding is that places with high fractionalization had lower balanced growth paths. In their empirical setting, every country has the same long run growth rate, but highly fractionalized ones will be poorer than homogenous ones. This shows up as a lower growth rate for fractionalized places because they are closer to their balanced growth paths to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EL go on to explore the idea that the reason for fractionlization’s effect on balanced growth paths is due to the interference in public goods provision. Their hypothesis is that fractionalization implies conflicts between groups, which implies an inability or unwillingness to get broad public support for things like education or infrastructure, and this makes them poorer in the long run. And what EL find is that once you control for public goods provision (crudely, using things like the number of telephones per capita) the effect of fractionalization is no longer significant or as large. For EL, this shows that the impact of fractionalization works through the provision of these public goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stronger support for that idea comes from a different Easterly paper. He, with Alesina and Baqir, published &lt;a href=&quot;http://isites.harvard.edu/fs/docs/icb.topic700742.files/Alesina_Baqir_Easterly_Pub_Goods_Ethnic_Division_QJE_114_1999.pdf&quot;&gt;Public Goods and Ethnic Divisions&lt;/a&gt; in 1999. This looked directly at US cities, counties, and metro areas, and the share of government expenditures at those levels being spent on various public goods. They found that higher fractionalization was associated with a lower share of spending on roads (about minus 5%), welfare (minus 5%), and education (minus 10-17%). On the other hand, there was a higher share of spending on police (plus 2-4%) and health services (13-25%). The increased police and health share is not always enough to explain the lower shares in all the other areas of spending, implying that places with high fractionalization have a larger share of local government expenditures on “everything else”. That “everything else” includes debt payments and other poorly classified spending. The authors speculate it could be related to patronage, but there is no way to look at that directly. In terms of actual levels of taxes and spending, there found conflicting results. At the city level, fractionalization is associated with both higher taxes and spending per capita, but at the metro area and county levels fractionalization was associated with &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; taxes but &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; spending per capita. Either way, fractionalization was generally associated with higher spending per capita. And no, that wasn’t simply due to city/metro/county sizes, as this held while controlling for the total population of the city or metro area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the country level, where Alesina, Devleeschauwer, Easterly, Kurlat, and Wacziarg &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.harvard.edu/files/alesina/files/fractionalization.pdf&quot;&gt;extended&lt;/a&gt; increased the amount of data available on a cross-country basis, including ethnic, linguistic, and religious measures of fractionalization. Similar to Easterly and Levine, they find that fractionalization implies a lower steady state growth path. Also similar, this negative effect dissipates as you control for crude measures of public goods spending and government effectiveness. The authors appeal to a similar argument to before: fractionalization makes consensus hard to build, and so public goods do not get provided at a level more homogenous societies can manage. A few correlates of ethnic fractionalization include lower literacy, lower levels of education attainment, and lower indices of democracy and political rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting note to their paper is that &lt;em&gt;religious&lt;/em&gt; fractionalization has almost the exact &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; effects of ethnic and linguistic fractionalization. More religiously heterogenous countries tend to have higher growth paths, more education, and better measure of political rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problems&quot;&gt;Problems?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with a basic measurement issue. The fractionalization index is sensitive to the number of groups you divide everyone up into. That is, if your country has two ethnic groups, then the maximum value of the fractionalization index is 0.5. If your country has 10 ethnic groups, the maximum index is 0.9. That seems to make sense. More groups, more possible fractionalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that the definition of what counts as a group is not a fixed characteristic. If I give people in the US the options of white, black, Asian, Native American, or Other, then I am allowing for 5 groups, and max fractionalization of 0.8. We could double the number of groups to 10 by allowing each racial group to report as either Hispanic or non-Hispanic, and now the max index is 0.9. Or we could sub-divide white into “German-American”, “Irish-American”, and so on, and get ourselves up to like 40 or 50 groups if we really wanted to, and this would automatically drive up the fractionalization index to one. Or we could say f$&amp;amp;# it, and stop tracking racial identity completely, and get a fractionalzation index of zero by definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that the degree of fractionalization is not immutably fixed by arbitrary racial or ethnic groups designed by the Census Bureau. James &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/group/fearon-research/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Ethnic-and-Cultural-Diversity-by-Country.pdf&quot;&gt;Fearon&lt;/a&gt; has an excellent paper addressing the arbitrary nature of building an index of ethnic fractionalization. There is no &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; fractionalization index for any country. The number of ethnic groups tracked in a census or survey may not map to any meaningful political groups. The Hutus and Tutsis in Rwanda were are included in a single ethnic group in the original Soviet data, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to the empirical work, this raises some questions on how to interpret the results. When Alesina, et al, collected their updated measures of fractionalization, they noted that ethnic fractionalization in much of the Americas is based on racial definitions (black versus white), while in Europe and Sub-Saharan Africa ethnic fractionalization is based primarily on languages (think of Switzerland). So the ethnic fractionalization measures are not comparable across countries. What does it mean to compare fractionalization in Belgium (French versus Flemish speakers) with fractionalization in Bolivia (Mestizos versus Aymara versus Quechua)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alesina et al mention that they go out of their way to find the most disaggregated data on ethnic groups possible. That is, they make sure they maximize the number of groups in each country, thus maximizing the measure of fractionalization. This has the virtue of being a consistent strategy, but suffers because it is subject to variation in the level of disaggregation tracked by country, which is an inherently political decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could easily turn all of the empirical results I talked about around in the following way. Places with relatively dysfunctional political systems benefitted from setting ethnic groups against each other, preventing effective opposition. They thus focused on ethnic or linguistic differences, and made sure to track these carefully when they did censuses. It need not even be nefarious. Former colonies who were left with dysfunctional governments may also have inherited a tradition of close ethnic group tracking from their colonizers. Either way, places with dysfunctional governments would to have mechanically high fractionalization indices along ethnic lines. And their dysfunction also leads to poor economic outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don’t forget those results on religious fractionalization, which was associated with better political and economic outcomes. The effect of diversity can go either way, depending on how you define it. If you started measuring fractionalization along as many dimensions as possible - ethnicity, religion, language, home state, favorite Beatle, height, extroversion/introversion - you’d eventually come across some of them that were positively related, and some negatively, to things like public goods spending or growth, just by chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overarching point here is that even taking the studies on workplace diversity seriously, this does not imply that poor political outcomes and/or economic growth are a necessary outcome of ethnic fractionalization. At the political level, ethnic fractionalization and its salience to public policy is a choice variable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GDP, Productivity, and Financial Performance</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Accounting-Profits/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Accounting-Profits/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In my last &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Manufacturing/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, I got upset because people were using measures of productivity as measures of firm or industry financial performance. And as part of that, I made the point that GDP (which is part of measuring productivity) has nothing to do with profits, or financial success in any way. A few people asked me about this, because it wasn’t obvious to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think part of the issue is that lots of people interested in economics are business literate, meaning they understand what is on financial statements, and want to translate those concepts to the economy as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the economy as a whole is not just one big aggregate business. But, you can get some insight into what GDP is actually measuring by building it up from business accounts. So let’s give that a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a stylized example of an income statement you could find from any firm:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Rev - COGS - Exp - Wage - Int - Div - Rent - Dep - Tax - Bull = Earn&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The individual items are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rev&lt;/strong&gt;: Revenues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COGS&lt;/strong&gt;: Cost of goods sold. Think of raw materials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exp&lt;/strong&gt;: Expenses, specifically those which are paid to other firms, like advertising costs, legal costs, and the like.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wage&lt;/strong&gt;: Salaries and wages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Int&lt;/strong&gt;: Interest payments on any loans or bonds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Div&lt;/strong&gt;: Dividends.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rent&lt;/strong&gt;: Rent on property and/or items of intellectual property like patents or copyrights.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dep&lt;/strong&gt;: Depreciation of fixed assets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tax&lt;/strong&gt;: Corporate income taxes. It’s important here to note these are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sales taxes or excise taxes like tariffs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bull&lt;/strong&gt;: All sorts of other bulls%&amp;amp;^ that firms use to limit the earnings they need to pay taxes on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earn&lt;/strong&gt;: Reported net earnings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In evaluating a firm, you probably look first at &lt;em&gt;Earn&lt;/em&gt;, which indicates wow much money did they made. &lt;em&gt;Earn&lt;/em&gt; is the number you would use in a P/E ratio if you were evaluating the a public firm’s stock. You might also look at different concepts of earnings, like EBIDTA, which would be like &lt;em&gt;Earn + Int + Dep + Tax + Bull&lt;/em&gt;. Regardless, the purpose of this income statement is to evaluate the financial success of the company. You are interested in the bottom line number, earnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take this and use it to build up GDP. All that’s required is basic addition and subtraction. First, rearrange the income statement in the following way&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(Rev - COGS - Exp) - (Wage + Int + Div + Rent + Dep) = Earn + Bull + Tax&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two groupings on the left-hand side, and we’ll get to those in a moment. Before that, note that I’ve put &lt;em&gt;Earn + Bull + Tax&lt;/em&gt; together on the right-hand side. I’m going to rename this combined term as &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(Rev - COGS - Exp) - (Wage + Int + Div + Rent + Dep) = Profits&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of questions here. Why is &lt;em&gt;Bull&lt;/em&gt; part of &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt;? Because &lt;em&gt;Bull&lt;/em&gt; is purely accounting gimmick stuff to mitigate taxes. So while they list it like any other expense, we will not. Next, why is &lt;em&gt;Tax&lt;/em&gt; part of &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt;? Because what happens to those profits after they are made is a different question than how big those profits actually are. &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt; is really &lt;em&gt;Profits before corporate income taxes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, move that grouping of wages and interest and other items over to the right-hand side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Rev - COGS - Exp = Wage + Int + Div + Rent + Dep + Profits&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term on the left-hand side is called &lt;em&gt;value-added&lt;/em&gt;. The firm sells goods and services for &lt;em&gt;Rev&lt;/em&gt;, and that is the total value of those goods and services. But those goods and services required the value of &lt;em&gt;COGS&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Exp&lt;/em&gt; to produce, so the &lt;em&gt;value-added&lt;/em&gt; of the firm is the difference of their revenues and these expenses. Now we’ve got:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;ValueAdded = Wage + Int + Div + Rent + Dep + Profits&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great. At a firm level, we have that their value-added is, by definition, equal to their wages, interest payments, dividends, rents, depreciation, and profits. Whether that &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt; term is positive or negative is unknowable without knowing the other terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this equation holds for all the firms in the economy. It holds even for those firms who don’t produce formal financial statements, like your local food truck. It holds for federal, state, and local governments, who differ in how they assign money to different categories. Sum up both sides of the equation across all firms or entities that produce value added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;GDP = \sum Wage + \sum Int + \sum Div + \sum Rent + \sum Dep + \sum Profits&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left-hand side is GDP, because GDP is the sum of value-added across all firms, by definition. Go backwards, and note how GDP is built up. It is the sum of value-added across firms. Value-added is &lt;em&gt;Rev - COGS - Exp&lt;/em&gt;, which does not tell you anything about profits at the firm level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GDP can be decomposed among all those things on the right-hand side. And in fact the BEA reports exactly the right hand side in their Gross Domestic Income (GDI) estimate, which is equal to GDP except for a small statistical discrepancy (because adding up all these things across firms is hard).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GDP (or GDI) tells you nothing about the financial health or success of firms. &lt;em&gt;Profits&lt;/em&gt; could be big, or small, or negative, or positive. As a company, Amazon lost about 240 million dollars in 2014. But that doesn’t mean the services it provided didn’t count in GDP. They provided about 26 billion in value-added the same year. Sears Holding Company lost 1.13 billion dollars in 2015, which was better than the 1.68 billion they lost in 2014. At the same time, Sears Holding contributed about 5.8 billion to GDP in 2015, and 7.1 billion to GDP in 2014. It is not GDP’s problem that Sears seems to have more combined costs, like wages, rent, and interest, than can be covered by their value-added. It doesn’t change the fact that Sears provided goods and services to the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this a problem with GDP? The answer to that depends entirely on what you are trying to measure. If you are interested in knowing the value of all the goods and services produced in an economy, then GDP is what you want. To borrow a British phrase, it does what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you are interested in knowing if firms (or industries) in the economy are “doing well” or “successful” or “healthy”, then you should look at firm financial statements, and things like net earnings, or EBIDTA, or net income from continuing operations, or operating income, or gross profit, or whatever is your favorite financial indicator. Using those, you might decide that Amazon or Sears will go out of business in the future because they lose money. Or decide to sell or buy stock in those companies. Or decide to sue their CEO, or vote for a new board. But GDP isn’t here to tell you those things. GDP doesn’t care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why productivity measures like multi-factor productivity (MFP) or labor productivity are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; measures of firm health, success, or financial performance. These measures take GDP (in aggregate, or at the industry level) and divide it by numbers of inputs used. As GDP is not a measure of firm financial success, productivity cannot be a measure of firm financial success either.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Productivity measures productivity ... that&#39;s it</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Manufacturing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Manufacturing/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Justin Fox at Bloomberg put up a few articles (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-10-19/no-u-s-manufacturing-isn-t-really-booming&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-10-26/manufacturing-s-productivity-myth&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) recently digging into trends in productivity in the US manufacturing sector. The overarching theme of the two articles is that claims regarding the success of the manufacturing sector in the US (he cites Binyamin Applebaum’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobile.nytimes.com/2016/10/09/magazine/why-are-politicians-so-obsessed-with-manufacturing.html?referer=https://t.co/vEnqUjWznf&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; specifically) are overstated. Fox’s first article is titled “No, U.S. Manufacturing isn’t Really Booming”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to tell you that manufacturing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; booming. I’m also not going to tell you that Fox is right about it &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; booming. I am going to tell you that making claims about the business or financial success of manufacturing based on things like multi-factor productivity (MFP) or labor productivity, as Fox does, is using these measures incorrectly. The “health” or “success” or “boominess” of manfucturing are not things one can infer from productivity statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll pick on Fox’s articles here because they were recent, not because he’s done something especially egregious. They are two of many examples of how measures like MFP and labor productivity get misused to make points about financial or business performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message is that you all need to just let productivity &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; productivity, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mfp-is-about-value-added-not-numbers-of-goods&quot;&gt;MFP is about value-added, not numbers of goods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox takes issue with the measures of manufacuring multi-factor productivity because they involve quality adjustments made the BLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… the numbers are skewed by huge gains in real output in computer and electronics manufacturing that mainly reflect quality adjustments made by government statisticians, not increases in real-world sales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are couple of problems with this. One reflects some ambiguity. When Fox says “increase in real-world sales”, is he asking for a measure of business performance? I think, although I’m not sure, he means “increases in the number of physical &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt; shipped”. And if he means increases in the number of physical things, then this is precisely &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; the BLS makes these quality adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multi-factor productivity is simply a ratio of value-added to an index of inputs. Value-added in the manufacturing sector is a mesure of the economic value of all the goods produced. Not the physical number, the economic value. And hence manufacturing MFP is a measure of how much economic value that sector produces - not the physical number of goods - per unit of input used. I know this paragraph was redundant, but it is crucial to keep the distinction between value-added and the actual number of things clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all we were doing was counting units, then no quality adjustments would be necessary. But we are trying to measure value-added, so they are. You cannot just add the 50 or so million iPhone 7’s that will be sold this quarter to the 20 million or so iPhone 6’s that will be sold to get 70 million phones. That ignores the fact that these items are different goods. And this problem gets exacerbated when I try to compare value-added over time. How do I compare the 50 million iPhone 7’s to the 5 million IBM PC’s produced in 1986? The BLS makes these adjustments to try and make the measure of value-added - and hence the measure of MFP - comparable over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could quibble with their exact method - I think an iPhone 7 is roughly equivalent to 400 IBM PC’s, but the BLS thinks it’s equivalent to 500 - but without these quality adjustments, MFP would be uniquely scaled in each year. It would be impossible to compare MFP in 2016 to MFP in 2015, and hence to know if it grew or not. While imperfect, you can’t skip the quality adjustment if you want to make any comparisons over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other sectors are not “more real” than computer equipment because they have smaller adjustment factors. You could easily argue that the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; sectors are “less real” because they have improper quality adjustments. The BLS could be missing all the wonderful innovations we’ve made in refrigerator construction, for example, and understating MFP growth in that sub-sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignoring computer equipment in MFP does not give you a better read on what is “really happening” in the manufacturing sector. MFP is what is really happening to …. MFP. If you mean “are manufacturing firms profitable or successful or expanding or exporting”, then you mean something different than MFP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mfp-has-nothing-to-do-with-corporate-accounting&quot;&gt;MFP has nothing to do with corporate accounting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prior section hints at how people make the mistake of evaluating the economy as if it were a business. The following quote shows what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… but the adjustments do raise questions about what exactly the productivity numbers signify. They don’t necessarily mean, for example, that computer and electronics manufacturers in the U.S. are actually growing, or succeeding in international competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, they don’t. They’re not intended to. MFP is not a measure of whether firms or industries are “succeeding”, in any corporate or financial sense of that word. MFP is a measure of how much value-added the manufacturing sector produced for a given set of inputs. That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value-added is not profits, in any financial accounting sense. The &lt;em&gt;closest&lt;/em&gt; you can get to an analog in financial accounts is to take revenues minus cost of goods sold. And revenues minus cost of goods sold is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; profits. Why? Because the firm still has to pay wages, interest costs, taxes, and dividends, among other things. So firms could easily be losing money, either in the sense of having negative net profits or a negative cash flow, even though their value-added is positive. Or maybe they are making money, and then good for them. But it is &lt;em&gt;irrelevant&lt;/em&gt; to MFP whether the firms are making money or not. MFP and firm or industry “success” are fundemantally different things. One implies nothing about the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get back to the prior section, the BLS is not trying to produce a quality adjustment so that their numbers reflect the financial accounting position of manufacturing firms. They are producing a quality adjustment so that MFP reflects a measure of how much value-added we get per unit of inputs. If their MFP number doesn’t mesh with your intuition or knowledge of the financial position of manufacturing as a sector, then … so? It’s not intended to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mfp-is-not-about-competitiveness&quot;&gt;MFP is not about competitiveness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox quotes Michael Mandel, of the Progressive Policy Institute, on why one should pay attention to MFP as opposed to labor productivity,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because it includes a wider scope of inputs and costs, multifactor productivity is a better indicator of how innovative and competitive an industry really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, it’s not. It has precisely zero to do with how competitive an industry is. First of all, “competitive” is a word devoid of meaning. “Competitive” could mean “cheap”, like textile firms in Southeast Asia, which have lower MFP than US firms. “Competitive” could mean “very low profits can be made” because entry of competitors is easy, like gas stations or coffee shops. That has nothing to do with whether MFP is high is low in those industries. “Competitive” could mean “produces a product that has an export market”, but that could just mean that the industry holds patents or other IP that makes it hard for others to replicate their product. And having intellectual property rights over a product doesn’t mean your MFP is large or small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Mandel probably means is “profitable” or “growing in revenues”, but I don’t know for sure. If his meaning is along those lines, then MFP doesn’t tell us anything about that, for the reasons I outline in the prior section. MFP is not a measure of profitability or market size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also isn’t a measure of how innovative an industry is, because as I’ve mentioned before on this blog, MFP is not a pure measure of technology or innovation. MFP is a garbage dump for everything we don’t know how to measure, including technology. So MFP can be stagnant even if an industry is innovative, or vice versa. If there is any imperfect competition in the industry so that markups exist, then MFP is affected by the growth rate of labor and capital, and the direction of this effect is indeterminate without knowing more about input growth. If there are re-allocations of inputs across firms within industries, then this influences MFP, and again the effect is indeterminate until you know which firm is shedding inputs and which one is gaining them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mfp-is-a-ratio-not-a-story&quot;&gt;MFP is a ratio, not a story&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because they are ratios, both MFP and labor productivity can rise because the numerator (value added) rises or because the denominator (all inputs or just labor) falls. It doesn’t matter which one moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On the whole, the U.S. manufacturing sector does not appear to have been a hotbed of innovation and productivity gains in recent years. It has gotten by with fewer workers, but in many cases that seems to have been more about managing decline through layoffs and plant shutdowns than boldly leaping into the automated future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we’ve learned, you cannot say anything about “innovation” from looking at MFP. But this is accurate that manufacturing has not been a hotbed of MFP or labor productivity growth in recent years. But then there are a couple things to unpack in the last sentence of this quote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If MFP is stagnant but the manufacturing sector has shed workers, then this means either value added in manufacturing has fallen (it has not) or the other inputs like capital have risen (they must have). This indicates that labor productivity, value-added divided by number of workers only, must be rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s it. We’re done. It is irrelevant to MFP or labor productivity what the story is behind the decline in labor and the increase in capital. The fact that you cannot attribute the decline of labor to lasers or robots or AI or hologram technology doesn’t change the fact that labor use declined, labor productivity went up, and MFP stayed stagnant. Closing a plant reduces labor in manufacturing, and if value-added doesn’t fall by enough, labor productivity in manufacturing just went up. It’s irrelevant for productivity that this is layoffs or shutdowns versus automated whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just let productivity be productivity. It measures value-added - not profits, not sales, not cash flow - relative to inputs, and therefore tells us how effectively the economy - not businesses - turns inputs into value-added. Slower MFP growth means slower MFP growth, not anything about competitiveness or the future business success/failure of US manufacturing. Heck, it doesn’t even tell us anything about the &lt;em&gt;past&lt;/em&gt; business success or failures of US manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coda-manufacturing-is-a-relatively-small-sector&quot;&gt;Coda: Manufacturing is a relatively small sector&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last point isn’t directly related to the main post, but I like to harp on this, and its my blog, so you’re kind of stuck with it. Manufacturing represents a small slice of economic activity in the United States. And there is no reason why we should be particularly worried or concerned with productivity in this sector relative to other sectors, many of which employ more people and are responsible for larger portions of value-added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing used about 9% of the hours worked in the US in 2015 (all numbers from the BLS). That makes it about as important, in employment terms, to retail (10%) and the recreation, accommodation, food service sector (9%). It employs less than education and health (15%), government (15%), and profession and business services (14%). But no one seems to write articles worrying about the MFP numbers in any of those other sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drilling down, durable goods manufaturing - like, you know, “real” economic output - employed about 6% of hours worked in 2015. That means it is as large as … administrative and waste services (6%) and profession and scientific services (6%), and slightly ahead of the “other retail” sector (5%) and construction (5%). It’s behind accomodation and food (8%) and state and local government (12%). The vast majority of hours, and workers, are employed doing anything &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; putting together durable goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of value-added, manufacturing accounts for about 11% of the aggregate, comparable to profession and business services (13%) and government (12%), and well less than finance and real estate (20%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing is not the dominant origin of employment or value-added. Which means that any action in labor productivity or MFP in manufacturing has a small effect on aggregate labor productivity of MFP. For labor productivity, you’d use the share of hours worked to weight manufacturing, and for MFP, you’d use the share of value-added. So as a rule of thumb, the reported change in manufacturing only counts for about 1/10 of that in the aggregate. Labor productivity rises by 3% in manufacturing? Then this adds about 0.3% to aggregate labor productivity. Manufacturing MFP falls by 1%? Then aggregate MFP falls by about 0.1%. There is nothing magic or special about manufacturing that priviledges its hours or value-added above other sectors in the aggregate calculations. It’s a relatively small part of the pie.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Labor Recovery and the Productivity Slowdown</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Labor-Prod/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Labor-Prod/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone loves talking about productivity, and how it doesn’t grow as fast as it used to. Very low productivity growth rates, in same cases negative, have been used very recently as evidence of this long-run slowdown and why perhaps it will get worse. But inferring something about long-run trends in productivity growth from a few years of data, especially years that represent a recovery from a deep recession, is probably unwise. Now that I have the 2015 BEA data on sector-specific output and employment, let me try to illustrate what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Productivity growth is just output (value-added) growth minus input (however measured) growth. In this post I’m working with BEA data on value-added and full-time equivalents, so when I say productivity that is short-hand for “value-added per full-time equivalent”, which some might refer to as a measure of labor productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of the post is really just to point out that a notable feature of the slow growth in productivity in 2013 and 2014 was the incredibly &lt;em&gt;rapid&lt;/em&gt; growth in full-time equivalents. Aggregate value-added growth did not drop off appreciably. Rather, the growth rate of full-time equivalents was high, and hence measured productivity growth was very low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_bea_fteprod_Aggregate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Aggregate prod growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure shows the growth rate of productivity (value-added per FTE) as the thick black line, and then also includes the separate growth rates of value-added (thin gray line) and FTE’s (thin dashed line). What you can see in 2013, and in 2014 especially, is that productivity growth dropped to about -2% per year. But value-added growth was still about &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; 2% per year, and the entire reason for the decline in productivity growth was that FTE growth was over 3%. Compare that to the numbers from the rest of the time period I plotted, and that is an exceptional number. Labor force growth drove the decline in productivity, purely from an accounting perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, once the growth in FTE’s ebbs to only about 1%, and there is a slight uptick in the growth rate of value-added, we see productivity growth rise to positive 1%. It sure looks like the drop in productivity growth in 2013/14 was temporary and driven almost entirely by the acceleration of growth in FTE’s as the economy starts to recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the BEA data, I can dig backwards into the sector-by-sector contributions to productivity growth. And there are a few select sectors that appear to be driving this phenomenon. First, take a look at “Government”, which includes federal as well as state and local government spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_bea_fteprod_Government.png&quot; alt=&quot;Government&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of value-added declines noticeably from 2008 to 2013 before experiencing a slight uptick in 2014 (the light gray line). The growth rate of FTE’s in government also bottoms out in 2011 at about -1.5%. After that, the growth rate recovered, and by 2014 FTE’s in government were growing at 1% per year. As long as FTE’s are growing faster than value-added, productivity growth will be negative, and you can see the precipitous drop in productivity growth for government in the 2013/14. In 2015, with a smaller growth rate of FTE’s in government, productivity growth recovers closer to zero, but is still negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side note about “value-added” for government. This is going to include both salaries for public employees like teachers, cops, and fireman, and also capital spending like roads, bridges, and other infrastructure. The effect you see in the overall government sector is driven almost entirely by state and local governments. They shed workers like crazy after the recession, and in 2014 that reversed dramatically. Growth in state/local FTE’s went from -1.5% in about 2011 to +2% in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail is another sector with a dramatic acceleration of the FTE growth rate in 2014, illustrating this point. In this case the discrepancy between value-added growth (consistently around 2% per year) and FTE growth in 2014 (pushing 15%!) is very stark. The massive addition of labor to retail in 2014 explains everything about the massive &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; growth rate of productivity in retail, about -11%. And as retail work makes up about 20% of aggregate FTE’s, this negative growth rate of productivity puts a big drag on aggregate productivity growth. In 2014, the negative growth rate of retail productivity can essentially explain &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the negative growth in aggregate productivity in the same year. But this is all due to the massive expansion of employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_bea_fteprod_Retail.png&quot; alt=&quot;Retail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, with the reversal of FTE growth (-10%), productivity growth bounces up to positive 12%, which means it contributes about 2.4 percentage points to aggregate productivity growth. But these fluctuations are entirely due to the fluctuations in the FTE growth rate in retail. Note that growth in value-added remains roughly constant in these last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one other sector with a pattern is construction. Again, productivity growth is negative in 2014 (and 2013), but this is driven almost entirely by the higher growth rates of FTEs in construction in those years. In 2015, as FTE growth abates in construction, productivity growth looks positive again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_bea_fteprod_Construction.png&quot; alt=&quot;Construction&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other sectors have this effect present, but it looks pretty small (Manufacturing, Utilities, Wholesale trade). Some, like transportation and mining, have similarly large shifts in FTE’s, but these tend to act in the opposite direction to those in retail and construction. That is, in 2013/14, the growth in FTE’s was &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt;, and so calculated productivity growth was very &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt;. In 2015 recovery in the FTE growth in both sectors is associated with much lower productivity growth, as in both cases value-added growth doesn’t change a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One response to these figures is that this reflects some error in calculation or reporting. And believe me, I’ve gone back and forth with the BEA website to confirm that this is really what they are reporting for 2014 and 2015, and that I’m using the right data. I’ve picked over my Stata code a few times to see if I’m getting this wrong somehow, but this is what the data say. If I was calculating things wrong, you’d expect to see some &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; odd surges in growth rates in other years, at least for some sectors. And since we don’t, I believe I’m accurately reporting the right growth rates given the BEA data provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on the assumption that these figures are a good representation of what was going on with productivity growth, what does it tell us? The first reaction I have is that this is precisely why you shouldn’t get worked about a single year’s productivity growth rate. In 2014, it was negative in the aggregate thanks in part to retail and government as well as several other sectors. But given that this was driven entirely by a surge in FTE growth associated with a recovering labor market, I don’t know that there is any long-run information here. It certainly doesn’t provide any evidence that innovation is slowing down. Productivity is just a residual, so short-run productivity growth rates will always be subject to surges in short-run FTE growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second reaction may be, if these industries are adding all these FTE’s, then why isn’t value-added rising faster? Does this make sense for firms to hire these people (or raise their hours) if they are not getting more value-added? Perhaps the people they are hiring are relatively low-skill and low-productivity? Think of the Roy model idea I mentioned in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Roy/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about Alwyn Young’s recent paper. If the people who are being added are relatively bad at working in their sectors - because all the good people already work there - then putting them to work may not boost value-added growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were feeling optimistic, you might look at this as evidence that innovation &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; occurring. Perhaps firms have been adding labor quickly because they anticipate needing them over the next few years due to innovations coming on-line. They presumably are somewhat forward-looking, and so maybe this represents firms investing in building up a labor force in anticipation of new markets and new customers? Note that the drop in FTE growth in 2015 does not wipe out the FTE gains of the prior two years. FTE’s are still growing at the aggregate level in 2015, just at a slower rate. For Retail, FTE’s actually did fall in 2015 relative to 2015, but are still higher than in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you might take away regarding innovation, these graphs suggest that perhaps the drop in productivity growth in 2014 was really an aberration. If FTE growth returns to more typical rates, then productivity growth - remember, just a residual - would return to more typical rates as well. And just a note, this doesn’t provide an explanation for why long-run productivity growth has been lower over the last few decades, but simply an explanation for why very recent productivity growth looks weak. I think the message is to not get hung up on year-to-year productivity growth rates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Soooo...maybe the service sector isn&#39;t a drag on productivity growth after all?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Roy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Roy/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the running themes on this blog is that productivity (called total factor productivity or multi-factor productivity by those in the biz) is basically a garbage dump for all the stuff we do not know how to measure in the real economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s post provides another example of this. Alwyn Young published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/aer.104.11.3635&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; in 2014 on the “cost disease of services” and productivity growth. In short, the cost disease of services is an idea from William Baumol, and it is intended to explain why productivity growth tends to slow down during a structural transformation from manufacturing to services. The idea is that services have low inherent productivity growth compared to manufacturing, mainly because services are often provided in fixed units of time (you can’t get a one-hour massage in less than one hour). Combine that with the fact that services are highly income elastic, meaning we demand more and more of them as we get richer, and labor moves into services over time. Hence the average growth rate of productivity falls because everyone is now working in this low-growth sector. It is certainly one of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Baumol/&quot;&gt;leading candidates&lt;/a&gt; for an explanation of why productivity growth is relatively low in the last 15-20 years compared to prior periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young’s paper questions whether in fact services really do have slower productivity growth than manufacturing. His argument is going to be that we may be falsely under-stating productivity growth in services because we are not accounting for the fact that the labor flowing into services is, compared to existing service workers, relatively bad at doing service work. What looks like low productivity growth is in fact low growth (or negative growth) in average human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, productivity growth in manufacturing is over-stated because the workers that remains behind in manufacturing as people leave are only the very best workers, and hence the average ability of manufacturing workers (to do manufacturing work) is going &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; over time. What looks like high productivity growth is in fact high growth in average human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea comes from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/2662082&quot;&gt;Roy model&lt;/a&gt; (1951), a classic economics paper about the distribution in earnings. At it’s heart, the Roy model is about self-selection. Imagine that each person has some built-in ability to work in manufacturing, and some built-in ability to work in services. There may be some elements of these abilities that are correlated (maybe you are really smart and could figure out how to do either efficiently), but regardless you’ll have a comparative advantage in one of them. Yes, the same idea of comparative advantage as in trade. You may be good at both activities, but relatively speaking you’ll be better at one or the other when I compare you to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young works out an exact case of the Roy model where your comparative advantage is positively correlated to your absolute advantage. That is, people who are relatively good at manufacturing are &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; absolutely good at manufacturing. Let me be specific, because I know I always found these concepts hard to keep straight in my head. My daughter once took a few hockey lessons, but now has been swimming her whole life. She has a comparative advantage in swimming over hockey. I’ve played hockey for a long time, but I never really took swim lessons as a kid, and I’m always worried about losing my contacts in the water, so I know just enough to keep myself from drowning. My comparative advantage is in hockey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not only that, our absolute advantages are correlated with our comparative advantages. If we had a swim race, my daughter would win - absolute advantage matches comparative advantage. If we played hockey, I would win - absolute advantage matches comparative advantage. (This wasn’t true a few years ago. Despite my lack of swimming skill, when she was 7 I could still outswim her just because I was bigger. Not any more. But I can still &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; her on the ice.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Roy model, if there was demand for one swimmer and one hockey player, my daughter would self-select into the swim sector and I would self-select into the hockey sector. Now, if the economy changes and the demand for hockey falls and swimming rises (global warming?), then I will have to switch. This will unambiguously &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; the average skill level of swimmers, as I suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When comparative advantage and absolute advantage are correlated in a Roy model, any movement of a worker from one sector to another will &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; the average skill of the &lt;em&gt;receiving&lt;/em&gt; sector, and &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; the average skill of the &lt;em&gt;sending&lt;/em&gt; sector. If I get moved from hockey to swimming, I lower the average skill of swimmers. The dudes that remain in my hockey league will be the ones who are still better than me (i.e essentially all of them), and so I just raised the average skill level of my league by leaving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the essence of Young’s story, and he shows that if this is how things work, then it has an effect on &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; productivity growth in each sector. Just another example of how measured productivity growth is a garbage pile of all the things we don’t know how to keep track of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past on this blog, I’ve referred to measured productivity growth as the “residual”, R, and true productivity growth as A. So to be consistent with the blog, but not with Young’s paper, he finds that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{R}_j = \hat{A}_j + \xi \hat{s}_j&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the growth rate of the residual productivity measure (what you see reported by the BLS) for sector j. So &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}_{Manuf}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the residual productivity measure for manufacturing, as an example. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{A}\inline&quot;/&gt; is true productivity growth in sector j. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; is the growth in the share of labor working in sector j.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is how average worker ability/skill responds to a change in sector j’s share of the labor force. Young establishes empirically that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is less than zero. He has his own estimates based on using sector-level data from Europe and the US, and this is consistent with several other estimates drawn from the literature. These estimates come from regressing measured productivity growth, the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}\inline&quot;/&gt; things from many sectors over many years, on measures changes in labor shares, the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{s}\inline&quot;/&gt; things. An important element of this is that Young actually has these labor terms for 60 &lt;em&gt;types&lt;/em&gt; of labor, differentiated by gender, age, and education. Thus his estimate of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is not just picking up on the fact that perhaps manufacturing workers are older, male, and less educated, for example. It has to be mentioned here as well that Young’s estimates are very imprecise, with standard errors big enough that you cannot reject zero in many cases - his case is really made on the fact that the negative estimates are so consistent across different samples and specifications. So you could easily remain suspicious of these results pending some more precise way of nailing down the value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is estimated to be less than zero implies that measured productivity growth in a sector goes &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt; when more labor (of any of the types) is added to the sector. This is consistent with the theoretical case Young discussed within the Roy model of comparative advantage and absolute advantage being correlated. And now that we know &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; is negative, we can see what kind of an effect the Roy effects have on measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take manufacturing, which has a shrinking share of labor, meaning &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{s}&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt; for that sector. Combined with &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi&amp;lt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, this means that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}&amp;gt;\hat{A}\inline&quot;/&gt; for manufacturing. Measured manufacturing productivity growth is higher than true productivity growth. Flip the logic around for services, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{s}&amp;gt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, and you get that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{R}&amp;lt;\hat{A}\inline&quot;/&gt;. Measured productivity growth is &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; than true productivity growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young provides a table where he recovers the true productivity growth rates in each sector. This depends on the value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt;, and his estimates suggest that this parameter is somewhere between -0.5 and -1.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/young.png&quot; alt=&quot;Young&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the table, the first row just gives the regularly reported values for productivity growth in the US and the EU for manufacturing and service productivity growth. In the US, manufacturing (goods) has reported productivity growth of 1.57 percent per year, and services only 0.73. However, if Young’s estimate of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; of -0.5 is right, then in fact true productivity growth is more like 1.10 in manufacturing and 0.84 in services. If -0.75 is right, then services have a small advantage at 0.90 percent per year, manufacturing has 0.87, and they are basically equal. You get a similar pattern for the EU, where manufacturing and services show similar productivity growth once the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\xi\inline&quot;/&gt; parameter is big enough in size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This analysis suggests that perhaps Baumol’s story is wrong. Services may not have a built-in tendency towards slower productivity growth over time. Rather, we are measuring it wrong. Remember that residual productivity measures are junk piles, and what Young is suggesting is that service productivity measurement had a big load of crap dumped on it because of these Roy effects. Manufacturing does not necessarily have better productivity growth, because it also had a big load of crap dumped on it by the Roy effects. If you take Young’s work seriously, then he’s showing you that productivity growth across all sectors is roughly similar over time, and hence there is no need to worry about the shift from manufacturing to services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what Young doesn’t do is decompose his table by time periods, so we cannot examine the effects when aggregate produtcivity growth was large (the 90’s) and when it was small (the 10’s). Has the Roy effect gotten bigger or smaller over time, or is it unchanged? And these Roy effects don’t necessarily offer any explanation for the aggregate productivity slowdown we’ve seen in the last few decades. Note that adjusting for the Roy effects may make the true aggregate productivity growth rate go up (the EU) or down (the US). The best this table can do is explain that the slowdown &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; due to “Baumol effects” of moving into services. But that’s important, because it means that we are not somehow doomed to slower productivity growth just because we’ve moved into services. We’re doomed for entirely different reasons, apparently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few other notes about this paper. David Lagakos and Mike Waugh use this &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v103y2013i2p948-80.html&quot;&gt;same concept&lt;/a&gt; to explain why there is such a large gap in productivity between agriculture and non-agriculture in developing countries, and why that gap tends to disappear as countries develop. And that makes me wonder about accounting for productivity growth rates in sectors in the early part of the 20th century, when agriculture was the shrinking sector and manufacturing was growing. Based on Young’s logic, this means we were probably over-stating agricultural productivity growth and &lt;em&gt;under-stating&lt;/em&gt; manufacturing productivity growth. So perhaps Bob Gordon’s story of high mid-century productivity growth is even more extreme than I thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, if you want to learn how to write a lucid economics paper, read this one, or really any of Young’s work. It’s just so coherently organized and explained compared to the vast, vast, vast majority of what gets published.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hobsbawm on relative decline and social disruption</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Hobsbawm/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Hobsbawm/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently re-read Eric Hobsbawm’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2cJTPNr&quot;&gt;Industry and Empire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. I didn’t have a reason, other than that it was shelved near something else I was looking for in the library, and caught my eye. It was definitely before graduate school that I last read it, so it seemed worth revisiting now that I’ve got my fancy-schmancy education in economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bit of a mess as far as history goes. Yes, it deals with events and people that happened long ago. But so does Star Wars. It is a narrative informed occassionally by some vague stylized facts. It is pure interpretation. To my point, I’ll just note that Hobsbawm has a section of figures and tables, in the appendix. That appendix is prefaced by the following quote: “It is not easy to include a sufficient selection of quantitative data in a text without making it unreadable.” Well, it may not be easy, but it is possible. Instead, Hobsbawm’s book is all about the narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His main thesis is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The relative decline of Britain is, broadly speaking, due to its early and long-sustained start as an industrial power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, okay. But I think the immediate reaction to this should be “no kidding”. This is like saying that the relative decline of my height compared to my daughters is, broadly speaking, due to my early and long-sustained start at being alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending at least a little time thinking about the processes involved in economic growth, even intuitively, will suggest that this relative decline is going to be almost inevitable for the country who industrializes first. It is easier to copy technologies than invent them, so countries behind Britain (the US, Germany, etc.) are able to catch up quickly. Or, if you believe - wrongly - that growth is limited by stocks of natural resources, then Britain has no particular advantage over continental Europe, much less the US, so it would be impossible to sustain an early lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hobsbawm doesn’t even give you a clear notion of what he means by “relative decline”. In what? GDP per capita? Wages? Some measure of human well-being like health? Number of stripes on flags? He seems to have in mind some ambiguous concept like “dynamism”, which fits well in a narrative but of course is a completely empty term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His own review of the history of Britain belies the idea that Britain lacked dynamism, by which I mean the growth of new sectors or industries. While Germany and the US were ratcheting up their own manufacturing sectors, Britain was moving into services like insurance and finance, and shedding low margin work to those countries. But Hobsbawm appears to fall into the same trap as many of fetishizing manufaturing work over all else. So Britain’s continued use of older-generation spinning machines or blast furnaces compared to Germany is some kind of indictment of not just the economy, but British society. There was, according to Hobsbawm, a “genuine loss of impetus and efficiency”. Not that we are treated to a single piece of evidence regarding this assertion, or even told what impetus is supposed to refer to, or what is the definition of efficiency he has in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation offered for the relative decline of Britain is the empire. This provided an effectively closed market for manufactured goods, and British industry was thus able to survive without having to be competitive with newer German and US firms. There is probably an interesting argument to be made regarding the role of empire in British industrial growth, but that argument would involve, you know, data. And this isn’t necessarily the same argument as the one involving the relative decline of Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is quite harsh on my part. But for all that, there are some ideas in Hobsbawm worth thinking hard about. From his Chapter 4 (The Human Results of the Industrial Revolution), consider the following quote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those classes whose lives were least transformed were also, normally, those which benefitted most obviously in material terms (and vice versa), and their failure to grasp what was troubling the rest, or to do anything effective about it, was due not only to material but also to moral contentment. Nobody is more complacent than a well-off or successful man who is also at ease in a world which seems to have been constructed precisely with persons like him in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hobsbawm was talking about the aristocracy and “business class” of Britain during the early IR, who not only were made better off, but did not find themselves socially disrupted. The source of their money may have started changing, but they had a clear idea of where they fit in (i.e. schools, clubs, political positions). In contrast, the mass of people who were being drawn into industrial work were generally being asked to trade one low-paying occupation (farming or home craft work) for another (factory work) that had an entirely different set of social conditions. They were employees, not self-employed. They were subject to the clock, not the calendar. They were expected to live in cities, not the country. Think of this last one; what would it be like to go from living among familiar faces with the occassional stranger, to living among strangers with the occassional familiar face? Even if your material standard of living was unchanged, or even higher, it would be socially difficult to adapt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the merits of &lt;em&gt;Industry and Empire&lt;/em&gt; as an actual history, it left me thinking about the social transformations that are part of structural change to this day. The lingering move &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; of manufacturing and into services, and from certain services (trade, transport) into others (education, health), also involves social disruption. It even involves the movement of people from relatively rural - or small-town - environments to larger urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to Hobsbawm’s point, I find it highly likely that I do not appreciate the amount of disruption involved in these changes. My inclination would be to say that the transition we’re involved in now isn’t nearly as socially disruptive as the original industrial revolution. But how do I know? I am part of the “class” whose life has transformed very little in response to the decline of manufacturing and rise of “softer” services. I fit very nicely into a world that values educational achievement and professional skills. If anything, these economic changes mean that it is getting easier for me to find my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which leaves me wondering how complacent I am regarding these disruptions. Complacency, as Hobsbawm suggested for Britain, has consequences. &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2cYKxwg&quot;&gt;Polyani&lt;/a&gt; makes a set of similar points. For something more recent, I think you can do a lot worse than revisiting some of what Dani Rodrik has written, say &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrik.typepad.com/dani_rodriks_weblog/2016/06/brexit-and-the-globalization-trilemma.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/anti-globalization-backlash-from-right-by-dani-rodrik-2016-07&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, about the reactions to globalization over the last two decades. That backlash certainly smell similar to the reactions that Hobsbawm tracks in Britain around 1820 to 1850-ish: Luddites, Chartists, and the like. Were the complacent classes of Britain as surprised by these reactions - but why would they smash those looms? - as the complacent classes of today are surprised by similar reactions - but why would they vote to leave the EU?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no way to neatly wrap up this post. I’ve written six different final paragraphs, but none that do anything other than stray into my own Hobsbawm-sian data-free narrative building exercise. Let me just offer up that if one includes social disruption in the accounting, then structural shifts between sectors/industries/locations are perhaps the most important aspect of economic growth to consider, even more than the growth rate itself.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Balanced growth in theory</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/BGP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/BGP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The last post was on the empirics behind balanced growth paths (BGP), the key organizing principle of economic growth models. I was skeptical of these empirics, and it looked like only weak evidence was there to support the idea of BGP’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said in that post, essentially all the models of growth written down in the last half-century work very hard to ensure they have a BGP. Here, I want to show that this generates a set of pretty tight restrictions about how you can model the world. And hence it generates a set of pretty tight restrictions on how you think the world actually works. So tight that perhaps it seems implausible. Like I said in the prior post, I’m trying to be highly skeptical of these claims, in order to test my own beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uzawa-and-bgps&quot;&gt;Uzawa and BGP’s&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave aside the questions regarding the Kaldor facts from the last post entirely. Let’s assume that you do want your model of growth to have a BGP. What does this imply about how growth works?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key paper here is by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org.ezproxy.lib.uh.edu/stable/2296180&quot;&gt;Uzawa&lt;/a&gt; (1961), but I highly suggest you not read it. It is baffling. I suggest you take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.stanford.edu/~chadj/ss301.pdf&quot;&gt;Jones and Scrimgeour&lt;/a&gt; who have written a much more accessible explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me try to give you a flavor of Uzawa’s theorem. I’m going to try a different tactic than Jones and Scrimgeour, because I think I can keep it more accessible to a blog audience. There is math, but I hope nothing too terribly awful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, we’re going to assume that we have some kind of constant returns to scale production function. That CRS is crucial is necessary for BGP’s to exist. Let y be output per worker, and k be capital per worker. Let B denote the capital-augmenting technology - think of this as an index of how useful capital each unit of capital is for production. Let A denote labor-augmenting technology - again an index of how useful labor is for production. Okay, then let’s write the growth of output per worker as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{y} = \epsilon_K \hat{B} + \epsilon_K \hat{k} + \epsilon_L \hat{A}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where the “hats” on a variable denote its growth rate. The values &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_K\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_L\inline&quot;/&gt; are the elasticity of output with respect to that specific input. Because of constant returns, it must be that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_K + \epsilon_L = 1\inline&quot;/&gt;, and that will prove useful in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the equation says is that growth in output per worker is a weighted sum of capital-augmenting technological progress, labor-augmenting technological progress, and growth in capital per worker. The weights are the elasticities, which tell us how important capital and labor are to production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, one of the conditions for a BGP is that the rate of return on capital is constant. If you remember the prior post, we said that the rate of return could be calculated as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;r = s_K \frac{y}{k}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or capital’s share in output, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_K\inline&quot;/&gt;, times the output/capital ratio. The BGP also requires that the capital share is constant over time. So for the return, r, to be constant it must be that the ratio y/k is also constant. Which implies that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{y} = \hat{k}\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go back to the growth rate equation knowing this. Plugging in for &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{k} = \hat{y}\inline&quot;/&gt;, rearranging, and using the assumption that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_K + \epsilon_L = 1\inline&quot;/&gt;, we have that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{y} = \frac{\epsilon_K}{1-\epsilon_K} \hat{B} + \hat{A}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of output per worker depends only on the two types of technological progress. I didn’t have to say anything about exactly how capital is accumulated, but if we are insisting that the return on capital is constant, then it has to be that capital and output grow at the same rate, which means the growth rate of output per worker is dependent on only the growth rate of the technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, what does this leave us with? Along a BGP, the growth rate of output per worker is supposed to be constant. There are two ways to make this happen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cobb-Douglas production, constant labor- and capital-augmenting progress.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{B}\inline&quot;/&gt; can be non-zero, but then we have to ensure that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_K\inline&quot;/&gt; is constant as well. This restricts the production function to be a Cobb-Douglas, where the capital and labor elasticities never change. In this case, the fact that we call it “capital-augmenting” or “labor-augmenting” progress is irrelevant, as mathematically they are equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Cobb-Douglas production, but &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{B} = 0\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; When production isn’t Cobb-Douglas, the elasticity &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_K\inline&quot;/&gt; will change if &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{B}\inline&quot;/&gt; is non-zero. So the only way for this to work without a Cobb-Douglas production function is if capital-augmenting progress is exactly zero. Here, there really is a difference between “capital-augmenting” and “labor-augmenting” progress, and we have to have zero capital-augmenting progress.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are pretty restrictive. If you think an economy has a BGP, then what Uzawa indicates is that you have to think it either has a very specific production function (Cobb-Douglas) or a very specific rate of progress in capital-augmenting technology (zero).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels implausible that the real world actually would have the &lt;em&gt;exact right&lt;/em&gt; conditions for a BGP to happen. Taking a step back, maybe production isn’t even constant returns to scale in capital and labor in the first place. Are the empirics behind the BGP so strong that they should compel us to buy the theoretical restrictions they imply?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;relaxing-uzawa&quot;&gt;Relaxing Uzawa&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, maybe Uzawa’s restrictions aren’t necessary or aren’t as knife-edged as they seem. Here’s a few examples. Grossman, Helpman, Oberfield, Sampson, who got me going on this whole topic, propose one &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.harvard.edu/files/helpman/files/balanced_growth_despite_uzawa_110815gg.pdf&quot;&gt;solution&lt;/a&gt;. What GHOS suggest is that human capital growth may be sufficient to break the strict nature of Uzawa’s conditions. That is, they can write down a model of economic growth that doesn’t require Cobb-Douglas production, has a positive growth rate of capital-augmenting technological change, and yet still has a BGP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chad Jones has a different &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.stanford.edu/~chadj/JonesQJE2005.pdf&quot;&gt;approach&lt;/a&gt;, and he establishes conditions by which the &lt;em&gt;aggregate&lt;/em&gt; production function may be Cobb-Douglas, even though the underlying technical production functions of firms are not. This makes a BGP a reasonable outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this all presumes that we want to rescue the BGP - that economic growth necessarily involves a constant long-run growth rate, a stable capital share, and a constant return to capital. Given the information in the prior post, the question remains whether in fact the BGP is worth rescuing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;structural-change&quot;&gt;Structural Change&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give an example of where the dependence on BGP’s is possibly a problem. A lot of effort has been expended writing down models of economic growth that explicitly allow for multiple sectors (agriculture, manufacturing, services, for example) but that also display a BGP. You can think of there being an ancillary Kaldor fact that these papers want to explain, which is that there has been significant shifts of labor between sectors (generally, ag to manufacturing to services) over time in most economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/ucp/jpolec/v116y2008i3p467-498.html&quot;&gt;Acemoglu and Guerrieri&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/oup/restud/v68y2001i4p869-882..html&quot;&gt;Kongsamut, Rebelo, and Xie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v97y2007i1p429-443.html&quot;&gt;Ngai and Pissarides&lt;/a&gt;, among others, are built to deliver both structural change and a BGP. To do so is not trivial, so these models are quite clever in how they set things up to make this work out. In some way, they are writing down new versions of Uzawa that also allow them to account for structural change. They establish conditions for preferences or production functions that allow for economic activity to wax and wane in different sectors, but in aggregate continues to be consistent with Kaldor’s facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The danger here is presuming the original Kaldor facts are required. They work very hard to show that structural change can happen while the growth rate of output per capita remains constant in the long run. But what if the growth rate of output per capita isn’t constant in the long run? Or, if you don’t want to abandon the concept of a BGP altogether, what if there are different BGP’s depending on what stage of structural change you are in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the French figure from the prior post. You could argue that France had both a pre-WWII BGP (with relatively low levels of GDP per capita and a low growth rate) and a post-WWII BGP (with a higher level and growth rate). Who is to say that this kind of shift to a different BGP, perhaps with a lower growth rate, isn’t possible in a country like the US today? Who is to say that level shifts in the BGP, perhaps up or down, are not possible in the future based on structural change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;are-we-missing-the-point&quot;&gt;Are we missing the point?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Existing models that assume a BGP cannot, by design, deliver the kinds of jumps seen in the French example, or in cases like South Korea or Japan as they developed. Yes, those countries appeared to go from one BGP to another, so the existing models are good at capturing the dynamics within each BGP. But they have no way of explaining why it was that South Korea took off for a different BGP in about 1960, or why France’s growth rate shot up after World War II. These shifts are completely exogenous in these models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me ask it this way. If I could write down a model that could predict the conditions under which a country would accelerate like South Korea from poverty to rich-country living standards, would I discard it just because it failed to predict a strict BGP in the long run? I hope I wouldn’t, because a model that could identify those conditions would be incredibly valuable. But there is a tendency for growth economists to be skeptical of anything that doesn’t have a BGP in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take it from the other side, it may be that even if BGP’s are not strictly true in the data, that models with BGP’s are effective in capturing most of the interesting dynamics. The strict assumptions behind them need not be exactly true in real life, but are useful for simplifying our analysis. But the danger here is that we go too far, assert these strict assumptions are true because they deliver a BGP, and that would appear to be going in the wrong direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been operating in full skepticism mode, and so I should probably stop now before I manage to insult everyone who has done growth work in the last few decades. That, and I don’t want to discourage everyone from buying my &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/book/&quot;&gt;textbook&lt;/a&gt; with Chad Jones that talks very explicitly about BGP’s and models that deliver them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is there evidence of balanced growth?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/BGP-Empirics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/BGP-Empirics/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of attending the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nottingham.ac.uk/gep/documents/conferences/2015-16/degit/degit-programme.pdf&quot;&gt;DEGIT&lt;/a&gt; conference in Nottingham, UK last week. One of the plenary speakers was Gene Grossman, who talked about a &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.harvard.edu/files/helpman/files/balanced_growth_despite_uzawa_110815gg.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; he is working on with Elhanan Helpman, Ezra Oberfield, and Thomas Sampson. The paper is about “balanced growth”. I spent a good portion of the flight home thinking about the questions they posed, and ended up generating what will probably be two long posts on the subject. This first one was drafted in large part on that flight, having not slept the night before, so bear with me if I ramble a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the main organizing principle in growth economics over the last sixty years has been the “balanced growth path”, or BGP. BGP is really just a name for a set of conditions related to several major pieces of economic data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The growth rate of output per worker is constant over time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The rate of return on capital is constant over time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The share of output paid to capital is constant over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three conditions are part of the the “Kaldor Facts” established in by &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/Kaldor_1957.pdf&quot;&gt;Nicolas Kaldor&lt;/a&gt; in 1957. There are really six stylized facts in his article, but you can kind of boil them down to these three easily. These facts were supported by relatively sparse information gleaned from the period running from the late 19th century up to the 1920’s, and for most of them Kaldor ignored major changes that occurred in the Great Depression. For example, the fact regarding the rate of return is based largely on the 44 years from 1870 to 1914 in the UK. Saying that output per worker was rising steadily was inferred from several (uncited by Kaldor) sources in 1957, when the concept of national income accounting was only about two decades old. This was not a robust empirical exercise, is what I’m trying to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, the question for growth economists became: how must the economy work such that these three are all true in the long run? Subsequently, essentially every model of growth that has been written down has constricted itself to matching these facts. The term BGP is thus something of shorthand notation for saying that a model fits the Kaldor Facts, at least in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But does it make sense to constrict ourselves in this way in thinking about how economies grow? What I want to consider over this post and a planned follow-up is the answer to that question. Here, let me focus on the empirical side of things. The follow-up is going to deal with the theoretical side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take the Kaldor facts as given, then sure, you should write down models that can reproduce them. But should we take the Kaldor facts as given? Like I mentioned above, these are facts gleaned almost exclusively from a period running from the late 19th century into the 1920’s, if that. It seems well worth asking if they continue to be true. If they are not true, or might not be true, then constricting our theories of growth to those having BGP’s is unnecessarily limiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I go through this, I’m trying to take the most skeptical viewpoint I can on balanced growth paths. And this is precisely because I think the BGP is a good way to mentally frame our thinking about growth. The worry is that I (and maybe most growth economists?) are too stuck on the BGP as our organizing principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-growth-of-output-per-worker-constant-over-time&quot;&gt;Is growth of output per worker constant over time?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the most prevalent figure in growth economics plots log GDP per worker in the US over time, usually from 1870 to until roughly 1990-2015, depending on the vintage of the paper you’re talking about. I probably have six or seven versions of it on my laptop in various folders, and one is included below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/cbo_fit_postall.png&quot; alt=&quot;US GDP per capita&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarkable thing about this figure is how consistent the slope is, and the slope (given that this graphs the log of GDP per capita against time) is just the growth rate. That is the first Kaldor fact, presented visually. Even after the disruption of the Great Depression and WWII, the US returned right back to the same trend line (the “linear prediction” dashed line) from before. So for the US, it seems there is very powerful evidence for the first Kaldor fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as is the case with far too many stylized facts, this is just the US. Not every country has such a consistent trend line. The figure below shows four major economies including the US, and you can see that Japan and Germany do not have this same consistent trend (while the UK does). Now, while this makes the first Kaldor fact strictly untrue, this doesn’t necessarily spell the end of the idea of a BGP. As I implied above, a BGP is really a statement about what happens in the long run. Like Germany or Japan after World War II, you could be off of the BGP, but as you can see with both countries they eventually settle into a situation of constant growth rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/figure_3_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Other Countries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;France is a further departure, because it displays not only a shift in the level of the BGP, like Japan, but also a change in the slope. After World War II France move up to a higher level of output per capita (the intercept of the dashed line rose) but also a higher slope, meaning the growth rate was permanently higher. Now, one can still argue that the two separate dashed lines represent BGP’s, but what France demonstrates is that the growth rate itself along a BGP could change. And if it can change for one country, why can’t it change for others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/france.png&quot; alt=&quot;France&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two colleagues of mine, David Papell and Ruxandra Prodan, wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S026499931400251X&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; recently that looked at the presence of BGP’s more formally. For 26 countries they look at whether their path of GDP per capita follows a strict BGP, meaning that over the 139 years of data there is no shift in the level or growth rate of GDP per capita. In essence, they are asking if those 26 countries have graphs that look like the one for the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the US and Canada, the answer is yes, they have a strict BGP. But for the rest of the OECD and the other Asian countries they look at, the answer is no. Each of those countries has a distinct change in the level of GDP per capita (i.e. the intercept of their trend line shifts up or down) or a distinct change in the growth rate of GDP per capita (i.e. the slope of the trend line changes). Some, like France, exhibit changes in both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The counter-argument to these figures is that yes, occassionally there are breaks in the level or growth rate, but in between these breaks economies appear to be on what looks like BGP’s. So it still is worth thinking about models that have BGP’s, because those will be useful in describing lots of the observed behavior in economies. And, models that have BGP’s also describe what sets the level and growth rate of GDP per capita, so we can use those same models to understand what could cause these distinct breaks we see at times in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s call this a qualified “Yes”, with some significant caveats, to the question of whether GDP per capita growth is constant over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-the-rate-of-return-to-capital-constant-over-time&quot;&gt;Is the rate of return to capital constant over time?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second Kaldor fact was a constant rate of return on capital. This was based on information from the UK and US. For the US, Kaldor relied on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.roiw.org/2/2.pdf&quot;&gt;Kuznets&lt;/a&gt; who gave evidence that the return on capital was roughly 3 percent a year between 1919 and 1948.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the return on capital persist over longer periods of time? The issue with answering this is coming up with measures of the return to capital. For Kuznets, it was straightforward, take the share of output paid to capital (as dividends, rents, or interest) and divide it by the capital/output ratio. In other words, take total payments to capital (the share times output) and divide by capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can replicate this with newer data from the BLS. I posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/the-declining-marginal-product-of-capital/&quot;&gt;something&lt;/a&gt; a while back on this very series, and the clear decline in the MPK over the last fifty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_MPK_1960.png&quot; alt=&quot;MPK&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two series in the figure differ in how I calculated the share of output going to capital, but the same story emerges regardless. There was a distinct decline in the return to capital over the post-war period. There is also a distinct level difference in the return with Kuznets. The BLS data indicate a return of 15%-ish in the 1960’s, and the decline still leaves the return at 10% currently, compared to Kuznets’ 3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, maybe this isn’t the right way to measure the return to capital (although it is the way that any model of growth would measure it internally). Kuznets compared his return calculation to bond yields. I grabbed the seasoned corporate Baa bond yield from FRED as a comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_corp_baa_yield.png&quot; alt=&quot;Baa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it isn’t clear that this is constant. If you wanted to say there was a tendency for the corporate rate here to be about 5% over the long run, okay. But that 40-year deviation from 5% between about 1970 and 2010 seems like an abuse of the word “tendency”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have more luck with the S&amp;amp;P earnings yield, which perhaps we could think of as a better measure of the return to capital. I think I got this graph from a Brad DeLong post a while ago, but I don’t have the underlying data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_yield.png&quot; alt=&quot;SP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This travels around a lot as well, but it is easier to squint and see something that looks like a tendency to be around 6-8% over the long run, with a distinct dip in the recent few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, Piketty’s book contained a wealth (see what I did there?) of data on capital/output ratios, which are a key component of calculating the return to capital as in Kuznets. Here’s his plot of the capital/output ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/piketty_ky.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pik cap output&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obviously shows a lot of variation. And unless the share of output paid to capital changes demonstrably over time and in just the right way, this implies that the return to capital showed a significant amount of variation as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Piketty’s evidence on the return to capital shows, at least for the UK, a remarkable stability over long periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/piketty_r.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pik return&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is noticeable here is that it really is the post-war period that is an anomaly, and so maybe the US is in the same boat. Perhaps the decline in the rate of return I showed in the US MPK is just part of recovering back to this long-run flat trend like in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For France, the evidence is less clear about stability, but you can convince yourself, I think, that there is no distinct trend to the return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/piketty_r_france.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pik return France&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it isn’t obvious what to make of Kaldor’s fact regarding rates of return. Are there clear &lt;em&gt;trends&lt;/em&gt; in rates of return? That depends a lot on the time frame you look at. For the US post-war, it sure looks like there is a downward trend. But for the UK and France over time, there are fluctuations but not a clear trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that a qualified “Yes” is quite right. This seems like a weaker set of evidence than we have for the growth rates. It all appears to depend on the time frame you are talking about. So this one makes me nervous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-the-share-of-output-paid-to-capital-constant-over-time&quot;&gt;Is the share of output paid to capital constant over time?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s stick with Piketty for the moment. Part of the story about returns mentioned above involved the share of output paid to capital. And Kaldor took as a fact that this share was roughly constant, or at least did not display a clear trend. Piketty has come data on these shares for several rich countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/piketty_share.png&quot; alt=&quot;Piketty&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks as if the capital share is rising over the last 40 years for all these countries. I pulled BLS data for the US to go back farther, and you can see a similar story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/fig_cap_share.png&quot; alt=&quot;US cap share&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inverse of this is the decline in labor shares. Karabarbounis and Neiman (working paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/gp14879nzbarzju/depreciation.pdf?dl=1&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) have investigated both if and why this is occurring. Grabbing a graph from their paper, you can see the decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/kn_labor.png&quot; alt=&quot;KN labor share&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve got something that suggests the capital share is not constant over time. Whether these deviations are temporary or not is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll go back to qualified “Yes”, in the sense that we just can’t know if the recent increase in capital share is an anomaly or part of a longer-run trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sooooooo&quot;&gt;Sooooooo?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it time to abandon the Kaldor facts on which the whole BGP concept rests? I think this is a case of asking what your null hypothesis is. If the null hypothesis is that the Kaldor facts are &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;, then I don’t think the evidence I’ve got in this post is sufficient to reject that null. Meaning, until we see some kind of crazy trend in the capital share, return to capital, or crazy movements in GDP per capita, we’d keep working with the Kaldor facts and the BGP as an organizing principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you started with a null hypothesis that there were no stylized facts about growth, as if you were Nicolas Kaldor but had all the data available now, would you feel like you could reject the null? That is, would you look at the figures I showed here and conclude that the growth rate of output per worker was constant over time, the rate of return was constant, and the capital share was constant? I’m not sure you would. Those were all qualified “Yesses”, and in some cases very qualified. If you started fresh today, you’d have to do a lot more work to convince people that those were decent approximations of reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the BGP paradigm is that it has become the default null hypothesis, and hence when you see the data above, you’re inclined to assume any deviations are temporary. Are we really looking at the data, or filtering it through our belief in the BGP idea?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m going to do in the next post, which I hope will go up later this week, is work through some of the &lt;em&gt;theoretical&lt;/em&gt; issues in the BGP concept. In short, by taking Kaldor’s facts as given, and forcing our models to have BGP’s, have we been forced to make other assumptions that do not make sense? And are we trying to hard to rescue our existing models, when maybe we should be trying out new ones?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>More on Measured Productivity and the Labor Share</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Cake/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Cake/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mattyglesias&quot;&gt;Matt Yglesias&lt;/a&gt; dug up an old &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/labors-share-profits-and-the-productivity-slowdown/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; of mine about labor’s share of output and the measurement of productivity. The short version was that the decline in labor’s share may be part of the explanation for why measured productivity growth has slowed down in the same period of time. The original post was a bit math-heavy, and several people on Twitter were looking for a more intuitive explanation of what was going on. I was at the beach (sorry, &lt;em&gt;down the shore&lt;/em&gt;) last week, so this response is coming in a little late, but here’s my attempt at explaining how this works. No math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;let-them-measure-cake&quot;&gt;Let them measure cake&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Productivity is just output divided by input(s). “Labor productivity” is output divided by the number of workers (or hours worked). “Total factor productivity” (TFP) or “multifactor productivity” is output divided by an index that measures a combination of inputs, like labor and capital. But it is always output divided by some measure of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue we have is in measuring inputs. For TFP, we divide by an index of inputs. How do you form that index? If it doesn’t conform exactly to how inputs are used in production, then our measure of TFP is going to be influenced by the amount of the inputs we use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analogy I like here is that GDP is like cake, and inputs are like ingredients. It’s easy to measure “total ingredient productivity” (TIP) by dividing the volume of cake by an index of the various ingredients included. Let’s say that index of ingredients is very crude, just the total weight of ingredients used. Add the weight of flour to the weight of the eggs and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I add another cup of flour - which should be around 120 grams - then my index of inputs goes up by 120 grams. My cake volume will probably increase very slightly, and it will end up being kind of crispy and dry. My TIP falls due to a change in the use of one of the inputs. There was no technological change (e.g. no new step in the recipe), and yet TIP changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens because my index of ingredient inputs does not treat flour the same way that the actual recipe (the production function) treats flour. My index treats flour as a perfect substitute for other ingredients, and the cake production function uses flour as something close to a perfect complement to other ingredients. Because of this mismatch, my measure of TIP is mechanically influenced by the amount of ingredients I use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is this kind of mismatch that makes our measure of TFP mechanically influenced by the amount of labor and capital we use. The production function for GDP uses inputs in a way slightly different from how we incorporate them the index of inputs that we divide by to get TFP. Labor’s share of revenue matters here because we often use it to guide us in how to incorporate labor (and implicitly capital) into our index of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If labor’s share of revenues is low (affecting our index of inputs), but labor’s role in production is high (affecting GDP), then measured TFP is affected as well. The low labor revenue share means our input index is &lt;em&gt;understates&lt;/em&gt; labor’s role in production, and hence some of the growth in labor inputs gets picked up as measured TFP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of how we typically construct the input index, if we understate labor’s role, then we &lt;em&gt;overstate&lt;/em&gt; capital’s role. This means we falsely attribute some productivity growth to capital accumulation, and hence measured TFP growth is lower because of our overstatement of capital’s role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the labor share falls, this exacerbates the issue. Because capital tends to accumulate faster than labor (except maybe &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/describing-the-decline-of-capital-per-worker/&quot;&gt;not any more?&lt;/a&gt;), the drag on measured TFP growth from overstating capital’s role is bigger than the boost to measured TFP growth from understating labor’s role. So as labor’s share of revenue falls, so does measured TFP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the original post I went through all this stuff about markups and how those are related to labor’s share. That isn’t necessary to make the direct point that if we misstate labor’s (and capital’s) importance in our input index, then inputs matter for measured TFP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-technical-but-still-no-math&quot;&gt;More technical, but still no math&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re happy with the above explanation, feel free to stop there. This section just gives you a little better idea of what I mean by “misstating” labor and capital’s role in production, and how that influences measured TFP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with labor productivity, GDP divided by labor. I think most readers would be fine with the idea that both technological improvements &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; increases in capital raise labor productivity. The first is using a better “recipe”, and the second is increasing the other ingredients besides labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intuitively, it seems obvious that capital matters for labor productivity, because we have this notion that they are complements to some extent. But the mechanical reason it matters is that GDP - the numerator in labor productivity - has some positive elasticity with respect to capital. At the same time, the denominator in labor productivity - labor - has a zero elasticity with respect to capital. Hence our measure of labor productivity responds positively to changes in the amount of capital, as the numerator rises while the denominator doesn’t change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology improvements also increase GDP holding constant inputs, so labor productivity also rises due to technological improvements. This would be like coming up with a better recipe for cake (whisk the egg whites separately?) that used the same inputs as the old recipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we measure labor productivity, we are thus measuring some combination of capital accumulation and technological improvement. If capital accumulation slowed down (which it looks like it did recently), so would measured growth in labor productivity, and vice versa. Labor productivity isn’t a pure measure of technological improvement. And this is because the elasticity of output with respect to capital in the numerator is different than the elasticity of the input, labor, with respect to capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, now let’s take on total factor productivity (TFP). Recall that all this involves is dividing GDP by an index of inputs, rather than just labor. When we form that index of inputs, we have to specify the elasticity of the index with respect to each input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we pick exactly the right elasticity for capital in our input index, then in reponse to an increase in capital, our index in the denominator will rise by exactly the same percent as GDP rises in the numerator. The effects will cancel, and there will be no effect of the increase in capital on our measured TFP. This same logic works for labor as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the exact right elasticities in our index of inputs, TFP will &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; respond to changes in technology. It wouldn’t tell us exactly what the new technology involved (whisk the egg whites separately?), but it would tell us that this new technology raised GDP holding all inputs constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we even talk about whether we get these elasticities right, what happens if we get them &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;? Then the elasticity of GDP with respect to an input (in the numerator) doesn’t match the elasticity of our index with respect to the input (in the denominator), and our measure of TFP is not neutral with respect to changes in that input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we understate an elasticity in our index, then any increase in the associated input will increase measured TFP. This is the exact analogue of the situation I described with capital growth and labor productivity. There, we understated the elasticity with respect to capital in our denominator (i.e. we set it to zero), and so more capital meant higher measured labor productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if we overstate an elasticity in our index, than an increase in the associated input will &lt;em&gt;decrease&lt;/em&gt; measured TFP. If our index says that the elasticity for labor is 0.8, but the elasticity of GDP with respect to labor is actually 0.6, then measured TFP will &lt;em&gt;fall&lt;/em&gt; (with an elasticity of -0.2) as we add workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that getting the elasticities in our index wrong means that measured TFP deviates from true technological growth. But it doesn’t mean that technological growth itself is affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why might we be getting the elasticities in our index wrong? For several reasons. The elasticities embedded in the numerator, GDP, are the actual elasticities of output with respect to each input. The elasticities are like a number than captures the nature of the chemical reactions between flour, baking powder, sugar, milk, eggs, and the other inputs. In the cake example we might be able to figure these out by doing a bunch of chemistry experiments. In the economy, we’d have to know the exact engineering specifications for every business in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we don’t know the exact elasticities, we try to infer them from what we can observe. This is like trying to infer the chemical reactions involved in baking from observing how different cakes come out of the oven. Based on some minimal economic theorizing - namely that firms try to minimize their costs and face competitive factor markets - we think that the elasticity for an input should be equal to its share of total costs. If total wages are 60% of total costs, then this would imply the elasticity was 0.6, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a whole lot of reasons this might be getting things wrong. If factor markets are not competitive, then the share of costs paid to an input would not necessarily equal its elasticity. If firms are not cost minimizing, then we’d have the same problem. We might substitute an input’s share of &lt;em&gt;revenues&lt;/em&gt; in place of it’s share of &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt;, and this would only be correct if we also assumed firms were competitive and earned zero profits. We might assume that capital’s share of revenues was just one minus labor’s share, which again only works if firms are competitive and earn zero profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is almost no way that we are getting the elasticities in our index of inputs exactly right. Even the BLS, who tries really hard to get good estimates of labor’s share of costs, isn’t getting them right. And because we are not getting the elasticities in our index right, our measures of TFP growth are influenced by growth in capital and labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I did in the original post was to look at a particular way in which we are not getting the elasticities right. The crucial part of that was assuming that capital’s elasticity in our input index was equal to one minus labor’s elasticity. Now we’re back to the situation I described in the prior section, where if labor’s share in revenues is low, then we are probably understating labor’s role in our input index, and overstating capital’s role in our input index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because capital tends to grow faster than labor, the effect of overstating capital’s role (which lowers TFP growth) outweighs the effect of understating labor’s role (which raises TFP growth). Hence TFP growth is lowered by some amount, and as labor’s share falls, this gets worse. TFP growth will be smaller than technological growth, and the gap will grow as labor’s share falls. Slower TFP growth doesn’t necessarily imply that technological growth is slow. It may be that our measure of TFP growth isn’t just picking up technology, but also changes in inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-we-probably-care-anyway&quot;&gt;But we probably care anyway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From everything I described, it sounds like measured TFP growth is just wrong, so why should we care about it? If we could generate an index of inputs that used the right elasticities, then our measure of TFP would be exactly equal to a measure of technology. And that’s what we care about, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not necessarily. Susanto Basu and John Fernald theorized in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/eecrev/v46y2002i6p963-991.html&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; that we should actually care about measured TFP even if it is not exactly a measure of technology. In their setting, we have information on both labor’s share of revenues and capital’s share of revenues (so we are not just assuming it is one minus labor’s share). If we use these revenue shares as our estimates of the elasticities in our input index, then they will be less than the elasticities in the production function for GDP, and given this understatement, &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; capital and labor growth will add to measured TFP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds wrong again, just in a different way. But what Basu and Fernald point out is that while not a good measure of technological growth, measured TFP growth would be a good measure of &lt;em&gt;welfare&lt;/em&gt; growth. Their theory is that what matters for welfare is both the quantity of consumption goods we provide (which comes from generating GDP) but also the cost of providing the inputs (spending time working, or saving output rather than consuming it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revenue shares of labor and capital may not accurately reflect their role in production, but they do accurately reflect the cost of providing those inputs. A low labor share means lower wages, for example, which means that the benefit of providing labor is low and we get less labor provided. Similarly for capital. If the revenue share is low then the benefit of providing capital is low, and hence we get less capital accumulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we do get welfare from the things that labor and capital help produce. And what Basu and Fernald point out is that the value of those things is higher than the cost of providing the inputs when the revenue shares are low. Which means that any additional provision of labor or capital actually adds to welfare, even if it doesn’t change technology. Measured TFP picks up this benefit of providing additional inputs on welfare, and hence is more important than just technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean that the value of output is higher than the cost of providing inputs? Think of when we have increasing returns to scale. If we doubled our input provision, we’d get more than twice as much output, and hence we get more value in output than we paid in costs of input. In my setting here, with IRS the elasticities in the production function add up to more than one, while the revenue shares used in the input index can only ever add up to one. And hence measured TFP captures both technological improvement as well as some adjustment for increasing supplies of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, we might not have increasing returns, but we may have firms with market power. In that case, firms are charging a markup over marginal cost, meaning the price you pay for output is higher than the marginal cost of producing it. Again, if we added inputs, the value of output produced would be higher than the cost of providing it. In terms of accounting, the elasticities in the production function may add up to one (constant returns), but with markups some of the output is paid out as profits/rents, so the revenue shares of labor and capital have to add up to less than one. Again, we understate the elasticities in our input index, and measured TFP rises with additional inputs of either capital or labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the source, measured TFP growth is a better metric for welfare growth than just technological growth. With either IRS or market power, we &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to use a measure of TFP that is “wrong” in order to capture welfare gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, a falling labor share could also lower measured TFP growth (and hence welfare growth), but it is a little fuzzier whether this follows for sure. It depends on how markups respond, and whether the lower labor share is offset by increased profit shares or increased capital shares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The - very long in coming - conclusion is that measured TFP growth is not “wrong”. There is information in measured TFP growth even if it does not precisely measure technology growth. And measured TFP growth can be influenced by the labor share. When that falls, it can pull down measured TFP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How big is that effect? That’s a different question, and something that I’m playing around with at getting a better handle on. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Did Real Manufacturing Output Grow Faster than We Thought?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Manuf-Share/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Manuf-Share/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing this post was kind of depressing, because all it did was highlight for me how &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; things I’ve got in my reading list to think about and digest. I was reading Brad DeLong’s recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://equitablegrowth.org/equitablog/expenditure-shares-price-measurement-and-true-relative-labor-productivity-growth-in-post-wwii-manufacturing-what-the-aggregate-deta-suggest/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on manufacturing’s share in output, and realized that I’ve got about four more posts from Brad stacked up in the queue, along with all the other stuff I’ve been meaning to read more carefully. So, respectfully, Brad, please stop saying interesting things related to growth. I need time to catch up. How about a nice run of posts about the history of monetary policy or something like that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeLong’s motivating fact(s) are about manufacturing’s share of output, both in nominal and real terms. He grabbed the following from the BEA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/6823742/delong1.png&quot; alt=&quot;DeLong Manuf Graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and developed the path of the real share by making a crude calculation. As he freely admits in the post, this isn’t exactly how one would want to calculate the real share of manufacturing in output. But, for the purposes of his post, I don’t think it makes a huge difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, he establishes three main facts that he wants to understand. First, note that the nominal share of manufacturing in nominal output has been declining steadily since the late 1940’s. He gets a value of -1.4% per year as the growth rate of the nominal share. Second, the relative price of manufactured goods (compared to aggregate output) has been declining by -1.4% per year as well. This gives us the final fact, that the real share of manufacturing in real output has not grown (or shrunk) over time, as you can see in the figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeLong then proceeds to ask himself how to reconcile all of these three facts. What must be true about demand and/or technological change to explain this? And he will come to a conclusion that we are probably not measuing the price decline, and hence the real share of manufacturing, correctly. That will in turn imply that real economic growth has probably been understated over this entire period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think DeLong is too quick to make that conclusion, and that there is in fact a way to understand his three facts that does not imply economic growth has been understated. My brain moves a little slower than DeLong’s, so here’s how I worked through his reasoning. First, let the following be the demand curve for real manufacturing goods, in log terms&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\ln Q^M = \epsilon_I \ln Y - \epsilon_P \ln P^M + \ln D^M&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Q^M\inline&quot;/&gt; is the quantity of real manufactured goods, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y\inline&quot;/&gt; is real income, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P^M\inline&quot;/&gt; is the relative price of manufactured goods. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_I\inline&quot;/&gt; is the income elasticity of demand for manufactured goods, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_P\inline&quot;/&gt; the price elasticity of demand. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?D\inline&quot;/&gt; is just a “demand shifter” to account for anything changing demand for manufactured goods that isn’t related to either real income or the relative price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\ln P^M\inline&quot;/&gt; to both sides, and subtract &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\ln Y\inline&quot;/&gt; from both sides. That leaves me with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\ln Q^M + \ln P^M - \ln Y = (\epsilon_I-1) \ln Y + (1 - \epsilon_P) \ln P^M + \ln D^M.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left-hand side is, if you combine the log terms, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\ln Q^M P^M/Y\inline&quot;/&gt;, or the log of manufacturing’s share in nominal income. Also, it’s important to note that the left-hand side can be written as &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\ln Q^M/Y + \ln P^M\inline&quot;/&gt;. This is the log of manufacturing’s share of &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; income, plus the relative price level of manufactured goods. So it has both the nominal and real share of manufacturing in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To work with this in DeLong’s terms, it will be easiest to talk about growth rates of all of these items. And with everything written in log terms, getting growth rates is straightforward. Let &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{q}^M\inline&quot;/&gt; indicate the growth rate of real manufacturing goods, and define a similar “hat” term for each element of the equation. We’ve got&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(\hat{q}^M - \hat{y}) + \hat{p}^M  = (\epsilon_I-1) \hat{y} + (1 - \epsilon_P) \hat{p}^M + \hat{d}^M.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that I’ve done a little rearranging there. Inside the parentheses on the left is the growth rate of manufacturing’s &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; share of &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; income. That gets added to the growth rate of the relative price of manufacturing to deliver the growth rate of manufacturing’s share of nominal income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to DeLong’s pieces of information. First, the growth rate of the nominal share of manufacturing is -1.4% per year. This means that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(\hat{q}^M - \hat{y}) + \hat{p}^M = -0.014\inline&quot;/&gt;. Second, he says that the growth rate of the relative price of manufactured goods is also -1.4% per year, meaning that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{p}^M = -0.014\inline&quot;/&gt;. Last, the data said that the growth rate of the manufacturing’s real share of real output was zero, meaning that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(\hat{q}^M - \hat{y}) = 0\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then he goes to work trying to understand how all of those facts can be true at the same time, given the above equation. Here are two possibilities that DeLong dismisses as not making sense - and I think he’s right to dismiss these possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the income elasticity is 1 and the price elasticity is 1, then &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(\hat{q}^M - \hat{y}) + \hat{p}^M = \hat{d}^M\inline&quot;/&gt;. Which means that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0 + -0.014 = \hat{d}^M\inline&quot;/&gt;. In other words, there must have been a sustained shift in the demand curve for manufactured goods over the last 70 years. We just decided we didn’t like manufactured stuff as much any more. DeLong says this doesn’t make sense. That’s probably right, but hold onto that thought about a shift in the demand for manufactured goods - it will show up again later in the post.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the income elasticity is 1 and the price elasticity is 0, then &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(\hat{q}^M - \hat{y}) + \hat{p}^M  = \hat{p}^M + \hat{d}^M\inline&quot;/&gt;. Then, plugging in the facts, we have that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{d}^M = 0\inline&quot;/&gt;. DeLong says this helps, because it doesn’t require us to assume any kind of exogenous shift in demand for manufactured goods. But, it does require us to assume that the price elasticity is zero, which DeLong says doesn’t make sense because manufactured stuff is useful, so you’d expect that demand would go up if the price fell. That’s probably right, too - the price elasticity probably isn’t zero.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeLong then asks how this is all supposed to work if we instead assume that the income elasticity is 1, the price elasticity is something more reasonable like 1/2, and we dismiss the idea of a purely exogenous shift in manufacturing demand. And this leads him to a problem with reconciling the data. With those assumptions, it means that the growth rate equation is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(\hat{q}^M - \hat{y}) + \hat{p}^M  = 0.5 \hat{p}^M.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this equation, it is impossible for DeLong’s facts to all be true simultaneously. That is, we can’t have the growth rate of the real share (in the parentheses) be zero, the growth rate of the nominal share (the entire left-hand side) be equal to -0.014, while at the same time &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{p}^M = -0.014\inline&quot;/&gt; on the right-hand side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to fix this? DeLong suggests that both his second and third facts are probably wrong. If the relative price of manufacturing actually fell by 2.8% per year, so &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{p}^M = -0.028\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; share of manufacturing actually &lt;em&gt;grew&lt;/em&gt; by 1.4% a year, so &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(\hat{q}^M - \hat{y}) = 0.014\inline&quot;/&gt;, then everything works out. Specifically, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0.014 + -0.028 = 0.5\times-0.028\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if we assume a reasonable price elasticity of 1/2, and if we take the growth rate of the nominal share of manufacturing (which is relatively easy to measure) as given, then we cannot do anything but conclude that the growth rate of the real share of manufacturing was in fact 1.4% per year, not zero. Over the roughly 70 years DeLong is talking about, that means the real share of manufacturing should be about 2.5 times higher than we observe in his graph. It would be about 28% of real output today, not 12%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the relative price of manufacturing falling twice as fast as we thought, and real manufacturing output growing relative to real output, this implies that we really are better off than we thought. I won’t get into the mechanics of this calculation here, as the post is already getting long, but it would imply that real output growth was actually about 0.3 percentage points higher per year over this period. Real output grew at about 3 percent per year, so that’s a pretty big difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here is where I think DeLong’s gone one step too far. He focuses on the price elasticity, but assumes the &lt;em&gt;income&lt;/em&gt; elasticity is equal to one in all cases. His alternative scenario where growth in the real manufacturing share and faster true growth in real output is contingent on this assumption. Let me propose an alternative way of reconciling the numbers that doesn’t imply anything is mismeasured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s use DeLong’s price elasticity of 1/2. I don’t have any strong reason to quibble with that number. And let’s retain the assumption that there is no exogenous demand shift. But rather than assuming the income elasticity is one, let’s leave it as a free variable. So now the growth rate equation is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(\hat{q}^M - \hat{y}) + \hat{p}^M  = (\epsilon_I-1) \hat{y} + 0.5 \hat{p}^M.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the original facts as correct, and let me add one additional fact. The growth rate of real income reported by the BEA over the same time period as DeLong is working with is 3% per year. This is the growth rate of aggregate real income, not per capita. Putting all this in our equation gives me&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;0 + -0.014 = (\epsilon_I-1) 0.03 + 0.5 \times -0.014&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and everything makes sense if &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\epsilon_I = 0.77\inline&quot;/&gt;. That is, if the income elasticity of demand for manufactured goods is a little less than one. An elasticity less than one means that if your income goes up by 10%, your expenditure on manufactured goods rises by less than 10%. It goes up, but not by a similar percent. This income elasticity less than one acts a lot like the “demand shift” that DeLong dismisses in his first scenario. If you like, I’ve just given a very specific form to that demand shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that reasonable? I sure think it is. It’s entirely consistent with the literature on structural change for rich countries like the US. Income elasticities for manufacturing less than one reflect people’s preferences having some kind of “limit” on the amount of manufactured goods they want to consume. I’ve used the refrigerator example before. If we get even more productive at producing refrigerators, then they will become less costly and/or become higher quality. But that doesn’t mean I’ll buy another one. I’ve got two at my house already, and it would take a &lt;em&gt;massive&lt;/em&gt; drop in price or increase in quality to get me to buy another one, even just to replace the existing ones. Similarly, my income is due to go up in October thanks to the raise pool at UH this year. I’m not using it to buy a fridge, or probably many manufactured goods at all. I’ll use it to help pay for a trip we’re taking in December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the original facts that DeLong lays out are entirely consistent, including the fact that the real share of manufacturing in output has stayed constant over time. We don’t need to assume that prices fell faster than we thought, or that real manufacturing output grew faster than we thought. And thus output growth isn’t understated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeLong could still be right, of course. This is all dependent on competing assumptions about the size of elasticities. If the income elasticity is actually one, then DeLong’s story is more plausible than mine. I think I’m on the right track, but I don’t have the time at the moment to collect various references to back up my income elasticity argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last interesting note. The income elasticity doesn’t have to be constant over time. In fact, I’d guess it was closer to one, if not &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; than one, back in the early part of the period DeLong considers, the 1940’s and 1950’s. If the income elasticity is bigger than one, then this means DeLong’s adjustments for that period would be even bigger than what he calculated in his post. I have to think harder about this, but I’m wondering if this is some way to reconcile/explain Robert Gordon’s facts about rapid measured productivity growth in those decades relative to the current period of time. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
