<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <atom:link href="https://growthecon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>https://growthecon.com/</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 22:58:55 -0500</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>Where did all the investment go?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Investment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Investment/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The fact that economic growth has slowed in the last few decades is not news, at least not on this blog. And I’ve been through a series of possible explanations over the course of the last few years. One bit of data that I played around with a few years ago was the decline in the growth rate of capital per worker. In this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/describing-the-decline-of-capital-per-worker/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; I looked at some figures using BLS data that showed the amount of capital per worker was &lt;em&gt;declining&lt;/em&gt; in 2010-2013. That was unprecedented, as even during recessions in the past it was the case that capital per worker kept growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new working paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/2_gutierrezphilippon.pdf&quot;&gt;German Gutierrez and Thomas Philippon&lt;/a&gt; (GP) has taken on this same topic, only in much more detail, and with a lot of effort put into understanding &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; investment has been low recently. Moreover, they document that investment by firms has been falling over a longer period of time, coincident in large part with the productivity slowdown of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;investment-is-lower-than-youd-expect-given-profits&quot;&gt;Investment is lower than you’d expect given profits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GP start by documenting that firms remain profitable over time, but that their investments are declining over time. This first figure shows the net operating return on capital for non-financial firms (which do the bulk of non-residential investment). “Business” here is the umbrella covering both corporate and non-corporate firms. What is apaprent from GP’s first figure is that the net operating return on capital has remained constant, or grown, over time. For corporations, it is about 10% throughout this period, while for non-corporate firms it has gone up from about 20% to almost 30%. So the decline in investment by firms is not because they are unprofitable. Even the financial crisis in 2009 only produces a slight dip in the net operating returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net operating return on capital&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second figure shows the crux of the story in GP. Net investment (investment spending minus deprecation) relative to net operating surplus appears to have shifted down after 2000. Prior to that, net investment averaged roughly 20% of net operating surplus, while afterwards it averaged only about 10%. I’m not sure how hard to think about the spike in this ratio in the 1990’s - this may be a temporary thing driven by the same technology surge that appears to have driven productivity growth - but you might be able to argue that the average net investment rate got down to 10% as early as 1990. Regardless, it is clear that the investment rate out of operating surplus fell, and stayed low, in the 2000’s. This, derived from more finely-grained data, is the equivalent of what I was talking about in my post from a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net investment relative to net operating surplus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as GP point out, it is not the case that we should expect this ratio of net investment to net operating surplus to be constant over time. Firms are (presumably) optimizing their investment behavior to maximize profits, and based on changing conditions it might make sense to invest more or less of their net operating surplus. What GP work through is a standard model of firm behavior, and link net investment to Tobin’s Q. This metric is, roughly, the market value of a firm relative to the replacement cost of its capital. If Q is more than 1, then the firm should be investing enough to &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; its capital stock, because market value they get from having capital is more than what it costs to install it. If Q is less than one, the firm should let its capital stock run down (allow depreciation to outweigh investment) as the they are not generating as much market value with their capital as they would pay to replace it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two measures of Q&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation, then, for the decline in net investment relative to net operating surplus is just that Tobin’s Q fell. And Tobin’s Q would fall if people expected particularly low future earnings (and hence gave firms lower market values) or if the replacement cost of capital was rising. But as GP show, Q wasn’t falling. It was &lt;em&gt;rising&lt;/em&gt;, at least for corporate firms. The two measures of Q differ by how exactly GP calculate it, as it isn’t obvious how to treat a set of miscellaneous assets and liabilities at firms in order to come up with the market value part of the Q ratio. Regardless, however Q is measured, it is now relatively high compared to the 1980’s, and only lags the very high values seen in the late 1990’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net investment versus Q ratio&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GP then use the data on investment rates and Q from 1990 to 2001 to get a baseline relationship of the two. Given that relationship, they look at what the net investment rate &lt;em&gt;would have been&lt;/em&gt; given the Q values we had in the 2000’s, if investment had continued to follow that 1990-2001 relationship. In the above figure, this is plotted as the orange dashed line. Compared to that is the solid green line, which is the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; net investment rate. You can see that starting in 2000 the observed investment rate is always &lt;em&gt;below&lt;/em&gt; the predicted investment rate, and sometimes by substantial amounts. Based on this, GP conclude that firms are under-investing compared to how they used to. This, despite the fact that they are profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blame-it-on-concentration-and-institutional-ownership&quot;&gt;Blame it on concentration and institutional ownership&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; are firms investing less given their Q ratio and profitability? GP go through an extensive list of possible explanations, which I will not repeat here. Let me jump ahead to the two explanations that hold up across all of their analysis: concentration and institutional ownership. Before I get on to that, let me say that their analysis consists of regressions of net investment rates at either aggregate, industry, or firm level on various sets of control variables. In each case, they control for Q itself, to capture the natural fluctuations in net investment rates. The other control variables are there to see if they are significantly &lt;em&gt;correlated&lt;/em&gt; with net investment rates. GP have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www8.gsb.columbia.edu/faculty-research/sites/faculty-research/files/finance/Macro%20Lunch/IK_Comp_v1.pdf&quot;&gt;companion paper&lt;/a&gt; which does more work trying to see if those significant correlations are in fact causal. For the time being, let’s just hang in there with the correlations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across all these regressions, what keeps showing up is a significant correlation between net investment rates and measures of concentration and measures of institutional ownership, while other possible correlations are insignificant or disappear once you control for other variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For concentration, what GP mean is fewer firms within small sub-industries, implying that each remaining firm has possibly more market power. At the aggregate level, the following figure shows that the rate of firm entry and exit has declined over time, consistent with all the evidence that the John Haltiwanger-led posse of researchers has been banging on for several years. Less entry means fewer new competitors entering, and less exit means fewer firms are being forced out of business. This is consistent with higher concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Establishment exit and entry rates&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would concentration limit investment? The simple intuition is that if you don’t have to worry about competing with anyone, why bother to blow any money investing in a better product? Think of a cable company (&lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt; Comcast &lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt;) which has a monopoly in a local market. What incentive do they have to either upgrade their technology to make it more reliable or faster, and what incentive do they have to invest in, say, more repair vans and extra technicians? None, because they know you can’t go anywhere. Be careful to not run too far in the other direction, however. If firms have &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt; market power, they also will have no incentive to invest, because any advantage they get will be immediately competed away. Somewhere in there is some kind of market power/concentration level that maximizes firms incentives to invest (and innovate, by the way). GP’s results suggest we are on the “back side” of the curve, and increasing concentration is leading to less investment (i.e. more Comcasts) rather than creating incentives for firms to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second significant correlation GP find is with institutional ownership of firms, which can include mutual funds and pension funds. Since 1980, these institutional investors have taken on larger and larger stakes in corporations, to the point that the average firm has about 60% ownership by institutions as opposed to individuals. I’ll admit to not being quite clear on what a “transient” institution means, but the “quasi-indexers” are things like actual index funds as well as widely-diversified mutual funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp10b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Institutional ownership&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the share of quasi-indexers rises, GP find, the rate of net investment falls. Now, you can tell yourself a lot of stories about this, both good and bad. The bad is that quasi-indexers are pushing firms to think only about short-term ((e.g. quarterly) results, and as such firms are loath to spend on long-term investments. The good is that quasi-indexers are pushing management to be more thoughtful about exactly what they invest in, which would imply that the high rates of net investment before were probably &lt;em&gt;too high&lt;/em&gt;. It isn’t obvious which one of those interpretations is correct, on the face of it. The prima facie evidence would be that the growth rate of GDP has fallen in the same period in which the net investment rate has fallen, suggesting the bad interpretation is correct. But there could be other forces at work that kept the growth rate high in the 1980’s, even though the net investment rate was too high. So don’t pull out the torches and pitchforks just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gp10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Buybacks and payouts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the intepretation of the institutional ownership, what GP do document is that share buybacks have climbed over this period. Mechanically, spending more on doing share buybacks means less money left over for net investment. It appears that firms, since the early 1980’s, have been using more of their net operating surplus to buy back existing shares (driving up the market value for existing owners) and less on investment. The total payouts/assets in this last figure include buybacks and dividends, and after 1982 you can see that the trend upward in total payouts/assets is driven by an increase in buybacks. GP note in the figure 1982 as an important point because this is when the SEC passed a rule (10b-18) allowing companies to repurchase their own shares on the open market without any regulatory limit. Prior to that, there were restrictions on how much they could repurchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a major shareholder of a firm, you can think of two major ways of making money off your holding. First, you could pursue long-term investments to grow the business and/or expand your market. This would raise the value of your shares by increasing the assets of the firm. Second, you could get the firm to buy back existing shares, driving up their price, and the value of your shares would increase proportionately. This second strategy is faster (you don’t need to wait to install the capital) and arguably less risky, because you don’t have to make a commitment to a new plant or location that may or may not prove to be profitable. Of course, you could go back and argue again that firms were over-investing in the past, and that the buybacks allow those shareholder who were bought out to reinvest their money in higher-return projects. Again, the prima facie evidence is working against you here, but that doesn’t mean you’re wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note here is that GP look separately at the effect of concentration and institutional ownership on capital expenditures (e.g. physical equipment) and R&amp;amp;D spending. Higher concentration and more institutional ownership are correlated with lower rates of spending on both. The decline in investment they document is not just for physical equipment (which perhaps one could argue is becoming less relevant for production) but also for R&amp;amp;D (which one could not argue is becoming less relevant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-it-really-matter-for-growth&quot;&gt;Does it really matter for growth?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last section of GP covers the implications of this for growth. I’m not going to go through their work in detail, as they are trying to line it up with some work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/fernaldtextsp17bpea.pdf&quot;&gt;Fernald, Hall, Stock, and Watson&lt;/a&gt;, and that gets more complicated than I want to cover in a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But GP do sneak in an interesting point in their discussion about the importance of falling investment for growth. If we think that the underlying growth rate of productivity has fallen, which is what appears in the data regarding productivity growth, then this implies that the long-run capital/output ratio should &lt;em&gt;rise&lt;/em&gt;. For those of you who grok the Solow model, the capital/output ratio is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K/Y = s/(n+\delta+g)\inline&quot;/&gt; in steady state. Lower g, higher K/Y ratio. Except that we do not see a higher K/Y ratio over time. It has remained relatively constant, even as the trend growth rate of productivity has fallen. So something else must be going on, and one possibility is that “s” has fallen. In the Solow model, that “s” is the share of output that is turned into investment goods (“saved”) every period. Consistent with the GP story, if s has fallen at the same time g has fallen, then the K/Y ratio will remain roughly constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that the growth rate of GDP gets pulled down even more than it would be through just the decline in g. If s stayed constant, then the drop in g would lower the growth rate of GDP, but the increase in the K/Y ratio would offset that by a little. With the coincident drop in s, we don’t get that offset, and so the effect of the drop in g is particularly pronounced. GP speculate that increased market power of firms can explain why s dropped at the same time as g. That story is consistent with the data that is accumulating, for sure. I have not worked through their companion paper on causality in detail yet, so I can’t offer any opinion on whether increased concentration or market power appears to &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; the decline in s. For now, let’s leave it out there as a very plausible story for what has occurred. Whatever the causality, their initial evidence is clear that there has been a decline in net investment, and that warrants attention if we’re trying to account for why the growth rate of GDP has fallen over the last few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why don't tax cuts boost growth?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxing-GDP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxing-GDP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Relative to current events, this probably seems less important at the moment, and a week or so too late, but the tax cut proposed by th Trump administration is still kicking around. There have been any number of responses to it, and responses in particular to the claim that it will “supercharge” economic growth, and ultimately pay for itself. In short, it won’t do either of those things, which is the conclusion you come to after reviewing all the evidence available. I did so here, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxes-Growth/&quot;&gt;prior post&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/posteverything/wp/2017/09/28/i-helped-create-the-gop-tax-myth-trump-is-wrong-tax-cuts-dont-equal-growth/&quot;&gt;Bruce Bartlett&lt;/a&gt; just posted an article where he also comes to that conclusion, and recants his earlier stand in the 1980’s pushing the whole “tax cuts increase growth” line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is not to rehash the arguments and evidence showing that tax cuts do not increase growth. Rather, I want to think a little about &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they do not increase growth. Because the claim that they do &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; right, but fails in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with some basics. If you want to raise economic growth - meaning an increase in real GDP - then you need to increase the amount of capital, labor, and/or productivity. Whether that is pulling new capital, labor, or innovations into the economy, or putting idle capital, labor, and innovations back to work is irrelevant. You want to increase the inputs to increase GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of economics is that people respond to incentives. In the case of inputs, the incentives to provide them are the returns they earn, like wages, dividends or interest, or profits. If you tax those returns, that lowers the returns, and people will provide less labor, capital, or innovations. So if you lower that tax, the idea is that people will provide &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; labor, capital, or innovation. Nothing here is rocket science. Why does it not work the way we think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;small-elasticities&quot;&gt;Small elasticities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think that if you lower the tax rate, and hence raise the returns to inputs, we should get more of them. But to “supercharge” growth in GDP, or to have any appreciable effect on GDP at all, you need that the elasticity of that input supply with respect to those returns is really big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For labor, there appears to be good evidence that this elasticity is in fact &lt;em&gt;small&lt;/em&gt;. There is not some pent-up store of workers and human capital out there that is just a 35% tax bracket away from getting off their ass and going to work. This labor supply elasticity is found to be essentially zero in almost every case, with the exception of married women. You can see some citations on this in the review paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/jeclit/v50y2012i1p3-50.html&quot;&gt;Saez, Slemrod, and Giertz&lt;/a&gt; (SSG).  With an elasticity close to zero, no matter how much you lower the tax rate, and raise the return to labor (i.e. the wage), you can’t induce a substantial increase in labor supply. And without a substantial increase in labor supply, you don’t get a big increase in GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the capital side, this is tougher to estimate because while it is easy to assert that reported wages are payments for real labor, it is much harder to say what part of reported business income is a payment to “capital”. Dividends are probably one of the cleanest things to look at, as they are direct payments to stockholders. But when &lt;a href=&quot;https://eml.berkeley.edu/~yagan/DividendTax.pdf&quot;&gt;Yagan&lt;/a&gt; looked at the 2003 dividend tax cut, he found there was no effect on corporate investment (i.e. real capital inputs). In other words, the elasticity of real capital inputs to the tax rate was zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For innovation, there is some better evidence of an effect of taxation on R&amp;amp;D activity (although we have to be careful to distinguish between R&amp;amp;D activity and innovation itself). &lt;a href=&quot;http://economics.mit.edu/files/12817&quot;&gt;Dechezlepretre, Einio, Martin, Nguyen, and Van Reenan&lt;/a&gt; have a working paper that uses a change in the threshold for qualifying for an R&amp;amp;D tax credit in the UK on both R&amp;amp;D spending &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; patenting, meaning they are trying to see an effect on actual innovation. They find significant effects of R&amp;amp;D tax incentives on R&amp;amp;D and patenting. Now, tax incentives (like an actual tax credit or allowing firms to write off R&amp;amp;D spending) are not exactly the same as tax rates. And the current tax proposal, so far as I can tell, does not include a specific change to R&amp;amp;D incentives. Changing the marginal tax rate on individual income or corporate income is not the same as providing R&amp;amp;D tax incentives. But, if you are looking for an avenue for tax policy to spur growth, then creating incentives for R&amp;amp;D and innovation appears more plausible than lowering tax rates on labor and capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-tax-financial-flows-not-inputs&quot;&gt;We tax financial flows, not inputs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing reducing the impact of tax cuts on GDP is that taxes are not levied on only the transactions that are part of GDP, they are levied on all kinds of transactions. Think of the fact that every year there are billions (and maybe trillions) of individual transactions that take place in the economy. &lt;em&gt;Some&lt;/em&gt; of those transactions involve payment for a real input like labor or capital, which means they are part of GDP. But &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of those transactions are purely financial, and so are not. But the tax code does not make this distinction; you are not taxed only on your transactions that contribute to GDP, you are taxed on all (okay, most) of your transactions where you receive some money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break this down to four different kinds of transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taxed, and income is from providing a real input. Your paycheck is an example. You provide a real input (labor) to your employer, and hence this income is part of GDP. The income you earn is also subject to taxation. So if you lower the tax rate on this income, you presumably will supply more labor, which will raise GDP. As we saw above, this response would be small for both labor and capital, so GDP would not go up by much. Lower taxes on R&amp;amp;D or innovation might have a more tangible effect.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Untaxed, and income does not come from providing a real input. Think of a small gift of cash, under the IRS threshold, from your grandparents to you. This is income, in the sense that you have an inflow of money, but it is not in return for a real input. It is untaxed because it happens to be small in size.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Untaxed, and income is from providing a real input. You could think of small scale payments for work that fall below IRS reporting thresholds, like babysitting or some home services. Now, because they do not have to be reported to the IRS, they are untaxed, but its also likely they don’t get picked up and &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; as part of GDP. But technically, because they involve someone providing a real input like labor, this income &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be measured as part of GDP. Regardless, because they are untaxed, lowering tax rates would do nothing to change the real inputs people provide here; your babysitter is not going to offer to do a 2nd night a week if the marginal tax rate falls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taxed, and income does not come from providing a real input. Here we’ve got a whole world of financial transactions. If you buy shares of stock for cash, there is no real input provided, so this transaction does not add to GDP. But, this transaction is taxed, in the sense that the capital gain to the seller is subject to tax. If you lower tax rates, then you will get more of these financial transactions, but that will not add anything to GDP. [A side note is that the &lt;em&gt;commissions&lt;/em&gt; on this trade &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; get counted as part of GDP, because they are made for providing a real service.]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big reason that tax cuts do not boost growth in GDP is that tax cuts apply to transactions of type 4, as well as type 1. Lowering the tax rate should increase transactions of both types In practice, the elasticities involved in type 1 transactions are small, so there is little change in &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; inputs provided by tax cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But tax cuts may have a big effect on those type 4, financial, transactions. Those type 4 transactions may boost &lt;em&gt;taxable incomes&lt;/em&gt; by making the transactions more attractive, but have no impact on the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; provision of inputs which would go into raising GDP. SSG use the example of the 1986 tax reform to demonstrate this. In response to this, there was a surge in reported S-corp income (i.e. “pass-through” income), which implies a legal shift from corporations to S-corp’s, but this had no practical effect on the supply of inputs to the economy. It is just reshuffling the paper ownership of companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, you &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; make the argument that if you want to raise GDP it would be ideal to raise taxes on financial transactions (a la the Tobin tax) to reduce the incentives to do those type 4 transactions, but lower taxes on type 1 transactions dealing with the provision of real inputs, and definitely provide incentives to R&amp;amp;D spending and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to convince me that these financial transactions of type 4 &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have an important effect on real GDP growth, then you’d have to talk me into believing that facilitating the exchange of ownership leads to a more efficient allocation of management ability, or something like that. For that to be true, it would have to be that there are a lot of exchanges of ownership that are not currently taking place because they are not worth it due to high taxes. But the prima facie evidence works against you, because you’d want to show me that there has been some kind of decline, or stagnation in financial transactions like this over time, and that is just not the case. But that’s your in, if you are looking for one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That aside, I think it’s key to reiterate that claiming tax cuts will not have an effect on growth is not a denial of the basic theory. Rather, the claim is based on the low elasticities, which mean that the responses are small, and a disconnect between the returns that are &lt;em&gt;taxed&lt;/em&gt; and the returns that are paid to real inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Harvey</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Harvey/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Harvey/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You may or may not realize that the global headquarters of Growthecon.com is in Houston. So it’s been an interesting few days, to say the least. This post has nothing to do with economics. It’s just things that keep running through my head as we clean up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live a charmed life, for so many reasons. But most recently, it’s the fact that we made it out of the storm with a dry house (barely) and with everyone safe. Lots of our neighbors are not so lucky, so we’ve been doing what we can to help. It doesn’t feel like much. I hope it makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this post is me documenting things I don’t want to forget, which includes a lot of raw emotions in response to some amazing events. So farther down you are going to find me taking some shots that maybe one day I’ll regret. Maybe. But right now I don’t think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-is-what-lucky-looks-like&quot;&gt;This is what lucky looks like&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday night, the 26th, is when the rain started hard in the Houston area. We didn’t sleep. We just watched the rain come down, and ran outside during breaks to clear debris away from the storm drain in front of our house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Houston Flood Control district has an online system recording rain totals around the bayous in the city. If you watched the news, you know the bayous are a series of artificially widened creeks that drain the city into the Gulf. Here’s the time series of rainfall totals from the Braes Bayou near Stella Link road, the closest gauge to our house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_rain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rainfall totals&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already had 1.32 inches during the morning of the 26th, and then before midnight we added another 3.56 inches. For some sense of scale, 4.88 inches is right around the typical &lt;em&gt;monthly&lt;/em&gt; total for August in Houston. And that was before the heavy stuff came. Between midnight and noon on Sunday, the 27th, we took 9.92 inches, most of that between midnight and 3am. I cannot describe for you how fast and how hard the rain came down in the first few hours of Sunday. And our area wasn’t the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a break Sunday morning, and this was the view out of our front door. That front areas of bricks was under an inch of water that you can’t quite make out in the picture. Under the street light, on the left, is the storm drain. When I waded out there to check it for blockages, the water was at my waist. Across the street from the light is supposed to be a fire hydrant. It was under water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_worst.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flooding&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That water rose not just because it rained hard, but because the bayou overflowed, and there was no place for it to go. The flood district also provides plots of the level of each bayou at certain stations, and here’s the time series of Braes Bayou. You can see the essentially vertical rise right around midnight of the 26th, into the 27th. At that point the rains continued, and the bayou, thanks to our rain, rain upstream flowing down, and rain downstream backing it up, stayed above flood level into Monday the 28th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/harvey_bayou.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bayou level&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you flip back to the rain chart, you’ll see that we still got 3.2, 2.28, and 6.24 inches of rain in the 36 hours &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the heavy stuff. Believe it or not, this is where we got lucky. That let-up of 3.2 and 2.28 inches allowed the bayou to recede, just a little. It bought us a few inches to spare, so when the 6.24 came, our house was able to survive. When I wandered downstairs at about 1:30am on Monday morning, the water had at retreated about one foot from our house, and it wouldn’t come closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its height, we came within 1-3 inches of flooding, depending where exactly around the house you looked. Over the rest of the morning of the 28th, Monday, the water retreated further, and we (personally) were out of trouble. Some tense moments occurred on Tuesday as we took more rain, but never enough to flood the bayou near us again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said, this is a story of amazing luck. Through all that, we didn’t flood. We didn’t even lose power throughout the storm. We didn’t do anything special, it just turns out that our house is one or two inches higher than a few others on our street. People just a few doors down our street are now ripping out carpet and drywall. I don’t know the exact number of people we know who flooded, but it’s more than I can count up quickly in my head. We’ve tried to help people out, but it feels like very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;people-really-are-amazing&quot;&gt;People really are amazing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just about a week ago, I was still reading stories about alt-right neo-Nazi shitheads with brittle egos and tiki torches. And right as Harvey was hitting land the first time, known terrorist Joe Arpaio was getting pardoned for taking a dump on the Constitution. But for each and every one of those people, I saw over the last week hundreds and thousands of decent human beings put everything they had on the line to help perfect strangers. Hundreds and thousands. Remember that when the news gets back to publicizing the worst among us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a few of the best:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everyone with a boat. They came from Houston itself, from the rest of Texas, from Louisiana, from Kentucky, from Michigan, and hundreds of places I missed. Brave, selfless, and inexhaustible. These people drove &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; the shitstorm that was Harvey and got to work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jeff Lindner and everyone at the Houston Flood Control District. Step by step, Lindner came on TV or radio and talked everyone through the situation with the bayous and rivers. Never flustered, never hyperbolic, never flippant, he is part of the reason this didn’t turn out more chaotic than it already was.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;City of Houston and Harris County emergency response teams. I hope you all can go home and sleep for six months. I hope &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; families and &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; homes are safe and dry. And yes, that includes Mayor Turner and Judge Emmett (the county administrator). Those two somehow kept it together the whole time. I’m sure you can find some mistake they made along the way, but anyone who wants to nitpick their decisions should be invited to kiss both of their asses.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eric and Matt at &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacecityweather.com&quot;&gt;Space City Weather&lt;/a&gt;. Those two were a beacon of sanity and reality throughout the weekend. The TV weather guys were not over the top, but were often just struggling to keep up with the constant series of tornado and flood warnings. Eric and Matt were able to put out clear and concise summaries, about every 3-4 hours, of what was coming.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The National Weather Service. Without the information provided by these people, this and every hurricane (not to mention most tornadoes) are mass casualty events. Keep this in mind when you start getting antsy to cut funding at federal agencies to support a tax cut. Weather information doesn’t “trickle down”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I haven’t mentioned all the people that are out right now volunteering their time to clean out their neighbor’s houses, or cook them food, or help evacuees fill out FEMA forms, or … everything else they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every editor of every newpaper, magazine, and website out there, here’s the deal. Go out and find every single one of these magnificent people. Go find them and tell their story. Until you do that, I don’t want to see or hear another piece that involves the term “real America”, or how some unnamed official is “distressed” at something happening in the White House, or provides a profile of some shitbag neo-Nazi with a self-esteem issue. And until you find all these people, I don’t want to read any Vox or Atlantic columns on “What Harvey says about …”. It’s a catastrophe, not a fucking metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you wondering why the whole city didn’t evacuate, do you really think that the city was shocked to discover it could be hit by a massive hurricane? Sheltering in place was not some shoot-from-the-hip wild guess of a strategy. It’s the best of bunch of crappy options. If you want to have a discussion, say a month from now after the worst of this is all over, about whether there are ways to effect an evacuation during the next Harvey-like event, great. Let’s do it. In the meantime, your homework is to devise a plan to evacuate the &lt;em&gt;entire state of Massachusetts&lt;/em&gt; subject to the following constraints. (A) you have 48 hours, (B) you can’t use Rhode Island, Connecticut, or New York, and (C) everyone needs shelter for up to 10 days. Go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read this far, thanks. It was a self-indulgent brain dump from someone with exactly zero problems right now. I should be outside finding a better way to help than generating a blog post. If you have a mind to help, one charity that my wife has been involved with, and does a great job locally, is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.houstonfoodbank.org&quot;&gt;Houston Food Bank&lt;/a&gt;. Go there, give them money. Let them feed people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rising Markups and Falling Productivity</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/DE-Markups/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/DE-Markups/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In between checking weather updates here in Houston, I finally got around to reading the new working paper by Jan De Loecker and Jan Eeckhout (DE), on “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.janeeckhout.com/wp-content/uploads/RMP.pdf&quot;&gt;The Rise of Market Power and the Macroeconomic Implications&lt;/a&gt;”. The authors find that the markup of price over marginal cost charged by public US firms has been rising steadily since 1960, and in particular after 1980. It has generated a lot of commentary already, as in this &lt;a href=&quot;http://noahpinionblog.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by Noah Smith, this &lt;a href=&quot;https://niskanencenter.org/blog/markups-market-power/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by Karl Smith, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2017/08/rise-market-power.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; from Tyler Cowen. A lot of the discussion so far has been about how to interpret their results, and whether it indicates a rise in “market power”, and that devolved somewhat into a discussion of how to define “market power” in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to jump in with some of my own thoughts on the paper, but I’m going to avoid getting into this “market power” interpretation thing. I’m more interested in what DE’s results have to say about the productivity slowdown. Let’s start with how DE get these numbers in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;estimating-markups&quot;&gt;Estimating markups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing; you can’t observe these markups. While the price of a specific good might be knowable, the marginal cost of that good is not. The average cost of producing that good - total costs divided by number of goods sold - is not the same thing as the marginal cost. I’d be willing to bet that a lot of firms would be hard-pressed themselves to tell you the marginal cost of an additional good. And that doesn’t even get into the issue with multi-product firms, where their aggregated financials cannot tell you about the specific prices and costs associated with specific products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when DE are talking about estimating markups, they are extracting the markup of a firms “price” over the firms “marginal cost”, where the price is some agglomeration of the prices of their various products, and the cost is some agglomeration of the cost of their various inputs. That’s not a knock on the approach, but it should be kept in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you extract this markup if you don’t have the exact costs, or even prices? DE assume that firms are cost-minimizers, a less forceful assumption than strict profit maximization. Whether firms are pricing their goods to maximize profits or not is immaterial to DE, but they assume that firms are trying to produce their goods or services using the lowest-cost combination of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the logic involved in the firm’s decision pretty easily. If a firm’s markup is the price relative to marginal cost, then for the marginal good it produces, it should be that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Rev = Markup \times MC \times Inputs&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Rev\inline&quot;/&gt; is the revenue from that marginal good, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Markup\inline&quot;/&gt; is the … markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC\inline&quot;/&gt; is the cost of an additional bundle of inputs, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Inputs\inline&quot;/&gt; are the bundles of inputs it takes to produce that marginal good. Simply rearrange this to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Markup = \frac{Rev}{MC \times Inputs}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you’ve got it. DE have data on firm-level revenues, and they have data on firm-level costs for inputs. There is an extra step, which is that this kind of condition should hold for each separate input (i.e. labor and capital) as opposed to “Inputs” the way I’ve described it. All this does is insert a parameter into this expression that weights revenues by how important that specific input is to production. If we were working with labor, for instance, we might say that the revenue &lt;em&gt;attributable to labor&lt;/em&gt; is only 60% of total revenues, and so divide 0.6 times revenues by the cost of labor to arrive at the markup. For the purposes of this post, though, I think you can easily stick with the idea that markups are obtained from ratios of revenues to costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DE do this for all the public firms they have data for, for all the years running from 1960 to recently. The figure below is the central result, which is that markups rose steadily from 1960’s - when they were about 1.18 on average - to today, when they are about 1.67 on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DE_2017_Fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Evolution of Markups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those papers where it shocks you that no one has done this before. This paper takes some relatively off-the-shelf techniques, and uses them to generate an incredibly interesting set of estimates. Granted, the authors are some of the people who put those techniques up on the shelf in the first place, but the innovation in this paper is the application to the long panel of US public firms, not the techniques. The results in this figure are what have generated a lot of commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the big empirical caveats. If you want to disbelieve DE’s results, then you’d have to think hard about the effect of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sample is only public firms. Probably the biggest question mark. The average markup charged by &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; firms in the economy may not have changed much over time, but if there was a distinct change in the choice to either go public, or stay public, starting around 1980, and that change was related to markup sizes, then this could just be sample selection. For example, you could argue that as investors became laser-focused on quarterly earnings, this meant that the only firms willing to go public or stay public were those with large markups that could generate the expected earnings growth. All the low markup firms are private, and so don’t show up in the DE dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Industry production functions are assumed to be identical for all firms and over time. I mentioned above that DE actually use specific inputs in the calculation, and for that they need these weights (like the 60% for labor I mentioned). To get those, they estimate production functions for each industry using their data. And that estimation assumes that the weights are identical for all firms in an industry (i.e. American and United each have a weight of 44% on labor) and over time (i.e. United’s weight on labor is 44% every year from 1960 forward). DE have an appendix where they relax this assumption, and show that the growth in markups over time (but not their level) is unchanged, so this is unlikely to be driving the results.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cost minimization may not hold. This doesn’t seem like a strong assumption, and it is certainly weaker than assuming full profit maximization. But it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an assumption. If the firms in the DE dataset are not operating to minimize costs (perhaps they just care about maximizing market share or executive compensation?) then the first order condition DE use would be picking up something other than the true markup. I don’t have a great sense of how the bias would work here, or a great sense of whether this could be a big or a small problem. But it could be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to take the DE results as indicative of what is happening in the US as a whole, then the second half of their paper is for you. Here, they break down several secular trends in the economy (e.g. declining labor shares, declining productivity growth) and show how the rise in markups can account for them. As the association of markups with productivity is something I’ve been banging around on for a few years - you could start with this &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Cake/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; and work backwards - let me focus on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;productivity-accounting&quot;&gt;Productivity Accounting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presence of markups - and changes in markups - have implications for measured productivity growth. And DE corroborate that, while offering the data to be more precise about the effects. But they do it using a slightly different line of attack than I have in the past, so let me digress for a moment to try and link this all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways we could describe aggregate output. The first is using a production function, like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = T X&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T\inline&quot;/&gt; is &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X\inline&quot;/&gt; is an index of &lt;em&gt;inputs&lt;/em&gt;. Technology, T, is the for-realisies measure of how good we are at transforming inputs into useful output. It is what we really would like to measure. Based on this production function, we could back out technology as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = \frac{Y}{X}.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave that aside for the moment, we’ll come back to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also describe aggregate output using incomes, meaning we can write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = \Pi + wX&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\Pi\inline&quot;/&gt; are economic profits, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w\inline&quot;/&gt; is the “wage” of inputs. For those wages, think of something like a weighted average of actual wages (to labor) and payments to capital and/or natural resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are profits? Well, let’s assume that there is a markup, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu\inline&quot;/&gt;, which recall measures the ratio of price to marginal cost. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu = 1.5\inline&quot;/&gt;, then firms are charging 50% over cost. So profits are equal to 50% of costs. Another way of saying this is that profits are &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\mu - 1\inline&quot;/&gt; times costs,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = (\mu - 1)wX + wX = \mu w X&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or total output can be expressed as the markup times the wage times the inputs used. We’re still the world of pure accounting, by the way. No behavioral assumptions have been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, go back and compare the original production function version of output, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = T X\inline&quot;/&gt;, to this markup version, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y = \mu w X\inline&quot;/&gt;. From these, it shows us that we could write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = \mu w.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or technology is equivalent to the markup times the wage. I like to think of this expression this way: technology (or an increase in technology) can be used for one of two things (a) raising the markup or (b) raising the wage paid to inputs. One quibble with DE is that they say something along the line of “if markups go up, this raises technology”, which should more accurately be phrased “if markups go up, this implies that tecnology was higher”, which eliminates the implicit causal statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’ve got two ways to backing out technology, T, from the data. Either use &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T = Y/X\inline&quot;/&gt;, or use &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T = \mu w\inline&quot;/&gt;. In terms of growth rates, the first says that the growth rate of technology (using little hats to denote growth rates) is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{T} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X}\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the second says that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{T} = \hat{\mu} + \hat{w}\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s great, but when we go to the data is it quite plausible that we make mistakes. That is, we go to the data and calculate residual &lt;em&gt;productivity&lt;/em&gt;, P. And unless we are exactly right about how the world works, our measure of P may not be equal to T. Here’s what I mean. Take the production function version of things, which I’ve talked about a lot before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{P} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X}^{wrong} = \hat{Y} - \hat{X} + (\hat{X} - \hat{X}^{wrong}) = \hat{T} + (\hat{X} - \hat{X}^{wrong})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of productivity is the growth rate of output minus the growth rate of &lt;em&gt;a possibly mismeasured index of input use&lt;/em&gt;. This mismeasurement may be because we really don’t know how to count units of capital or human capital correctly, or because we are weighting those counts incorrectly. The point I’ve made in a few posts in the past is that by ignoring markups, you could may be making a weighting mistake, and this would lead to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{X}^{wrong} &amp;gt; \hat{X}\inline&quot;/&gt;, so productivity growth understates technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you instead were going to try and measure productivity growth using the real wage, then you could get something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{P} = \hat{\mu}^{wrong} + \hat{X} = (\hat{\mu}^{wrong} - \hat{\mu}) + \hat{\mu} +  \hat{X} = \hat{T} + (\hat{\mu}^{wrong} - \hat{\mu})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where you might be making an error about how fast markups are growing. If you do, and in particular if you assume &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\hat{\mu}^{wrong} &amp;lt; \hat{\mu}\inline&quot;/&gt;, which you might do if you assumed markups were unchanging over time, then your productivity growth term understates technological growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what DE essentially do in the very last part of the paper. They say that by falsely assuming markups are constant, productivity growth measured using changes in real wages is understating true technological growth. When they make an adjustment to allow for the real growth in markups they observe, they find that true technological growth was around 3-4% per year over the last few year, as opposed to almost 0% growth in measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a massive difference, and suggests that (a) technological progress is clipping along very nicely, thank you, and (b) that almost all of the gains from this are being leveraged into higher markups rather than higher real wages to inputs like labor. Entirely consistent with stories of increased market power and concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t a glaring issue with the analysis that DE do here, but they could go further with it. The papers that establish the discrepancies between growth in productivity, P, and technology, T, point out that much of the problem stems from trying to do this at the aggregate level alone. If you had individual firm-level (or plant-level) data on technological growth, then you could add those up directly (suitably weighted by their size), to arrive at &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T\inline&quot;/&gt; directly. No need to back it out from aggregate information on inputs used, or wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And DE have all the data to do this. When they estimate the production functions that allow them to recover the markups, they also recover an estimate of technology for each firm. It would be straightforward to find technological growth from the “bottom-up”, and compare it to what we get using aggregate methods. This would give us (a) a true(r) measure of technological growth and (b) help identify what precisely we are doing wrong with the aggregate measures of productivity growth. I’ll let DE add that to the near-infinite list of things that people have suggested they do with this data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-are-markups-higher&quot;&gt;Why are markups higher?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of productivity, and for most of the other secular trends DE talk about, the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; of the markup is irrelevant. Arguing about whether markups represent market power or not, or whether monopolistic competition is equivalent to market power, adds nothing to the discussion of the implications. They would matter if we were talking about how to change markups. But at this stage DE are simply documenting the growth in markups and showing that these can be associated with a number of phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much of the discussion about the markups has circled around market power, let me point out two additional possible sources of markups, and growth in markups. First, scale. If there are increasing returns to scale, then the markup will be above one. Think of a firm with big fixed costs. They have to charge above marginal cost in order to recover those fixed costs. You could imagine that what has changed over time is that the firms in the DE dataset invested in some fixed costs that gave them increasing returns to scale, and the markups are covering those costs. The problem with this explanation is that you wouldn’t expect labor’s and capital’s share of output to be declining over time in this case, which they are. So perhaps it doesn’t matter much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it could be us. That is, the markup could be rising because consumers are getting more particular about their bundle of purchases. Whether these firms are true monopolists, or involved in monopolistic competition, or compete in some kind of strategic game with one another, the more inelastic our demand gets for their product, the bigger the markups they can charge. I think of this as a caveat of structural change. As our basic material needs get met more easily over time, we get pickier about the goods and services we consume, making our demand more inelastic. This could explain some of the rise in markups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take seriously the DE findings, then decomposing this rise in markups into different sources is the natural next step. The other step is to find ways to confirm that this rise in markups is robust to non-public, and possibly non-US, firms. Tracking similar changes across countries would help eliminate or confirm some explanations (US-specific anti-trust policies). Nevertheless, I found the DE paper an intriguing (and very large) step forwards.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Are some places &quot;More Malthusian&quot; than other?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Constraints/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Constraints/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve got a new working paper out (&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2017-06-28-Constraint.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/hou/wpaper/2017-192-55.html&quot;&gt;repec&lt;/a&gt;), co-authored with Ryan Johnson, on Malthusian constraints. There is some material that we’re cutting from the paper, because it is already getting too long, but I kind of like the graphs and the results, so I figured I would write them up here. Fair warning: there will be some math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Malthus/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; I wrote not too long ago on what “Malthusian” means, I said that a key feature of a Malthusian economy was that living standards are &lt;em&gt;inversely&lt;/em&gt; related to population size. Typically, we’d think of this as being due to fixed (or very expensive to acquire) amounts of agricultural land. What Ryan and I are trying to figure out is exactly how sensitive living standards are to population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is related directly to the elasticity of agricultural output with respect to land. That is, by what percent does ag output go up if I increase the supply of land by 10%? Now, I just said you &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; change the supply of land, but that doesn’t mean we cannot think about a hypothetical where you could. So what Ryan and I do in the paper is try to estimate that elasticity very carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see the logic, and how we get there, let me lay out a little math. Agricultural production is given by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = A X^{\beta} L^{1-\beta}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where A is productivity, X is the amount of land, and L is the number of people. The value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is the elasticity I was talking about. If you divide both sides of this equation by L, you get an expression for output per worker (i.e. living standards) of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y/L = A (X/L)^{\beta}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which says that living standards depend inversely on population size, L. That’s the Malthusian assumption. What this expression also says is that the elasticity of &lt;em&gt;living standards&lt;/em&gt; with respect to L is equal to &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this fairly intuitive. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; tells us how important land is for producing food, relative to labor. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is close to one, then land is the only thing that matters. It’s as if the land produces a fixed amount of food every year, regardless of how much work we put in. In that case, adding extra people reduces living standards by a lot, because there is no extra food to go around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is close to zero, then land doesn’t matter much at all. Most of what drives food production is the effort of the workers. In that case, if we add population, living standards only fall by a little, because each new person is able to produce a lot of extra food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the paper, we refer to an economy where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is large as having “tight Malthusian constraints” because living standards are very sensitive to the number of people. In constrast, an economy with a a low &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; has “loose Malthusian constraints” because the number of people doesn’t affect living standards by much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To figure out the size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;, we do the following. Think of a bunch of economies with a similar living standard, so Y/L is a constant, and call that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\overline{y}\inline&quot;/&gt;. Then rearrange the equation for living standards above to be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;L/X = \frac{A^{1/\beta}}{\overline{y}^{1/\beta}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This says that population density will be high where productivity, A, is high, holding constant living standards. But notice that the strength of this relationship depends on the size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. In areas with “tight” Malthusian constraints, and high &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; values, the sensitivity of population density to productivity should be &lt;em&gt;low&lt;/em&gt;. Because land matters a lot to production, the population gets spread evenly over all the land available, even if that land has fundamentally different productivity levels. If everyone tried to crowd into the highest productivity place, they’d drive down living standards by a lot. We should see similar population density across places with different inherent agricultural productivity levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In places with “loose” Malthusian constraints, the opposite logic holds. The sensitivity of population density to productivity will be &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt;. Everyone can crowd into the small area of land with the best natural fertility, and living standards remain high, because living standards aren’t very sensitive to the size of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a slightly more complicated setup, this is the logic that Ryan and I use to estimate the size of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. We look at how the density of rural population is related to measures of inherent land productivity, and we do that for districts within states (i.e. compare all the counties in Texas to one another), using data from all around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can also do this a little more loosely using historical data on the density of population by country, and this analysis isn’t going to fit in the paper. What we do is take the data from the paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v101y2011i5p2003-41.html&quot;&gt;Quamrul Ashraf and Oded Galor&lt;/a&gt; that I mentioned in the Malthusian post, which establishes that population density in 1500CE is positively related to productivity across countries, just as the last equation predicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those guys, though, threw all the countries in the world together to do their analysis, and what Ryan and I did was look at the relationship of density and productivity in their data for specific regions, like Europe, Africa, etc.. Here’s the graph showing what we found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_ag_regions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Density and Productivity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “residual agricultural productivity” term on the x-axis is variation in agricultural productivity after we controlled for all the other things that Ashraf and Galor control for (latitude, etc..). Agricultural productivity is an amalgam of things related to how much of a country is suitable for cultivation. It’s based on climate characteristics and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that Europe looks a lot different than the other three regions plotted: Asia (really South and Southeast Asia), Sub-Saharan Africa, and the Mideast/North Africa. For Europe, there is no distinct relationship between density and productivity. This, using the logic I laid out above, says that the land constraint in Europe was very “tight”, with a high &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. If you take the math seriously, it says that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is approaching infinity, as the slope of the line should indicate a value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1/\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. That is probably wrong, and is one of the reasons we like our district-level data for this job instead. Regardless, compared to the other regions, Europe looks like a place where living standards were very sensitive to population size. The other regions show a higher slope, indicating that more productive places were a lot more densely populated, and that is consistent with “loose” Malthusian constraints. Their living standards were apparently less sensitive to population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference in the average level of density (i.e. all of Europe’s dots are shifted up compared to the other regions) is capturing other unobserved “stuff” about Europe that just made it have high population density. For our purposes this shift isn’t as interesting as the relationship within each region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, great, Malthusian constraints were tighter in Europe than in other regions historically. So what? To see the importance, let’s go back to the relationship of living standards, Y/L, with productivity and land, and realize that there is more to life than food. That is, Y/L is my little model here is &lt;em&gt;agricultural&lt;/em&gt; output per person &lt;em&gt;in agriculture&lt;/em&gt;. For lots of historic economies, nearly everyone is in agriculture, and food is a massive share of what they consume, so just talking about “output” and “population” is fine. But to see the influence of constraints on development, we can be a little more subtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be specific that we’re talking about agricultural output per agricultural person, so&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y_A/L_A = A (X/L_A)^{\beta}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, let N be the total population, which includes both agricultural workers, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?L_A\inline&quot;/&gt;, and non-ag workers (e.g. urban dwellers, etc..). I’m going to multiply and divide the left-hand side by N, and do some re-arranging of this equation. You can check my work, but I’m pretty sure this holds up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{Y_A}{N}\left(\frac{N}{L_A}\right)^{1-\beta}\left(\frac{N}{X}\right)^{\beta} = A.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the right is just productivity. The left side tells me what I can do with that productivity. If productivity goes &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt;, for whatever reason (i.e. the Glorious Revolution! The Columbian exchange! The Pope bans consanguinous marriages! Horse collars are invented! Someone planted turnips!) I can translate that into any or all of three things: increased food per person, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_A/N\inline&quot;/&gt;, increased population per agricultural worker, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N/L_A\inline&quot;/&gt;, or increased population density, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N/X\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; features here in the trade-off between increasing population per ag worker or population density. In places with “tight” constraints, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is large, a small increase in population density would “eat up” the productivity gain very quickly. At the same time, because &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1-\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is small, it takes a big increase in the population to ag worker ratio (i.e. urbanization) to “eat up” the productivity gain. A tight Malthusian constraint makes urbanization relatively cheap compared to increasing density. The opposite logic says that a loose Malthusian constraint makes density relatively cheap compared to urbanization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence places with tight contraints, like Europe, may have had a built-in advantage in &lt;em&gt;development&lt;/em&gt;, even if they didn’t have an advantage in &lt;em&gt;productivity&lt;/em&gt;, A. It could be &lt;em&gt;part of&lt;/em&gt; the explanation for why Europe took off relative to the rest of the world, given that other areas had high productivity levels and productivity growth at least during some periods of their history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a lot to load onto one figure and a couple of equations. Ryan and I think we do a good job in the paper of establishing that the differences in &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; across regions of the world are robust, and those differences appear related to underlying geographic characteristics (i.e. Malthusian constraints are tighter where winters are colder). The implications of those differences are harder to get at, of course, but we think there’s a plausible story floating around in there somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application of this isn’t confined to historical development, either. For current developing countries, the tightness of the Malthusian constraint dictates the relative cost of urbanization versus density. We find very loose land constraints in tropical areas of Sub-Saharan Africa and Central America, perhaps offering some clue as to why they fell behind areas like East Asia, despite having similar starting conditions in the mid 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Return of Peasant Mentality?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Peasant/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Peasant/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Without intending to, I ended up taking a blog hiatus (blacation?) for about a month. But in that month I built up a whole reserve of speculative energy that I now need to disgorge all at once. So strap in, because this one gets hairy towards the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thing that has interested me since grad school is the clear gap in labor productivity between urban and rural areas, or between non-agricultural workers and agricultural workers. There are two big questions that come up given that fact. Why do those gaps exist? What effect do those gaps have, if any, on development? I’ve taken a couple of swipes at the second question &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/JDE_Final.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/dvhc2014.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those papers, I did have to think about the first question, why the gaps exist at all. It seems like if there were big labor productivity gaps, then there should be big wage gaps, and if there were big wage gaps, then people would have moved from the low-wage rural areas to high-wage urban areas already. One possibility is that those gaps exist because of differences in human capital of workers between the two sectors. If rural workers have less human capital, then their &lt;em&gt;labor&lt;/em&gt; productivity (output per hour, say) will be lower than urban workers, even if the &lt;em&gt;human capital&lt;/em&gt; productivity (output per unit of HC) is identical in rural and urban areas. In this case, the labor productivity gap may not represent any distortion or friction, as the return to a unit of human capital is identical across sectors, and therefore would not imply any kind of macro-level inefficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And over the years, I’d say that more and more evidence accumulates that this is the case. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/oup/qjecon/v128y2013i4p1727-1785.html&quot;&gt;Alwyn Young&lt;/a&gt; has a recent paper showing that there is a ton of movement back and forth between rural and urban areas in developing countries, and so it seems unlikely that some kind of friction, or moving cost, is keeping people from responding to any gaps in wages that might exist. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v104y2014i5p165-70.html&quot;&gt;Gollin, Lagakos, and Waugh&lt;/a&gt; find that gaps in human capital productivity are smaller than the gaps in labor productivity, although there is still a gap. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/red/sed014/364.html&quot;&gt;Schoellman and Herrendorf&lt;/a&gt; look at raw wage gaps - which should be related to labor productivity - across sectors in a number of countries, and find that they are explained almost entirely by differences in human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one issue with these studies is that they (and me in my earlier papers) are comparing two different groups of people: rural workers and urban workers. There may be unobservable differences in their human capital that we cannot account for using things like education or experience, and so we don’t really know if our measures of human capital productivity are accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to a recent working paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/nbr/nberwo/23253.html&quot;&gt;Hamory-Hicks, Kleemans, Li, and Miguel&lt;/a&gt;. The authors use longitudinal data from Indonesia and Kenya, meaning they can track the same individuals over time. This allows them to look at people who move from rural to urban areas, and hence have an identical set of human capital in both places, by definition. As their human capital is identical in both locations, if they earn more in one place than another then this indicates a difference in their human capital productivity, and not a difference in some unobservable human capital. So when people move from rural to urban, or urban to rural places in these countries, do their wages change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Indonesia, they do not. Once you are effectively comparing the same person in two different places (i.e. using individual fixed effects) the authors find a zero gap in wages. If they compare individuals who switch between agriculture and non-agriculture (as opposed to rural vs urban), there is also effectively no wage gap. The wages of individuals do not change when they move sector of employment or from rural areas to cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Kenya, some small gaps remain, but they are small compared to the raw difference in wages between areas. There seems to be about a 13% wage premium to either living in an urban area or working in non-agriculture, even for an otherwise identical individual. That number, though, is not a statistically significant estimate, so it could be zero (or it could be a 20 or 30% gap, we don’t know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HHKLM paper is consistent with the earlier research, in that when you just look at the average wage gap (i.e. labor productivity) between urban and rural areas in Kenya and Indonesia, it is quite large (on the order of a 60-80% wage premium for urban/non-agricultural work), but when you control for human capital, it falls. The HHKLM paper is better at controlling for human capital (because they compare people to themselves), so it validates a lot of this earlier work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of facts tells you that there is selection out of rural/agricultural work and into urban/non-agricultural work for people with lots of human capital. There is not some distortion that prevents rural people from moving to higher wage positions, apparently, its just that all the really skilled or smart people move off the farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Indonesia, the people who start rural and stay rural have the lowest levels of education. The people who start urban and stay urban have the highest levels of education. People who go either rural-to-urban or urban-to-rural have similar levels of education, and its about in the middle of the other two groups. The same holds for Kenya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s really interesting is that this pattern shows up in the Raven’s Z-scores as well. If you read Garett Jones’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2uscIem&quot;&gt;Hive Mind&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll know this is a crude, but effective, proxy for IQ. It’s a simple test that you can administer in the field, and correlates well with broader measures of intelligence (it’s a non-verbal pattern recognition test). So it’s not just that people who are lucky enough to get an education in an urban area stay there, and people unlucky enough to miss out on schooling in rural areas stay there. People with better measures of inherent smarts tend to end up in the city, or are in cities to begin with. HHKLM don’t have information on urban residents for Kenya, but the data for the rural stayers and leavers conforms to the Indonesian data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Everything that follows is all me riffing on the result in HHKLM. Don’t blame them if it doesn’t make sense.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So urban places and/or non-agricultural work looks far more productive than rural/agricultural work because the people doing the urban/non-agricultural work appear to have more human capital, both inherent (Raven’s) and acquired (school). And by explaining the gap between these areas this way, it leads back to an concept that was often invoked in the early 20th century to explain the raw productivity gap: the peasant mentality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As industrialization started, and these raw productivity gaps opened up for the first time, people started to speculate about why they existed if people could move back and forth relatively freely. Chayanov, in 1925, published &lt;a href=&quot;https://vertov14.files.wordpress.com/2016/08/alexander_chayanov_the_theory_of_peasant_economy.pdf&quot;&gt;The Theory of the Peasant Economy&lt;/a&gt;, which speculated about peasant farm organization. In it, he suggested that you cannot think of peasant families as acting according to typical economic logic (maximizing consumption or profits), rather they had a “peasant logic” or “peasant mentality”, which was focused on eking out enough to subsist year to year, but without much thought towards expanding, saving, or growing. One of James Scott’s earlier books, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2urVdLm&quot;&gt;The Moral Economy of the Peasant&lt;/a&gt; provides a study of peasants in southeast Asia, how their motivations were driven by subsistence constraints, and paints a similar picture to Chayanov.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of those authors are sympathetic to the peasants. Others looked at the same situations and get frustrated with the peasants ignorance, stubborness, and unwillingness to experiment with new techniques or technologies. For some, it was the small-town peasant mentality that was holding back economic development. When Ted Schultz published &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2tyjVNW&quot;&gt;Transformaing Traditional Agriculture&lt;/a&gt; in 1965, he attacked both interpretations of the peasant mentality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, he said, peasants were very much rational maximizers, just as economics would assume. They might have additional constraints (subsistence needs) and face more uncertainty unlike “normal” people, but they were maximizing their utility nonetheless with respect to those constraints. Schultz said we should be analyzing peasants with the tools of modern economics; we did not need different theories for them. That brought development into mainstream economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, in questioning the idea that peasants operated on some kind of different set of rules from other people, he attacked the idea that peasants were different at all. They were just like anyone else. The implicit assumption in Schultz’s work is that if you dropped an urban person into one of their villages, they’d make the same choices as the peasants. Peasants were not different, their environment was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if they are different? That seems to be an implication of the HHKLM study. If people are sorting themselves between rural and urban areas, or between agricultural and non-agricultural work, based on some inherent characterstic captured by the Raven score or some other aspect of their human capital, then doesn’t that imply the people in the rural areas &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; different than the people in urban areas?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t mean that rural people are not rational maximizers, but do they come to different conclusions about how to maximize, or what to maximize? If you look at the literature in Jones’ book, you’ll see that things like the Raven score are correlated with other characteristics like patience. Does the sorting of people across locations mean that in rural areas the people are less patient, and so they decide - rationally - to invest less? Are the things that frustrated outside observers of these peasant economies - unwillingness to experiment, ignorance - a result of the selection of low Raven-score, or low human capital individuals, into those areas? Were they right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your gut reaction is “No, or course not”, I get it. So was mine. But let’s not confuse a positive (i.e. factual) finding with a normative conclusion. Finding that rural residents score low on the Raven, and that people with low Raven scores select into rural areas, should change nothing about your opinion regarding interventions to aid development/health/etc in these areas. It doesn’t change Schultz’s conclusion that aggregate development probably requires a massive investment in those rural peasant villages. But the HHKLM data do suggest that the nature of those investments, and how you design the incentives to make them, might need to be different than in urban areas. Think of it like tailoring a class to match the learning styles of different kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the HHKLM study is replicated in other contexts - which may be a big “if” - then perhaps we need to walk back some of the changes in thinking that Schultz initiated fifty years ago. Perhaps we should take seriously the idea that peasants are really different, not just in their constraints (which the development literature has explored in great depth), but in their underlying preferences as well (which has been done far less).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding the Cost Disease of Services</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/What-You-Spend/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/What-You-Spend/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As my internal clock is not on internet time, I’m only now getting up a post in reaction to the death of William Baumol, who has been a consistent reference on this blog over the years. My topic page on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Productivity-Slowdown/&quot;&gt;productivity slowdown&lt;/a&gt; is in many ways an extended riff on his work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can share no personal stories about the man, as I never met him. What I can do is spend some time digging through what I consider the key paper of his most famous idea, the “cost disease of services”. I’d like to think that as an academic, he’d appreciate this as much as an anecdote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, Baumol was one of the handful of towering figures of economics who recently passed, along with Ken Arrow and Allan Meltzer. In response, I would like to suggest that someone move Robert Solow to a secure underground bunker, and encase him in bubble wrap, just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to Baumol. The central paper is “&lt;a href=&quot;http://piketty.pse.ens.fr/files/Baumol1967.pdf&quot;&gt;Macroeconomics of Unbalanced Growth: The Anatomy of Urban Crisis&lt;/a&gt;”, published in 1967 in the American Economic Review. For me, this contains a handful of insights that allow you to understand much of the story of economic growth in the fifty years since it was published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, Baumol divides economic activity up in the following way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The basic source of differentiation resides in the role played by labor in the activity. In some cases labor is primarily an instrument - an incidental requisite for the attainment of the final product, while in other fields of endeavor, for all practical purposes the labor is itself the end product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first case, labor as an instrument, you can read “manufactured goods”. He uses the example of an air conditioner. Just by looking at the A/C unit, or using it, there is no way for you to assess how much labor went into producing it. The labor is just incidental from your perspective as a consumer of the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast that with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On the other hand there are a number of servics in which the labor is an end in itself, in which quality is judged directly in terms of amount of labor. Teaching is a clear-cut example … An even more extreme example is one I have offered in another context: live performance. A half hour horn qunitet calls for for the expenditure of 2 1/2 man hours in its performance, and any attempt to increase productivity here is likely to be viewed with concern by critics and audience alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, labor is the very essence of the product. If you go see the horn quintet, then you are buying the 1/2 of each of those players time. Likewise, for a class you are in many ways buying the teachers time. At a (nice) restaurant, you are often purchasing the time and attention of a waiter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first big conclusion, which is really an assumption of Baumol’s, is that labor productivity growth in the first kind of production (goods) is relatively fast, while labor productivity growth in the second kind (services) is relatively slow. This is just due to the nature of the work involved. For most services, you cannot do “more with less”. No one wants to see the 1/2 hour horn quintet played in only 12 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does the cost disease come in? The next crucial assumption Baumol makes is that labor costs (wages) in the two kinds of activities move together. To be clear, he doesn’t assume (or need to assume) that wages are identical in the two sectors, only that a wage increase in one sector puts upward pressure on wages in the other sector. This would be the case if labor was somewhat mobile between the two activities. Another way of saying this is that workers could work in either sector. (They may not be equally productive in both sectors, as in Alwyn Young’s recent paper, which raises the possibility that Baumol is wrong about relative productivity growth. Maybe go read &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Roy/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; and his paper after you finish this one.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re done. Productivity growth in the goods sector raises the wage in that sector, but also raises the output of that sector. So the ratio of wage to output - a measure of the &lt;em&gt;cost&lt;/em&gt; of a unit of output - stays constant over time. Higher wages in the goods sector put pressure on wages in the service sector, so wages rise over time there. But (taking the exteme position) productivity is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; growing in services, and so &lt;em&gt;output&lt;/em&gt; is not growing. The ratio of wages to output in services - a measure of &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; - is thus rising over time. This is the “cost disease of services”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crucial elements are, again, the assumption that labor productivity growth is relatively slow in services, and the assumption that labor is mobile between sectors. Given this, the cost of services will rise over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my money, the biggest insight Baumol had was to to notice the differential in how labor matters to production in goods and services. The subsequent logic is, by itself, not a major breakthrough. The Balassa/Samuelson effect - developed by those authors in articles published in 1964 - is the same idea. They distinguish between tradable and non-tradable goods, rather than goods and services per se, and they are thinking about a cross-sectional comparisons of countries, rather than one country over time, but the outcome is identical. Countries that are very productive in tradable goods will tend to have high aggregate price levels (an empirical regularity known as the “Penn Effect”), as that productivity drives up costs in their non-tradable sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is worth noting that labels matter. If you call this “cost disease”, it sounds like a problem. If you call this “the Penn Effect”, it means that rich countries have higher prices, and is just an empirical oddity. “Cost disease” sounds bad, but is a lot like dying in your 90’s from old age. It’s awful that you are dying, but let’s not overlook that you made it into your 90’s. Baumol’s cost disease is a result of incredible affluence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precise symptoms of the cost disease depend on further assumptions. Baumol traced out the possibilities in the rest of the paper. We have that the costs (and thus prices) of the service sector are rising relative to the goods sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We may inquire what would happen if despite the change in their relative costs and prices the magnitude of the relative outputs of the two sectors were maintained … if the demand for the product in question (&lt;em&gt;services - DV&lt;/em&gt;) were sufficiently price inelastic or income elastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the next essential insight, which is that demand for services is price inelastic and/or income elastic. What this means is that despite the rising costs, people continue to consume services, and may in fact &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; their expenditure on services as they get more expensive. Baumol traces out the implications of the demand for services on the aggregate economy. In the following quote, the “progressive sector” is the goods sector, with rising productivity, and the “nonprogressive sector” is services, with slow productivity growth. Italics are Baumol’s original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If productivity per man hour rises cumulatively in one sector relative to its rate of growth elsewhere in the economy, while wages rise commensurately in all areas, then relative costs in the nonprogressive sectors must inevitably rise, &lt;em&gt;and these costs will rise cumulatively and without limit&lt;/em&gt;. … Thus, the very progress of the technologically progressive sectors inevitably adds to the costs of the technologically unchanging sectors of the economy, unless somehow the labor markets in these areas can be sealed off and wages held absolutely constant, a most unlikely possibility. We see then that costs in many sectors of the economy will rise relentlessly, and will do so for reasons that are for all practical purposes beyond the control of those involved. … If their relative outputs are maintained, an ever increasing proportion of the labor force must be channeled into these activities and the rate of growth of the economy must be slowed correspondingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to summarize this in my own words three or four times, but I don’t think I did a better job than Baumol. Many posts on this blog have been about the realization of Baumol’s prediction regarding slowing productivity growth as we transition into the non-progressive sectors. I’ll just reiterate that the slowdown in aggregate growth implied by Baumol’s cost disease is driven by the nature of demand, not a technological limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often people interalize the cost disease part of Baumol’s paper, without taking into consideration the second part regarding the effect of the demand for services. Scott Alexander has a recent post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2017/02/09/considerations-on-cost-disease/&quot;&gt;cost disease&lt;/a&gt; from a few months ago that demonstrates this. Alexander’s post is not unique, it just happened to be the last thing in my reading list on this topic, and so I’m using it to illustrate a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a (very) long post, but Alexander goes through education, health, and government services, effectively documenting the cost disease. He crystallizes this by asking the following kind of question. “Which would you prefer? Sending your child to a 2016 school? Or sending your child to a 1975 school, and getting a check for $5000 each year?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He then does this with college; modern college, or your parent’s college plus 72,000 dollars? And then with health care; modern health care, or your parent’s health care (plus ACE inhibitors and some other now off-patent technologies) plus 8000 dollars each year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander’s implicit answer to all these questions is that you would choose the the second option; the older level of service plus the cash. Much of the post is spent explaining that the service offered today is of no better quality than the service offered a generation ago. And while I’d quibble with that broad conclusion, that’s not the point. Let’s stipulate that the quality of healthcare and education have not changed in a generation, which is like taking Baumol’s thought experiment as a precise statement about the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the question that Baumol implicitly asked himself. What do people spend all that extra money on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They could use it towards a new car or a major appliance, both manufactured goods. Perhaps this is what Alexander has in mind; he never says what he thinks happens to the extra money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they might spend that extra five or eight thousand dollars to finally take a well-deserved vacation, meaning it is spent on tourism and hospitality services. Or they may well decide to spend that money sending their kids to a better (and more expensive?) school, or putting them in a full time daycare rather than part-time. Or in sending one of their kids to college who might not otherwise have gone. Perhaps the savings are used to send someone back to get a Master’s degree to get a promotion at work, or acquire a new certification that increases their wage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some of those savings might be spent on health services. Individuals may undertake procedures to permanently deal with chronic problems rather than only alleviating symptoms. Maybe the kids get full orthodontic treatment, rather than the partial work that only straightened one tooth. The savings Alexander proposes could be spent on seeing specialists to deal with persistent health issues, rather than relying on a GP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Baumol’s second insight, the demand for these kinds of services is &lt;em&gt;income elastic&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;price inelastic&lt;/em&gt;. Which means that a huge part of the money people get back from Alexander’s thought experiment is plowed &lt;em&gt;right back into education and healthcare&lt;/em&gt;. What does that do? It shifts the demand curve out for healthcare and education. And then what happens? The price goes up, and the actual amount of new health care or education acquired is not that large. Moreover, there is no appreciable decline - and there may be an increase - in the share of total GDP accounted for by healthcare and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the same outcome Baumol described, even though for him the origin of this was a productivity increase in the goods sector. But the origin of the productivity increase is unimportant, what matters is the structure of demand for services. So long as our demand for services is income elastic and price inelastic, the share of healthcare and education in GDP are going to rise as we get more productive, no matter where that productivity improvement comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a claim that healthcare or education are efficiently run, by the way. I can list, off the top of my head, a good five or six university administrators that I would get rid of tomorrow without any noticable effect. We could spend the next week swapping stories of ridiculous medical bills for $20 band-aids and the like. But their high costs are not entirely due to deliberate inefficiency, and lowering these costs would not lower their share of GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Alexander’s post is one example (of many) taking the “disease” part of “cost disease” too literally. Rising costs in education and healthcare do not always represent a pathology. In a lot of ways we are the victims of our own prosperity and preferences here. There is nothing about Baumol’s analysis that implies living standards are lower or welfare is impaired by the cost disease. Remember that the cost disease is a consequence of productivity improvements in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While “cost disease” may not have been the best choice of names, Baumol has to be credited with anticipating the path of economic growth and structural change in developed countries over the late 20th century. He did this without resorting to any math beyond what I could use in an intermediate college course, and in language accessible to anyone. If you’re interested in economic growth, it is well worth finding some time to sit down are read through his body of work.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sigh....No, tax cuts won't boost growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxes-Growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Taxes-Growth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I guess we need to go over this again. No, cuts to corporate tax rates and/or the reforms/cuts proposed on individual income taxes will not boost economic growth in any appreciable way. Not to 4%, nor 4.5%, nor 5%. There is no evidence supporting this claim. And even theoretically, there is no reason to believe that these tax reforms/cuts can boost growth to those rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prima-facie-evidence&quot;&gt;Prima Facie Evidence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with a simple smell test. The figure below plots two series: the backward-looking 5-year average growth rate of real GDP and the forward-looking 5-year growth rate of real GDP. For example, in 1981, the backward looking series is the average growth rate of real GDP from 1976-1981, and the forward looking series is the average growth rate of real GDP from 1981-1986. For any given year on the graph, we can compare the growth rate people had experienced in the recent past (backward looking) to what they would experience in the near future (forward looking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_growth_tax.png&quot; alt=&quot;Growth and Taxes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also on the figure are red lines indicating when significant tax legislation was passed, and whether it was considered a tax cut, or a tax increase. 1981 and 1986 are the “Reagan tax cuts”, 1990 is the Bush tax increase, 1993 is the Clinton budget agreement that raised top tax rates, 2001 and 2003 are the younger Bush tax cuts, and included the 2012 “fiscal cliff” agreement under Obama that raised taxes on those earning over 400,000 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you can look at is whether the forward-looking growth rate differed appreciably from the backward-looking one. If the argument about tax cuts stimulating growth is correct, then you’d expect to see that the forward-looking rate exceeds the backward-looking rate. In 1981, this looks true. Growth from 1981-1986 was about 3.5% per year, versus 2.8\% per year in 1976-1981. But examining the other tax cuts, you’ll see the opposite is true. In 1986, growth was slower &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the tax cut than before. In 2001 and 2003, growth is lower &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the tax cut than before. For the 2003 cut, the difference is very striking because of the onset of the financial crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, look at the three tax increases. For Bush (the elder) in 1990, there was essentially no difference in the forward and backward growth rate. For the 1993 increase, growth was &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; higher after the tax increase than before, and for the 2012 increase we’d need to get data through the end of 2017 to make the same comparison. But for what it is worth, growth in the four years from 2012-2016 has been a shade over 2%, meaning it is much higher than the five years prior to the tax increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You cannot take this as any kind of definitive proof of anything, of course. Tax cuts &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; boost growth, but each time we passed a tax cut it just so happens that some other big negative shock hit the economy at the same time, masking those positive effects. That’s … possible. The more likely answer is just that substantial tax cuts have small effects on economic growth. On the other side, the last time we averaged 4% growth over a 5-year period was the late 1990’s, right after the tax increase of 1993.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the smell test, this isn’t a new question, and people have picked around at the relationship of tax rates and growth rates before. I reviewed a few studies in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/taxes-and-growth/&quot;&gt;early post&lt;/a&gt; here on the blog. Short answer, there is no relationship of the tax rate to the growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this same question on from a narrower pespective, Menzie Chinn has a recurring series of posts tracking Kansas’ economic growth and employment since Brownback became governor and signed off on a massive tax cut. The short version of these posts is that employment and growth in Kansas has stagnated and/or outright fell since the cut. There are several similarities between the Kansas cut and the one proposed by the current administration. Most notably, lowering the tax rate on “pass-through” income from partnerships and proprietorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2017/04/kansas-employment-rises-to-0-3-below-previous-peak&quot;&gt;Kansas employment rises to 0.3% below peak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2017/03/kansas-employment-decline-continues-2&quot;&gt;Kansas employment decline continues (part 2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2016/12/trends-in-kansas-gdp&quot;&gt;Trends in Kansas GDP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2016/12/kansas-employment-decline-continues&quot;&gt;Kansas employment decline continues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2016/10/the-kansas-economy-three-pictures&quot;&gt;The Kansas economy: three pictures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://econbrowser.com/archives/2016/10/more-on-the-kansas-employment-collapse&quot;&gt;More on the Kansas employment collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lower tax rate on pass-through income was supposed to generate a burst of growth in Kansas. The TL;DR version of Menzie’s posts is that it hasn’t happened, which you can probably tell from the post titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-dont-tax-cuts-boost-growth-by-much&quot;&gt;Why don’t tax cuts boost growth by much?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, the evidence doesn’t support the idea that tax cuts boost growth, but at least &lt;em&gt;theoretically&lt;/em&gt; it’s true, right? Kinda sorta. Smarter people than I have tried to estimate how sensitive people’s work efforts are to income tax rates, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://eml.berkeley.edu/~saez/saez-slemrod-giertzJEL12.pdf&quot;&gt;they find&lt;/a&gt; very, very small effects. The main effect of changes in tax rates and/or reforms is that people with the means to do so shift the legal definition of their income (e.g. from personal income to profits at a proprietorship). The effect on hours worked is very small, and that is the margin we’d care about if we want to study economic growth. From the corporate side, there isn’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://eml.berkeley.edu/~yagan/DividendTax.pdf&quot;&gt;any evidence&lt;/a&gt; that the 2003 dividend tax cut had any effect on corporate investment, or on labor earnings. Rather, the dividend tax cut generated a substantial amount of payouts to existing shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s say that these guys are all wrong, and &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; tax reform/cut proposed by the current administration is * different&lt;em&gt;. For realsies, it is going to incent lots of firms to invest more, employ more people, and stimulate the economy. *That&lt;/em&gt; is going to boost growth to 4%, or maybe more, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrong. The issue is that the effects of any tax cut are going to take time to manifest themselves. In particular, corporate tax cuts that have the stated purpose of raising investment will need years or &lt;em&gt;decades&lt;/em&gt; to manifest themselves in higher GDP, assuming that the savings are actually used for investment spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been over this before on this blog, and now that I have my handy Topics pages, you can go see all the gory details &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Converge-Reform/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The short story is that tax cuts/reforms change &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; GDP (possibly), and it takes a long time for us to converge from today’s GDP to that potential GDP. The analogy is to think of GDP like your weight. If you cut “taxes” on your weight by exercising less, then you will gain weight. But not all at once. It will take months or years to reach your new potential, heavier, weight. The same thing happens with GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you think the effects of these tax cuts on potential GDP are massive, which is unlikely, you can’t generate significant changes in growth rates. There are several posts on the Topics page that do this, but let me repeat the basic calculation. Real GDP in the US is just about 17 trillion (2009 chained) dollars as of Q1 2017. A generous estimate of the current growth rate of real GDP would be about 2.5% per year, without the tax cuts. Now, let’s say the proposed corporate and individual tax cuts/reforms raised &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; GDP to something like 18 trillion dollars. In other words, what if there was 1 trillion in extra economic activity that was not taking place because a bunch of people have John Galt-ed themselves out of investing or working due to the current tax system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much faster would growth in real GDP be after the proposed tax cuts/reforms? To figure this out we need one extra piece of information, the convergence rate. This rate is the percent of the gap between current GDP and potential GDP that closes every year, and it is commonly estimated to be about 2%. In the weight example, if your current weight was 150 pounds, and your potential weight is 300 pounds thanks to your cut in exercise, then this 2% convergence rate says that in the first year, you will gain .02&lt;em&gt;(300-150) = 3 pounds. And next year, you’ll gain .02&lt;/em&gt;(300-153) = 2.94 pounds. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can do the same calculation for GDP, and figure out the growth rate of GDP implied by this convergence. Current GDP is 17 trillion, and potential GDP is 18 trillion, so the economy should add an extra .02&lt;em&gt;(18-17) = .02 trillion, or about 20 billion in economic activity. Now, remember, GDP was going to grow at 2.5% anyway without the tax cut. So GDP next year was going to be 1.025&lt;/em&gt;17 = 17.425 trillion. Add the extra 20 billion on top of that, to get 17.445 trillion in economic activity next year. So overall growth in GDP would be 17.445/17 - 1 = .0262, or 2.62%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s …. not 4%. Or really anywhere close. It is hard to move the growth rate of GDP, in the same way that it is hard to change the heading of an oil tanker. But maybe I’m just being pessimistic. So let’s play around with some numbers. What if the convergence rate is 4% per year? Then growth would be 2.73% next year. What if the convergence rate is 10%? 3.09% growth. Which is still not 4% per year, and there is no evidence that the convergence rate is 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you’re worried I’m underselling the effects of the tax cut itself. So let’s say that the proposed reforms raise the potential GDP of the US to 19 trillion - which is ridiculous by the way - but whatever. With a 2% convergence rate, that would lead to a growth rate of … 2.73%. How about potential GDP of 20 trillion, meaning that tax rates &lt;em&gt;alone&lt;/em&gt; are keeping GDP &lt;em&gt;three trillion&lt;/em&gt; under where it could. Then growth might hit … 2.85%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental issue here is that it takes time for all that pent-up investment (if it exists) to manifest itself. Firms cannot expand production overnight. It takes time to generate the plans for a new location, or plant, or product. And this all assumes, contrary to the available evidence, that there are substantial effects of tax cuts or reforms on the willingness of firms to invest and/or people to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no magic elixir of tax rules that will generate 4% growth. You don’t need to see anything more than the one-page outline put out by the current administration to get to this conclusion. Filling in the details will not change the fact that their plan, if passed, will have no appreciable effect on economic growth in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Topics in Economic Growth</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Topics-Pages/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Topics-Pages/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Less of a post, and more of an announcement. I just created some new pages here at Growthecon.com that collect resources and materials related to specific topics regarding growth. See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/topics/&quot;&gt;Topics&lt;/a&gt; link in the header of the webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an exercise in intellectual housecleaning, and a way to organize some materials for possible use in classes in the future. Each topic has links to my own posts on the subject, links to other web articles or resources, and some selected academic citations. The topics are thus more accessible, but less comprehensive, then the pages of &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/references/&quot;&gt;references&lt;/a&gt; that are also posted on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, the topics include&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Are-We-Rich/&quot;&gt;Are we rich?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Converge-Reform/&quot;&gt;Can you reform your way to higher growth?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Comp-Assumptions/&quot;&gt;Does growth depend on competition?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Dev-Growth/&quot;&gt;Does economic growth mean economic development?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Productivity-Slowdown/&quot;&gt;Productivity slowdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Manuf-Special/&quot;&gt;Is manufacturing special?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Robots-Jobs/&quot;&gt;Robots and jobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Inst-Geography/&quot;&gt;Deep determinants of development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Growth-Nature/&quot;&gt;Does economic growth harm the environment?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a decent start, and there may be a few more topics to show up. The first job is probably to split the topic on productivity slowdown into separate pieces, maybe just on measuring TFP, and then on the Baumol effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aggregate Productivity versus Aggregate Technology ... Again</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/TFP-With-Profits/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/TFP-With-Profits/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You can file this as another example of how measured aggregate TFP growth is like a trash can. It happens to include aggregate technology (which got tossed in there by accident while cleaning up kitchen), but also all sorts of other junk (like leftover coffee grounds). Today’s example shows that even if you are smart about how you construct your measure of aggregate TFP growth, you can still end up with some garbage in there because of aggregation issues. I know this is pushing the analogy, but actually measuing aggregate &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt; is like trying to wipe up just the waffle crumbs your kids left behind, but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the drops of syrup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me try to give the English-language, and non-garbage related, version of this before turning to the math. To calculate TFP growth, we look at how fast aggregate GDP grew relative to how fast aggregate input use grew. But there is a discrepancy about how we measure GDP growth and how we measure input growth. Aggregate GDP growth is a summation of the growth rate of each individual sector, with each weighted by how big a part of GDP they are. Manufacturing is about 12% of GDP, so a 3% growth rate of manufacturing output would add 0.12 x 0.03 = 0.0036 to total GDP growth, or about one-third of one percentage point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, aggregate input growth is the summation of the growth rate of inputs of each individual sector, but with each weighted by how big a part of total &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; they are. So if manufacturing is about 10% of total costs, a 2% growth rate of input use would add 0.10 x 0.02 = 0.002 to total input growth, or about one-fifth of one percentage point. Why costs, and not GDP? We want our measure of total input growth to reflect how inputs are really used across sectors, not how output is valued across sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we’re measuring aggregate GDP growth by weighting sectors by their share of GDP, but measuring input growth by weighting sectors by their share of costs, we’ve created a problem. If there are differences in market power (and hence profits) between sectors, then a sector’s share of GDP is no longer equal to its share of costs. For a sector with a big profit share, it would look over-weighted in GDP growth, but under-weighted in input growth. If its input use is growing, this will show up as &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; aggregate TFP growth. The opposite case can also happen. If we have a sector with a very small profit share, it will look under-weighted in GDP growth, but over-weighted in input growth. If it has rapid input growth, this will show up as &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; aggregate TFP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But neither case reflects any actual technological change. We’re just moving inputs from one sector to another. Once we start aggregating sectors, all the differences in market power between sectors are going to stick to aggregate TFP like the drops of syrup to the waffle crumbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This holds true even though we’re being really smart about how we calculate the input growth, and I was reminded of this in class when a student presented a paper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aejmac/v3y2011i2p29-74.html&quot;&gt;John Fernald and Brett Neiman&lt;/a&gt; that happens to be about Singapore. They construct a measure of aggregate TFP growth, and show how it contains both aggregate technology growth but also an adjustment term that picks up on these differences between sectors in their cost and GDP shares. This is true despite the fact that using cost shares for input growth is the right thing to do (as opposed to just using the GDP shares over again, basically).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows next is the math behind this, and then I’ll pick up again on the English explanation and try to think through how this might be applicable to the US productivity slowdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-math&quot;&gt;In Math&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s back up a step, to review what the issue may be. If I want to calculate a measure of TFP growth, then I want to calcualte the difference between the growth rate of output and the growth rate of “inputs”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta TFP = \% \Delta GDP - \% \Delta Inputs&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But constructing the growth rate of inputs is non-trivial. There are multiple inputs (capital and labor, at least), and so I need some way to sum up the growth rate of all the inputs into a single measure of the growth rate of inputs. Basically, I need to subtract off the growth rates of all the inputs, but I need to scale each of them by how important they are to production. To be more precise,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta TFP = \% \Delta GDP - \omega_K \% \Delta K - \omega_L \% \Delta L&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I’m assuming there are two inputs, capital and labor. The &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt; measure how important each is to production. I need those because a 10% increase in capital, for example, doesn’t translate directly into a 10% increase in GDP, because of diminishing returns. I want the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt; to capture these diminishing returns, meaning I want the elasticity of GDP with respect to capital. And there is a similar story for labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve mentioned before here that a traditional way of measuring these is to assume that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt; is equal to labor’s share of GDP, meaning total wages divided by GDP, and that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt; is just &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 - \omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt;. This would be fine only under some very specific conditions: zero profits and constant returns to scale. And the world might not work that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more robust way of doing this is to use the capital’s share of total &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; to measure &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt;, and labor’s share of total &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; to measure &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt;. This doesn’t require an assumption about either profits or constant returns to scale. All we need to believe is that firms are cost-minimizers. With cost minimizers, the cost share of an input will be equal to the elasticity of GDP with respect to that input, and we’re all good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that we might not be good. The problem is that when we have multiple sectors (or firms), to add up to find the growth rate of GDP, we use each sector’s share of GDP as a weight. For an example, I’m going to go with two sectors, manufacturing and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta GDP = \frac{P_M Y_M}{GDP}  \% \Delta Y_M + \frac{P_S Y_S}{GDP}  \% \Delta Y_S&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger the fraction of GDP made up of services, for example, the more important the growth rate of services is for aggregate growth in GDP. If you’re unsure about that, just ask yourself what the growth rate of GDP would be if there were no manufacturing sector, only services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the measure of TFP growth, I still need those &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_K\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt; weights. And for those weights I need the cost share of capital and labor at the &lt;em&gt;aggregate&lt;/em&gt; level. To calculate the aggregate cost share of capital, for example, I would use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\omega_K = \frac{Costs_M}{Costs}\frac{RK_M}{Costs_M} + \frac{Costs_S}{Costs}\frac{RK_S}{Costs_S}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where R is the rental rate of capital, and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K^M\inline&quot;/&gt; and &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K^S\inline&quot;/&gt; are the actual amounts of capital used by manufacturing and services. Writing it this way, the ratio &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?RK^M/Costs^M\inline&quot;/&gt; is the share of capital in the costs of manufacturing, and similar for services. But I weight those by manufacturing’s (or service’s) share of total costs. Again, the effect of an individual sector depends on how big it is in the economy, except now we measure that size by costs, not by GDP. There is an essentially identical equation for &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\omega_L\inline&quot;/&gt;, only using total wages instead of the total cost of capital within each sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can start to get a flavor of the problem now. We are aggregating GDP growth by using shares of &lt;em&gt;GDP&lt;/em&gt;, but we are aggregating cost shares by using shares of &lt;em&gt;Costs&lt;/em&gt;. This is a problem once we have either sector earning profits, and thus their share of GDP is not the same thing as their share of costs. In particular, if manufacturing (say) earns profits, then its share of GDP is necessarily bigger than its share of total costs. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_M Y_M / GDP &amp;gt; Costs_M/Costs\inline&quot;/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fernald and Neiman work out just the effect that this has on measured TFP growth. To kind of match their analysis, and because it helps simplify, let’s assume that manufacturing earns profits, while services do not. Then what they show is that you can write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\% \Delta TFP = \% \Delta Technology + \frac{s_{\Pi}}{1-s_{\Pi}}\left(1 - \frac{P_M Y_M}{GDP}\right)\left( \% \Delta Inputs_M -  \% \Delta Inputs_S \right).&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth rate of &lt;em&gt;measured&lt;/em&gt; TFP (the thing on the left) combines two terms. The first term on the right is the “true” growth rate of technology. The second term captures the effect of having sectors with different profit shares. We can take each part of that second term in turn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_{\Pi}/1-s_{\Pi}\inline&quot;/&gt;: This is the ratio of profits to costs in the aggregate economy. The larger this is, the bigger an impact this adjustment to TFP growth gets. This ratio will be relatively big when manufacturing is a big fraction of the economy, and relatively small when manufacturing is a small fraction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1 - P_M Y_M/GDP\inline&quot;/&gt;: This captures how important manufacturing is in the economy. If manufacturing made up all of GDP, then this whole second term would disappear, as the aggregate economy would look exactly like the manufacturing sector. But the smaller is manufacturing, the bigger the effect this term has.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\% \Delta Inputs_M -  \% \Delta Inputs_S\inline&quot;/&gt;: I know I dropped in some new notation here. This is the difference in the growth rate of total input use in manfucturing and services. Technically, there are separate terms in here referring to capital and labor, but this does the job. This last difference is what determines whether the whole second term is positive or negative. If input use in manufacturing is growing faster than in services, then this term would be positive, and it would make measured aggregate TFP growth higher. On the other hand, if services have higher input growth, then measured aggregate TFP growth would be lower.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-to-english&quot;&gt;Back to English&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the math confirms (I hope), is that aggregate TFP growth depends not only on aggregate technology, but also an adjustment for whether input use is growing faster in a high-profit sector (i.e. manufacturing) or a low-profit sector (i.e. services). To the extent that services have faster input growth, measured TFP growth will be &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; than actual technology growth. This is because input use in services is a little over-weighted compared to manufacturing, but the share of GDP in services is a little under-weighted. When inputs flow into services, it is like we are counting the input use more than we count the GDP growth that comes with it, and since TFP growth is just GDP growth minus input growth, it looks like TFP is growing more slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this is an additional effect of moving into services, over and above the plausible story that services have relatively low “true” technological growth. It’s also complete speculation, because I’m just spitballing this idea that the profits in manufacturing are larger than services. It might make more sense to just think about high-profit and low-profit sectors, and ask if inputs are shifting from the former into the latter. Either way, once you’ve got sectors tha differ in their profit shares, your measure of aggregate TFP growth has this possible problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the lesson here is that you really cannot use only aggregate data if you want a measure of aggregate technology growth. You will always run into the garbage can issue. If you want a measure of aggregate technology growth, you should calculate technological growth for each individual unit (firm or sector) separately, and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; add those up, if you want any chance. Since I know you were hoping for another breakfast food analogy, imagine using a tweezers to pick up each individual crumb of waffle to ensure you do not touch any syrup.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Update on the Profits from Housing</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Ricardian-Housing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Ricardian-Housing/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Profit-Accounting/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; I used some findings by &lt;a href=&quot;http://home.uchicago.edu/~barkai/&quot;&gt;Simcha Barkai&lt;/a&gt; and the BLS to infer that housing may a major source of the rise in the share of profits in GDP. I got an e-mail from Simcha regarding the post, and the upshot is that I’m wrong. First, and foremost, it turns out that I got confused reading his paper, and all his calculations &lt;em&gt;exclude&lt;/em&gt; residential housing. This means that my inference from comparing the BLS profit share to his profit share is invalid. You cannot conclude that residential housing profits are driving a rise in profits share of aggregate GDP, because there is no information on housing in Barkai’s number. He documents that the profit share of the non-financial corporate sector is rising over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my bad on that. Simcha also made a point in his e-mail about how the BLS calculates profit shares, and it makes me lean towards his calculations as being correct. But let’s leave that for another day and post. For the time being, you should go forth and freak out about the increasing profit share in the non-financial corporate sector, whatever your preferred explanation for that may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still had housing on the brain, though, so I wanted to figure whether I was wrong about profits rising in the housing sector. Effectively, I’d like to recreate Barkai’s analysis, but now for the housing sector only. To figure that out, I need to look at the data on the stock of residential housing capital (K), and the imputed flow of value-added from housing (Y). The other thing I need to calculate is the required rate of return on housing (R).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the stock and flow, which I pulled down from FRED. The stock, K, is the “Current-Cost Net Stock of Fixed Assets: Residential” from the national income accounts. That includes all privately owned residential assets, which encompasses both owner-occupied and tenant-occupied. The flow, Y, is “Gross housing value added”, which comes from Table 1.3.5 of the national accounts. This is the BEA’s estimate of the total flow of housing services (including imputed rents for owner-occupied housing) minus the cost of any intermediate goods. Those intermediates would include maintenance and repairs on your house, or the cost of property management services if you owned a rental building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_housing_ky.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing YK&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first figure is the ratio of Y/K, or roughly the average product of housing capital. On average, the flow of housing services is equal to around 8% of the stock of housing. But there are clear fluctuations, with a big dip after WWII, and then subsequent dips around 1980 and 2009. But there is also a tendency for the ratio Y/K to rise from WWII to today, from maybe 6% to 9%. This tendency of Y/K to &lt;em&gt;rise&lt;/em&gt; means that the ratio of K/Y is going to &lt;em&gt;fall&lt;/em&gt;, and that is going to matter in my little profit share calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want profit’s share of the flow of housing output. I’m going to assume that no labor is used in providing housing services. Don’t get freaked out by that, the flow of housing services is not the same thing as construction. Construction - which does use lots of labor - is the flow of &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; housing (or other structures) into the stock. What we’re talking about here is the flow of services provided by &lt;em&gt;existing&lt;/em&gt; housing, which does not involve much labor at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means I am assuming that the flow of housing can be split as follows, &lt;strong&gt;Y = RK + Profits&lt;/strong&gt;. In shares, this is just &lt;strong&gt;1 = RK/Y + Profits/Y&lt;/strong&gt;. If I know RK/Y, I can figure out the profit share easily. Note that RK/Y depends on K/Y, which was falling over time, based on the prior figure. So that, by itself, suggests the profit share was rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, it seems likely that R was falling over time. If you remember from the prior post, we could write &lt;strong&gt;R = i - g + d&lt;/strong&gt;, where R is the return on capital, i is the nominal interest rate, g is the expected inflation in the capital price, and d is depreciation. For i, the obvious choice here is the mortgage rate. I (or rather FRED) does not have mortgage rate data going back as far as 1930, but it does have it for the 1970’s forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_housing_mort.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing Mortgage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a big surprise that mortgage rates have fallen over time, much like any other nominal interest rate. They’re under 5% now, from a high of around 17% in 1981. By itself, this is going to drive R lower over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other information I need is on g and d. I’ve played around a lot with these, and I can’t come up with any reasonable assumptions about them that can overcome the drop in nominal mortgage rates over time. That is, if you really wanted to make R go &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; over time, you’d need people to believe that housing prices were going to &lt;em&gt;fall&lt;/em&gt; significantly (so g&amp;lt;0) or that depreciation rates on houses have risen significantly over time. I can’t get my head around how either of those could be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the figure I’ll show below, I’m assuming that g = 3% at all times (not true) and d = 1% at all times (not true). I’m not going to get hung up on the actual numbers, because what we’re interested in is the change in R over time, not the actual level. It’s also a blog post, not a paper. So take the data on the mortgage rate, and combine that with my assumption on g and d to get a measure of R over time. Use that R, and combine it with the data on K/Y, and you’ve got a time series for RK/Y. With that time series, you can solve for &lt;strong&gt;Profits/Y = 1 - RK/Y&lt;/strong&gt;, and I’ve got my profit share in housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_housing_profit.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing Mortgage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to get your eyes off the gigantic negative number in 1981. According to this calculation, the profit share on housing was negative 100%. To be more concrete, what this is saying is that the rent you could get on a house (Y) in 1981 was equal to about half of the cost of the mortgage (RK). You were implicitly losing money owning a home, but if it was owner-occupied, you were losing money to yourself. That dramatic negative profit share is a function of the spike in mortgage rates during the Volcker disinflation, and as I said, it is hard to see around it in the figure. But notice that the profit share started to climb around 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_housing_profit90.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing Mortgage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled the 1990-2016 period out to show the evolution of the profit share more clearly. Here the rise in the profit share is apparent, from about 20 to about 80% from 1990 to 2016. I don’t want to get too stuck on the precise level of these numbers, which depend in part on my assumption regarding 3% expected house price inflation and 1% depreciation. But the trend is clear. Because of the decline in the mortgage rate, the cost of owning a home fell, but the flow of output produced by houses did not. In essence, you can rent out your owner-occupied home for more than you’d pay in mortgage costs, and you are profiting. You may be paying those profits to yourself, but there is a profit involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s round this back to the discussion of profit shares in the wider economy. Barkai found that the profit share is rising in the private, non-housing, sector. My mini-analysis here suggests that the profit share in the housing sector is rising as well. Combined, that means the profit share in aggregate GDP is rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference from the last post is that the rise in housing profits is not mutually exclusive with the rise in profts in the private, non-housing, sector. The source of the rise in profits is similar in both cases, as it turns out. The drop in nominal interest rates means that the required return for capital (housing or non-housing) is falling over time, but the flow of output produced in part by that capital is not, so the profit share is rising.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is Housing Driving the Rise in Profits?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Profit-Accounting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Profit-Accounting/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Um, this has nothing to do with health care or repealing the ACA. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/Markups/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; was on the profit share in GDP. I drew on some work by &lt;a href=&quot;http://home.uchicago.edu/~barkai/&quot;&gt;Barkai&lt;/a&gt;, who calculated that the profit share in GDP had been rising steadily over the last thirty years. To save you the bother of clicking any links, here is his figure showing the profit share over time, rising from about 2.5% of GDP in 1985 to over 15% in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/barkai3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Barkai figure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while back, I also did some &lt;a href=&quot;https://growthecon.com/blog/the-changing-composition-of-productivity-growth/&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; about how the BLS calculates multi-factor productivity. As part of that the BLS also provides a breakdown of GDP into payments to labor, capital, and profits. Here’s that figure, which runs back to 1950.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig_output_share.png&quot; alt=&quot;BLS figure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of the two figures isn’t the same, but I don’t believe it is too hard to see that there is a significant difference in the profit share of output in the two analyses. There is, for all intents and purposes, no increase in the profit share using the BLS data, while Barkai finds that dramatic increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can explain the difference? To answer that, I have to dig into how both sources construct their estimates of the profit share. The method is similar between the two, but they differ in the data they use, so it turns out that the difference is all in the data, and that will have an interesting implication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;calculating-profits-share-of-output&quot;&gt;Calculating Profits Share of Output&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let me outline the method they use, and why. Both the BLS and Barkai want to decompose output into something like &lt;strong&gt;Output = Wages + Capital Payments + Profits&lt;/strong&gt;. This would be easy if national income accounts reported those three separate components, but they don’t. National accounts will tell you that &lt;strong&gt;Output = Wages + Proprietors Income + Rental Income + Corporate Profits + Net Interest + Taxes on production&lt;/strong&gt;. Accounting-wise, it must be that &lt;strong&gt;Capital Payments + Profits = Proprietors Income + Rental Income + Corporate Profits + Net Interest + Taxes on production&lt;/strong&gt;, but there is no way to know how big Capital Payments and Profits are from this. No, “Corporate Profits” are not equal to Profits. The former is &lt;em&gt;accounting&lt;/em&gt; profits, and the latter refers to &lt;em&gt;economic&lt;/em&gt; profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both the BLS and Barkai, the solution to getting economic profits is to combine data on the total capital stock, K, with an assumption about the return to capital, R. The Capital Payments are then defined as RK, and once you know the Capital Payments, you can back out the Profits. In other words, &lt;strong&gt;Profits = Output - Wages - RK&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Barkai, the value of K is taken directly from the BEA. That stock of capital, K, is broken down into a lot of categories and sub-categories are structures, equipment, and intellectual property. Structures include non-residential structures like warehouses, lodging (e.g. hotels), and amusement and recreation (e.g. Six Flags), among others. Structures also include residential structures like single family homes and apartment buildings. Intellectual property includes things like software, as well as (as of 2013), a capitalized value of R/D spending by different industries. Finally, equipment includes all the things that you normally think of as capital, like computer equipment, engines and turbines, metalworking equipment, ships, railroad, oil wells, and photocopiers (which get their own sub-category under “information processing equipment”, which I find humorous for some reason).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For R, he constructs an implicit rate of return, something like what you’d do if you tried to come up with the implicit rent an owner pays themselves if they own their home. He follows &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~rehall/Tax-Policy-AER-June-1967.pdf&quot;&gt;Hall and Jorgenson&lt;/a&gt; (1967), which assumes that investment decisions are not made randomly, but rather must reflect some economic logic, and so the rate of return R is described by &lt;strong&gt;R = i - g + d&lt;/strong&gt;. i is the nominal interest rate. g is the growth rate of the price of the capital good (capital gains), and d is depreciation. The intuition of the effect of these three terms is straightforward if you spin this around into &lt;strong&gt;i = R + g - d&lt;/strong&gt;. Think of a firm borrowing money to buy a capital good. They pay i as a nominal interest rate. That asset yields a return of R to them for using it, plus they get the capital gain (or loss) that goes along with the asset. The asset also depreciates at the rate d. In equilibrium, the cost of borrowing (i) should be equal to the benefit (R + g - d).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barkai makes some assumptions to solve for R. He uses the interest rate on triple-A rated corporate bonds to stand in for the nominal interest rate i. He uses the observed inflation in the price of capital goods, available from the BEA’s data, to get his value for g. And the BEA also provides a number for the depreciation rate of different types of capital goods, based on their expected years of service, which he can use to get d. He solves for R for each of the three main types of capital goods - structures, equipment, and intellectual property - allowing each to have different values for g and d. At that point he can calculate RK for each type of capital, and then add up those total payments to get aggregate payments to capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once he knows the capital payments, he can back out the Profits. And once he knows Profits, he simply calculates Profits/GDP to get profits share of output, which is what you see plotted in that first figure. There is nothing that immediately jumps out about Barkai’s method that would suggest it is wrong. Could you use a different series for the nominal interest rate? Sure. But if you jump onto the FRED database, and look at any series of nominal interest rates over time, they decline sharply from the early 1980’s until today. Is the required return to capital, R, not related to i + g - d? Maybe. But it would be weird if somehow the return paid to capital deviated a lot from that value. If the R value were in fact much &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; than what Barkai calculates, then this would lower the Capital Payments even further, and in turn make profits share rise by even more, and the deviation from the BLS data would be more pronounced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, to solve for the profit share you need to infer something about the payments to capital. What the BLS does is quite similar to Barkai. They use some different values for i, g, and d, but that isn’t what is really driving the difference in the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-drives-the-difference&quot;&gt;What drives the difference?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key distinction is in the overall scope of their analysis. For Barkai, &lt;strong&gt;Output = GDP&lt;/strong&gt;. For the BLS, &lt;strong&gt;Output = Private Business Output&lt;/strong&gt;. The distinction is, very roughly, &lt;strong&gt;GDP = Private Business Output + Government + Imputed GDP from Owner-Occupied Housing&lt;/strong&gt;. The concept of output is wider for Barkai than it is for the BLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This difference carries through to the capital stock that the BLS uses. For the BLS, the capital stock is a subset of the capital stock that Barkai uses. The BLS uses equipment, intellectual property, and tenant-occupied housing (e.g. apartment buildings). They exclude the stock of owner-occupied housing, which is included in Barkai’s calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically the reason Barkai gets a rising profit share is that he finds a fall in the share of GDP going to Capital Payments over time. For the BLS, the share of output going to capital, as you can see in the second figure, does not change much - and when it changes, it is offset by changes in the labor share, and so there is no big change in the profit share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does Barkai find a fall in the capital share compared to the BLS? It may be due to an increase in the imputed value of housing in GDP. This is going to be more clear if I drop in a real equation, so here we go&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{(RK)^{BLS}}{Y^{BLS}} &gt; \frac{(RK)^{BLS} + (RK)^{Houses}}{Y^{BLS} + Y^{Houses}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fraction on the right is the capital share in output calculated by the BLS, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y^{BLS}\inline&quot;/&gt; stands for private business output. This fraction is bigger than the fraction on the right, which is meant to capture what Barkai is calculating as the capital share. In the numerator, he has both the return on capital that the BLS would capture, but also the return on capital going to owner-occupied housing. In the denominator, Barkai has “GDP”, which is - very roughly - the sum of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y^{BLS}\inline&quot;/&gt; and the imputed flow of GDP from owner-occupied housing, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y^{Houses}\inline&quot;/&gt;. For this inequality to be true, we need that the payments to capital for houses are not “too big”, but the imputed flow of GDP from owner-occupied housing, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y^{Houses}\inline&quot;/&gt; are “very big”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing. If the imputed GDP from owner-occupied housing is very high, but the payments to capital required by housing are small, then by implication the &lt;em&gt;profits&lt;/em&gt; on owner-occupied housing are high. The rise in profits share seen in the Barkai paper could well be driven by the market power of house owners, and not by the market power of corporations, which is the intuitive response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;profits-on-housing&quot;&gt;Profits on housing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to jive with other information. The figure below is from Matt Rognlie’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattrognlie.com/brookings_capitalshare.pdf&quot;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt;. Rognlie is looking not at the separate shares of output going to profits and capital, but rather their sum. If you like, he is interested in the share of GDP &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to labor. What he did was to decompose this total non-labor share into a part accounted for by housing, and for a part accounted for by non-housing. As you can see in the figure, the share of GDP going to housing (either as a return to capital or as profits) was increasing from 1950 to today. It rose from about 3% of GDP to about 10% in this period of time, while the share of GDP going to non-housing capital (either as a return to capital or as profits) was declining slightly. Combined, these two trends lead to a rise in the share of GDP going to capital as a whole, and was one of the key elements of Piketty’s book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/rognlie.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rognlie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rognlie’s decomposition is consistent with the story about rising profits in owner-occupied housing. The total amount of GDP getting paid to owners of homes is rising over time (Rognlie). But at the same time, the required rate of return on capital is falling (Barkai and BLS), which means that the &lt;em&gt;profits&lt;/em&gt; on owner-occupied housing must be rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by profits? Remember that these are &lt;em&gt;economic&lt;/em&gt; profits, not accounting profits. Owners of homes are not seeing an increase in their cash flow. As a home owner, I can assure you that my house does nothing but suck &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; cash, as opposed to producing it. Those economic profits are coming in the form of a higher imputed flow of GDP from my house over time. This implicit flow of value, a rent I’m charging myself, is getting cranked upwards over time, even if I don’t see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To think about how this works out as an economic profit, consider the following example. Let’s say you can take out a mortgage at 4%. That’s the nominal interest rate i. Let’s say houses depreciate at 1% per year, and you expect capital gains on your house to be something like 2% per year. Then the required rate of return to break even would be &lt;strong&gt;R = 4 - 2 + 1 = 3%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your house is worth 500,000, a 3% return would mean charging 15,000 in rent per year, or 1,250 per month. Now, if you look out at the market and find out that you could actually rent your house out for 2,000 per month, you are making 750 in &lt;em&gt;economic&lt;/em&gt; profit. The price you can charge for your house, 2,000, is higher than the marginal cost to you, 1,250. Profits!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter if you are paying &lt;em&gt;yourself&lt;/em&gt; that rent or not. If your house can rent for more than the marginal cost, then you are making profits. The rise in the profit share in the Barkai analysis may be driven in part - or maybe mostly? - by the rise in the imputed value of rents going to owner occupied housing. If the BEA is overstating the value of the flows going to home-owners, fine, but then the implied increase in the profit share in Barkai’s analysis is overstated as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications of an increasing profit share coming from owner-occupied housing are a lot different from the implications of an increasing profit share coming from corporate market power or concentration. I need to think a lot harder about housing, it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Text</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Markups/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Markups/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve put out a few posts in the past on the effect of higher markups on the &lt;em&gt;growth&lt;/em&gt; in measured productivity. But in those cases I’ve generally avoided the question of whether higher markups have an effect on the &lt;em&gt;level&lt;/em&gt; of measured productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evidence-on-higher-profit-shares-and-markups&quot;&gt;Evidence on higher profit shares and markups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/0nk9egcg8tf1sdv/figure_kcl_2.png?dl=0&quot; alt=&quot;Testing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-effect-of-markups-on-productivity-levels&quot;&gt;The effect of markups on productivity levels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say something about the effect that markups could be having on productivity, we need some conception of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; firms are able to charge a markup over marginal cost, and also some conception of what drives those markups. For the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;, we assume that firms have some market power based on …. something about them. Maybe they have a patent on a product, meaning they are the monopoly provider. Or maybe they have created some kind of brand, or reputation for quality (deserved or not), that makes people want to only buy &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; product. Think Apple. Or maybe they have some kind of locational advantage, like being a coffee shop in a busy train station. Whatever the reason, these firms have enough market power to charge a markup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What determines the level of that markup, and why would it change? In general, the elasticity of demand for their product with respect to price is what matters here. The higher the elasticity (the “flatter” the demand curve), the less market power a firm has, and the smaller a markup they can charge. The lower the elasticity (the “steeper” the demand curve), the more market power a firm has, and the bigger a markup they can charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high elasticity would be the case if there were lots of close substitutes for the product, so people were willing to abandon a firm’s specific product if the price went up just a little. Think of gas stations, which have a tiny bit of market power due to location. But lots of people would stop going to a gas station that raised its price by 1 or 2 cents per gallon. A low elasticity would be the case if there were few substitutes for the product, or the product was a strong complement to other things people buy. Then, no matter what the firm charges, people will buy some. Think of an iPhone. Apple has convinced people - whether you believe it or not - that there is no substitute for an &lt;em&gt;iPhone&lt;/em&gt;; other smartphones just aren’t the same. So they can charge 600 bucks for one, while the marginal cost is something closer to 100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the evidence says that markups have gone up, then one interpretation is that the elasticity of demand for different goods has gone &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt;. I think of this as meaning that people have gotten very picky. I want an &lt;em&gt;iPhone&lt;/em&gt;, not a Samsung. I want a double chai skim latte, not a coffee. I want a Lululemon pair of yoga pants, not the ones from Target. Just imagine that everyone has become a 13-year-old girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if markups are higher because the elasticity of demand for individual goods is lower, what does this imply for measured productivity? Well, in most typical settings, this would lower measured productivity. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with a very standard way of thinking about how to model this, with a constant elasticity of substitution across firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of the paper is that if both labor’s share and capital’s share are falling, then by necessity profit’s share is rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analytically, we like to talk about profits as a function of markups - the ratio of price to marginal cost charged by firms. If the profit share is rising, then it must be that markups are rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked before about the impact of markups, but the Barkai paper lays out clearly the effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is output lower with higher markups? Within the setup that Barkai uses, it is because the lower shares going to labor and capital lower the wage and rate of return, respectively. With the benefit of working or investing lower due to higher markups, labor supply and savings are lower. Output is lower because we provide fewer inputs to the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an alternative, imagine that both capital and labor were inelastically supplied. Then, regardless of the labor or capital share, we’d have the same amount of inputs, and hence the same amount of output. The only difference would be the distribution of output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, wages stagnate for two reasons. First, labor’s share of output is lower, so they are taking a smaller slice of the pie. Second, the pie is smaller as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-mechanisms&quot;&gt;Other mechanisms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanism here is that higher markups lower factor supplies. And that fits within the model Barkai uses, which uses a bunch of standard assumptions. There is monopolistic competition between firms, with a fixed elasticity of substitution between them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Who are you calling Malthusian?</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Malthus/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Malthus/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had a student ask me if I was a “Malthusian”. It’s not the first time someone has asked me that, and I’m never quite sure what to make of it. It’s always asked in a way that implies it is a belief system, similar to “Christian”, “Muslim”, or “Packer Fan”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how to reply. I’m not a Malthusian “believer”, because that isn’t a thing. But I do think that several of Malthus’ assumptions about how economies function, in particular prior to the onset of sustained growth during the 1800’s, are well founded. And those assumptions have implications that help make sense of the world in that period of time. Some of the assumptions Malthus made may still be relevant today, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is therefore an attempt to lay out what I think Malthusian means, and then I’ll touch on a few alternate uses of the term that are not quite right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stagnation-in-living-standards&quot;&gt;Stagnation in living standards&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My concept of a Malthusian economy involves two characteristics. First, living standards are negatively related to the &lt;em&gt;size&lt;/em&gt; of population. This would occur if we had some sort of fixed factor of production. Typically, one might say it was agricultural land, but you could just say resources if you like. It isn’t even important that they are truly fixed. So long as the resources are inelastic, whether due to a physical limit or because bringing them into use is prohibitively expensive, you’d satisfy the first characteristic of a Malthusian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know that there is much controversy around whether this holds, in particular in the era prior to sustained growth. I cribbed the figure shown here from Oded Galor’s book, which took if from Greg Clark. When population crashes after the Black Death, wages spike. They stay high while population is low, and then fall once population rises again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/clark2001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clark wage and population&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second characteristic is that population growth is positively related to living standards. This may be because kids are a normal good, and so fertility rises when people have higher incomes. Or it may be because health is a normal good, so people take better care of themselves (and their kids) when they have higher income. Higher fertility and/or lower mortality rates would lead to more rapid population growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or maybe people don’t make concious choices like that. Maybe it is purely biological, and women with higher living standards (e.g. healthier diets) will bring more babies to term, and those babies will be more likely to survive to become parents themselves. It isn’t important here whether the fertility and mortality outcomes are subject to rational calculation or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malthus’ original work involved this positive relationship, and he seemed to have in mind a combination of choice and biology. His preventative checks were choices made by people to have fewer children, or marry later, in response to poor living standards (hence living standards and fertility are positively related). His positive checks were lower fertility and higher mortality that would occur somewhat automaticallywhen living standards fell sufficiently far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the first characteristic, the evidence for the second is ambiguous. The major issue is that there is little data available on fertility and mortality at the individual level from the period prior to 1800, and so it is difficult to test the relationship of those demographics with living standards. England is one of the places that has some data, and hence the debate on this tends to be over English demographics. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/services/aop-cambridge-core/content/view/S0022050712000678&quot;&gt;Kelly and O Grada&lt;/a&gt; (2012) find evidence of preventive checks (i.e. marriage rates), and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cesifo-group.de/DocDL/cesifo1_wp6167.pdf&quot;&gt;Cinnirella, Klemp, and Weisdorf&lt;/a&gt; (2016) find evidence that births were spaced in response to living standards. But there are a number of studies that conclude the marriage rates were not responsive to living standards. &lt;a href=&quot;http://wrap.warwick.ac.uk/28332/&quot;&gt;Crafts and Mills&lt;/a&gt; (2009), for example, conclude there is no positive check operating, and that preventive checks break down by the 1700’s. If you are looking for reasons to “dis-believe” Malthusian economics, then this is the spot. Perhaps population growth isn’t positively related to living standards after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this characteristic holds, then you’ve got what I’d call a Malthusian economy. At this point, everything else follows. If there are only a few people, then from the first characteristic we know that living standards are high because the resources per person are high. But high living standards mean high population growth rates, so the number of people expands, and this pushes down resources per person, and hence pushes down living standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are a lot of people, then the opposite logic holds. Things are crowded, so living standards are low. Low living standards means slow population growth. When things are sufficiently crowded, it will mean negative population growth, and the population falls. Falling population means more resources per person, and so living standards rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything in the system is pushing back towards some middle ground where the resource per person, and hence the living standard, is at just the right level so that population growth is zero. With no change in population, there is no change in living standards, so there is no change in population growth, so there is again no change in population. The economy becomes &lt;em&gt;stagnant&lt;/em&gt; at the living standard which delivers zero population growth. If you’d like a nice treatment of this mathematically, I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/aer.101.5.2003&quot;&gt;Ashraf and Galor&lt;/a&gt; (2011) is the cleanest description you’ll get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m rambling on about Malthusian economics, let me offer a few observations that are not immediately obvious from what I just described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The stagnant level of living standards is not necessarily at a biological minimum.&lt;/strong&gt; Malthus, being something of an eternal pessimist, thought that living standards would be driven down to some bare minimum to survive. This isn’t a necessary conclusion from his two assumptions. Population growth can respond positively to living standards, even if the living standard at which population growth is zero is quite high. It all depends on preferences for kids. All Malthusian economies do not stagnate at the same level of living standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shocks to technology/productivity will only temporarily raise living standards, but will permanently raise population size.&lt;/strong&gt; Positive shocks to productivity raise living standards immediately for those alive, but this induces them to have more kids (or induces their kids to not die as quickly, so to speak), leading to population growth, which lowers living standards. Variation in productivity across countries will thus show up in higher population, but not necessarily in higher living standards. This is what Ashraf and Galor (2011) showed in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first shows that population density is positively related to a measure of land productivity across countries in 1500 CE, consistent with the long-run effect of productivity on population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ashrafgalor2011a.png&quot; alt=&quot;AGone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second shows that living standards (GDP per capita) are not related to the same measure of land productivity across countries in 1500 CE, consistent with no long-run effect of productivity on living standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ashrafgalor2011b.png&quot; alt=&quot;AGtwo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The adjustment back to the stagnant level of living standards can take a long time&lt;/strong&gt;. This means that a given Malthusian economy may have living standards that wander all over the place in the data. Nippe Lagerlof has a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nippelagerlof.com/research/happening/Waves_August_2016_post.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; showing that a Malthusian economy with random shocks to productivity and a realistic age structure will display living standards that do look Malthusian in the sense of being fixed and close to some stagnant level, but display waves of growth and collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/nippe2017.png&quot; alt=&quot;nippe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nippe has built a tendency for all economies to move towards sustained growth, but the point is that the four different economies have waves of growth and collapse that last for decades, even though they have the exact same underlying Malthusian structure. The random shocks to living standards persist over time because of the effect on age structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you ask me if I’m a Malthusian, then I guess the answer is yes, if you mean everything I just said in this section. Now what about other uses of the term Malthusian? Let’s take a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;population-and-factor-prices&quot;&gt;Population and factor prices&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term Malthusian has been applied at times to people who assert that changes in population size, acting through factor prices, influence social relationships. Historians like Postan and Le Roy Ladurie advance this kind of thesis, but I think that &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2kIGVT9&quot;&gt;North and Thomas&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;The Rise of the Western World&lt;/em&gt; may be the purest example of this, and the most known to economists. North and Thomas argue that changes in population, by changing relative wages and the bargaining power of peasants, were instrumental in changing institutions in Western Europe prior to the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like Robert Brenner and Guy Bois took issue with this explanation (and each other), arguing that Postan and Le Roy Ladurie (and North and Thomas by extension) were ignoring the issue of class in explaining changes in relative wages and the institutions governing labor. Glossing this “Brenner Debate” is well beyond the scope of this post, so suffice it to say that Brenner and Bois argue that changes in population are not sufficient to change institutions. The effect of population changes on labor conditions depended on the actual political power of peasants, which was not necessarily affected by population. See the compilation &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2lp39Zh&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for all you’d ever want to know about this debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the details of that argument, and it is a fascinating read, Brenner and Bois use the term Malthusian to describe their opponents and their theories. And to me, this is an incorrect use of Malthusian. The concept that population size influences wages is not Malthusian, it is economics-ian. There is nothing Malthusian about Postan, Le Roy Ladurie, and North and Thomas, at least when it comes to their explanation of institutional change. This doesn’t make Brenner and Bois wrong. It makes them semantically confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;limits-to-growth&quot;&gt;Limits to Growth&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third way I think Malthusian gets used is in terms of &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2kIQ269&quot;&gt;limits to growth&lt;/a&gt;, environmental collapse, and the like. Here, the authors or speakers believe firmly that there is a fixed supply of resources available, and hence living standards must be negatively related to population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can class the limits to growth people into two groups. The first takes population growth as given, and doesn’t think much about whether it responds to living standards. The fact that population growth is positive - at the global level - is sufficient to create declining living standards, and thus we need to either conserve resources or exert some kind of birth control policy. The second group has internalized the post-demographic transition &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; relationship of living standards and population growth. Once the planet gets so crowded that living standards fall, this will &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; the population growth rate, and we’ll be in a death spiral towards misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view, of either group, is often called Malthusian because of the negative effect of population on living standards. And that, it seems, is only about half right. There is no stagnation in the sense that I described above, as in either case population growth continues (slowly or in an accelerating manner) until the living standard is zero. Which I guess would be stagnant, if it stayed at zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I don’t consider myself a Malthusian in this sense of the word, and that is because the finite limit of resources gets progressively looser over time. This post is already stretched out too long, so I don’t want to get into a lot of detail here. But there are two reasons for this. First, because technological change will make some resource constraints less binding or eliminate the need for certain resources. Second, because the income elasticity of demand for resource-intense goods is low, our use of those resources will not grow as fast as limits to growth types would suggest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that my original description of Malthusian economies ignores this second effect, coming through income elasticities. Ashraf and Galor’s model, for example, would suggest that no matter how high productivity got, we are always producing goods using the same resource-intense production function. That may be fine if you are just describing the stagnant economies prior to sustained growth - or maybe it isn’t fine, if you read Lemin Wu’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://behl.berkeley.edu/files/2015/02/WP2015-01_Wu.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; - but breaks down if you allow for any appreciable non-resource based sector (e.g. services of any kind).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yes, ideas are harder to find. Don't panic yet.</title>
        <link>https://growthecon.com/blog/Idea-TFP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://growthecon.com/blog/Idea-TFP/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nick Bloom, Chad Jones, John van Reenen, and Michael Webb have a new &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.stanford.edu/~chadj/IdeaPF.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on how productive we are at producing “ideas”, which one can argue are the ultimate source of all economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The splash graphic from the paper, which I believe made a brief tour of the Twitter-verse a month or so ago, is shown below. It shows that the TFP growth rate (in blue) peaked around the 1940’s, and has declined since then. The axis measurement here is a big funky, as you could see more of the details of this line if they had made the left axis go up to say 5%, rather than 25%. Regardless, the TFP growth rate is smaller than it was in the past, following Robert Gordon’s numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In green is the relative number of researchers compared to the number in 1930. This isn’t the &lt;em&gt;number&lt;/em&gt; of researchers, its a measure of &lt;em&gt;effective&lt;/em&gt; researchers, found by dividing total R and D spending by the nominal wage of high-skilled workers. Relative to 1930, we have almost 25 times as many (effective) researchers at work today. This leads to the author’s title question - “Are ideas getting harder to find?”. And the author’s answer is “Yes”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jones_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Idea TFP and TFP Growth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;measuring-idea-tfp&quot;&gt;Measuring Idea TFP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BJvRW measure how “hard” it is to find ideas by looking at what they call “idea TFP”. This is easy to back out from some data. Let’s write the growth rate of ideas (I) as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{I}_t}{I_t} = \alpha_t S_t&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where the left side is the growth rate of ideas at time t, and on the right-hand side we’ve got the determinants of that growth. &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S_t\inline&quot;/&gt; is research effort, and here think of the measure of effective researchers. How much work do we put into coming up with new ideas? The second term is &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_t\inline&quot;/&gt;, which is the “idea TFP”. It tells you how much idea growth you get out of those researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you tell me the growth rate of ideas (the left) and the number of effective researchers (S), then I (well, the authors) can back out the measure of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_t\inline&quot;/&gt; year by year. And this is what BJvRW do, in a variety of contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they do first is to equate the growth rate of ideas with the growth rate of TFP (actual aggregate TFP in producing GDP). That doesn’t mean that each idea is equal to one “unit” of TFP, it just means that if the number of ideas grows by 10%, then TFP grows by 10%. This is a big leap - but let’s not get hung up on this. It isn’t important in this first context. With the data from the first graph on the TFP growth rate (&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{I}/I\inline&quot;/&gt;), and the number of effective researchers (&lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S_t\inline&quot;/&gt;), we can back out &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_t\inline&quot;/&gt;. This “idea TFP” is, awkwardly, the “TFP TFP”, or our productivity at producing TFP given a set of researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jones_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Idea TFP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second graph plots the &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha_t\inline&quot;/&gt; they back out, relative to 1930. You can see that it falls to about 1/64th of the level in 1930. Because we are 1/64th as effective at turning researchers into TFP, but we only have 32 times as many researchers, our growth rate of TFP is about 1/2 as high as it was in the 1930’s/1940’s. Hang on to the “why” question for a moment. For now, we’re just looking at the pure accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first exercise using (actual) TFP as the measure of ideas is a bit crude, and what BJvRW go on to do is examine individual industries or types of products to establish that the “idea TFP” is in fact falling within each of these as well. This is relevant because the first result using TFP does not tell us what is happening at the “micro” level. We could have constant (or even rising) “idea TFP” within individual industries or lines of research, and yet in aggregate falling “idea TFP”. It may be that ideas are not perfectly translated to TFP, or it may be that the we are spreading our research efforts over an ever-expanding list of industries or lines of research. In the latter case, idea growth in individual industries/lines may be falling because of the decline in numbers of researchers, not because of declining idea TFP. But in aggregate, this would look like declining idea TFP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus looking at individual industries/lines will help us sort out what is happening. The first example is transistors, and the count of transistors per square inch on a chip. Famously, this appears to obey Moore’s Law, which is that the number of transistors per square inch doubles every 18 months. If we count the number of transistors per square inch as “ideas”, then this translates to a growth rate of 35% per year. At the same time, the effective number of researchers working at chip companies (Intel, AMD, etc..) has grown by a factor of about 80 since 1970. Plotting this together yields their next figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jones_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Moores Law&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative to the first graph, there is no decline in the growth rate of transistors. But there also isn’t an increase, despite the increased number of researchers. What this means is that “transistor idea TFP” is falling over time, at about 10% per year. As they point out in the paper, Moore’s Law still holds, but it takes 78 times more researchers to figure out how to double transistor density than it did in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, the paper works through several other examples. I’ll leave it to you to look at the specifics. But overall, the message becomes clear. For crop yields, idea TFP is falling at between 3% and 9% per year, except for cotton, where it rose slightly over time. For “new molecular entities” (e.g. drugs) idea TFP has fallen to about 1/4 of its value in 1970, or about 3% per year. BJvRW also look at firm size, measured in different ways, which should be related to their productivity (and ideas). In each case, their size is not growing as fast as their RD spending, implying their idea TFP is falling at about 8-15% per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;implications-for-economic-growth&quot;&gt;Implications for Economic Growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The looming question here is whether this implies economic growth is due to slow down to zero. And the answer is “No”. It is possible for ideas to have a constant growth rate (and GDP per capita to have a constant growth rate as well) even if idea TFP is falling over time. For “semi-endogenous growth theory”, a term often associated with Chad Jones, this falling idea TFP is consistent with constant, positive growth in GDP per capita.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what is in the Jones/Vollrath &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2k0pcbz&quot;&gt;textbook&lt;/a&gt; (buy 1, buy 10, buy 1000!) when we teach how ideas accumulate. Modify that first equation I showed you to look like the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{I}_t}{I_t} = \frac{\alpha}{I_t^{\beta}} S_t.&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where idea TFP is now the ratio of a constant, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt;, and the number of ideas, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I_t\inline&quot;/&gt;, raised to the power &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;. The value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta\inline&quot;/&gt; is quite important. If &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta=0\inline&quot;/&gt;, then the level of ideas has no effect on idea TFP, and idea TFP should be constant. This is what was in the original Romer model, by the way. What Jones did was to say that this implies a very knife-edge condition, and there was no reason to assume that &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta=0\inline&quot;/&gt;. When &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\beta&amp;gt;0\inline&quot;/&gt;, as we accumulate more ideas, the growth rate of ideas falls - idea TFP goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just because idea TFP falls as we get more ideas doesn’t mean the &lt;em&gt;growth rate&lt;/em&gt; of ideas (the left hand side) is falling. Why? Because &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S_t\inline&quot;/&gt; is rising over time due to population growth. If the share of people working as researchers is constant, then their absolute number is rising over time. In that case, there is a growth rate of ideas such that the growth rate of ideas stays constant over time, &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\dot{I}/I = n/\beta\inline&quot;/&gt;, where &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n\inline&quot;/&gt; is the growth rate of population (and hence of researchers). Idea growth need not slow down just because idea TFP falls over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence the “don’t panic yet” comment in the title. Falling idea TFP may well be the natural course of things, without resulting in lower actual TFP growth. The observed fall in actual TFP growth would have to come from some other forces involved in generating research effort. Start with an explanation that might imply a permanent fall in the TFP growth rate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The growth rate of the effective population has fallen&lt;/strong&gt;. If the population that provides researchers (and it is best here to think of the total population of advanced countries, not just the US) starts to grow more slowly, then S grows more slowly, and the long-run growth rate of ideas is going to be lower. Maybe the slowdown in TFP growth is due to slower population growth in developed countries. A counterargument would be that this is offset by the increasing shares of Chinese and Indian populations that are in the pool of possible researchers. A counter-counterargument would be that age distributions matter too, and we’ve got too many stodgy old people, and not enough inventive young whipper-snappers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other explanations might imply that the drop in the TFP growth rate will be temporary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A downward shift in the share of that population that is doing research&lt;/strong&gt;. This would generate a lower measured short-run growth rate of ideas because S would have a lower short-run growth rate for a while as we moved to a lower share of people doing research. This doesn’t appear to be true in the data, where an increasing share of workers are reported as doing RD work over time - and that should be pushing &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; the short-run growth rate of ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An exogenous drop in the level of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In this case, the growth rate of ideas would eventually rise back up to what it was before, after we had lower measured TFP growth for a while on our way to a new equilibrium. If we’re going to argue about the value of &lt;img src=&quot;http://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?\alpha\inline&quot;/&gt;, though, then we should start over with our theory about how ideas get generated, as saying “it was a random exogenous shock” ends up being kind of useless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, maybe semi-endogenous growth theory is wrong. Maybe this just isn’t the way to look at things. Alternative theories might say idea growth could be affected by policies (subsidies for basic research, tax policy regarding treatment of RD spending, etc..) and what we’ve seen is a continuous deterioration of the policies supporting idea generation. This one is a little hard to square, though, just because it seems odd that there would be such growth in the number of researchers if the returns to that research at the firm or individual level were going down so much. I can see how taxes on RD would lower the resources devoted to it, but why would that affect how effective RD efforts are? You’d have to argue that policies were incenting companies to work on useless ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
